So this is a very exciting day because
we are officially starting the
Gay to Lease journalism course.
Traditionally, we've
understood journalism and
research as this method of
just collecting information,
organizing it, and then expressing it.
But then along came a man named Gay to
Lease, and he transformed journalism.
He transformed the way we
understood research. So
we created something
called literary journalism,
which is the idea
that journalism can be
by itself be literature.
The Gay to Lease method is going to teach us
how to be creative, how to be imaginative,
and how to engage with reality
and engage with people.
We don't teach you this in school.
In fact, we teach you the opposite.
We teach you the opposite. Don't explore.
Just do what the teacher tells you to do.
Where did he learn this? Well,
he learned this at home.
The reason why is that
his father was a tailor.
His father was a tailor.
And he had a tailoring
business in New Jersey.
And his mother...
took care of the business while
his father made the clothes.
So what does this have to do
with exploration and reflection?
Well, his mother was responsible
for the business aspects.
So these very wealthy people
would come to the shop
and order very nice suits.
And her job was to deal with them.
But it's actually very hard
to deal with rich people.
They can be very demanding.
So her strategy was to
become their friend.
And how do you become someone's friend?
What do you do in order to
become someone's friend?
What must you do? Talk.
Wrong. Not talk.
The opposite. Listen.
Okay? Do you understand? So...
In the family living room,
the mother would say,
I want to sit down on the
couch talking with these
very wealthy people.
And she would talk just by listening.
Okay? So her strategy for this is
that I am interested in you.
So that's how she became friends
with all these very wealthy people,
even though she herself was not wealthy.
She had a mindset that
whoever came into her living room,
whoever was a client,
was first and foremost a friend.
And she was interested in this person.
She was interested in people.
So she would spend hours and
hours just listening to that
person talk and talk and talk.
And so you can say that
this is exploration.
Curiosity. Okay?
Exploration. But in the other room,
the father would by himself sit
and work on the clothes.
Right? I'm not sure if
you've seen Taylor's work.
They are very precise.
They are very exact.
They are very meticulous.
They're very disciplined.
They're very patient.
So he could spend days
and days in his room just
working on a piece of suit.
Right? This is the idea of reflection.
The pursuit of perfection.
So exploration is the
pursuit of curiosity.
And reflection is the
pursuit of perfection.
This is a Gay Talese research method.
This is what I'll be teaching you.
This is something that will not just
help you become a better writer,
but someone who will be much more creative
and a much more effective researcher.
So even if you are going to the sciences,
I guarantee you that the skills you'll be learning
in this class will help you wherever you go.
I want you to go around
Beijing and take pictures.
Again, the idea is contrast.
Remember that here he says, New
York is a city of things unnoticed.
New York is a city of contrast.
I want you to do the
same thing for Beijing.
Take your camera and take
pictures of contrast.
Things that other people would not notice.
Okay? And take pictures of things
that are contrast of each other.