Okay, so good morning. We finished the Bronze
Age today with the Indus Valley civilization.
So we've done Egypt, we've done Mesopotamia,
now we're doing the Indus Valley civilization.
And today I'm going to look
at three questions, okay?
First of all, what is it that
makes the Indus Valley civilization distinct
or different from other civilizations?
Second is, why did they decline?
They reached their peak
about 2600 to 1900 BCE,
and then for the next three to
four hundred years, they declined
and ultimately disappeared.
Okay, why did it happen?
The last question is,
what is their legacy?
What is their contribution to the
development of Western civilization?
Okay? All right. So,
let's look at the Indus
Valley civilization.
To do so... We need to first
understand the world at this time.
And this is about 2500 to 2000 BCE,
okay? This is what we call
the Middle Bronze Age.
Because most people were using
bronze for weapons, for tools.
So, over here is Egypt.
And as we discussed, by far, Egypt is
the wealthiest country in the world.
And it's the most advanced
civilization in the Bronze Age.
Over here, across the Red Sea, is Arabia.
And even though Arabia
isn't really discussed that
much in world history,
it's still significant
because it's part of the trading network.
Okay? So, the Arabia, it's many nomads
who
take goods from Mesopotamia over to Egypt
and then into the Middle East.
And then, the Mediterranean,
which acts as all of Europe.
This is Sumer,
which is the beginning of the
Mesopotamian civilization.
Okay? Up here is Anatolia,
the Levant.
And then, the Indus Valley
civilization is over here.
And today, it would cover
the countries of Afghanistan,
Pakistan, and the Middle East.
First off, here is Pakistan.
First off here is Pakistan.
First off here is Pakistan. First off here
is Pakistan. First off here is Pakistan.
First off here is Pakistan.
trade. And in this valley civilization,
what was unique to them
are certain products,
for example, indigo dye, which
was really sought after in
Mesopotamia and in Egypt.
Their handicrafts, their jewelry,
were also very famous
throughout the world.
They usually traded with Sumer
and Egypt by trading with the
Gulf state nations of Bahrain
and Oman and Dubai.
And they actually had a
colony by the Persian Gulf.
This civilization was so good at trading
that we believe they
even traded with China,
which is pretty far away,
but their ships were huge
and they were very good navigators.
As a the Bronze Age developed over time,
bronze was in heavy demand
and the main components of
bronze are copper and tin.
Tin is mainly found in the
mountains of Afghanistan over here,
which
meant the Inis Valley civilization
started to now expand over to Afghanistan
in order to access the tin trade.
So tin was really sought after, but there
was also a lot of gold in the desert.
So the gold was mainly found in the
mountains of Afghanistan, but there was also another stone called lapis lazula,
which is really sought after by
the Egyptians for its spiritual
and aesthetic qualities.
And over here,
because
of the trade with Afghanistan,
land would start to develop into Anatolia
and Mesopotamia.
And as well, because of
this trade in Afghanistan,
new civilizations start
to develop as well.
And they're not as advanced,
as large as the three major ones,
but they're still pretty advanced.
So for example, up here is what we
call the Oxus Valley civilization.
The technical term used by
archaeologists are the
Bactrian -Margiana Archaeological Complex.
You don't have to know this,
okay? It's called BMAC.
What makes this civilization important
is it interacts with the steppes people,
called the Andromeno culture.
So as you can see, the
Inis Valley civilization,
through its partners,
the Oxus Valley civilization
and its colonies over here,
the Inis Valley civilization, through its
partners, the Oxus Valley civilization and its colonies over here, now trade with the entire world.
There's no piece of the Western world the
Inis Valley civilization does not touch.
Does that make sense? So
this is a world about 2500 to 2000 BCE.
It's a world that's
heavily interconnected.
And there are two major sources of demand.
The Egyptians are extremely wealthy,
and they want these valuable jewelry
and handicrafts for their burials.
That's one source of heavy demand.
That's one source of heavy demand. The main
source of demand is actually Mesopotamia,
where the city -states of Sumer are
fighting wars against each other.
And in wars, bronze
makes a huge difference,
because bronze armor is much
more stronger than copper armor.
So these two places are driving demand,
and as such,
the Inis Valley civilization is
growing wealthy through trade.
Does that make sense? Any
questions so far before I continue?
Okay, so even though
the Inis Valley civilization
is connected with Egypt
and Mesopotamia, it's a radically
different civilization.
Okay? So the first thing that
makes the Inis Valley civilization
interesting is it's a huge area.
It's actually, in terms of size,
larger than Egypt and
Mesopotamia combined.
It has a population of, at its
peak, about 5 million people.
Okay? So this is a huge area.
What's really interesting is we have
found no evidence of any
organized warfare in this
region during this time.
The reason why is this region
is connected through trade.
Okay? So what we have found
is five major urban centers.
In the Inis Valley civilization.
And these urban centers,
you can consider to be what
we call value
-adding processing centers.
Okay? These are urban centers that
specialize in taking raw goods,
like metals
and agricultural products,
and turning them into finished
products, like jewelry, handicrafts.
To be shipped,
to be traded with mainly Mesopotamia,
but also Egypt, and
possibly China as well.
It also goes north to the
Oxus Valley civilization,
which then trades with the steppe
people, the Andenov culture.
Okay? What we know as the Yamnaya people.
Alright? So this trade network,
it's very, very complex.
And
everyone is involved in some
capacity in this trade network.
Okay? So that's the first thing that's
interesting about the Inis Valley civilization.
They trade internally peacefully.
They trade externally peacefully as well.
We have absolutely no evidence that
they ever had organized warfare.
they have any intention
of organized warfare.
Meaning we have not found any weapons.
We have found tools. We
found hunting weapons.
We have not found, like,
maybe armor and helmets.
Okay? Yeah? Is there
any particular defense
that we can expect, like that
there is no organized
warfare in that situation?
Yeah. Great question. So how do we
know there's no organized warfare?
So we know there's a lot of
organized warfare in Mesopotamia and
other places because
of what we have dug up.
So we look at cities.
We see parts of the city
that have been built
on top of or destroyed.
Meaning there might have been some fires
or there might have been some warfare.
Okay? But with these five urban centers
that we've dug up, we have
found them pretty intact.
Meaning they were not built on
top of or they were not destroyed
when they were around.
So that's the first
major piece of evidence.
The second major piece of evidence
is we've dug up their graves.
So if you look at maybe the civilizations
of the Andronovo culture or Mesopotamia,
they tend to bury warriors
with their weapons.
Okay? So, you know, helmets and armor.
But when we've dug up
the IVC culture people,
first of all, we don't find
a distinct cast of warriors.
Also, we don't find any
helmets or armor or weapons.
Okay? So that's the first thing.
That's what led us to believe they
don't engage in organized warfare.
But there's also evidence to
suggest our evidence is not solid.
Okay? The first piece of evidence
is they don't bury their dead.
These people don't have a
tradition of burying their dead.
Some are buried. Okay? But
not everyone is buried.
Second of all, we don't know
where they buried their dead.
We assume they buried
their dead in the cities.
But that may not be true.
Okay? So the evidence leans towards
they were a peaceful civilization.
But as we dig up more and
more over time, we may
discover this was not true.
Okay? But right now the evidence
suggests they were peaceful.
And also what's really important about
the IVC, the Nisvalik civilization,
is this is a new discovery.
We've only known about them
for the past 100 years.
So what's interesting is the Indians
themselves never knew they existed.
It was the British who
discovered these cities and
started the work in archaeology to start
to reconstruct their civilization.
Okay? All right.
But thanks for the question. Okay.
So as I said,
the first thing that's interesting about
their civilization is it
was relatively peaceful,
okay, compared with what's
happening in Mesopotamia.
The second thing that was
interesting for us is,
and surprising is, for a
very large civilization,
they are egalitarian.
Okay? Meaning in Mesopotamia,
when we look at these
old cities, Ur and Uruk,
there were these huge palaces and
temples which
suggested a culture of
power in the priesthood
and in the king.
Okay? But when
we look at these five
urban centers of the IVC,
there are no palaces.
There are no temples.
Okay? In fact, these cities
are extremely well designed.
There are these walls around the city.
And then as you go into the city,
you're able to access every
single part of the city.
Okay? But if you were to go into a city,
say, in Sumer, if you go into the city,
you're only able to access
the temple or the palace.
Okay? So authority is
centralized in Sumer.
Whereas authority is sort of
decentralized in the IVC.
Now here's a question. If we know,
if we suspect they are
not engaged in warfare,
why do they have walls?
Why would, there are a lot
of walls inside these cities.
Why are there walls? Can anyone guess?
Okay. Customs.
Taxes. Okay? Meaning,
this is again a value added,
adding process center.
And the way they survive
economically is by collecting tolls
and customs on people who trade.
And the way they collect taxes is, when
you enter the city, you
have to go to the capital.
You have to go to the
customs house. And then
you pay whatever is required of you.
And then you can access the city.
Okay? And that's the way they centralized,
centrally controlled the
economy and trade in the IVC.
These cities are amazing.
These are the first people
to invent the sea toilet.
The private sea toilet.
This is about the year 2800 BCE.
Okay? So, when you go into
these cities, you'll find
that in private homes,
everyone has a private toilet.
And then the feces is
put into a sewage system
and the water flushes it out.
Okay? That's pretty amazing.
These are people who
are very concerned about the
well -being of all its citizens.
So, when we look at skeletal
remains through DNA analysis,
we've discovered the majority of the people
ate about the same high quality of food.
There wasn't these
disparities between people,
as you would find in other civilizations.
At least half the people, we
think, lived past the age of 55.
That was an amazing achievement back then.
In terms of innovation,
they have research.
They have reservoirs. They
also have public baths.
They also had really amazing
things called wind towers.
I'm not sure if you've studied these wind
towers, but they're basically air conditioners.
What they do is, these are high towers
and there is a hole on top.
So, what happens is,
the higher the air is,
the cooler it is. So,
this wind that's cool gets
strapped into the wind.
So, the wind comes down and it pushes
out the hot air from the other side.
This is what cools the
houses in the summer.
This is a pretty advanced technology.
Another really cool
thing about the IVC is,
even though it covers a huge area,
they have standardized
weights and measurements.
They have standardized
Which means that every brick
that they have is the same size.
Which means that
their buildings, their structures,
are extremely stable and resilient.
That's why, 5,000 years later, we
still have their cities intact.
You can actually go to the
cities and live in them.
That's how stable the technology was.
So, this is a pretty
advanced civilization.
Unfortunately, we don't have it.
We don't know what
their writing system is.
So, if they had writing, and
we can't know for sure
if they had writing,
it was like Chinese in
the idiographic language.
Meaning, it is not phonological.
Their spoken language is not the
same as their written language.
In other words, it is impossible for
us to decipher their written language.
We don't have that
many artifacts of writing.
We have seals with
characters written on them.
But we don't have anything else.
And the reason could be, if you
look at Egypt, they use papyrus.
Papyrus is stable,
or it keeps in the dry Egyptian air.
If you look at Samarian
culture, Mesopotamian culture,
they use cuneiform on clay tablets.
Which keeps forever.
But if they had a writing
system, and they did write,
it would be on palm leaves.
Which degrades very
easily in the jungle air.
So, we don't have access to their writing.
This is problematic, because
without access to their writing,
we don't have access to their religion.
We don't know what their religion is.
And one thing that you've learned in
this class that's very important is,
religion, or mythology,
it is the operating system of religion.
It is the operating system of the culture.
It is the collective consciousness,
the collective worldview, that
gives life to their culture.
It explains why they do what they do.
And unfortunately, we
don't know their religion.
But, so,
it's a complete mystery to
archaeologists, to scholars,
as to why this very advanced
civilization was very peaceful
and very egalitarian.
We can only speculate. Any
questions so far, before I continue?
Okay, so, I'm going to speculate
as to why they were peaceful
and egalitarian. So, again,
the key is the religion.
What is the religion? Because that
will give us clues as to their
mentality, their value system.
Right? We know that the
Mesopotamian people,
their religion focused on
struggle and achievement.
We know that the Egyptians, their
religion focused on the afterlife.
Okay? This life that we live is,
what's important is not the here and now.
What's important is what
happens afterwards.
Okay? And that's why the
Egyptians built the pyramid.
That's why they focused so much on
funeral rites and on burial goods.
Alright? So, there had to
be a religion in the IBC
that was different from the
belief system in Sumer in Egypt
that made it into a peaceful and
egalitarian civilization.
Okay? Alright. So, what is this
religion and why were they different?
My speculation is this.
The key is to understand that this
is a civilization based on trade.
And they've been traders ever
since they were born as a culture.
Meaning they were trading
for at least 7,000,
8,000 years before they
became a civilization.
Okay? And if you're a trader,
first of all, you're able
to access the entire world.
So, we know for a fact
they traded with Sumer
and the Persian Gulf states.
Because we have, we have artifacts
from the IBC in these places.
Okay? We know for a fact.
We can speculate it.
They also traded with Egypt and
with China just based
on their technology and
their trade networks.
So, this is a civilization based on trade.
And as traders,
they're able to see what's going
on in Mesopotamia and Egypt.
They know they built
the pyramids in Egypt.
They know there's
massive warfare in Sumer.
And I would think that
if you were a trader and you saw these
things, you wouldn't be impressed.
Okay? In fact, you might be disgusted,
especially by the warfare in Mesopotamia.
This idea called the dialectic, right?
And I think this is a
very important idea for
us to appreciate how history is often
driven by the idea of the dialectic.
So, an example that
we have in today's world is,
you look at Japan and China.
Okay? These are two
radically different societies
that are next to each other.
And the question then is,
why are they still different?
I think the answer is because
Japan knows China very well.
And a lot of cultural practice Japan
developed over the centuries
have been in response
to what they see as failings or
successes in Chinese culture.
Okay? Another example that
Doug will appreciate is
Canada and the United States.
The United States is probably the
most belligerent nation in the world.
Okay? They cannot get
their hands off anything.
And then you go north, Canada,
and Canada and the United States
share the world's longest border.
Basically, Canadians are
cousins of the Americans.
Okay? I mean, like, there's
really no difference.
We speak the same language.
We have the same cultural practices.
But while Americans are the most
belligerent nation ever in human history,
Canadians invented peacekeeping.
Okay? The idea, like,
nations should strive for mediation
and peace.
Okay? And I think a lot of
Canada, a lot of Canadian values,
especially its political system,
is in response to what it believes to be
failings and successes in the American model.
Okay? You also have New
Zealand and Australia.
So there are many different examples of the
dialectic going on in our global political systems.
And I believe that's what happened
with the IVC, where these traitors
saw what's happening in Egypt
and saw what's happening
in Mesopotamia, and
they were kind of disgusted,
especially by all this
warfare in Mesopotamia.
Okay? Warfare back
then was pretty awful.
And so in Mesopotamia,
the way they fight is,
they fight with these clay bullets.
Okay? And you take a slingshot
and you throw it at someone.
And these things kill.
They hurt. So think of David and Goliath.
Okay? And if you're a traitor,
you know, you'll see
this warfare going on.
You'll see people being, being beheaded.
And why are they doing this?
They're doing it in the name of God.
Okay? Every city -state has a patron god
that it believes it must defend
and honor and protect.
And whenever there's a dispute, it's
because they feel their god has been
dishonored by another city -state.
So they go to war and
they kill each other.
Okay? And again, if you're a traitor and you
see this, you don't think this is a good thing.
And you go to Egypt and
you see these pyramids,
and these pyramids are,
again, extremely impressive.
But at the same time, you also need to
see the consequences of these pyramids,
which is just massive inequality,
massive corruption, just massive waste.
All right? So I think
that by trading with these two
civilizations and other civilizations,
it reinforces the deep cultural
values of the IBC people
and it basically compels
them towards peace
and egalitarianism. Okay?
That's what I believe happened. All right?
Now, you could... There
are other arguments.
For example,
maybe these people are
just genetically peaceful and egalitarian.
But I've made the argument
in this class that
from the onset of early human
history, we were peaceful
and egalitarian people, but
different geographic
circumstances changed our outlook.
Okay? So, for example,
the people in the steppes,
who we call the Anar people, because
of the grasslands, because
it is such a poor and
rugged and unforgiving environment,
they're forced to be cattle ranchers.
They're forced to engage
in cattle raiding.
Okay? And over time, their
culture became very aggressive,
expansionist, and
opportunistic. Opportunistic.
Opportunistic just means they'll
do whatever it needs to survive.
If they face a...
They'll trade with people if
that's what benefits them.
They'll kill people if
They are not that moral.
Okay? They're very opportunistic. And
I remember, as I said, these
people with their cultural values
would go in and
conquer all of Europe
in about 200, 300 years.
Okay? And they were
called the Anar people.
Back in the steppes,
these Anar people continued
to evolve over time.
And over time, they became
even more aggressive,
more expansionist, and more opportunistic.
Okay? Eventually, the Mongols,
Genghis Khan and Mongols,
will come from this civilization.
Okay? So that's my argument to you.
And again, it's my speculation.
It is because of the reaction
of other cultures that
convinced them to pursue a
peaceful and egalitarian lifestyle.
Now, there are still inequalities in IBC.
We know there are classes. We
know there's wealth inequality.
But relative to Mesopotamia and Egypt,
it was a relatively peaceful
and egalitarian society.
Okay? Okay,
any questions before I continue?
Okay, so the question is,
were they invaded the IBC?
Okay, because as we discussed
in previous classes,
when you're peaceful in a
egalitarian society, we know that
old Europe, okay, before
the Amna invasion,
was a peaceful and egalitarian society.
You will eventually get
invaded by other cultures.
Okay? And for the longest time,
there was a theory out there,
first proposed by,
basically the Nazis, okay,
called the Indo -Aryan Invasion.
And the idea is, you
have these white people
sweep into India,
conquer the people, and
introduce civilization
to the Indians.
Okay? This is called the
Indo -Aryan Invasion.
Even though this theory
has been discredited,
there is a slight kernel
of truth to this theory,
okay, which I will explain to you.
Okay, so, let me explain this
theory and what happened.
So you have the IBC, which is
a very advanced civilization.
The problem with this civilization is,
their entire economy is
basically based on trade.
Right? Now, we know about,
there's something called
the 4.2 -kilo -year event,
which is basically a massive
climate change around the world. And
the 4.2 -kilo -year event brought
basically an end to the
Egypt O Kingdom. Right?
It also brought an end to what
we call the Akkadian Empire in Sumer.
A man named Sargon of Akkad
conquered all of Sumer
and built the Akkadian Empire.
And because of this drought,
because of climate change,
his empire collapsed.
Okay? So in other words, trade networks
that the IBC is heavily dependent on
start to collapse.
Okay? And as a result,
their cities now, which
are dependent on trade,
start to depopulate.
Meaning a lot of people start to return
to the farms where they are from.
They start also migrating
to the rest of India, to the Ganges.
Okay? As well, because
of this climate change,
the IBC itself is being affected heavily.
Okay? So there's drought,
the rivers are drying up.
Remember, like the Indus Valley Civilization,
it's called the Indus Valley Civilization because
it's dependent on the Indus
River, among other rivers.
Okay? So there are some drought issues.
Also, what we learn in this class is
over time,
all civilizations face eternal tensions.
Okay? And
these eternal tensions can be
divided into two major tensions.
The first tension is a
conflict among the classes.
Okay? So the idea of elite overproduction.
You have too many people
striving for limited status.
Right? And the conflict is
mainly between upper nobility
and lower nobility.
Okay? And so here in the IBC,
we can imagine the conflict
might be between these families
that are large training houses
against families that are
small training houses.
Okay? Or it could be like
internally among the families.
Okay? But there's going to be
some social tension going on.
The other social tension that we
discuss is the idea of rat utopia.
Where, and it's basically conflict
between the old and the young.
Again, the problem in the IBC is you have
too many old people living for too long,
which means less opportunities
arise for achievement for the young.
Okay? And that creates conflict as well.
So what we believe that it also is
that during this time, there
was massive social tension
within the IBC.
And some people would even say
it was a revolutionary time.
Okay? When old customs and
old mores were being overthrown.
Okay? Because
of climate change, the people in the Angelovo
culture now are forced to leave the steppes.
These are steps are no longer
suitable for their children.
They should give up off off
the oxus value civilization
and over time they will
assimilate it into themselves okay
so the idea here is this is
not an intentional invasion okay it's
not like you have a general in an army
and they go into the oxus
value civilization and then
they conquer it okay
it's more opportunistic
where at first you're trading and
as the oxus value
civilization declines because
of trade trading networks because
of the declining trading networks
they will start to come in
and push out the people and
again the culture of these
people it's very aggressive
so there are two strategies that
they were employed the first
strategy is they might wipe
out villages okay these villages
are depopulated anyway they come in
and they wipe everyone out which
means they kill everyone the second strategy
is to come in they'll kill all the men
and marry all the woman okay and
again this is a gradual
process of assimilation cultural conquest
but it's not a military invasion okay does
that make sense now after
the internal culture and
the oxus culture merge this
creates a new civilization a new
culture called proto
-indo -iranian okay
which should give
off a
new outer
outer outer outer outer
Zoroastrianism comes from this
merger of the Proto
-Iranian culture into the Iranian plateau.
This is a process we call
synchronization, by the way.
Where two major religions merge
and share the same gods.
There are three distinct characteristics
of the Proto -Indo -Iranian culture
that becomes salient in the
new Zoroastrian religion.
The first is the use of a
ritual drink called soma.
Again, you don't have to know this,
but I'm just telling
you the cultural impact.
Soma comes from the Proto
-Indo -Iranian culture.
Second is the worship
of fire, fire rituals.
Fires are used heavily
in the religious practice.
As we know, Zoroastrianism
does use a lot of fire rituals.
The last is horse sacrifice.
Meaning that warriors are
buried with their horses.
This is an emphasis on the
warrior culture of these people.
Okay? Okay? So that's
what happens in Iran.
They become the Persian people.
We will discuss the Persian
people at a later point.
Okay? Not now, but I just want
you to know this is what happened.
These people will also push into the IBC.
And over time, and this is a
process that takes about 500 years,
they'll push out the indigenous people.
Okay? And then
the indigenous people
move into South India.
Where they merge with the folk culture.
The animism of the local people there.
Okay? And guys,
what's amazing about this is this
process will create two
major world religions
that are still influential today.
Okay? The first we know as Hinduism.
Hinduism is the merger,
the synchronization of Proto
-Indo -Iranian religions.
And then the second is the integration of the
local religion with the local IBC religion.
Okay? And as the IBC pushes south,
this will create a new
religion called Buddhism.
Okay? All right?
But Buddhism is just the major one.
There are others that are being
created as well through this process.
Right? The others are
being Jainism and Shikism.
And again, these are the major ones.
Okay? That are still with us today.
Like basically this
process created thousands,
tens of thousands of new religions.
All right? So this is what happened.
It's not a military conquest.
It's not an invasion. But
it's a process of, you could
argue, cultural genocide.
Okay? Where new people come in and over
time, because they are aggressive,
experiencing opportunities in culture,
they will eventually
take over the culture.
Okay? Mainly by the...
Marrying the local woman. Because the
people who come in are basically males.
Okay? They will marry the local woman.
And they will either kill
or enslave the local man.
And this is where we get the
caste system from in India.
All right? So
this is a more subtle
explanation of the Indo
-Iran invasion theory.
Okay? And this is what
scholars today accept happened.
And again, what's really important
is to avoid generalizations
and simplifications.
Because this is a process that
took about 300 years, 400 years.
And there are different strategies
employed by different people.
Some of it was peaceful.
Some of it was violent.
Okay? It was a mix. It's
hard for us to generalize.
But the overall general effect
is the creation of Hinduism
and Buddhism.
Which now are the two
major world religions.
Okay? Any questions?
But thanks for the question, Nicol.
Any more questions? Before I move on.
..
....
..... .
. That's right. .
Yep..
Okay. So, that's a great
question Doug, okay?
So, when you trade, there's always a
problem of piracy and banantry, right?
So, how do you protect
yourselves against that?
Okay. We know like
Mesopotamia became violent
because it was being
surrounded by violence, right?
The nomads in Arabia, the nomads in the Zagos
Mountains were all pretty violent people.
You had to be because to survive, you
had to be aggressive and opportunistic.
So, how is it the, sorry,
the IVC was able to, be peaceful
yet at the same time trade?
And the solution is they set up colonies
and trade partners in
order to facilitate trade,
okay? So, we know for example, they
traded heavily with the Oxus civilization.
There were lots of trade agreements,
long -term trade agreements.
We also know they had a colony
within the Oxus Valley civilization,
okay? We know they traded heavily
with a place called Dilman,
which is now modern day. Okay?
So, these are their main trading partners.
And so, you would think their
trading partners were the ones
who were responsible for
local security, okay?
We can also suspect they also went to other
places as well to seek new trading partners.
What's important about this world is this
is still a relatively peaceful world.
There's tremendous violence in
Sumer, but that's still rare,
right? And there's some unique, you know,
characteristics about Sumer
that make it a violent people.
But in this world, and this
is about 5,000 years ago,
people are still relatively peaceful.
Organized warfare is still new
and rare in the human experience.
And that's why I think the
experience in Mesopotamia was
so shocking because the idea
that you could sack a city,
the idea that you could
kill hundreds of people,
give off ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice you can trust basically yeah okay
and any more questions before I continue
yeah I'm actually moving
into Buddhism okay
and but any more questions
before I continue okay
so the last thing I want
to discuss is what is
the legacy of the IBC they were great
civilization are they completely lost to us what
is your contribution to Western civilization
so
the legacy of Egypt are the pyramids
right we know Egypt because
of the pyramids the legacy
of Mesopotamia are many
they invented a lot of things like
writing cuneiform also
they introduced world
literature right the
epic of Gilgamesh what
I want to argue now is the
legacy of the IBC is in their
special spiritual practice
okay their spiritual values
so
if you look at Hinduism
okay it's very different from Jorastinism
and that's kind of strange because
they're both proto indo
-iranian religions right
but let's look at very
quickly at Hinduism and
it isn't believes the reality we
live in is false okay
the reality is called Brahmin
the true absolute reality
so
we live in this false reality as we
live in this false reality we collect
karma karma is basically just an
accounting of your good deeds
and your bad deeds and
guess what throughout your life you're
gonna accumulate more bad deeds than your argument than your good deeds
and
your karma means your soul
called the admin is
stuck here okay because
the Brahman it's pure you know you you can only
return to Brahman to heaven if you're a pure person
so
it will take many lifetimes
for you to cleanse
your soul your admin in order to return
to the Brahman this process of cleansing
your soul it's what they
call Dharma okay Dharma
the right path
if you if the Dharma over thousands
of lifetimes if your Dharma is correct if
you have cheap Dharma you
achieve what is called moksha
which is basically liberation moksha releases
you your soul from the physical world
and also you return to the Brahman where
you will live eternally
in paradise okay that
is the one of the
basic ideas of Hinduism
another really important
idea of Hinduism is this
entire process is being meditated
or sorry mediated or gatekeep
by priests called Brahmins okay
so
you think being a good person is enough no
it's not you have to listen to the Brahman
because only the Brahman understand the
Brahman and the Brahman is the Brahman and the Brahman is the Brahman understands Dharma
and depending on who
you are your Dharma will be different
so
in Hinduism there's a
hierarchy okay at the very top are
of course the priest the Brahman because
they have access to spiritual
knowledge below them are the warriors
and the Kings and
then below them are the
farmers and the merchants
who keep the economy running
and that at the very
bottom are the servants and
the laborers okay now what's what's
really interesting about the
system is this
system can be differentiated
by the color of one skin right
because remember the
Polar Indo -Iranians they
have white skin the IBC
culture the The people
who call the pro -Darwinians, no, sorry,
the pro -Darwinians,
they have darker skin. So
the IVC people of the lower
class don't intermix with
the pro -Indo -Iranians.
And so basically the pro -Indo -Iranians
accumulated and centralized power
through the idea of Hinduism,
they're the priest class. So
that's a basic theory of Hinduism.
And again, Hinduism is an
extremely complex religion.
I don't want to oversimplify it, but
I have no choice because I want
to explain the differences, okay?
So in this system, who's
really unhappy now?
In this system? Which group of people
are very upset with this system?
Can you guys echo?
Can you applaud?
Can you clarify what we've learned in
this semester and answer the question,
all these four groups,
who's the unhappiest?
And who most wants change,
or revolutionary change?
Excuse me? The lower nobility.
The lower nobility, and who's the
lower nobility in this system?
The kings, okay?
Does that make sense? The kings actually
in this system are the lower nobility.
The upper nobility are the Brahmins.
Because it's the Brahmins
who control access
to the Brahmin, okay?
And so the kings must obey the priests.
So the kings aren't happy with this.
And so from this conflict,
you have the creation of Buddhism, right?
Remember, Sirhatta Gautama,
who was considered the first Buddha, he was
actually a prince before he became a Buddha.
And the man most responsible
for spreading Buddhism in India
and around the world, his name is Ashoka,
he was the king, the emperor
of the Moran Empire.
And he was the one who
institutionalized Buddhism
as state religion,
who sponsored missionary
projects to China.
His highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest Nirvana.
You don't need the Brahmins to access
spiritual enlightenment. You
can do it by yourself through
spiritual guidance by monks.
That's a major difference. As you can see,
Buddhism is, in many respects,
a revolutionary religion to overthrow
the power of the Brahmin class.
In response to Buddhism,
what did the Brahmins do?
Do you guys know? They
created the caste system.
After the rise of Buddhism,
Hinduism started to implement what
we call today the caste system.
Which is to say,
these classes must
separate from each other.
They are not allowed to intermingle.
They're not even allowed
to touch each other.
to touch each other's food.
These two at the very bottom are
what we call today the untouchables.
This system was developed
by the Hindu priest,
the Brahmins, in response
to the threat of Hinduism.
Now over time, because Hinduism,
like the Proto -Iranian
people, are aggressive,
expansionist, opportunistic, they
will defeat Buddhism in this struggle.
And the one way, one really important way,
is to defeat Buddhism is
by adopting most of Buddhism's practices.
So like yoga meditation, and also Nirvana.
The Hindu Brahmins will adopt
whatever is popular in Buddhism.
Another thing that the
Hindu priest will do is,
they will start basically assimilating
other religions as well. So
most Indians throughout its history
believed in their local folklore gods.
Eventually all these gods will be
assimilated into the Hindu hierarchy.
That's why you have like a million
gods in the Hindu religion.
Because they were all, over time,
assimilated into the hierarchy.
And obviously, these gods are lesser gods.
The higher gods, the Holy
Trinity, are Brahmin gods.
Okay? All right. So
now's the chance for Doug
to ask his question about
Buddhism before I continue.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So maybe you
get the chance to ask that.
Go back to the point about the IEP,
the Weston -Bowinger.
Yeah. So way,
way back a bunch ago, you were talking
about the early Indo -European ideas.
That's right. Right? And there's
been a lot of archaeological work.
That's right. To put
that back together. Yep.
Do you know if there's been a similar process
looking at the different Indian religions,
like Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism?
Yeah. And is there a certain
common denominator that
perhaps could be taken back to the IEP?
Okay. Great question. Okay?
So what is the IVC religion,
the portal religion?
Okay. I want to make an argument.
And again, it's speculation.
It's a very strange argument.
And most scholars probably will not agree.
I think the religion of
the IVC is Proto -Buddhism.
And the reason why is,
if you look at Zoroastrianism,
and you look at Proto -Indo -Iranian,
the religion, there are a
lot of similarities. Okay?
And Proto -Zoroastrianism actually fits into the
larger Proto -Indo -European religion framework.
When you look at Hinduism,
you've got this strange idea,
a belief in karma, dharma,
reincarnation, impermanence,
Brahma, the ultimate reality.
Like this is not part of the Proto
-Indo -European religion in anywhere.
Okay? So at the same time, Hinduism,
Buddhism, Jainism, and
Shikism all share this
fundamental belief in the world
that this world is a false reality.
It's a reality created
by our false beliefs.
And if we learn to tame our emotions,
if we learn to see the
underlying reality governing
all human structure,
then we will be released from this world.
Okay? Now, where would that come from?
That must have come from the IVC
because there would be no other place.
Also, it explains why these religions,
have such huge followings in India, right?
They don't have any followings
anywhere else. Okay?
Like Hinduism is basically
localized to India.
So is Jainism, so is Shikism. So
they are appealing to a fundamental
sense of the world among Indians.
They're basically appealing
to nostalgia. Right?
And where is this nostalgia from?
It must be from the IVC.
Okay? So I would make that argument.
I would make that argument. I
would believe, I would bet that
if we're able to construct
the religion of the IVC,
the proto -religion,
we would see a proto -Buddhism.
Okay? The beginnings of Buddhism.
It would be very different.
Okay? Because Buddhism evolved
over thousands of years.
But the underlying
assumptions about the world,
basically the idea of oneness.
Okay? Okay?
The idea of false reality.
I think these two ideas would
be very apparent in the IVC.
As they are apparent now in all
four major Indian religions.
Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism, and Shikism.
Okay? Do you want to continue or?
No, no, no, no, no. I'm finished.
But like do you want to
respond to my argument?
No, it's okay. Okay.
And I think that's a good argument.
Are you guys following along?
Does it make sense to you guys?
In fact, I would argue
that
we as humans fundamentally have
a nostalgia for these two ideas.
Oneness and false reality.
Okay? Because if you
look at the West, okay?
If you look at us today,
there are two ideas.
The most powerful today
in Western civilization.
The first idea is Plato's
Allegory of the Cave.
Right? The idea that we
live in a shadow world.
And the truth is out there.
But we have to seek it.
It's a very powerful idea.
Right? And it's very similar, by the way,
to the ideas found in
Hinduism and Buddhism.
Okay? The Allegory of the Cave
is the first powerful idea.
And then the second powerful idea
is the idea of the Second Coming.
The return of Jesus.
Because what does the
return of Jesus signify?
It signifies paradise on earth.
It signifies the destruction
of our current reality
and the replacement of a new reality
that creates oneness,
completeness, and wholeness on earth.
So in many ways, I think
that's a good argument.
This is very similar to what
the Indians are proposing as well. So
what this is saying is
at a fundamental level,
everyone has nostalgia for a distant past.
And what is this distant past?
The distant past is the idea of animism.
So remember, 10,000 years
ago, 20,000 years ago,
we were in the Ice Age.
We were hunter -gatherers.
And the way we saw the world was very
different from the way we see the world today.
Okay? Back then, if you
were a hunter -gatherer,
you could only think you were the
same as the tree or as the animal.
Okay? It's the idea of oneness.
We're no different. We're
all part of the life cycle.
We're all part of Mother Nature.
Okay? The Mother Goddess. All right?
We also believe we inhabit different
realities at the same time.
Right? We live in this world,
which is the material reality.
We're also inhabiting the
spiritual reality as well.
And what we do spiritually matters a
lot more than what we do materially.
Okay? So we can hunt and
kill animals as long as we pay the
proper respects to the animals we kill.
As long as we contribute spiritually.
We contribute spiritually
to the cycle of life
and death. Okay?
So I think that's where
Buddhism comes from.
It comes from animism.
This Buddhism became reinforced
and became much more concrete
because it was experiencing
a reality in Mesopotamia
and Egypt that
was abhorrent to the
people experiencing it.
Okay? War goes against
the human experience.
Inequality and corruption in ways
goes against the human experience.
We fundamentally believe
this to be evil and wrong.
Okay? So that
is my argument about the IBC.
Any questions?
Any comments?
You seem to believe that
human beings are incredibly benevolent
and kind until they're back to the
state they've been trained to be.
Okay. That's a good question.
Do I believe that human nature
is fundamentally benevolent?
I don't believe human
nature is benevolent.
I believe humans naturally seek
a spiritual understanding of the world.
I think humans want to know why.
Why are we here? Where are we going?
Where do we come from? Okay?
We want to know why. We're also curious.
We want to explore the world.
Okay? So I think trade
is not a new invention.
I think it's a very inherent
thing to human nature.
I think the idea of globalization.
This was a globalized
world like 5,000 years ago.
Okay? Extremely sophisticated,
complex, globalized world.
So I think that's what makes
us fundamentally human.
Okay? And you can say this is
a good thing or a bad thing.
And I would say, well, it
depends on the circumstance.
Right? But I think what drives
us as humans is our curiosity
and
our imagination.
Okay? That's what I think being human is.
And sometimes this is a good thing.
Sometimes this is a bad thing.
Okay? Sometimes in the IVC
this will lead to peace
and egalitarianism. But
this also is what drives the
idea of the second coming,
which is what's driving the
conflict in the Middle East today.
Okay? So it depends on the context.
It depends on the circumstance.
If this curiosity,
this imagination is channeled effectively,
then the idea of the second coming then I think that's a good thing.
If it's channeled opportunistically,
then it's a bad thing.
Okay? Okay, but thanks for the
question. Any more questions?
Okay. So this ends our Bronze Age unit.
Okay? So we looked at the three
major Bronze Age civilizations,
Egypt, Mesopotamia, and IVC.
Okay? Next class we'll start the Bible.
Okay? The Hebrew Bible. All right.