Okay, good morning.
So this is going to be
a very long class today
and I'm going to throw a
lot of information at you.
The reason why is I want to summarize
and review what we've
learned about Rome so far.
Compare and contrast it to the Greeks and
look forward on how the Romans
and the Greeks would influence the
development of Western civilization,
including Christianity. I'll
be throwing a lot at you today,
so if you have any questions,
please let me know.
If I'm being unclear, please let me know.
Just raise your hand. Alright, so
let's review what we know so far.
So the Romans and the Greeks are
very different civilizations.
If you remember the Greeks,
the Greeks are scattered across the Aegean
and across the Mediterranean.
They have colonies. Over the place.
So the Greeks are
primarily focused on trade.
Especially with the great
empires of the Near East.
Primarily Egypt,
Mesopotamia,
and Persia.
The three great civilizations that
we will discuss starting next week.
And so the Greeks have colonies
all over these three civilizations.
And as such, the Greeks are able
to absorb new ideas pretty easily.
And because the Greeks are
focused on trade, maritime trade,
they're very open -minded people.
Okay? So that's Greek civilization.
The Romans are completely
different because
they are across the Adriatic.
They are across the Adriatic.
In Italy. And they're inland.
So, they're a much more insular and
conservative people than the Greeks. Also,
the Romans have historically been
surrounded by very aggressive people.
Including the Latins, the
Sabians, the Tristians.
And so Rome has always had to struggle.
To survive in this very
hostile environment.
And in order to survive,
they developed a cultural system
that made them the world's greatest
military machine. Okay? And
the three pillars of
this culture are piety.
Right? Piety. Obedience
and loyalty to the gods.
To Rome. To the Greeks.
And to your fathers.
Second principle is the idea of liberty.
Which puts the nobility at the very heart
and center of Roman society.
Liberty means no kings.
Okay? No dictators.
No tyrants. And the third and most
important pillar is the idea of repubblica.
Right? The public good. Right?
The idea here is everyone
must sacrifice himself for the honor
and glory of Rome.
In fact, there's a competition.
You want prestige by winning
new territory for Rome.
Okay? And
this is a great system if you are a poor,
small nation always at war
and under threat from larger nations.
So remember in 216 BCE,
Hannibal destroyed every Roman army.
But at the same time, the Romans
were able to rally themselves
and ultimately defeat Carthage
in the Second Punic War.
Okay? So it's a great
system if you're a small
and poor nation always at
war with larger nations.
But this system breaks down
when you become a tyrant.
So you're a rich, big empire.
And you're the major hegemon in the area.
And this system will lead to three
major problems in the Roman Republic.
Corruption. Division.
Right? Civil wars.
The first one between Marius and Sulla.
And then between Julius Caesar and Pompey.
And then finally between
Octavian and Mark Anthony.
Okay? And also inequality.
So now Rome is in crisis.
And the ultimate resolution to
all these problems
was the beginning
of the empire.
Okay? The emperor. So
Octavian became the emperor.
He is now known as Augustus Caesar.
Okay? And
again what he does is he centralizes
all military authority in his hands.
Egypt is now his private estate.
And he uses it to bankroll the army
which is now composed of
professional soldiers.
Before they were citizen soldiers.
So they only volunteered
when Rome was at war.
But now in the empire there's
a professional standing army.
And they serve for like
20 years or 30 years.
And they're all paid by one man.
The emperor. Through his
land holdings in Egypt.
Okay? He also established something
called the Praetorian Guard.
And the Praetorian Guard is
basically the secret police of Rome.
Okay? So there are no soldiers in Rome.
But there's a Praetorian Guard.
And they're responsible for
peace and security in Rome.
And they're only responsible to one man.
Okay? The emperor.
So even though, but even though
Augustus Caesar has conquered Rome
and basically most of the world.
He still has three major problems that
he must resolve if he
is to be emperor fully.
Okay? The first problem he must
solve is the question of legitimacy.
Why is he emperor? And
this is the third prevention of
the crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown
the founding of the Roman
Republic. Now Julius Caesar
and Augustus Caesar are not,
do not come from either of these
two myths or families, okay?
So he has to construct a new myth that
shows that
his family called the
Julii go way back.
They go back to before Romulus,
okay? So while he was alive,
Julius Caesar planted the seeds of this.
Remember Julius Caesar is
a great myth maker, okay?
So the myth he came up with is this.
There was a man named Aeneas and
Aeneas is from Troy, right?
When Troy was destroyed,
Aeneas was able to escape
with some survivors
and they came to Italy and
they built the foundations
that would become Rome, okay?
So in other words,
Romulus is descended from Aeneas
but Julius Caesar is also
descended from Aeneas,
okay?
So that
is how Augustus Caesar
will cement his legitimacy,
right? So that's how he will cement his legitimacy,
right? So that's how he will promote the idea that
his ancestor was Aeneas, who
is the real founder of Rome,
okay? So he's winning a new myth
and he's trying to popularize it.
So that's the first problem he's
trying to solve, legitimacy.
This second problem he's trying to solve
is like a new Roman cultural identity,
okay? So remember,
the old Roman cultural
identity was based on!
! piety, liberty, and repulka.
And this creates problems in the emperor,
because remember, Marcus' Buddhist and
Desmond's Buddhist, they thought
that they were descendants of, sorry,
they thought they were
descendants of Lucius' Buddhist,
and therefore, they had a responsibility
to kill all kings, all tyrants, and
that's why they
assassinated Julius Caesar.
So you can't allow this
cultural identity to exist,
right? Because it will encourage other
Buddhists to come kill you, the emperor.
So you have to change this.
You have to get rid of the
idea of liberty and repulka.
You have to promote a new Roman
identity focused on obedience.
Piety and obedience. And
then there's a third problem that
Augustus Caesar must resolve as emperor,
which is this. Even though
the Romans have conquered
most of the world, okay,
basically the Mediterranean world,
culturally, it's the
Greeks who are dominant.
Because the Greeks have
a superior culture.
They have Homer, they have
Plato, they have Thucydides,
they have Aeschylus.
So all Romans acknowledge the fact
that Greek culture is superior.
And as Romans embrace Greek culture,
Augustus Caesar believes
they are corrupted, okay?
For Augustus Caesar, he
believes that Greek culture,
it is too hedonistic.
And that's ultimately what
happened to Mark Anthony.
Mark Anthony was this good Roman who
went off to Egypt
and became corrupted and seduced
by Cleopatra and Greek culture.
Mark Anthony became more Greek.
And that's why he betrayed Rome.
Augustus Caesar also believed
that's why Rome began
descending into civil wars.
Because Rome was starting
to embrace Greek culture
and it made everyone more individualistic,
more hedonistic, more selfish.
And that's why they
fought these civil wars.
Okay? So Augustus Caesar now has a very strong and
very strong relationship with the Roman Empire. And
he has to somehow destroy Greek culture
or the influence of Greek
culture on the Roman soul.
And he knows the very essence,
the very basis of Greek culture is Homer.
Especially the Iliad and the Odyssey.
These two books were essentially
the Bible of Greek civilization.
This is how children were educated.
When they were young,
they memorized the Iliad
and they memorized the Odyssey.
And that's what taught
them how to speak well,
how to think well, and how to debate well.
Okay? So
Augustus Caesar understands that
to defeat Homer, he needs to have another,
he needs to create a Roman epic
to replace Homer in the school of Rome.
So he invited a man named Virgil,
who
at this time is considered
the greatest living Roman poet,
to write another epic in Latin
to replace Homer as a cornerstone
of the education system.
Okay? And he wrote
something called the Iliad,
which is really about the
journey of Aeneas as he,
as he, creates Rome, as he founds Rome.
Okay? So
from 29 BCE until 19 BCE,
for about over 10 years,
Virgil worked on the Iliad under
direct supervision of Augustus Caesar.
Okay? So they were basically co -authors.
Virgil was a poet. He was the one
who could put the words together.
But it was Augustus Caesar who had the
vision of what the Iliad should be. And
the Iliad will accomplish all
three of these major challenges.
It will establish the primacy of the
July family as the first family of Rome.
It will establish a new Roman
cultural identity focused
on piety over liberty.
And it will show
that Greek culture is one of corruption
and hypocrisy. is one of hedonism.
And it must be repelled.
Okay? So you can make the argument that
Virgil's Iliad is the
greatest work of propaganda
ever in human history.
Right? So that's what
I will show you today.
Okay? To do this,
what I will do is compare and
contrast the Iliad and the
Odyssey with the Iliad,
to show you how different the Roman
worldview is from the Greek worldview.
Okay? So before I start,
are there any questions
about this framework?
Is this clear to you?
Okay. All right.
So let's start with the Iliad.
Okay. Okay.
And remember, this is
a very important idea.
Homer and Virgil are two
different individuals.
They're both poets. But Homer was writing
when Greek civilization
was just beginning.
So he's trying to create
the seeds of civilization.
Okay? He's trying to be a great
teacher. Virgil is writing
when Rome is an empire that
is everywhere and everything.
It's basically God. Okay?
So he's trying to,
to teach people
how to be part of this empire.
Do you understand? So you can
argue that Homer is an educator,
whereas Virgil is a propagandist.
All right? Okay. So let's
talk about the Iliad.
Okay. So the first thing is,
the Iliad is a very complicated world.
It's a universe unto itself
with like dozens of characters.
Okay? I'm only going to
focus on one character,
Achilles, and tell his story.
Okay? But, but, but please be aware,
the story I'm telling,
it is my interpretation.
There are different interpretations. Okay?
But it's the one interpretation
found in the universe of the Iliad.
Okay? So the basic
story, it's very simple.
Helen is the queen of Sparta,
married to the king of Sparta, Menelaus.
She is seduced by the prince
of Troy, named Paris.
They fall in love, and they
run off together to Troy.
Menelaus and his brother, again, Menon,
they raise an army to rescue Helen,
or to retrieve Helen. And they
take Helen back from the Trojans,
who refuse to give her up. And
what follows is a ten -year siege of Troy.
And the Greeks aren't
really getting anywhere,
because Troy, it is the largest
city in the world at this time.
It's a walled city, and
the Greeks don't know how to
break through the Trojan walls.
Okay? The Iliad starts when
Achilles, who is the greatest warrior,
of the Greeks, he gets into
a fight with Agamemnon.
They get into a fight, and
Achilles calls Agamemnon a dog.
You insult me, I fight for you,
I will not refuse to fight for you.
I will let the Trojans kill all of you.
And Agamemnon, the king,
wants to save face, so he tells
Achilles, I don't need you.
Okay? But, in fact,
the Greeks do need Achilles, because the
Trojans have a great warrior, named Hector.
And Hector recognizes that Achilles
has retired from the battlefield,
and Hector leads his
army against the Greeks.
Okay? And they push
the Greeks so far back,
the Greeks are now trapped
on their ships by the coast.
And what Hector wants to do is
burn down these ships, because
if he burns down these ships, the
Greeks cannot resupply themselves,
and they will eventually die in Troy.
Okay? So at this point,
Agamemnon has no choice but
to beg Achilles to return
to the battlefield,
because only Achilles can
defeat Hector in battle.
But Agamemnon doesn't
want to lose face, so
he sends a delegation of generals,
led by a man named Odysseus,
to beg Achilles to return
to the battlefield.
Okay? So Odysseus goes and sees
Achilles, on an inner ship,
and Odysseus says,
Listen, Achilles, we're dying out here.
If you don't fight for us,
we're all going to die.
Hector is destroying us.
If you fight for us, Agamemnon
will give you everything.
Okay? All these treasures
we are promised in Troy,
we'll give to you. Agamemnon
will give you anything you want.
He'll give you the world. And Achilles,
because he's an asshole, says,
No, I want Agamemnon
to come beg me himself.
Okay? So this goes nowhere.
And Agamemnon refuses to come beg, so
the Trojans advance further
and further, and they're about
to burn their ships. Patroclus
sees his best friends with Achilles,
and he sees that Achilles,
is conflicted. Because Achilles
wants to jump into the fray.
Achilles had a prophecy
before he came to Troy.
Okay? The prophecy is
this. He has a choice.
He can either choose to
die an old man at home,
and be a nobody, or come to Troy,
die young at battle, in the battle, and
be remembered forever as the
greatest champion of the Greeks.
And for Achilles, that's not,
that's not a choice, because for him,
as a warrior, he loves to fight.
He can only achieve eudaimonia in battle.
Okay? So for him to sit in a ship
and watch the Greeks being destroyed,
it is the worst punishment on earth.
But at the same time,
Achilles, he's arrogant,
he's vain, and he demands
Agamemnon to come apologize.
Which Agamemnon's not going to do. Okay?
Agamemnon would rather
see the entire Greek
army demolished than to
apologize to Achilles.
So, Patroclus tells Achilles, listen,
let me jump into the
battle to save the ships.
And Achilles says, fine,
I will let you stop the Trojan advance,
but do not, under any circumstances,
fight Hector in battle.
So, Patroclus jumps into battle
and he fights the Trojans.
And then what does he do?
He fights Hector, right?
And then what happens? He gets killed.
Achilles hears about the
death of Patroclus and
Achilles is so angry at the
death of his best friend
that he forgives Agamemnon.
He lets go of his anger at
Agamemnon and directs it at Hector.
He jumps into battle, he
challenges Hector to a duel,
and he kills Hector.
Okay? Then
what he does is he takes
Hector's dead body,
he ties it to his chariot,
and then he drags Hector's
body around the walls of Troy.
And on top of the walls of Troy
are Hector's parents, King
Priam and Queen Hecuba.
And they are screaming in anguish.
They hate this devil
who not only killed their son Hector,
but is now humiliating and
mutilating him in front of
the entire Trojan people.
Okay? So at this point,
you would think that
Achilles has achieved immortality.
He's defeated Hector in battle, he saved
the Greek army, and he'd be very happy.
But it turns out
he falls into a deep depression.
He cannot sleep.
He cannot eat. All he does
is think about Patroclus.
But he's so depressed, he
can't even cry for Patroclus.
So, this is
where Homer is really
the first psychologist.
Because Achilles is feeling this way
because he is raptured by the devil.
And this is not true. And
this is not true. And this is not true.
this is not true.
And this is not true.
grief of Patroclus to go into battle okay
so well knowing it
because because Achilles
lacks self -awareness he is
trapped by his guilt over
the death of Patroclus
and he is taking out his rage on Hector
okay he is supposed to return Hector's
body for a ransom to the Trojans
because everyone believes at this time
that the only day can only find peace
in the afterlife if they're buried okay
so
for Achilles to torment Hector's
body like this is means that
Hector can never find peace in
the afterlife his father
Priam is back in Troy
and he can't sleep either because
he's depressed over
what's happened to his son
so eventually the gods broker a peace deal
okay and they tell prime to go to Achilles
and Achilles will return
the body to prior all right
so
late one night prime
sneaks into the tent and
he's standing behind behind Achilles who
is busy discussing military matters with
his generals at this point
Priam can take out a knife
and stab Achilles to death and he wants to
because he's so angry
at this man who's killed
and mutilated his son Hector instead
and
this is the genius of Homer
okay Priam kneels down
and kisses the hand of Achilles the man
who has killed his beloved son
and
in response Achilles stands
and he is in in awe of this old man,
who at this moment has
demonstrated more courage,
more strength, than
Achilles has ever witnessed,
okay? So in this act of submission,
Priam has emotionally defeated Achilles,
and Achilles is ashamed of himself.
And by forgiving Achilles,
Priam allows Achilles
to now forgive himself.
Okay, does that make
sense to you? All right.
And so the two
then start to become friends,
because in the face of Priam,
Achilles sees his father, Peleus, and
he pities Priam for having lost his son.
And in the face of Achilles, Priam
sees Achilles, his son, Hector.
And they both hug and they cry.
And this is the first time that
Achilles has been able to cry
since the death of Patroclus.
And these tears release him
from the ghost of Patroclus,
who is haunting him, okay?
And this is how the Iliad ends.
What we've witnessed in the Iliad
is a character transformation,
of Achilles,
from a cold -blooded, merciless,
vain and arrogant warrior,
into a man who is capable of pity,
self -reflection, and
self -forgiveness, okay?
And you can argue that this
is a process of civilization.
And so the point of the Iliad is, even
though it's about war, it's really making
the argument that love, and love is the key to the Iliad.
It's the basis of civilization.
It's what unites us and inspires us.
Love is the unifying force
of the universe, right?
Even though Priam and Achilles
are the most bitter enemies,
because of Hector's love for,
because of Priam's love for Hector,
and because of Achilles'
love for his father, Peleus,
they're able to find common
ground and become friends.
That's the Iliad. Does that make sense?
So again, it is arguably the greatest
work of literature in human history.
And this is only one interpretation.
There are different interpretations,
okay? But you can see how rich and
complex, sophisticated the Iliad is.
It is, by reading it, you'll be inspired,
you'll be inspired, you'll be inspired to
reimagine yourself and the world around you.
That's how powerful it is. All right,
now let's move on to the Odyssey.
The Iliad is about Achilles and
its transformation into self -awareness.
The Odyssey is about Odysseus.
And unlike Achilles,
Odysseus does not want to
go to the Trojan War, okay?
It's not about the Trojan War. Achilles
jumps at the chance to win glory at Troy.
But Odysseus was given a different,
was given a prophecy, which is this.
If he goes to Troy, he'll
be gone for 20 years.
He lives in Ithaca with
his wife, Penelope,
and they just had a newborn
son, Temuchus, okay?
And the prophecy is if you go to
Troy, you'll be gone for 20 years.
10 years at war in Troy,
10 years lost at sea.
And Odysseus, who loves his family,
does not want to go to war, okay?
So he pretends to be crazy, insane.
And so what he does is he takes salt
and a plow.
And he plows the field and salts
it, which kills the field, okay?
So clearly this is a sign of insanity.
But the Greek soldiers
who come to retrieve him
are determined to kill him.
They're determined to get
him. Because they know that
Odysseus is the most strategic
and the wisest of the Greeks.
He will be the one who
will deliver victory
to the Greeks in Troy, because
Odysseus will come up with the
Trojan horse strategy, right?
He will, it is his idea,
the Trojan horse strategy.
So they need him. So to test him,
to see if he's really
mad, they put his son,
Tanarchus, who's only like,
in front of him, okay?
So if he's really crazy,
he would run over his son.
If he's not crazy, then he would stop.
And obviously he's not going
to run over his son, okay?
So his trick has been revealed,
and he's forced to go to war.
And he hates going to war, okay?
But he's determined to win
the war for the Greeks.
The first reason is he
believes the Trojans are unjust.
How dare you steal
another man's wife, right?
Second reason is he wants
to build a legacy for his
son, Tamarchus, right?
He wants to go home to Ithaca
and tell his son what a hero he is, okay?
He wants to build a legacy
for his son, right?
And the third thing is,
he wants to go to Rome, he
wants to reunite the family
which has been broken, right?
Menelaus and Helen. Just as he wants
to return to his wife Penelope,
okay? So this is what
we call his worldview.
The way he understands the world.
And the worldview is what
allows us to be human
and to exist, right?
The worldview explains to us
who we are, what do we want,
and what we should do.
The problem is,
after Odysseus comes up with the
Trojan horse, they sneak into the city
and they open the gates,
the Greeks come flooding in, okay?
And now it's total mayhem because the Greeks
are killing everyone inside the city.
Odysseus kills a Trojan
soldier who's attacking him.
The Trojan soldier falls to the ground.
And then suddenly,
his wife screams at the
death of her husband
and she comes and sobs
at the body of her dead husband, okay?
And this creates something
called cognitive dissonance.
Okay? Cognitive dissonance is when the
worldview and the reality do not match.
There's conflict between the
reality and the worldview.
Remember, Odysseus came to Troy
to... for justice,
to build a legacy for his son,
Timarchus, and to reunite a family.
And what he's doing now
is destroying families.
The Greeks are just massacring everyone.
It's not justice.
It's just slaughter. It's
just complete mayhem.
And so what happens is,
Odysseus is traumatized by what he sees.
Okay? And this is what
we call PDSD, right?
Post Traumatic Stress Order.
And after Troy, Odysseus
becomes lost at sea.
He becomes like a sex slave
to a goddess named Calypso.
Okay? So he's stuck on an
island for seven years,
and there's a goddess called
Calypso who's trapped him,
and he's basically like a sex slave.
Okay? And every day, when he's not
having sex with Calypso, which sucks,
he's crying on the beach. Okay?
He has PDSD. And
he doesn't even want to go home because
he's ashamed to face his family.
He's so ashamed by what's happened
in Troy, he cannot face his family.
So he's just stuck where he is.
Meanwhile, at home, Penelope, his wife,
she is waiting for him to return.
But, after some time,
people think, oh, Odysseus must be dead.
So there's about a hundred young
men, a hundred suitors, who
come and demand her hand in marriage.
Okay? But she refuses to
believe Odysseus is dead.
So she falls into depression as well.
Right? She's waiting for
her husband to return.
But all the signs are that he's dead.
She's been courted by a hundred suitors.
And she can't say no to any of them
because she's afraid her
husband is really dead.
And she doesn't want to be alone.
Okay? So she becomes depressed as well.
She becomes paralyzed.
So she's stuck. Right?
This means that Timarchus, the son,
is stuck as well. And he
becomes a depressed teenager.
Because if Odysseus were dead,
he would inherit his legacy.
He could become his own man.
But Odysseus is not dead yet.
No one knows if he's dead or alive.
So he's stuck where he is.
If Penelope were just to marry
and go somewhere else, he
would inherit the property.
But she's just stuck in her room.
So he's depressed as well.
So this entire family, okay, is depressed.
Odysseus is depressed. Penelope,
Timarchus, they're all depressed.
So they're just stuck there.
Athena, who is the
goddess of wisdom, okay,
and she favors Odysseus.
Athena sees all this from up high Mount
Olympus and she pities the family.
And she resolves to bring the
family back together again.
So she goes and tells Calypso, hey,
you've had your fun,
but you have to let go.
So now Odysseus is free to go home.
And Athena tells Odysseus,
listen, do not, when you go home,
you can tell Timarchus who you are, but
don't tell Penelope and anyone else who
you are because you might be killed.
There's a hundred suitors who would
kill you if they knew who you were.
So Athena disguises him as a different
person, as a beggar, basically.
Beggar. And so, when
Odysseus returns to Ithaca,
the first thing he wants to know is,
does Penelope still love him?
Remember, Odysseus is suffering from
post -traumatic stress disorder,
okay? He's lost his ability
to fight, to imagine.
He's lost his capacity for love. So
he doesn't even know if
his wife still loves him.
So he meets with Penelope, okay?
And again, he's still disguised.
Penelope has no idea who he is.
And he cannot reveal himself to Penelope.
But he sees Penelope is distraught.
And he tries to comfort
Penelope by telling her
that he has seen Odysseus.
Odysseus is still alive. Penelope breaks down
in tears at the thought that Penelope is dead.
But Penelope is still alive.
And then she asks Odysseus,
how do you know my husband is still alive?
Prove to me
that you've met my husband.
Now, Odysseus says, I will describe
something intimate about him.
Okay? He has a brooch that
he carries on his cloak.
And this brooch is beautiful.
And he goes into poetic detail
and describes his brooch.
And at this point, when
Penelope hears this, she
breaks down in complete tears.
Because now she knows this beggar
must be my husband, Odysseus, in disguise.
How does she know?
Because only Odysseus would know
all the details of the brooch.
What is a brooch?
The brooch is what Penelope
gave Odysseus as Odysseus
set sail for Troy.
Right? It is a brooch.
It is Penelope's gift to him.
And it is Odysseus' promise to her
that he will return. So even though
Odysseus has lost the
brooch in war, and at sea,
the brooch is implanted in his mind.
The brooch symbolizes his
everlasting love for Penelope.
So now that Penelope knows
Odysseus has returned,
they still have to figure out how
to get rid of these hundred suitors.
How to kill them. Because they
are still a threat to the family.
So Penelope has this great plan.
She is going to organize
an archery contest.
Odysseus has a bow. If the
suitors can string the bow
and shoot a target,
then Penelope will marry that suitor.
So she organizes this competition.
And all the hundred suitors,
they fail one by one.
They cannot string the bow together. Then
the beggar, who is
Odysseus, says, let me try.
And the moment he
strings the bow together,
the suitors are afraid.
Because they know this
can only be Odysseus.
Only Odysseus can string
the bow together and use it.
And then one by one, Odysseus takes
his bow and he kills all the suitors.
What the bow symbolizes is
his identity, who he is.
The bow, by stringing it together,
it represents the resurrection,
by stringing it together,
of his worldview.
He now remembers
that he is a father, a hero,
who fights for justice.
He fights to protect his family.
That's who he is, really. Okay?
And so,
this story is the power of
love to heal trauma after war.
And again, the main message is love is
the unifying force of the world.
It is what will heal you.
It is what will bring people together.
Okay? Okay?
So that's the Iliad and the Odyssey.
Does that make sense? And again,
the argument is love is
the basis of civilization.
It is the thing that makes us human.
It is what gives us our strength,
our courage, our power.
Okay. So,
are you clear about
the Iliad and the Odyssey
before I move on to the Iliad?
Any questions? Okay.
Let's do the Iliad. Okay.
So, neither the Iliad or the Odyssey
talks about the Trojan horse.
But the Iliad, the first thing it
does is talk about the Trojan horse.
So, the Trojans wake up one day
and they find this huge Trojan horse,
wooden horse, outside the gates.
And most are like, this
must be a Greek trick.
Let's just burn it down. Okay?
But then they capture a Greek soldier.
And this Greek soldier
is very eloquent.
With logic and with beauty and with power,
he tells a false story of
how the Greeks became disheartened
by the progress of the war.
And they decide to sail home.
And to ensure their safe journey home,
they built a wooden horse for
the gods to win their favor.
Okay? And the story is
so moving and so beautiful
the Trojans believe him.
Okay? And they let the Trojan horse in.
So, the Iliad is not as subtle
as the Iliad of the Odyssey.
Okay? It's propaganda. So what
this is telling us is this.
The real Trojan horse is Greek culture.
Right? Logic,
philosophy, and theater.
Okay? That's what Greek culture is.
Logic, philosophy, and theater.
And that's what the Greek soldier uses
in order to manipulate the
Trojans to lie to them.
Okay? So the message here is if
we Romans embrace Greek culture,
embrace logic, philosophy, and theater,
then our culture will be destroyed.
The real Trojan horse is Greek culture.
Therefore, we must resist it at all costs.
So, Aeneas wakes up and
he finds the city in flames.
The Greeks are going
around massacring everyone.
Okay? So Aeneas goes
and he tries to save Priam.
He runs to the palace and Priam
is on his throne and
he sees one of his sons being
killed by Achilles' son,
Neo -Ptolemus. Okay?
Neo -Ptolemus. And
Priam curses Neo -Ptolemus.
And he says, Your father,
you insult the honor of your father.
Your father was an honorable man.
We were friends. And then
Neo -Ptolemus goes up
to Priam and kills him
and says, My father is dead.
You should join him in the underworld.
Okay? It is a horrific scene.
Okay? So what this is telling
us, again, this is not subtle.
Okay? So, there is no place for
love, friendship, and forgiveness.
That's all a lie.
It's all just trickery.
Okay? Only brutality and force
will triumph in the end.
Aeneas is trying to save Priam
but then time dies. And then he discovers
that hiding somewhere, he sees Helen.
Okay? And
he thinks that Helen is the
one responsible for all this.
She's a whore. She's a slut.
If she just did her duty,
if she just stayed at home
where she was supposed to be,
this war would have started.
So he really wants to kill her.
Okay? In fact, he is about to kill her.
Then suddenly, a goddess named Venus,
okay, also, so the Romans call her Venus.
The Greeks call her Aphrodite.
And she is the mother of Aeneas.
She appears before her son and says,
my son, you are destined
for greater things.
Leave Helen. Return to your family.
So Aeneas has no choice but
to obey the laws of the world.
He's not going to do
anything. And he runs home.
And he sees that his family is fine.
His son is named Julius.
He has a father and a wife.
And they're fine. So he's
like, okay, you guys are fine.
I'm going to go and kill some Greeks.
I'm going to die with this city.
I'm going to fight until my
dying breath to save my city.
And the wife and the father
are begging him to not go
because you are one man
against an entire army.
You're going to get killed. But
Aeneas is stubborn and
he's angry right now.
Suddenly, Julius here is on fire.
And it's like a golden crown.
And the father says, you
see, Aeneas, this is a sign.
This is a sign that your son
will be the founder of a great empire.
We know this empire to be called Rome.
Okay? And this is what stops
Aeneas from committing suicide.
He's like, okay, now I understand.
It is my duty to save
my son and my family.
So he carries his father
who is unable to walk.
He carries his son.
And he carries both of them
to safety. They're
looking for ships, okay?
And his wife follows behind.
They get to the ship. Aeneas turns around
and he discovers his wife has disappeared.
He goes back and he's discovered
that his wife has killed herself.
Why? Because she knows
that in this new world
that they're going to,
she can only be a hindrance.
Okay? She wants him to embrace
the future and let go of the past.
Also, she's afraid that if she lives,
she'll be captured and become
a slave to the Greeks.
And she does not want to
dishonor him like that.
Okay? So that's what
a good wife is, right?
Now that's a bad wife because she's
independent and she's looking for love.
But a good wife is someone who
will kill herself for her husband.
Okay? So Aeneas
and his people, they're on ships
and they end up in Carthage.
And they're guests of a queen named Dido.
And Dido falls in love with Aeneas.
They get married. And Aeneas
is very happy in Carthage.
Okay? But the gods look at
Aeneas and says, Hey, man,
we told you this many times, but
you have a destiny to go to Rome.
Your son will be the
founder of a great empire.
Okay? That's the plan.
That's the destiny. That's your mission.
That's your duty. Stop fooling around
in Carthage and do what you're told.
So Carthage, so Aeneas has to go see Dido
and say, listen, I have to go.
Okay? And Dido goes insane
because she's in love with Aeneas.
And she kills herself. Okay?
So the message here, again,
this is not subtle, okay?
The message here is
love is a disease.
Right? Love is a disease,
a plague upon the world.
It was Helen's love
that caused the Trojan War. And
it was Dido's love for Aeneas
that will cause the war between the two.
And it was the love between
Carthage and Rome. Okay?
Because before she dies, Dido
instructs her people to destroy Rome.
In the future, a great city
called Rome will arise.
You, the Carthaginian people,
have a responsibility
to honor my memory
and destroy Rome.
And that's why Hannibal
went to attack Rome.
Okay? Again, this is
not subtle propaganda.
Aeneas ends up in Italy.
Like he's supposed to. And there,
he meets the local king.
His name is Latinus. And
he's the king of the Latins.
Okay? And he is mesmerized,
stunned by the nobility of Aeneas.
And he wants his daughter to marry Aeneas.
But his daughter has already,
is already supposed to marry
another prince called Aeneas. And
this is not the crown
crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown crown
crown crown crown crown
to his friend. Eventually,
Aeneas and Ternus get into a duel,
and Aeneas overpowers Ternus.
And at the very last
minute, Ternus gives up,
surrenders his sword, and begs for mercy.
And Aeneas wants to show mercy.
He's like, I've beaten you.
You're no longer a threat. I
can show some forgiveness, okay?
I can be merciful. But then
he sees the belt.
That he gave his friend.
And he knows Ternus has killed his friend.
And so he just plunges
his spear into Ternus.
And that's how the Aeneid ends, okay?
Now, the Aeneid is very
confusing for scholars,
because it's pretty awful.
And so scholars have debated whether...
Whether or not Virgil was
able to finish the Aeneid.
And the argument is, the
ending is too abrupt,
and therefore Virgil couldn't
have finished the Aeneid.
Okay, it's unfinished. But you think
about it, it is finished, okay?
Because remember, in the Aeneid, we see a
character transformation of Achilles, right?
Well, we also see a character
transformation of Aeneas in this book.
Okay? So remember, when
Aeneas sees Helen, he
really wants to kill her.
And he only stopped because
the gods intervened, okay?
Remember, Aeneas wanted
to abandon his family and
get killed in the streets of Troy.
The gods had to send him a message, okay?
So another divine intervention.
Remember, Remember, Aeneas
wanted to stay at Calvary.
He wanted to go to Carthage and be with
Dido. So the Greeks had to send a messenger to tell him, you can't do that.
You have to fulfill your
destiny and go to Troy.
Sorry, and go to Rome, okay?
But, at the very end, when
Aeneas wanted to kill...
When Aeneas wanted to kill Churnus,
the gods didn't have to intervene, okay?
He wanted to show mercy to Churnus.
And he didn't. And he recognized,
no, my duty is to kill this guy.
You understand? Okay?
So Aeneas has become
the embodiment of piety
and duty.
Before, the gods had to
instruct him to do his duty.
Now he recognizes what his duty is.
He embraces it. Okay?
Now what's important for us to just
remember, that throughout this play...
Oh, sorry. Throughout this book,
there's the idea of destiny.
That what Aeneas is doing has
been preordained by the gods.
Because the real purpose
of Aeneas is to go to Rome
so that his son can
build the Roman Empire.
So another major message
of this book is...
The endpoint of history
is Augustus Caesar.
Okay? Everything that
is happening is to move towards,
converge to Augustus Caesar.
Because Augustus Caesar
will create the Pax Romana.
What we call the Roman Peace.
Which is the idea of eternal peace.
Peace on Earth.
Remember that before Augustus Caesar,
there were all these civil wars that were killing millions of people, right?
Well, after Augustus Caesar became...
Emperor, there is now the Pax Romana.
Eternal peace. On Earth.
And this is the endpoint of history.
The Roman Empire will mean there
will no longer be any wars.
There will no longer be any conflicts.
Why? Because
what the Roman Empire will do
is transition us from love to piety.
Okay? Homer believed that
love is the best way to live.
Love is the basis of civilization.
What the Roman Empire will show is
that piety is the basis of civilization.
Love is the force that
comes from within you.
Okay? It grows within you.
Within. But piety is what is told to you.
Okay? It is what you must accept.
Love is what you can feel.
Love is the embrace of your emotions.
Piety means the rejection
of your emotions.
Don't listen to your feelings.
Listen to what you are told.
By embracing your emotions,
you have imagination.
Okay? But
piety believes imagination is destructive.
What matters is stability and harmony.
Okay? Stability.
Stability and obedience is what
will give peace to the world.
Okay? So for Homer,
love is the unifying
force of the universe.
But for Virgil,
love is the force that creates
conflict in the universe.
Right? Think of Helen.
Think of Dido. For Homer,
the imagination is the force that creates
conflict in the universe. For Homer, the imagination is the animating force of the universe.
It is what gives life. But for Virgil,
the imagination is the destructive
force of the universe.
It is what destroys. It
is basically you disobey
that creates chaos and conflict.
And so,
we now have a transition from the
Greek world to the Roman world.
That is focused on piety.
What Virgil is trying to create
is the idea of eternity.
Right? Eternity.
Something that lasts forever. What Homer is
trying to create is the idea of infinity.
How we can create the world
through our actions and emotions.
Okay? In the Pax Romana
and the Argos of Caesar,
all you have to do is obey
and the world will be perfect.
We have come to the end of history.
History has stopped. Because
we have found perfection.
We have found the perfect model
to organize human civilization.
We are the perfection. We are the end.
Okay. And so, this is the
idea of Roman eternity.
And this marks a radical
transition in Western civilization.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Any questions? One last
point is this. Okay?
The Romans were like the most non
-creative people in the world.
Okay? They were anti -creative. So, everything
that they had, they sold them somewhere else.
Somewhere else. Okay? So,
the question then is.
Where do they get the
idea of eternity from?
Can you guess? Egypt.
Okay? Next class I will show you
that the Romans are using the
Egyptian sense of eternity.
All right? Okay.
So, I know this is a lot to take in.
But I want to give you a little bit of a
summary. So, feel free to ask some clarification on any point.
Okay? Are you okay with this?
Yes. I still have one question.
Sure. Is that
the Romans rejected the Greek culture?
Well, Augustus Caesar wants
them to reject Greek culture.
But they cannot reject Greek
culture because it's so powerful.
Right? So, you know. Okay. So,
this lecture is not about
what happens in reality.
This lecture is about
the new conception of
reality as introduced by the Roman Empire.
Okay? But eventually, this
will become the new reality.
It will take time. Okay?
Okay. So, looking ahead.
The Romans will introduce a new idea that
will make piety and obedience
the cornerstone of society.
Okay? This idea is called Christianity.
Okay. Looking ahead. Right?
Like, this is not
happening right now because
the Roman
conception is not as appealing
as the Greek conception.
Okay? But eventually, the Romans will
create a new religion called Christianity
that will dominate and
make piety the cornerstone of society
and civilization.
Okay? But looking ahead.
Any questions?
Okay. So, next class.
We will. We will discuss Egypt.