Okay, so we are doing
X in the grade today.
Let us review last class
where
we discussed the father -son dynamic
between Philip II and his son Alexander.
We said that the father,
he is the founder
and the builder of a great organization
and
as such he will have three particular
characteristics unique to him.
First of all, he will
exercise really good judgment
because he's starting with nothing and
he has to build up slowly his
nation or his organization.
Second thing that
we said is he will promote talent.
He will be a very generous and
fair -minded individual who
will actively spot talent and
create a meritocracy. Okay,
the third thing we said was
this person will be selfless,
extremely disciplined and
this person will put the greater
good before his or her own interests.
Okay, and that will inspire loyalty
from his or her workers or soldiers.
We also said the son
will be very different.
Okay, because the son is inheriting
this enterprise or this nation.
The son will focus on expansion.
The son will be a very
aggressive risk -taker.
Okay, second characteristic of the son is
because he is under the father's shadow,
he will promote obedience and loyalty.
Promote loyalty. And
the final characteristic, the final
contrast between the father and
son is the son will be very selfish
because of the father's integrity.
The son will be focused on personal glory.
The reason why is the
son is insecure, right?
The son will hear people in
the background and shadows
whispering, oh, everything you've
achieved is because of your father.
And so the son is desperate,
very anxious to prove his own self -worth.
Okay, so we see this
dynamic in literature and in history.
That's important, or or or
or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or have to test
which true or not and
if it's true it does two things okay
first thing it does is it explains
does it help us understand
better understand the motivations
and behavior of people around us and
last class we thought we
focused on for the second and
we and that really helped us
to understand his motivations
and behavior okay today but the
second thing it must do is predict
okay it has to predict the
future if this analytical model
that we have is correct and
it will allow us to predict future events
and behavior okay and
that's what I propose
today I propose to use
this model to predict the
life of academic great okay
so
from this model we
can extrapolate three characteristics of
Alexander's reign when
he takes over as king okay um
what's the first
characteristic of Alexander
when he when he becomes
king okay
I go do you have any ideas of
what he will do as king exactly okay
so the first thing we will
say is that he will focus on
expansion okay he'll be a
very aggressive risk taker
you will take risks that
are not strategically wise okay
that's the first prediction
we can make about him
what's the second prediction
we can make about him based on
this exactly
we call this a tyrant okay he's gonna be
kind of like a tyrant or
or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or or
or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or or
because he's telling people
will counter his tyranny.
So we predict he will demand complete
and total obedience from his followers.
And what's the third prediction
we can make about him?
Well, the third prediction is that he,
the question is, will he ever be happy?
When will he stop his ambition?
Never, okay? So his ambition is boundless.
So these are the three predictions we can make
about Alexander if he were to become king,
just based on our understanding
of the father -son dynamic, okay?
The first is that he will
focus on aggressive expansion.
He will take risks that his
father will not take, okay?
That's the first thing. Second thing is,
he's gonna become a tyrant who will demand
total loyalty and obedience
from his followers.
And if you, for his own good,
speak up and try to reason with him,
he will see you as a threat, as disloyal,
and as an enemy who must
be eliminated, okay?
The third prediction we can make is,
his ambition is boundless.
He will never stop expanding.
He will never stop going to war, okay?
These are the three predictions we can
make based on this analytical model, okay?
And it turns out, these three predictions
basically cap to the essence
of Alexander's life, okay?
All right? So
now I will slowly explain the life
and times of Alexander the Great.
All right, so any questions so far?
Okay, so we are using
this analytical model
to understand the life and
times of Alexander the Great.
And while we're doing this,
we're trying to see if there are
problems with this model, okay?
All right, so we have to take
a very skeptical attitude.
We have this prediction model.
We're gonna apply it to
Alexander the Great, and
we're gonna see that on the surface,
it does actually capture well,
or explains well his life.
At the same time, we want to be
generous and skeptical, okay?
We want to ask ourselves,
is it possible that
we are blinded by our prejudice, and
maybe we are being unfair to
Alexander the Great, okay?
Does that make sense? All right, so
let's start with the first major
event in Alexander the Great's life,
which is the death of
his father in 3 3 C BCE,
okay? And Alexander right now, he's only 20,
and when his father dies, he is, he's dead.
He is automatically coronated as king of,
the kingdom of Macedon. Now, I want to
explain the circumstances of Philip's death,
because it's very important for us to
understand the sort of psychology of his son.
So, two years before his death,
Philip actually remarried, okay?
Now, remember that Macedon is a society
that promotes polygamy, okay?
So, Philip, at this point,
already has six or seven wives.
The problem is that only one of his wives,
named Olympias, has given birth to a son,
and therefore a heir,
okay? The son is Alexander.
The other wives have failed
to give birth to a heir,
and it seems Alexander will be anointed
king at the death of his father.
So, when Philip marries,
her name is Cleopatra Eurydice,
and it's extremely controversial,
okay? And it sort of disrupts
the political order of Macedonia.
The first reason is Cleopatra Eurydice,
she is actually Macedonian.
Before, Philip married foreign
wives for diplomacy reasons.
And what this means is,
if Cleopatra Eurydice
gives birth to a son,
this son will be more legitimate
here than Alexander.
And this pushes Alexander out
of the line of succession.
So, this is extremely controversial,
and it's like dynamite almost, okay?
So, that's the first
problem. Second problem is,
Eurydice is the wife of one
of Philip's great generals,
Attalus. And
actually, at the wedding
ceremony between Eurydice
and Philip, Attalus gave a toast,
and he said, I'm going to marry you.
Here's a toast, and I pray that
Macedon will soon have a legitimate heir.
And this is a direct
insult to Alexander, okay?
The other problem is that Attalus,
his father -in -law, is Parmenion, who
is really Philip's partner, okay?
The greatest general that Macedon has,
the person in control of the army, okay?
So, it seems like,
Alexander is being pushed out
of the line of succession.
And Alexander and his mother,
Olympias, are both freaking out, okay?
So, in 336 BCE,
Philip is assassinated by his bodyguard.
And no one knows why this happened, okay?
But we know what happened.
Afterwards, what happened
is, first of all, Olympias,
killed Eurydice and
her daughter and son.
The son was going to be
legitimate heir to the throne.
Now, they're all dead, okay?
That's the first thing that happens.
Second thing that happens is,
Attalus becomes afraid, and
he's about to rebel, okay?
And Attalus, again, is a general.
At this stage, at this point,
Parmenion is now the kingmaker, right?
Because Parmenion is now the
kingmaker. He's now head of the army.
He can choose to support
Attalus, his son -in -law,
and rebel, okay?
And maybe become king himself.
Or he can support Alexander, okay?
And at this point, the
faithful decision that
Parmenion makes is, he supports
Alexander and he kills Attalus.
And Attalus, again, is his son -in -law.
And this makes Alexander now
the legitimate heir to Philip.
He's now king of Assyria. Okay?
So, from this event,
we can surmise some things, okay?
The first thing we can surmise is,
Olympias and Alexander
are extremely ambitious,
right? They will not be pushed aside.
If they see any risk to their power,
they will act viciously.
Okay? They're not afraid to kill.
They will even kill the king
in order to address the king.
And they will not be able
to assure their power.
Okay? That's the first thing. The second
thing that's more important for us is,
Parmenion is absolutely
loyal to Alexander.
Because, if you think about it,
he's loyal to the memory of Philip.
Okay? Philip promoted
Parmenion to be his partner.
And in a show of loyalty and gratitude,
Parmenion now is being
loyal to the son, Alexander.
Okay? So, that's the first
major event in Alexander's life.
Any questions about this event?
Before I move on? Okay.
So, the second thing that
happens is, remember, like,
Philip is now in charge of this
white kingdom across Greece.
And when people hear about his death,
people start to rebel.
Okay? The Athenians want to rebel.
The Thebans want to rebel.
The Spartans want to rebel.
And then to the north,
the Illyrians rebel.
Okay? So, there are these rebellions.
The first thing that Alexander does is,
he mounts this extremely fast
and decisive campaign to
quell all eternal dissent.
Because, ultimately, his ambition is
to complete the dream of his father,
the conquest of Persia. Right?
So, he goes to Illyria, which is in north.
Which is north to Macedonia.
And destroys all opposition.
Next thing he does is, he
marches against Greece itself.
Against Thebes. And
Thebes is the main source of opposition.
And Sparta and Athens both promised
to send troops to support Thebes.
The problem is, Alexander
gets there really fast.
And he lays siege to Thebes
and destroys it completely.
The next thing that he does is,
he decides to massacre all the
males and enslave all the women.
Now, this is actually common practice
back then in terms of warfare.
But this is not done to Greek cities.
Do you understand? The Greeks
considered themselves special.
And so, in 404 BCE,
when Sparta defeated Athens
in the Peloponnesian War,
remember that Sparta did not do anything.
Sparta just basically said, guys, will
you promise not to bother us again?
And Athens says, we promise. That was it.
Okay? So, what Alexander the Great did,
destroying Thebes, which
is one of the great cultural
centers of the Greek world,
that was like basically
setting off a nuclear bomb.
Okay? And from then on, the Greeks were
committed to overthrowing Alexander
when the opportunity
arose. At the same time,
Alexander, by doing this,
by showing his ruthlessness,
he was able to, for now,
pacify all discontent.
People are now afraid of him.
And that's what Alexander wants.
He wants fear. Okay.
So, now that eternal
dissent has been pacified,
now that
his leadership has been legitimized,
he will now embark on the
massive invasion of Athens.
The invasion of Persia. Okay?
Now, originally his father,
Philip II,
his dream was a unified Greek world.
Okay? What we call Hellenistic.
Okay? Or the Hellenic world.
Because remember, at this point,
you have these Greek -Polish
that spread all across the
Aegean and the Mediterranean.
Okay? In North Africa,
in Italy, in Asia Minor,
in Anatolia. Okay? And
Philip's vision was to
unify all these places.
But Alexander the Great, his vision
was actually to conquer Persia.
Okay? So he's expanding
his father's vision.
So he's landing, he lands in Anatolia,
which is like modern -day Turkey,
with this massive invasion force.
Okay? And he's going
against the Persian Empire.
The way that the Persian
Empire is designed is,
it's not really an empire, it's more
like a confederation or alliance.
So, the provincial governors,
who we call the satraps,
they're the ones responsible for
defending their own territory.
And at this point, the king of Persia,
his name is Darius III,
he's not really bothered by Alexander.
Okay? He doesn't realize that
Alexander will pose a threat to his rule.
Okay? He just thinks this
guy, he's like 20 years old,
he's an upstart, he doesn't really matter.
So Darius doesn't really bother himself.
Okay? But he sends an advisor.
This guy, he's a Greek,
Menon of Rhodes.
So he's Greek, and he
understands Greek warfare.
And so, they have this war
council between the satraps,
the local governors,
and Menon of Rhodes. And
what Menon of Rhodes proposes is a
safer strategy to defeat Alexander,
which is basically what we
call a war of attrition.
And the idea is they will not encounter,
not fight, Alexander on the battlefield.
Because Alexander right now possesses
the greatest army in the world.
Right? Let's not fight him.
We will burn all the crops
and starve his troops.
At the same time, what we will
do is we will bribe Athens
and Sparta to rebel against Alexander.
And once he's overextended, he
has no choice but to go home.
Okay? The war is over.
It doesn't cost us anything.
Okay? The satraps refuse this plan
because it would mean
destroying their own property.
Okay? So satraps are like, no.
We can overwhelm him.
So the Battle of Granaticus in 334 BCE,
Alexander's forces destroy the Persians.
Okay? And this is the first
major battle of this war.
There will be three major battles. What's
important for us is during this battle,
Alexander displayed
tremendous recklessness.
Okay? He rushed to the
front of the battle.
He led his cavalry and he
was almost overwhelmed.
Okay? One of the satraps knocked him down.
One of the satraps was about
to kill him, slash him.
Okay? But then at the last minute,
a man named Plitus the Black,
Plitus the Black,
comes running in and he slashes,
he cuts off the satraps' arm.
Thus saving Alexander's life.
All right? So at this point,
there are two individuals
that Alexander should
be most grateful for.
Right? Parmonion, who basically,
he was a kingmaker
and he announced that the army
would be always loyal to Alexander.
Okay? And Plitus the Black, who
saved Alexander's life in battle. And
both of these men were individuals
promoted heavily by his
father for their talent.
Okay? So basically, it was his
father's man that saved Alexander.
So you would think Alexander would
be very grateful to these men.
Right? Unfortunately,
he would end up killing both men.
And this would forever change
the course of his life.
Okay? All right. So,
after the Battle of Granaticus,
Menna Rhodes was given
complete freedom to do what he wanted.
So Menna Rhodes tried to stop Alexander.
And when he realized he couldn't do it
because Alexander's army was too powerful,
Menna Rhodes set sail for Greece.
He was hoping to bribe Athens and
Sparta to join the war and
rebel against Alexander.
And here, something that happens.
And Alexander gets really lucky.
Okay? And we will find this in his life.
He gets very lucky a lot of times.
And what is it that happens when
Menna Rhodes sets sail for Greece?
About to, and he's about to unite the
Greeks and rebel against Alexander.
And remember, Athens and Sparta at
this point really hates Alexander.
So what happens? He dies.
Okay? He gets sick and he dies.
And when Menna Rhodes dies,
there's no more contact
with the Greek world.
And now Persia is left to
basically defend itself.
Okay? The Greeks cannot be counted on.
There will be Greek rebellions against
Alexander, but they will be sporadic.
They will not be coordinated. Okay?
So Darius has no choice but to confront
Alexander in two massive battles.
So the first massive battle
is in southern Turkey.
Anatolia caught the Battle of Isis.
Okay? In 333 BCE.
The second battle will happen two
years later in Guacamole in Mesopotamia.
And both of these battles
are about the same.
Okay? So I will explain what
happened in both battles.
So you're going to understand
Alexander's strategy of war.
All right. So usually in battles,
there are three major forces.
There's something called the left flank.
Okay? The center flank
and the right flank.
And both armies are like this.
Now, in both battles,
the Persians were heavily
outnumbered the Greeks,
two to one. Okay? So it's
a massive difference.
And the cavalry is usually on the sides.
Now, there are some certain differences.
Okay? The first difference is the
Persians have one leader, Darius.
And he's in the center being protected
by his bodyguard called the Immortals.
The Immortals are the best
troops of the Persians.
Okay? The Macedonians have two leaders.
Parmonion and Alexander.
Alexander is in charge of the cavalry.
Parmonion is in charge of the infantry.
What we call the phalanx.
And in both battles,
the same thing happens.
Which is, on the left side,
Darius commits most of his
forces against Parmonion.
Okay? So Parmonion is being
overwhelmed by superior numbers.
But here, the discipline is different.
The discipline of Parmonion
is just incredible.
Because even though they're being
overwhelmed, okay, they're being outnumbered,
and they're about to be outrun,
they hold their ground.
Okay? And then, in the
right, in the center,
there's so much conflict that eventually
what happens is there's a small gap
that allows Alexander to rush to Darius.
Okay? Remember, Darius is being
protected heavily because he's the king.
Right? And at this point,
Alexander and his forces are
overwhelming the cavalry of Darius.
And they're about to close up.
They're getting close to Darius.
And at this point, what Darius does, and this
is something you can never do in a battle.
What does Darius do now? And
he does this in both battles.
Isis and Coromala.
What does he do now? He sees
Alexander closing in, right?
But his left flank is about
to overwhelm Parmonion.
What does Darius do now?
In both battles? He runs away.
He runs away. And when he does that,
Alexander is now free to go back
and rescue Parmonion, and
then the Persians flee.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So this is what happens in both
battles, Isis and Coromala.
So now that you have the basic
overview of both battles,
let's analyze this to ask you,
let's ask ourselves, how great
a commander is Alexander?
Okay? And I want to make you, again, make the
argument that he's actually not a great strategist.
Okay? He's a great soldier.
He's very brave. But he's
not a great strategist.
Not like his father. Okay? The
first thing I will say is this.
When military historians look at
battles, they look at the wrong things.
Right? So they're usually
looking at manpower,
technology,
and resources.
Okay? What we'll call wealth. Right?
And if we look at battles
from this lens, right?
Manpower, technology,
and resources, wealth, then
we can argue the Persians were
heavily favored in this battle,
in this war. Right? We can say that.
But I think this is the wrong
way to look at military strategy.
I think if you really want to
understand who's a favorite
and who's the underdog, you have
to look at three different things.
These three different things are cohesion.
The idea of cohesion is unity.
Right? Are these soldiers
loyal to each other?
Are they friends with each other? Okay?
Second thing you want to
look at is discipline.
How well trained are these troops?
Okay? The third thing you want to
look at is the idea of devotion.
Devotion just means how
loyal are they to the enemy.
How loyal are they to their leaders? How
much purpose do they have in the battle?
Okay? Does that make sense? And
what I want to show you today is,
look at these three things.
They give you a much better
overview or analysis of
who the better military is. Okay?
So, if you just look at
manpower, technology,
and resources, then clearly the
Persians are the heavy favorites.
Right? But if you change
your frame of reference,
and you will look at who's the most powerful,
who has the most cohesion, discipline,
and devotion,
then the Macedonians are far superior.
Right? Because look, cohesion
means they have a culture.
They have a similar culture.
Right? They're all Greeks.
Whereas, the Persians are
a multicultural empire.
They don't speak the same
language, which means that
all these different units that Darius has,
they're basically fighting by themselves.
So, they are not coordinated. Okay?
Does that make sense?
That's the first thing.
Second thing is the idea of discipline.
If you're an empire, the problem with
an empire is your soldiers don't fight
that many battles. Right?
Because you're an empire. No
one's going to challenge you.
So, these soldiers, even though
they have these very expensive armor
and horses, they weren't disciplined.
They didn't have experience in battle.
Whereas, Alexander's army
is Philip's army, and
for the past 30 years, all they did was
fight battle after battle against the Greeks.
Okay? So, in terms of discipline,
the Greeks are far superior.
And then you look at
devotion. Darius is king.
Why are people loyal to him?
Because he pays them.
Right? It's profit. It's interest.
Whereas, the soldiers under Pommernion and
Alexander, they love their leaders.
Right? Their leaders have
taken them to victory.
To victory. To lots of victories.
So, they're very loyal to him.
Okay? So, just in terms of these,
if you just look at cohesion,
discipline, and devotion,
we can predict that
Alexander's army would win
regardless of the strategy.
Okay? And now, you can
also make the argument that
the strategy that Alexander employed,
right, this, we will confront
the Persians head on,
Philip would have thought
this was a stupid idea.
Okay? Because, first of
all, you're outnumbered.
Second of all, you're on enemy terrain.
Right? You're on enemy terrain.
Therefore, they are able to deploy the
resources much better than you are.
Okay? Now, the third problem is this.
The third problem is you
cannot afford to retreat.
Do you understand? There's
no place to retreat.
If your army ever breaks, right,
if Pommernion gets overwhelmed,
then you're all dead.
Why take that risk?
Right? Because you're not going to be able
to retreat. Also, before our full battle,
it is in Gargamola, Darius wants
to negotiate with Alexander.
Basically, Darius said, I
will give you half my empire.
Right? That's pretty generous.
And Alexander says, no, I need all of it.
Right? So,
historians will tell
you that Gargamola is,
just shows the military
prowess of Alexander.
And, but if you analyze it properly, I think,
you will see their lives are in danger.
They have lots of problems with
Alexander's strategy in both battles.
Okay? He was taking risks
that he shouldn't have.
And, he sacrificed a lot of men that
he didn't really need to sacrifice.
For example, it was all
about winning the war, right,
personal glory, whereas Philip
was concerned about the safety
and well -being of his soldiers.
So, Philip would not have
engaged in such a battle.
He would have preferred negotiation.
And, then, over time, slowly,
overwhelmed Persia.
Does that make sense?
Any questions so far? About this analysis?
Quick question. Yeah, great.
I think you just you are
fighting for power, right?
Yeah. You said it was a very big turning
against other states, right?
That must put you stressed
about things like the and
Yeah. Right.
Great question.
So, actually they didn't
really trust the Greeks.
The Greeks didn't consider
the Macedonians part of
they didn't consider
the Macedonians Greek.
And so when
Alexander sent his when
Alexander developed his invasion force of Persia,
there weren't that many Greeks actually in it.
It was mostly Macedonian.
Does that make sense?
You're right. Given what
Alexander did to Thebes,
he couldn't really trust
the Greeks anymore.
He couldn't really trust
the Greeks to switch sides.
And also there were a lot of Greek mercenaries
fighting for Darius in this battle.
Menon of Rhodes was Greek.
And he sort of knew the Greeks
really didn't like Alexander.
So it was more like a tribal
army rather than a material army.
That's right. But
again, we see this throughout history
where a tribal army, because of cohesion discipline and devotion,
they were able to conquer
the world, right?
So you look Yeah,
yeah. So you look at Mohammed,
you look at Genghis Khan,
and you look at Tamerlan, you
look at a lot of people, right?
They were all tribal armies,
but because they had cohesion,
discipline, and devotion, they were able
to basically conquer most of the world
before they themselves
devolved into civil war.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Any more questions before I continue?
Okay. Okay.
Okay, so while
Alexander was campaigning against
Persia, he was doing things
that sort of annoyed his soldiers, okay?
So for example, he conquered
Egypt without much resistance.
So he went to Egypt, and basically
the Egyptians hated the Persians.
For decades, for centuries,
the Egyptians were trying to rebel
against Persia without success.
So when Alexander came,
they saw him as a liberator.
So Egypt felt without resistance.
The first thing that Alexander does
is he takes a trip into the desert.
He disappears for weeks.
He goes to something called, he
goes to a place called the temple
of Zeus, Amon.
Amon is the highest Egyptian god,
and Zeus is the highest Greek god.
So they are like a synthesis, okay?
So this is the highest god in the world.
And this is found in the, I say, Oasis.
And Alexander goes to this
Oasis in order to seek counsel.
He wants to see his future. And at,
when he's at the temple of Zeus, Amon,
he's told that
Philip is not really his father.
Okay? Philip is not really his father.
Alexander's true father is,
take a wild guess, who the true father is.
Zeus, Amon, right? Alexander
is the first son of God,
right? He's the son of God.
He's like Heracles and Dionysus.
He's actually the son of God.
And so, when Alexander returns
to his soldiers after this revelation,
he expects his soldiers to
acknowledge this fact, okay?
So one thing is,
in the Macedonian army,
there's a lot of equality between soldiers
and officers, right?
So if you're a soldier, you
are allowed to speak your mind.
But now, Alexander demands,
if you come into his presence,
you must first kiss his feet.
Which is the Persian custom, okay?
You must first, you must
kiss the feet of your king.
And the Macedonians, of course,
didn't really like this.
So now there's growing concern
about the tyranny of Alexander.
Okay? People like Parmonion
and Cletus of Black, who were promoted
heavily by his father, are kind of annoyed.
Basically, Alexander renounced his father.
Philip's not really my father.
I'm really the son of a god, okay?
Zeus, Amon. Okay?
So, okay.
So now there's growing
discontent among his soldiers.
Does that make sense so far?
Any questions before I move on?
Is this clear to you?
Okay? Alright.
So, you know, in 331 BCE,
the Battle of Gorgomola
happens and Alexander wins this
incredible victory against
the Persian king, Darius.
Darius runs away, but then
he's eventually killed by
one of his generals, okay?
And the Persian empire now is basically
conquered. There's no resistance
against Alexander anymore.
There's some resistance, but
not organized resistance.
Okay? And at this point,
Alexander starts being a tyrant.
Okay? So the first major
sign that he's changing is in 330 BCE,
Parmonion is killed. Remember,
Parmonion, you can argue,
was the man responsible for all
of Alexander's victories, right?
Because Parmonion is the one
who's doing all the heavy lifting.
He's being overwhelmed by
most of Persian forces.
He stands his ground,
which allows Alexander
to claim his victory, okay?
In 330 BCE,
Alexander orders Parmonion to be killed.
And there's a lot of controversy
around what happened, right?
So I'll just basically tell you the basic
facts, and then we'll
analyze what happened.
So, there's a lot of
resentment against Alexander in the army.
And now and then there
are these conspiracies.
They don't go anywhere. But
there are these conspiracies amongst
officers to assassinate Alexander.
And one of these conspiracies
is found out, and
one of the officers who finds
out about this conspiracy goes to
Parmonion's son, okay?
And tells the son, hey,
go tell the king people are
trying to assassinate him.
The son, Parmonion's son,
he doesn't think this is a big deal.
And he's kind of drunk, okay?
So he doesn't, he forgets
to tell Alexander, okay?
The plot is uncovered, and the son,
Philolitus, Philolitus,
he's implicated, and he's tortured.
He had nothing to do with the
assassination, but he's implicated.
Because he didn't tell Alexander.
While he's being tortured,
he also confesses to his
father being part of the plot,
even though there's no evidence
implicating his father.
In fact, you can make the argument that his
father is completely loyal to Alexander.
Okay? And so, just based on this,
a forced confession under torture,
which is completely unreliable,
Alexander and the army decide
to have Parmonion killed, okay?
So an assassin is sent,
and Parmonion is killed.
Now, these are the basic facts.
And there's a lot of argument
about what happened, okay?
So the most generous argument,
the most generous interpretation
is Alexander didn't want Parmonion killed.
He knows Parmonion
is innocent, but because Alexander
was forced to kill his son,
Philolitus, Alexander didn't feel
he had a choice in the matter,
okay? Because Parmonion
might want revenge.
So to maintain
stability and peace within the army,
he had to get Parmonion killed, okay?
That's the most generous explanation.
But there's another explanation
that makes more sense, which is
Alexander has always been
jealous of Parmonion, right?
Because Parmonion has the
most legitimacy in the army.
Troops feel more loyal to Parmonion
than they do to Alexander.
Right? Because they've been, they've, uh,
Parmonion, um, they're more experienced
with Parmonion than with Alexander.
And Parmonion was responsible
for many great triumphs.
So Alexander was jealous of Parmonion.
Also, there were these new young
officers who wanted to climb the ranks.
And to do so, they needed to get
rid of people like Parmonion, right?
So maybe the conspiracy was
a fake conspiracy and
it was organized by these law
officers to implicate Philolitus,
and then in order to get rid of
Parmonion, okay? But
regardless of how you interpret this,
what we do know is, after
Parmonion was killed,
basically all the shackles, all the
restraints on Alexander went away.
Because there's no one in the, because
now there's no one in the army who
can resist Alexander, okay?
There's no one who
can basically urge restraint and caution.
So the next thing that happens is this.
In the year 328,
Cleitus the Black is killed.
Remember, Cleitus the
Black is the person who
saved Alexander's life at
the Battle of Branacus, okay?
But Cleitus the Black, again, he is a
loyal officer promoted by his father.
And now Cleitus the Black
has the same authority
as Parmonion once had.
So Cleitus the Black is
now a threat to Alexander.
So what Alexander does is,
he basically orders Cleitus the Black
to take some soldiers and go off
to a faraway place. It's
basically exile, okay?
Alexander is basically exiling
him from the main army.
And Cleitus the Black knows,
basically, he's finished.
So before Cleitus the Black
is meant to go into exile,
they have a large banquet, okay?
And they're all drunk. And
Cleitus the Black now is angry.
And he gets into a vicious argument
with Alexander. And
Cleitus the Black basically
says, to Alexander,
you've betrayed your
people, the Macedonians.
You've come to Persia,
and you could only conquer
Persia without our help.
And now you're turning
into a Persian, okay?
You're adopting Persian customs, like
forcing officers to kiss your feet.
You're promoting Persian
officers within your army.
Okay? You're turning your back away
from the culture that made you great.
Then, he says something that really
pisses Alexander off. What is one thing
that you can say to Alexander that would really piss him off?
In fact, he would want to kill you now.
Everything that you've
achieved, Alexander,
it's because of your father.
This is not you, okay?
This conquest of Persia, it's not you.
It's your father.
It's your father who
built this amazing army.
It's your father who developed
this plan to conquer Persia.
Okay? Alexander gets so angry that
he's about to lunge at
Cleitus the Black, okay?
But before he can do so, his party guard
surrounds him and stops him,
and they pull away his sword.
And so this makes us think, he's
been doing this a lot, okay?
Alexander the Great gets drunk a lot
and kills a lot of people, basically.
Um, and then Cleitus the Black,
he's taken out of the room.
But Cleitus the Black is so strong,
he forces himself back in the room.
He starts to continue
arguing against Alexander.
Alexander then goes and takes a spear
and throws it at Cleitus the
Black, killing him on the spot.
So, Cleitus the Black is now dead.
The two men who are most responsible for
Alexander's victories in
Persia are now both dead.
Okay? And he's becoming more
and more of a tyrant.
Um, soon afterwards,
there's a conspiracy, there's
a real conspiracy to kill him.
What happens is this, okay?
Uh, the king, Alexander,
uh, goes on a boar hunt
with his pages, okay?
His servants. Now, the custom in Persia is
the king has the right to the first kill.
But these are, but his pages are
Macedonian, so they don't know this.
So one of the pages is the
first to kill the boar.
Alexander is so angry, he beats him.
He beats the crap out of this page.
The pages get together that night, and
they resolve to kill, kill this tyrant.
And, um, they develop, they,
they, they organize a schedule so that
on one night, they will be all in the bedroom,
looking after Alexander while he sleeps.
And then, and then of course they will
take out their their daggers and stab Alexander to death, okay?
That's the plan. What happens is, that
night, they were supposed to do this
act, Alexander goes out drinking.
He gets drunk, and he
does not come back until
the early morning when
the pages are gone, okay?
At this point, one of the
pages gets nervous, and
tells Alexander about the conspiracy,
and Alexander has everyone killed, okay?
But during the trial, the pages
accuse Alexander of being a tyrant.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Then, what happens is,
in 326 BCE,
after Alexander has conquered all Persia,
he decides to take his
army to India, okay?
Now, his army is not
happy about this because,
look, there are lots of good
reasons to invade Persia, right?
The first reason is,
Persia is very wealthy.
Second reason is, um,
Persia invaded Greece,
right? So Greece, so Persia was always a
threat to the Greece, the Greek mainland.
The third reason is, there are lots of
people who suspect it was the Persians
who killed Philip, okay? So there's
lots of good reasons to invade Persia.
There's actually no reason
to invade India, okay?
They've never been to India,
they have actually no idea
what they will find in India.
It's a different geography, okay?
But in, but Alexander forces his forces,
his army, to invade India, in
basically modern -day Pakistan.
And there, they win these victories,
but the soldiers are
really pissed off because
they're far away from home,
they have absolutely no
idea when this war will end,
and the weather in India
really sucks, okay?
So they basically mutiny,
they refuse to fight.
And Alexander at this point has no choice
but to give in to the,
but to retreat, okay?
To return back to Babylon.
But he does two things to show his anger.
The first thing he does is, he kills
all the leaders of the mutiny, okay?
Those who spoke up on behalf of their
fellow soldiers were all killed, one by one.
So the second thing that happens is,
rather than take his soldiers
back the original way,
Alexander made them march
through a desert, which
killed many of them, okay?
Many died because of
dehydration and starvation.
It was a brutal march across the desert.
So, Alexander takes his
army back to Babylon,
and at this point,
Alexander decides he can't invade
India, so he'll go invade Arabia,
okay? He'll go invade
Arabia, which is desert.
There's a reason why no one invaded
Arabia, and the reason why it's all desert.
There's no reason to invade
Arabia. But Alexander wants to
be the first to conquer Arabia,
because his ambition is boundless, okay?
He has to prove he's the
greatest conqueror in the world.
The only way he can do that is
by conquering the entire world.
He's very suspicious of his own soldiers,
because they mutiny against him in India, right?
So he's starting to replace his army with
Persians, who are much more obedient.
He wants obedience. Then
something else happens. Back in Macedonia,
the general in charge, Antepater, who
again is one of
Philip's most loyal generals,
he gets into an argument
with Olympias, okay?
Olympias answers his mother, and
Antepater don't see eye to eye.
And Olympias tells
Alexander, and Alexander
invites Antepater to Babylon, where
they will settle matters, okay?
And Antepater knows what
happened to Parmenion.
He knows what happened
to Clytus the Black.
And at this point,
most of Alexander's generals
are unhappy with the fact
that the army is being Persianized, right?
They're being replaced by Persian
officers who are more loyal
to Alexander. So in 323,
Alexander dies.
And again, no one will ever
know what actually happened,
but the theory is this, okay?
I think the theory that
makes the most sense is basically the
top echelon of the Macedonian army,
Antepater and the other generals,
basically decided Alexander has to go
because he's a tyrant.
And eventually, he's going
to kill everyone, okay?
So what happened was there was a
banquet, and Antepater and his son,
he's the cupbearer to
Alexander, the person
who pours the drinks to
Alexander during meals.
The son puts poison in the cup.
Alexander drinks from it,
and he starts to vomit, okay?
So Alexander leaves the room to vomit.
And then the son, Antepater's son,
brings a feather laced with more poison
to help Alexander vomit some more,
okay? But, and so Alexander
should have died on the spot.
But Alexander is so tough,
he's such a strong man,
that he lasts for a few more weeks, okay?
And he dies in bed. So Alexander now is
dead. Okay?
Okay, this is important because
even though he's dead, in the ten years
that he's been around, he's been able to conquer
most of the world, which includes Egypt,
Mesopotamia,
Iran, Afghanistan, Pakistan.
Okay? He's able to conquer
most of the known world.
And this creates a
problem for the generals
who succeed him. Right?
Because once you conquer most
of this world, and remember,
the plan was not to
conquer most of the world.
It was just Alexander's balanced
ambition that made them do so, okay?
Another question is how do you govern?
And so because of this pressure,
they have no choice but to
develop something called Greek culture
and spread it in order to create
legitimacy for themselves.
Okay? And this is something
that we will talk about
next class, which will conclude
our session on the Greeks, okay?
The legacy of Alexander. He's conquered the
world, and now his generals must govern it.
And to govern it, they must use
something called Greek culture.
So they must invent Greek culture,
and then spread it around the world.
And when they do so, what will happen is,
the Greek culture will merge with
local cultures to create new ideas,
okay? Greek culture,
one of these cultures that Greek culture
will merge with is called Judaism.
Judaism. And when
these two cultures merge,
a new idea will emerge
from this mixture called Christianity
that changes the world forever, okay?
That's why Christians love Alexander the Great,
because they feel that without his conquest,
Christianity could not
have been born, okay?
So there are many Christians who
feel like Alexander the Great, yeah,
he was a tyrant, but he
was part of God's plan.
He was all part of a plan. He did
what he did because he truly is
the son of Zeus Amon, and Zeus Amon
commanded him to conquer the world.
Okay? But again, that is
a Christian perspective.
Alright, so that is it, okay?
So let's review what we did today.
We basically looked at
this analytical model,
and we made three predictions about Alexander
based on this analytical model, right?
The first is that he
would focus on expansion,
second is he would become a tyrant, and the
third is that he would never stop expanding.
And it turns out, he was
exactly like this, okay?
This explains, this
predicts his life in time.
Alright? So, any questions?
Okay. So, next class,
what we will do is we will look at
the spreading of Greek culture and
the building of the Hellenistic world.
Okay? And that will end
our section on the Greeks.