Today we will be discussing
the second American Civil War.
I want to make the argument that
a conflict is very likely.
We will be discussing why it is likely,
how this war will benefit itself,
and what will happen after this war.
The first thing to know about America is
that it is a country that
enjoys violence.
You can say that
Americans are addicted
to violence.
For example,
America has
434 guns.
Sorry. 434 million guns.
That's 1.3 guns for every one person.
And the guns they have, a lot of
them are like semi -machine guns.
So it's a very gun -obsessed society.
Not only that, but they believe that
gun ownership is their
sacred right as Americans.
So the Second Amendment of the
Constitution is the second amendment.
The third amendment is that every
American has the right to bear arms.
Then there's American football.
Have you guys seen American football?
Where guys just bang at each other?
It is an extremely violent sport.
In fact, America is really the only
country that plays this sport.
And Americans love football.
The Super Bowl is the most
watched TV event every year.
And
the game of
football causes a lot of
psychological injuries.
So there are a lot of football players who
at age 30, they either commit
suicide or they will kill someone
because their brains have
been destroyed by the game.
It is an extremely violent sport.
And even though it is
barbaric, Americans love it.
Americans also...
worship their history of wars.
They believe that fighting
wars is noble and it's sacred.
So the second thing to
know about America is
that it has a long
history of fighting wars.
In fact, you can make the argument that
America has been continuously at
war since its founding in 1776.
Even before that.
So the first major war that America
fought, of course, was the Revolution.
1776. War of Independence.
And the reality is
that Americans believed
this war was sacred.
And it was a revolution in human affairs.
But if you actually look
at the history of this war,
you'll discover that the Americans
didn't really fight this war.
They fought this war for a good
reason. They fought this war
because the British were taxing them.
If you think about it, well, the
British were providing defense.
They were providing an army, right?
So the British had a very good
reason to tax the Americans.
But the Americans didn't really
like this, so they rebelled.
And the rebellion was actually
the first American Civil War.
Because there were actually
a lot of Americans who
wanted to remain in the Union.
And so these loyalists,
a lot of them were
terrorized by extremists
who wanted independence. So
that is the American Revolution.
But after the American Revolution,
the Americans embarked on
something called Manifest Destiny.
And the idea of Manifest Destiny is that
it is God's will that
America controls all of the world.
All of the Americas. North
America and South America.
So the Americans embarked on
a violent colonization of all lands.
Killing many natives and
other peoples to control America.
Manifest Destiny. And then this led to,
from 1861 to 1865,
the American Civil War.
Okay? Which killed 800,000,
a million Americans. But
it was the deadliest war
that America ever fought.
Much more so than World
War II and World War I.
In fact, more people died in
this war than in World War I
and World War II combined for America.
And we looked at the
reason for the Civil War.
Again, you're like, they didn't
actually have to fight this war.
Okay? So, at the founding of the nation,
America was divided into North and South.
And the difference is that
the North was very industrial.
And the South was agricultural.
Okay? And because the
economies were different,
the way they structured their politics
and culture and society were different.
So the North believed in free labor.
Meaning that you were free
to do any job you want.
And employers were free to
hire anyone they wanted.
And this system is obviously
much more efficient.
Because it's a much
better use of manpower.
And so this caused the North to prosper
and become very wealthy and expanded.
Okay? So at the start of
the Civil War in 1861,
the North had a population
of 22 million people.
Okay? Very wealthy, very powerful.
The South was an
agricultural base economy.
And therefore, it had
to rely on slave labor.
All right? And
even though slave labor made
wealthy people very prosperous,
it was not good for
the economy as a whole.
Okay? It was an inefficient
use of manpower.
And at the start of the war, they
only had about 9 million people.
Okay? But what's important
to remember is that
the North was an industrial base economy.
The South was an
agricultural base economy.
So in terms of weapons manufacturing,
in terms of logistics,
in terms of organization,
the North had a huge
advantage over the South.
All right? Now, why
did they fight the war?
And the standard explanation is because
the North wanted to get
rid of the evil of slavery.
And that's not true.
That's not what happened.
So at the beginning of the
founding of the nation,
the Constitution permitted slavery.
Okay? Slavery was legal.
And so the South were free to have
as many slaves as they wanted.
The North didn't want,
didn't need slaves because
it was an industrial -based economy.
The problem was the nation
was expanding westwards.
Okay? The nation was expanding west.
And they were adding more
states into the Union.
And the more states there are,
they can send senators and
representatives to Washington, D.C.
Okay? And the fear was that
if these western states were pro -slavery,
then that would tip the balance
in favor of the pro -slavery cap.
But if the reverse were true,
if the western states were anti -slavery,
then the South would be marginalized.
Okay? So for decades,
there was this fierce debate
as to how to handle the South.
And
there was a fight to keep them from doing
that, to keep them from doing that, to
keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that, to keep them from doing that,
to keep them from doing
that, to keep them from doing
that, to keep them from doing that,
to keep them from doing that,
to keep them from doing that
So some of these western
states, for example Kansas,
would want to be anti -slavery.
So for decades,
this was a huge issue
politically in America,
which divided the nation. The
turning point was in 1860,
when
Abraham Lincoln was elected
President of the United States.
And Lincoln was radically anti -slavery.
He believed that slavery was evil
and had to be abolished at some point.
The rest of the world abolished slavery.
Why is it in America
there are so many slaves?
So that was Lincoln's agenda.
But Lincoln was also a lawyer,
and he believed that
the South legally had a right to slavery.
But over time,
what we can do is limit
slavery in the West.
And therefore over time,
in maybe 100 years time,
slavery would naturally cease to exist.
That was Lincoln's plan.
Now the South did not like this plan,
and they were afraid of what Lincoln
might really do as President.
So they declared independence
from the United States.
They basically succeeded.
And Lincoln's response invaded the South.
So basically,
the Civil War was a
battle over how much power
the federal government had.
So from the perspective of the South,
they were fighting the war
for their right to freely
express their political views.
And the North was fighting
to maintain the Union.
Slavery was not the main issue.
In fact, Lincoln himself said that
if I could end the
war without freeing any
slaves, I would do so.
Slavery is not the main issue.
Keeping the Union intact
was the main issue.
Does that make sense?
But again,
they could have chosen to
politically compromise.
They could have had discussions.
They could have even broke apart.
But they chose to fight
a gruesome Civil War.
The third thing you need to
know about America is that
America resolves conflicts through
violence. Okay?
Okay. It doesn't really
have a history of diplomacy.
It has a history of war making.
Okay? That's how America
usually resolves issues.
So given this history,
now let's look at the conflicts in
America today to see how serious
the division is. And the reality is that
today is actually very, very serious.
Far more so than in 1861.
Okay? When they fought
the first Civil War.
Okay? So let's look at the divisions.
The first major division is
basically between the haves
and the have -nots. Okay?
So inequality and debt.
So the wealthy, the top 1%,
not only do they control most
of the wealth in America,
but they also control what we
call the means of production.
Meaning that if new money comes into the
system, they're going to have to pay for it.
They will seize it. Okay?
So basically the top 1% have a
monopoly over wealth production.
And the way they make most of their money
is actually through collecting debt.
Okay? By exploiting other people.
And this is what we
call a rentier economy.
Okay? Now what exaggerates makes this
situation worse are the culture wars.
So America is divided
between left and right.
And this division actually goes back to
the very founding of America in the 1600s.
Okay? So in America,
in its founding, there were two
opposing visions or strands.
Okay? The first strand are
people who are in the middle.
People who came to America
to build a kingdom of God.
A Christian nation that
follows the laws of God.
Okay? These are the
pilgrims and the Puritans.
Okay? And we've discussed them
before. And they've always been there.
Okay? And they today comprise the right.
And the right are people who
believe in conservative Christian values.
Okay? The left.
But there's also another strand.
The left. There's a
group that's
been there ever since. There's been a
group that's been there ever since. There's been a group that's been there ever since. There's been a group that's been there ever since. There's been a group that's been there ever since.
There's been a group that's
been there ever since.
Constitution is a document based on deism,
separation of church and state.
And they want to create a multicultural,
secular empire.
And today it manifests itself in the left.
Now, there's actually a lot of,
a lot of crossover between
the left and the wealthy.
Because if you look at the left,
it's usually urban,
liberal, and college educated.
Okay, and coastal. Okay,
and these are the people
usually with all the money.
So the inequality only makes
the culture wars much worse.
And so the right feel left out, okay?
Another major division in America that's
important is the one between empire
and democracy.
Meaning that there are
many people in America
who benefit from America being an empire.
But the rest suffer from the
fact that America is an empire.
Okay? So for example, the
wars in Afghanistan and Iraq
made Wall Street very rich, right?
But it was the poor, the right,
who sent their sons to
fight in these wars, and
who lost their lives,
or lost a limb, okay?
It was the poor who
were taxed in order to fund these wars.
And it's the poor who must pay
off the debt from these wars.
Okay? So the right feel left out, okay?
The right is also very isolationist.
Meaning like they don't
want to fight these wars.
They think that America
should be an island.
It should not intervene in
the affairs of the world.
Okay? So
there are a lot of divisions in America.
The problem today is that
there's no actual solution
to any of these divisions, okay?
And the problem is that there's no actual
solution to any of these divisions, okay? And the reason why, there are three major reasons why
a civil war would
probably break out, okay?
The first major reason is
the over -militarization of America.
And so what this means is that, okay,
first of all, we've already said that
in America there are
434 million guns, right?
In private hands. So every individual
has access to one or two guns.
That's the first problem.
Second problem is that
if you go to a small town in America
and you look at like the police there,
you think that, okay, it's
a small town, it's safe.
They should have, I don't
know, pistols, right?
In fact, they have armored vehicles.
Sometimes they have tanks.
They have helicopters. They
have bulletproof vests.
They have machine guns, okay?
They got weapons. They got
all this from the military.
So that's just like a local police force.
I'm not even talking
about the state militias,
okay? The National Guard.
These guys are basically
an army unto themselves.
Then you have federal
agencies like the FBI
and the CIA and Homeland Security, okay?
NSA, okay? There's dozens
of these federal agencies.
They themselves are their own army,
meaning that the FBI and the CIA
all have their special forces.
Tanks, helicopters,
jets, bombs, missiles, okay?
So these guys can go to war
against each other, okay?
Then you have the U.S.
military. The U.S.
military is divided into the Army,
the Air Force,
the Marines, the Navy, okay?
And then you have something
called the Space Force, okay?
All right. To show you
how powerful the U.S.
military is, okay,
let's look at the top five
air forces in the world, okay?
The top five institutions or countries with
the most powerful air force in the world.
Who's number one? Who's
number one, do you think?
U.S. Air Force, right? Who's
number two, do you guys know?
The top five air forces in the world.
Number one would be the
U.S. Air Force, right?
Who's number two, do you think?
Guess. Take a guess. Who's number two?
Yeah, okay. Actually, I
said number three, okay?
The Russian Air Force
would be number three.
Who's number two, though?
The UK, the British, right?
Nope, okay. Number two
is actually the U.S.
Navy. Who's number,
number three is Russia.
Number four is who?
Can you guys guess? The U.S.
Army. And who's number five?
Can you guys guess? It's the U.S.
Marines. Okay? So
four of the top five air
forces in the world are an arm of the U.S.
military. Okay?
Number one is the U.S. Air Force.
Number two is the U.S.
Navy. Number three is Russia, the
entire country of Russia, okay?
Number four is the U.S.
Army. Number five is the U.S.
Marines. That's how powerful the U.S.
Army is. That's how powerful America
is. But then you have special forces.
And again, we've discussed special
forces in this class before.
And we said that
special forces are
good for special circumstances,
like, for example, hijackings, okay?
Or covert operations.
The problem with special forces
is they cannot be controlled.
Okay? So in Mexico,
the people who run the drug
cartels are former special forces.
Okay? Do you understand? The people
who run the drug cartels in Mexico
and who commit the most violence in the world
are former members of their special forces.
That's why you want to
limit your special forces.
Okay? So in the year 2000,
America had 38,000 special forces.
Today, it has 75,000.
And in the year 2000, it
has 72,000. Or 73,000.
I can't remember. Okay? That's
a lot of special forces.
These guys are trained in
demolition, destroying buildings.
They're an army unto themselves.
Okay? It would take exactly
1,000 of these guys,
exactly 1,000 of these
guys, to overthrow the U.S.
government. Okay? And guess what?
Delta Force. Which
is the most elite special
force unit in the world.
And in America, has exactly 1,000 members.
So you have this guy who runs Delta Force.
And he's like, I want to over for the U.S.
government for whatever
reason. He can do so because
they're so powerful.
Okay? So I think special forces,
it's just a bomb waiting to explode.
So the first major issue is just
the over militarization of America.
Where anyone who has access
to weapons can use weapons.
And can choose to start a war.
Okay? That's the first problem.
Second problem is the
breakdown of narratives.
Okay. So
a nation is a fiction,
a narrative that everyone believes in.
And there are certain narratives that
have kept America united.
Okay? So for example, the first
narrative is the American dream.
Right? The equality of opportunity.
So that as long as you work hard
and you play by the rules,
you will succeed in America.
Right? That's the American dream.
Guess what, guys? No one
believes in this anymore.
Okay? And the reason why is.
The inequality in America as
well as the cultural wars.
So if you're a young
person, you don't believe
that if you work hard, you own a house
and you will be wealthy.
You don't believe that. Okay? You think
like the game is stacked against you.
You believe that Washington is corrupt.
It only serves the interest of the rich.
You believe that the wealthy
have stolen everything.
They monopolize wealth.
And you believe that
whatever money you make
will be stolen by the rich
and by the government. Okay? So there's
actually no reason to work hard.
So this idea that
if you work hard, you
will succeed, it's dead.
Okay? Now the new American dream
is how do I stay out of debt?
Right? If you're a college graduate,
you have tens of thousands
of dollars in debt.
Consumers have thousands of
dollars in credit card debt.
You can no longer afford houses.
If you buy a house, you
can't pay off the mortgage.
Okay? So this idea of the American dream,
it's basically dead for most people.
Then you have the narrative that
America is good.
Okay? You believe that
America represents democracy.
It represents liberty.
It defends freedom around the world.
Guess what, guys? Most people in
America don't believe this anymore.
Okay? So, for example, on the left,
people are taught
that America is a nation
founded on slavery,
violence, and war.
America is a force of
destruction and evil.
Okay? That's what people
on the left are taught.
People on the right believe
that
America is an imperialist power
that goes around and destroys
countries for no reason.
Okay? So most people
don't actually believe
that America is a force for good anymore.
Right? And then you look at
what's happening in Israel.
Right? Well, more young people now believe
that America is a force
of evil in the world.
The other narrative that's really
important is the narrative of liberalism.
And the idea of liberalism is that
even though we have differences,
there are mechanisms for us
to work out our differences.
For example, the right
to freedom of speech.
Okay? Freedom of speech.
You can say whatever you want.
Okay? Then you...
But what's important is
to debate the opponent
and come to a compromise based on logic,
evidence, and the facts.
Okay? So for the longest time,
liberalism was what brought the left
and the right together. Okay?
Liberalism tried to be in the middle.
But now...
Okay? Liberalism is dead.
Okay? And the reason why is in 2016,
Donald Trump became President
of the United States.
And the liberals in America went crazy.
They could not believe that
Donald Trump could be elected.
So they came to believe that the
problem was democracy itself.
The problem is that
people could not be reasoned with.
Therefore, liberalism makes no sense.
If people are stupid,
if people cannot be reasoned with,
why give them freedom of speech?
Why let them debate? Why let them vote?
Okay? So liberalism today is dead.
So the stories that
basically bind the country together, make it
so that we can have a free, no longer work.
Okay? Does that make sense? Then
the third problem is
breakdown of
authority or institutions.
Okay? What kept the country
together was the fact
that people believed
that the elites in power
knew what they were doing and they were...
They cared about the well -being
of the nation and of the people.
Okay? But recent events
have shown this isn't true.
Okay? So for example, the
wars in Afghanistan and Iraq.
Right? Well, why did
America fight these wars?
For no reason. Then
you have the 2008 financial crisis where
the banks basically stole from the nation,
stole from the poor, and kept the money.
And everyone was screwed. Okay?
There was a crisis, there was a crisis,
there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis,
there was a crisis, there was
a crisis, there was a crisis,
there was a crisis, there was a crisis,
there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis, there was a crisis,
there was a crisis,
there was a crisis, there
was was actually dangerous.
Then the government made everyone
take a experimental vaccine.
And people were like,
why are we doing this?
So elite actions over the past 20 years
have made people cynical of power.
So that in today's
world, there's actually,
in today's America, there's
no more trusted institution.
Before you had government,
you had media,
like New York Times, Washington Post,
you had science, you had military.
And the government is like,
they're just corrupt.
Screw them, Congress is
just hated by everyone.
They're just dead,
they're dead, dead,
dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead,
dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead,
dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead,
dead, dead, dead,
dead,
dead, The military fights
wars for no reason.
Look at Ukraine, look at Israel.
So in other words, there's
no institution in America
that can bring people together anymore.
They're not trusted. Oh, and also,
I forgot about universities.
Before people started universities, but not
anymore because of the culture wars, right?
So that's the problem
in America right now.
You have three things going on.
You have the militarization
of society where
anyone can start a war for no reason.
Okay. Second is that you have
a breakdown of the stories
and narratives that bind
the country together.
So no one knows what it
means to be American anymore.
And number three is there are
no more authority figures,
no more institutions that
can bring people together.
They're going to divide people.
Okay. Does that make sense?
Okay. And this is getting worse.
So we've seen the government fall,
the media fall, the science fall, military
fall, universities, but there's also the justice system, right?
The courts. And
this is falling as well
because of Donald Trump.
Remember like last week in New York City,
Donald Trump was convicted
guilty of 34 felonies.
Okay. And so
people are now no longer
trusting the courts.
The court system, the justice system.
Okay. So again, all
these sacred institutions
in America, they're
all falling one by one.
Okay. So does this make sense?
So if you look at all this, okay.
America's history of violence,
the conflicts ranging in America,
and the fact that
America no longer believes in institutions
and in narratives.
Okay. Then the most likely
outcome is a civil war.
Okay. Does that make sense?
So any questions so far? .
Yeah. So Celine asked
a very good question.
Like how powerful is
the American president?
And the answer is that
he's really a figurehead.
Okay. He's not that powerful. Okay.
Because as,
Celine points out, power is to
fuse in America, in institutions.
And if these institutions are corrupt,
there's very little the
president can do about it.
And that's why this
year in November, 2024,
we will see the lowest turnout,
one of the lowest turnouts of voters in
American history, because people just give up.
Okay. Right. Four years ago,
they came out to kick Trump out
of office because they believed
that Trump was a threat to democracy.
And with Biden, people recognize
that, no, it's all corrupt.
Just burn the system down. Who cares?
Okay. So no one cares
who's president anymore.
And that's going to
help Trump in November.
Okay. Any more questions
before I move on? Okay.
So Celine asked a question, what
will the civil war look like?
Okay. That's a very good question. And
the answer is it will look
nothing like the first civil war.
Okay. Because in the first civil war, there
was clearly a division that divided the nation.
Okay. A pro -slavery camp
and an anti -slavery camp.
Okay. But as you can see from
this chart in today's America,
conflicts, there are
many sorts of conflicts.
There are many sorts
of factions in America.
Okay. And therefore, the civil
war will not be one event,
but it will be a series of
violent episodes over 10,
20, 50 years. Okay. Does that make sense?
So let's go over these events.
Okay. The first thing that
would probably happen are
sort of riots and unrest.
Okay. And we saw that during
the first Trump presidency
because of the George Floyd
Black Lives Matter protests.
Okay. So we'll see more of that.
When Trump becomes president, where
people are
so angry at his election,
they'll start rioting.
Okay. And there'll be a lot of unrest.
Second is basically civil
conflict, meaning that neighbors
take guns against each other.
So America is divided
between left and right, but
there are actually
pockets of America where
left and right are very
they live very closely
with each other, okay?
So it's very likely they'll
take arms against each other.
But these would be small, isolated affairs
where maybe one or two
people get killed, okay?
So you have civil conflict.
Then you have state or city secession.
Secession, sorry, I spelled this wrong.
Secession, meaning that
you have maybe one city,
New York City, or one state,
California, and they're so
disgusted by the state of affairs,
they declare independence,
okay? They succeed. And guess what?
They have their own army.
Their citizens are armed, okay?
But they'll most likely be attacked
by other states or different groups,
okay? So that would be a
more major conflict, okay?
Then you have what
we'll call insurgencies.
So basically,
a political conflict between
a political group who's
trying to form a government
of some sort, okay?
So it's possible that
you have Christian extremists
or maybe left -wing extremists
who try to overthrow the government of,
I don't know, New York or Virginia, okay?
Then you have coup d 'etat,
where basically, an arm of the military,
maybe special forces, most
probably special forces,
tries to overthrow the government, okay?
So I think in, because
of the way things are structured,
in the next civil war,
all these things will
happen at once, okay?
And they'll build on top of each other.
But remember that America,
it's a very large country.
So there could be a lot of places
where, you know, it's very peaceful.
There's no war, okay? But
there could also be some places
like New York City or Los Angeles
where there's just a lot
of violence going on.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay. So
whether or not the US government is going
to be able to do this, whether or not the US government is over -thrown, that's a very specific question.
I don't know. Okay? The only
thing I can do is like,
look at the structural forces
and conclude that a
civil war is very likely
and that the civil war,
it will be very chaotic.
But what will actually happen in a
civil war, I don't actually know, okay?
Okay? But what I will say is that
given the nature of the civil war,
I think like once the war ends,
the outcome will be
that America becomes a Christian
isolationist theocracy. Okay?
And the reason is very simple.
Okay? The reason is very simple.
Remember that at the founding of America,
there were two opposing
visions of the country.
The first was to build a multicultural,
secular empire to spread democracy
and freedom around the world.
Okay? That was the first vision. And
America has achieved that vision.
And America has achieved
that vision. Okay?
And it's led to all this conflict.
The second vision, which
is also very strong,
is to believe in America
as a white Christian nation
dedicated to the rule of God.
Okay? And so
I think there'll be extremists in America
who will want to push this agenda.
And why would they win?
Why would they win?
Why are they most likely to win this war?
Okay, the answer is they're
most willing to fight
and to die for what they believe in.
Okay? And guess what, guys?
A lot of these people happen
to work in law enforcement,
the military, and
especially the special forces.
Okay? All right?
So that's what I think will
be the most likely outcome
of the Civil War when it ends.
But I don't know when it will end.
Okay? And I don't actually
know what happens in between.
The specifics, okay?
All right? So any more
questions before I finish?
Okay, the last thing I
want to talk about is
the specifics of how the
Civil War will start, okay?
What will ignite this war, okay?
Yeah, yeah, Peter? Yeah,
yeah, Peter? Yeah, yeah, Peter?
What is your sense of the fact that
the war can be still
going on in the college?
Okay, so Peter asked a
great question, which
is universities in the past few
decades have become more politicized,
okay? Meaning they're not actually
interested in teaching you how to think.
They're interested in teaching you
how to think a certain way, okay?
Which is very left wing, okay?
So for example, the belief
that America is a society
based on violence, right?
And the enslavery and
exploitation of minorities, okay?
So there's a lot of correctness
in universities today.
And Peter asked the question, okay,
so what can we learn in university?
And the answer is that even though
universities have become more politicized,
your education in university
is up to you, okay?
Why? Because the university is very big.
There are a lot of professors. And there
are a lot of different classes, okay?
And so it's up to you to
structure your own learning
and to be clear about
what you want to learn
and to understand the limitations of
the education you're getting, okay?
Does that make sense? All right,
any more questions before I move on?
. Okay, that's a great question, okay?
So Jack, I'm sorry. I'm sorry to
interrupt, but I just want to ask a question, like who are the ones who don't trust universities?
And the answer, of course, are people
who are left out of the system, right?
So people who don't actually go to university,
the people on the right, basically, okay?
People on the left are
composed mainly of college
educated individuals
who are wealthy, okay?
But at the same time,
there are many universities
who do not like what's going on.
So there's a faction
within the university,
professors, professors and students who
are dismayed by what's going on, okay?
But they're only a small fraction
of the total population, okay?
Most universities have become
extremely, extremely left wing,
okay? Any more questions before I move on?
. Okay, all right. All right, so
I'll move on to my next point, which
will answer your question, okay?
All right, now let's talk about how
the Civil War will actually start, okay?
And it will start with the election of Donald
Trump, the re -election of Donald Trump.
And the reason why is that
Trump is a unique figure
in American politics.
And the reason why is that he embodies.
.! Okay? Meaning, like,
the people on the left, all
that they hate in the right,
manifests themselves
in Donald Trump, okay?
He's white, he's sexist,
he's racist, he's a pig.
And he doesn't apologize for any of this.
He has no manners. He's not educated.
He has no values, okay?
All the left hate in the right,
manifests themselves in
the body of Donald Trump.
And that's why the right
loves Donald Trump,
right? Because their
enemies hate them, okay?
So, and for many on the right,
Donald Trump is the messiah, okay?
He's the Jesus. And
everything that's happened
in the past eight,
nine years for them has confirmed
that Donald Trump is evil.
He's the Jesus. Okay?
And the reason why is Donald Trump,
ever since he became elected president,
the left, the elite, has been
trying to persecute him, right?
Remember that when he became president,
they were spreading, the media
was spreading stories that
Trump was a Russian agent.
He was a spy of Putin.
That's just nonsense.
There's no evidence of that.
But people believe that, okay?
Then they were trying to say, then
they tried to use the justice
system against Donald Trump, right?
They impeached him twice.
They raided his house, okay?
They're trying to send him to prison.
A judge in Colorado tried to remove
Donald Trump from the ballot.
Meaning you couldn't vote for him.
So, everything that
the elite has done has been
to destroy Donald Trump.
And therefore, people on the right think,
this guy is our savior.
He's Jesus. He's the Messiah, okay?
Does that make sense? Now,
let's figure out this.
If you are on the left,
if you're the elite, if you're the
rich, and you hate Donald Trump,
there's exactly one way, and only one way,
you can destroy Donald Trump forever.
How? You guys know?
What would you do if you really
wanted to destroy Donald Trump?
And you were like rich
and liberal and elite?
You go to Donald Trump, you
have dinner together, and
you say three words, and you will
destroy him. What are these three words?
Okay. What you say to Donald
Trump, what you do is you say,
Let's be friends.
Friends. Right?
Why would I destroy Donald Trump?
What's the appeal of Donald Trump?
Why do people on the right love him?
Why does Niagara love him? Because?
That's right. Because he is an outsider.
He's the enemy of the elites.
Because the elites hate him, okay? So,
all the elites have to do is become
Donald Trump's friend, right?
Invite Donald Trump to his parties, say all
these nice things about him on the media,
and support Donald Trump.
And then people on the
right will be like, Oh,
we were fooled into thinking Donald Trump is
an outsider when he's actually an insider.
Okay? Then you've destroyed Donald Trump.
Why won't the elite do that?
No, it's not because they're too proud.
It's because what? Why won't they do that?
Like, why won't they become
friends with Donald Trump?
And you know, it's something that Donald
Trump probably wants as well, right?
Yeah, it's hatred, okay?
Do you understand? It's pure hatred.
I want to kill this guy.
Okay, do you understand?
So, you can see, like,
the hatred between left and right.
Remember that Donald Trump
manifests all the right.
Okay? All the cultural
values of the right.
Okay? And so people, the elite,
hate this guy so much that
they're willing to do anything
to get rid of this guy.
But the irony is that
because of this anger and hatred,
they're doing everything to
make Donald Trump invincible.
Okay? This is what we call TDS,
or Trump Derangement Syndrome.
The inability to...
recognize who Donald Trump is.
And the inability to think properly about
how to deal with Donald Trump. The...
Not only are the elite trying as hard
as they can to destroy Donald Trump,
but at the same time, they're
destroying the institutions
and the narratives that
hold America together.
Okay? Ever since Donald
Trump became president,
the mainstream media, New York
Times, CNN, Washington Post,
have relentlessly attacked him.
Therefore, destroying their credibility.
Okay? Therefore, destroying liberalism.
It's the elites themselves who
have destroyed the narratives
and the institutions that
bind America together.
And it's all because of
the hatred of Donald Trump.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So, it's really going to be
this hatred of Donald Trump
that drives the second American Civil War.
Okay? Right?
Does that make sense? All right.
So, let's see how this will play out.
Okay. So, what will
start the Civil War is...
Is... Is... Is... Is...
Is... And
the first thing that
Trump has to figure out
once he becomes president is, how does he
stay in office for the rest of his life, okay?
And the reason why is, the moment he
leaves office, he's going to be sued.
He's going to be put in jail. He's going
to be attacked by the elites, okay?
So the first thing he needs to
figure out, the only thing that
he actually cares about is, how do I
stay in office for the rest of my life,
okay? Now,
there's a trick he can use to stay
in office for the rest of his life,
okay? Because the Constitution says
that you can only serve
two terms as president.
But there's nothing in
the Constitution that says
you can't serve as vice president
for as long as you want.
Do you understand? So what
Trump can do in 2028 is
have his son,
run for president, and he
becomes the vice president.
But everyone will know that
he'll still be the president.
You understand? Does that
make sense to you guys?
That's a trick he can use in 2028, okay?
Because I guarantee you, the moment he
steps into the White House, he's like,
okay, how do I stay in here forever?
Because it's either the White House
or the jailhouse for me, okay?
So he's going to think
about how to stay in office.
And the easiest thing he
can do is have his son,
Don Jr., run as president.
He's run as vice president, okay?
But everyone will know that
he's still a president.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So you can imagine that
if Trump does this,
then this will create a
constitutional crisis in the country
where the left
go insane,
okay? You're talking about
riots on the streets.
Civil conflict. Maybe New York
City and Boston will be like,
we're leaving the union if Trump
becomes president again, okay?
You have these insurgencies all around
America to rebel against the Trump regime,
okay? So this is something that
Trump can do in 2028, okay?
Another question then is,
what can he do to ensure
that he wins in 2028?
And the easiest answer is,
in his, over the next two,
three years, start a war with Iran, okay?
All right? Start a war with Iran.
The reason why this is important is
that by starting a war with Iran,
he wins over the deep state, right?
He wins over the Israel lobby.
He wins over the military
-industrial complex.
He wins over a lot of
the elite on his side.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Now, we discussed that
America can't win over Iran. America
cannot possibly win a war against Iran.
This war can only drag on, right?
Now, let me ask you this question.
Why would this be good for Trump?
If this, if this, in 2028, okay?
He's running for vice president.
His son is president. He's
running for president.
And the war in Iran is dragging on.
Or it seems the United States
is going to lose this war.
Why would this be good for Trump in 2028?
The entire society, the entire left, is
mobilized to get rid of Trump, right?
Because they want this
war in Iran to stop.
So why would this war be
good for Trump in 2028?
Okay. I just say this, okay?
But there's going to be
a group of people who
are doing anything they can to
ensure that this war continues.
And who are they? Within America.
There's a group of people who are the
most pro -empire of everyone else.
And they fight a war. They want the
war to, they want to win the war.
And they'll do anything they can to ensure
that this war is won.
And who are they? Which
part of the military?
Exactly, okay? Do you
understand? Special forces, okay?
These guys are the military. These guys
are the problem. Special forces, okay?
In 2028, if there's a war in Iran and
Trump is running again
to maintain the war,
I guarantee you, these guys and
other steep state members will come
in and commit acts of terrorism,
acts of political assassination to ensure
that Trump wins, okay?
You'll also have election meddling,
election interference, okay?
They're going to cheat on behalf of Trump.
You understand? But if that's the case,
okay, if 2028 is an extremely
contested election,
then we can imagine at that point
the entire civil war blows up, okay?
New York City declares independence.
Boston declares independence.
California declares independence.
You have all these wars
breaking out across America,
okay?
Meanwhile, the United States is still
fighting this pointless war in Iran.
So I think that's what's going to happen.
All right. Any questions?
Or is there anything
you're not clear about?
Okay. So the U.S.
military, so Jack's question
is like, who will the U.S.
military support, okay? So the U.S.
military is very complicated because
it's divided into a lot of
different departments, okay?
So the military is not one beast.
It's like many, many
different beasts, okay?
Second problem is how the leadership
of the military is actually
extremely democratic.
But the base, the soldiers,
are extremely Republican, okay?
So you have this ideological
mismatch between the leadership,
the generals, and the soldiers, okay?
So it's most likely that
given these differences,
the military does not
intervene in the civil war,
okay? But there is a group in the military
who has the leeway, the flexibility,
and the will to intervene in this
war and its special forces, right?
Because they're not
controlled by bureaucracy.
Does that make sense? So question
then is, who will the U.S.
military support? Who will the special
forces support? And the answer is that
different special force units will
support different factions, okay?
That's why the civil war can
be extremely violent, right?
Because Americans will
have access to guns,
but these guys have
access to jets and bombs
and tanks, okay?
Does that make sense? Plus, like, again,
each one of these guys can
be a general in a war, right?
Special forces is
extremely powerful, okay?
Does that answer your question,
Jack? Okay. Any more questions?
Okay. So Celine asked
a great question, okay?
And this is actually the
most fundamental question.
It is really impossible
for the left to imagine
that Donald Trump will attack Iran because
Trump is seen as a leader.
He's seen as extremely anti -war, okay?
Donald Trump, when he was
a first -term president,
didn't start any wars.
And so the left is not expecting
Donald Trump to declare war
because he didn't do
so and he's declared he won't do so, okay?
But here's what we know.
First thing we know is that
presidents on the campaign trail
do things radically different from
when they become president, okay?
Every president is the same way.
What you say in public
before you become president
and what you do as president are
two very different things, okay?
That's the first thing.
Second thing is that
Donald Trump has recently said publicly
that Joe Biden is not doing
enough to protect Israel,
meaning that he will do
more to support Israel.
Well, what does that mean? It means
that he'll give Israel more weapons.
He'll give Israel more weapons and he
will defend Israel against its enemies,
which include Hezbollah and Iran, okay?
That's the second thing.
The third thing is that
there are now a group of billionaires who
are coalescing around Donald Trump, okay?
And these billionaires are Miriam Adelson,
who
is the most pro -Israel billionaire in
all of America. And she plans
to give Israel more weapons.
And she's going to give
Donald Trump $90 million,
okay?
That's a lot of money. But then you
also have someone like Stephen Swartzman
and Bill Ackman, okay?
All these guys are extremely pro -Israel.
They're Jewish billionaires
who are extremely pro -Israel.
Now why are they giving
Donald Trump a lot of money?
It's because they want something, right?
And what I'm guessing is what they want
is for Donald Trump to make millions.
Nikki Haley, his vice president,
okay? And to staff his cabinet,
his government, with pro
-Israel individuals, okay?
Who include Mike Pompeo
and others, okay?
In other words, Donald Trump presidency,
the government is going
to be extremely anti -Iran
and pro -war with Iran.
Nikki Haley, a couple
weeks ago, went to Israel.
She visited Israel. And she
took a picture of herself.
And what she did was
she signed a bomb, okay?
A bomb that was being dropped
on Gaza and said, finish them.
America loves Israel.
Nikki Haley, okay? She's calling for
mass genocide against the Palestinians.
That's Nikki Haley, guys. All right?
So given the way things are turning out,
I imagine that Nikki Haley
becomes vice president.
And that's good for Trump because
she's a scapegoat now, right?
Trump can say, hey, this war,
it's all Nikki Haley's fault, right? Okay?
Also Trump believed
that he won in 2020, okay?
He won in 2020.
But why did he lose the presidency?
Because a deep state. Rigged the election.
And why did a deep state
rigged the election?
Because he refused to fight wars.
So if he wants to become president,
then he has no choice but to play
along with the deep state, okay?
Which means going to war. So
a lot of what he will do as president depends
on if he picks Nikki Haley to be VP or not.
We'll know in August if he wants
Nikki Haley to be his VP, okay?
But if he picks Nikki Haley as VP.
That's good. That's a sure sign that
he's going to go to war
with Iran, I think.
Okay? Because she'll be
pushing for war with Iran.
Okay? But then the question is,
how will Donald Trump's base react?
Okay? Because his base is actually
extremely anti -Nikki Haley
and anti -war, right?
And the answer is, at first,
what will happen is that the
leadership of the Democratic Party,
the elite, the mainstream media,
will support Trump in his war with Iran.
Okay? And you have a lot of people
who support Trump who
feel, who felt betrayed.
Okay? But then over time,
what will happen is that
Donald Trump will figure
out how to manipulate his base
so that his base comes back to him.
Do you understand? Okay?
And so, there are different
ways he can do that.
First of all, what he can do is
blame Nikki Haley in the deep end
and says, oh, I was fooled.
I was manipulated. I now
want out of this war.
Okay? After he wins in 2028,
he can change directions and
say, I now want to end this war
and make America into a Christian
isolationist theocracy.
Okay? Okay?
Do you understand? That's
something that he can do.
Okay? So, I mean, something that
he can do is go against Israel.
Okay? And just say that it's Israel
that planned all this.
Okay? It's Israel that conspired
to trick America into going to war.
He can say that. And there'll
be a lot of people who say that.
Okay? It was the Jews who
conspired against us.
All right? So, there's a
lot of things he can say.
But whatever he does,
all it's going to do is create more war.
Okay? Within America. All he's going
to do is inflame the civil war.
Okay? No matter what he does,
there's going to be people who love him and
there's going to be people who hate him.
And they're going to go
to war with each other.
And that's why I think Donald
Trump, as long as he's in office,
the civil war is going to break
out and it's going to be very,
very violent.
Okay? Because he's...
I mean, again, I don't know what it is about
Donald Trump, but he brings up the worst in people.
Okay? In 2016,
before Donald Trump was president,
America was actually a pretty sane place.
Now, it's insane.
Now, it's like you can't
recognize it anymore.
Okay? Now, I mean, I'll
be honest with you.
Okay? I am very much on the left.
Okay? I think like a person on the left.
Now, my values are extremely
liberal left values.
Okay? And in 2016, when
Trump became president, I was traumatized.
I believed the world had fallen apart.
Okay? I believed the world was destroyed.
Everything that I
believed in was destroyed.
And it took me a long time
to step out of the trauma.
But, you know, I still
have these liberal friends.
And I give... And like the
moment we talk about Trump,
if I say anything nice about Trump,
which is like, okay, you know what?
Trump is an idiot, but
he's representing people
who feel marginalized.
They become so angry with me.
Okay? Like I feel insecure or unsafe.
I feel as though they're
about to punch me.
Okay? If I say anything
nice about Donald Trump,
then people will want to punch me.
Okay? And like I'm their friend.
I've known them for like
decades. And they know that,
like, I hate Donald
Trump as much as anyone.
Okay? But you're not actually anything
nice about Donald Trump among liberals
and leftist people. Okay?
So, does that answer
your question, Celine?
Okay. So it's complicated. Okay? But
I think this is what could happen.
All right? Any more questions?
Yes. So, what is the political data that
can demonstrate what about the
separation of the US and the U.S.
and the U.K.? Okay.
So, this goes back to
the question of empire.
Okay? So, again, unfortunately,
there are a lot of Americans
who benefit from empire.
Okay? That's why they want war with Iran.
So, these people work on Wall Street.
They work for the military
industrial complex.
And they tend to live in the suburbs.
Okay? Okay.
Any more questions? Is there
anything you're not clear about?
Does this argument make sense to you?
Does the logic here
make sense to you guys?
Okay. Is there anything you don't...
You want me to clarify?
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.