Okay, so good morning. We finished the Bronze Age today with the Indus Valley civilization.
好的，早上好。我们今天完成了古铜时代的印度河谷文明。
So we've done Egypt, we've done Mesopotamia, now we're doing the Indus Valley civilization.
我们已完成古埃及古巴塞尔的古河谷古河谷。
And today I'm going to look at three questions, okay?
今天我会去看三种问句。
First of all, what is it that
先于此，印度河谷文明是什么使其与其他文明不同？
makes the Indus Valley civilization distinct or different from other civilizations?
第二个是：先前的…
Second is, why did they decline?
先前…
They reached their peak about 2600 to 1900 BCE,
他们在公元前2600年至1900年左右达到顶峰，随后三百多年衰落并最终消失。
and then for the next three to four hundred years, they declined
他们在公元前2600年后…
and ultimately disappeared.
…
Okay, why did it happen?
好的，为什么会出现？
The last question is, what is their legacy?
最后一问：…
What is their contribution to the development of Western civilization?
好的…
Okay? All right. So,
好的？全部好。然后…
let's look at the Indus Valley civilization.
看起来…
To do so... We need to first understand the world at this time.
先…
And this is about 2500 to 2000 BCE,
和这约在公元前2500到2000年之间，
okay? This is what we call the Middle Bronze Age.
好的？这就是我们所说的中青铜时代。
Because most people were using bronze for weapons, for tools.
因为大多数人使用青铜制造武器与工具。
So, over here is Egypt.
好的，位于此处是埃及。
And as we discussed, by far, Egypt is the wealthiest country in the world.
如前所述，埃及在百年前的百年里，最…
And it's the most advanced civilization in the Bronze Age.
...
Over here, across the Red Sea, is Arabia.
Over ... ... ... … … … … … … ... … … … ... … … … ... … … … ... ? … …... … ? … … … JSON … … ... … … Over …………………………………………………………………………………
And even though Arabia isn't really discussed that
...
much in world history, it's still significant
because it's part of the trading network.
翻译：...
Okay? So, the Arabia, it's many nomads
...
who
take goods from Mesopotamia over to Egypt
...
and then into the Middle East.
And then, the Mediterranean, which acts as all of Europe.
...
This is Sumer,
这是 Sumer ！
which is the beginning of the Mesopotamian civilization.
Okay? Up here is Anatolia,
OK? 这里是安纳塔尔。
the Levant.
...
And then, the Indus Valley civilization is over here.
And today, it would cover the countries of Afghanistan,
Pakistan, and the Middle East. First off, here is Pakistan.
巴基斯坦，和中东
First off here is Pakistan. First off here is Pakistan.
第一条是巴基斯坦
First off here is Pakistan.
...
First off here is Pakistan. First off here is Pakistan.
第一条...
First off here is Pakistan.
第一条是巴基斯坦。
First off here is Pakistan. First off here is Pakistan.
第一条是巴基斯坦。第一条是巴基斯坦。
First off here is Pakistan. First off here is Pakistan. First off here is Pakistan.
第一条 … ?
First off here is Pakistan.
...
First off here is Pakistan. First off here is Pakistan.
第一条是巴基斯坦。第一条…
First off here is Pakistan.
第一条…
First off………..??
trade. And in this valley civilization,
?
what was unique to them are certain products,
翻译结果
for example, indigo dye, which
]\}We need to translate cues [49] and [50] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translations. Let's translate: cue 49:
was really sought after in Mesopotamia and in Egypt.
在马萨波特里亚和埃及被广泛追捧的东西
Their handicrafts, their jewelry,
在马萨波……??
were also very famous throughout the world.
...
They usually traded with Sumer
and Egypt by trading with the Gulf state nations of Bahrain
...
and Oman and Dubai.
和奥马尔·奥马尔与杜拜。
And they actually had a colony by the Persian Gulf.
??
This civilization was so good at trading
这文明的贸易实力很强
that we believe they even traded with China,
这文明的两种方位
which is pretty far away, but their ships were huge
哪一段落?
and they were very good navigators.
...
As a the Bronze Age developed over time,
bronze was in heavy demand
...
and the main components of bronze are copper and tin.
和铜、锡是青铜的主要成分。
Tin is mainly found in the mountains of Afghanistan over here,
锡在此处的山脉里有可供的量。
which
...
meant the Inis Valley civilization
started to now expand over to Afghanistan in order to access the tin trade.
...
So tin was really sought after, but there was also a lot of gold in the desert.
So the gold was mainly found in the mountains of Afghanistan, but there was also another stone called lapis lazula,
which is really sought after by the Egyptians for its spiritual
which is really sought after bythe Egyptians for its spiritual
and aesthetic qualities.
And over here,
在此处...
because
因为...
of the trade with Afghanistan,
...
land would start to develop into Anatolia
陆地开始在安塔尔里亚和马尔萨波特里亚发展起来。
and Mesopotamia.
And as well, because of this trade in Afghanistan,
和...因为...在阿富尔之...
new civilizations start to develop as well.
...
And they're not as advanced,
它们不如前面三大文明那般先进，但它们依然很有进步。
as large as the three major ones, but they're still pretty advanced.
它们不如前面三大文明...
So for example, up here is what we call the Oxus Valley civilization.
[82] So for example, up here...
The technical term used by
[83] The...
archaeologists are the
考古学家是巴塔克里-马格尼亚考古学复合体。
Bactrian -Margiana Archaeological Complex.
You don't have to know this, okay? It's called BMAC.
你不必知道这个，好的？它叫BMAC。
What makes this civilization important
...……………………………………………
is it interacts with the steppes people,
]\}We need to translate cues [86], [87], [88] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translations inorder. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use preferred terms. Let's translate: [86]
called the Andromeno culture.
??
So as you can see, the Inis Valley civilization,
翻译1
through its partners,
翻译2
the Oxus Valley civilization
翻译1
and its colonies over here,
??
the Inis Valley civilization, through its partners, the Oxus Valley civilization and its colonies over here, now trade with the entire world.
伊斯河谷文明通过其伙伴、乌克斯河谷文明及其在此的殖民，已与全世界进行贸易。
There's no piece of the Western world the Inis Valley civilization does not touch.
还有一条”??
Does that make sense? So
那算得了吗？所以
this is a world about 2500 to 2000 BCE.
这是一段约2500年到2000年BCE的世界。
It's a world that's heavily interconnected.
它是一个高度互联的世界。
And there are two major sources of demand.
它有两个主要的需求来源。
The Egyptians are extremely wealthy,
and they want these valuable jewelry
and handicrafts for their burials.
...
That's one source of heavy demand.
That's one source of heavy demand. The main source of demand is actually Mesopotamia,
where the city -states of Sumer are fighting wars against each other.
在 Sumer 的城市-州之间，...
And in wars, bronze makes a huge difference,
翻译
because bronze armor is much more stronger than copper armor.
??
So these two places are driving demand,
翻译
and as such,
?
the Inis Valley civilization is growing wealthy through trade.
the ... ...
Does that make sense? Any questions so far before I continue?
...
Okay, so even though
好的，......
the Inis Valley civilization is connected with Egypt
...
and Mesopotamia, it's a radically different civilization.
和..................
Okay? So the first thing that
...
makes the Inis Valley civilization interesting is it's a huge area.
使得印度河谷文明很大…
It's actually, in terms of size,
]\}??\}??????????????????????????????翻译?????????\{
larger than Egypt and Mesopotamia combined.
比埃及马萨多合起来更大。
It has a population of, at its peak, about 5 million people.
在其巅峰时，人口约为5万千人。
Okay? So this is a huge area.
...
What's really interesting is we have
found no evidence of any
...
organized warfare in this region during this time.
在此时期，该地区的有组织的战争已被记录。
The reason why is this region is connected through trade.
该地区通过贸易连接而已形成。
Okay? So what we have found is five major urban centers.
在此时刻，已知五个主要城市中心。
In the Inis Valley civilization.
在印度河谷文明中。
And these urban centers,
和这些城市中心
you can consider to be what
你可以考虑...
we call value
我们把它们称为“值”加工处理中心。
-adding processing centers.
我们把它们城市中心的“值”处理中心
Okay? These are urban centers that specialize in taking raw goods,
...
like metals
像金属
and agricultural products,
和 …
and turning them into finished products, like jewelry, handicrafts.
… …
To be shipped,
待运送，
to be traded with mainly Mesopotamia,
主要以美索福尼亚为主，
but also Egypt, and possibly China as well.
...
It also goes north to the Oxus Valley civilization,
它也向北延伸至奥克苏斯河谷文明，
which then trades with the steppe people, the Andenov culture.
它们在此后又与之……
Okay? What we know as the Yamnaya people.
…
Alright? So this trade network,
...
it's very, very complex.
And
...
everyone is involved in some capacity in this trade network.
每个人都以某种方式参与了这条贸易网络。
Okay? So that's the first thing that's interesting about the Inis Valley civilization.
好的？这就是印度河谷文明的第一件有趣的事。
They trade internally peacefully.
他们内部贸易顺利如同
They trade externally peacefully as well.
他们也以外部贸易顺利如同
We have absolutely no evidence that they ever had organized warfare.
我们完全没有证据他们曾有组织战争
We have absolutely no evidence that
我们完全没有证据
they have any intention of organized warfare.
他们有意外部战争吗？
Meaning we have not found any weapons.
我们没能找出武器？
We have found tools. We found hunting weapons.
我们找到了工具，能有点？
We have not found, like, maybe armor and helmets.
...
Okay? Yeah? Is there any particular defense
that we can expect, like that
...
there is no organized warfare in that situation?
有点...
Yeah. Great question. So how do we know there's no organized warfare?
好的，先来个翻译吧！
So we know there's a lot of organized warfare in Mesopotamia and
]\}We need to translate cues 157 and 158. Provide JSON with translations arrayof two strings. Use simplified Chinese. Use terms. Let's translate: cue 157:
other places because
其他地方...??
of what we have dug up.
]\}We need to translate cues 159 and 160. The previous context? We have earlier cues. Let's parse. The current cues: [159] other places because [160] of what we havedug up. We need to translate these two cues into Simplified Chinese. Use natural phrasing. Provide array with two strings. Let's produce translations. For cue 159:
So we look at cities. We see parts of the city
其他地方因为我们挖掘出的东西
that have been built on top of or destroyed.
我们挖掘出的东西的那部分
Meaning there might have been some fires or there might have been some warfare.
...
Okay? But with these five urban centers
that we've dug up, we have found them pretty intact.
...
Meaning they were not built on top of or they were not destroyed
when they were around.
当他们在那里的时候。
So that's the first major piece of evidence.
那是第一条主要的证据。
The second major piece of evidence is we've dug up their graves.
So if you look at maybe the civilizations
...
of the Andronovo culture or Mesopotamia,
翻译成中文
they tend to bury warriors with their weapons.
...
Okay? So, you know, helmets and armor.
OK? 这句...
But when we've dug up the IVC culture people,
但当我们发掘出印度河流域文化人们...
first of all, we don't find a distinct cast of warriors.
...
Also, we don't find any helmets or armor or weapons.
Okay? So that's the first thing.
好的？这就是第一件事。
That's what led us to believe they don't engage in organized warfare.
这就是我们认为他们不从事有组织的战争的原因。
But there's also evidence to suggest our evidence is not solid.
还有证据表明我们所用的证据并非十分可靠。
Okay? The first piece of evidence is they don't bury their dead.
好的，先前两句…
These people don't have a tradition of burying their dead.
这些人没有埋葬死者的传统。
Some are buried. Okay? But not everyone is buried.
有些人被埋葬。好的？但有时候有个别的。”
Second of all, we don't know where they buried their dead.
第二个，...
We assume they buried their dead in the cities.
...
But that may not be true.
但那可能不是真的。
Okay? So the evidence leans towards they were a peaceful civilization.
好的，先前两句…
But as we dig up more and
但随着我们不断挖掘，逐步发现…
more over time, we may discover this was not true.
...
Okay? But right now the evidence suggests they were peaceful.
好的？但现在的证据表明他们是和平的。
And also what's really important about the IVC, the Nisvalik civilization,
以及……
is this is a new discovery.
这……
We've only known about them for the past 100 years.
我们只在过去100年里才知道了它们的名字。
So what's interesting is the Indians themselves never knew they existed.
印度人自己也没能给出它们的名字。
It was the British who
英国人先给了它们的名字。
discovered these cities and
发现这些城市并开始考古工作以重建它们的文明。
started the work in archaeology to start to reconstruct their civilization.
好的？一切都好。
Okay? All right.
But thanks for the question. Okay.
但感谢你的提问。好。
So as I said,
我刚才说过的那一条
the first thing that's interesting about
第一条有点儿…
their civilization is it was relatively peaceful,
...
okay, compared with what's happening in Mesopotamia.
好的，与美索不太相同。
The second thing that was interesting for us is,
“可”…
and surprising is, for a very large civilization,
并且令人惊讶的是，对于一个大规模文明，它们是平等的。
they are egalitarian.
并且…
Okay? Meaning in Mesopotamia,
OK? 先前在美索里亚里…
when we look at these old cities, Ur and Uruk,
?
there were these huge palaces and
...??????????????????????????????????????????…”””……”……”…”……………………”……………………………??…????……………………1?…???????…???…?……………………………???…..?????..?????..?????..?????..?????..?????..???\{
temples which
?……..??..???……..??……..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..………………………………………………………………………
suggested a culture of power in the priesthood
...
and in the king.
在...??……????…??…??…??…??…??…??…??……??…………………………………………………………………………………
Okay? But when
OK? 先前…
we look at these five urban centers of the IVC,
我们看着这五个城市中心的I...??……??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??……??…??…………??…??…………??…………??…???…??…?????…??..?????..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..???…??………??…???…??...????????..??..??..???…..??..??..??..??..点…??…??..??..??………??………??………??………..??…??……??……..??………..??…..??……?…..??…..??..??…?…..??………..??…??……
there are no palaces.
...
There are no temples.
Okay? In fact, these cities are extremely well designed.
...
There are these walls around the city.
And then as you go into the city,
当你进入城市时，
you're able to access every single part of the city.
你可以访问城市的每个部分。
Okay? But if you were to go into a city,
好的，若你要进入城内
say, in Sumer, if you go into the city,
好的，若你先前往城内
you're only able to access the temple or the palace.
你只需要访问寺庙或宫殿。
Okay? So authority is centralized in Sumer.
好的，...
Whereas authority is sort of
在此时，...??
decentralized in the IVC.
...??
Now here's a question. If we know,
???
if we suspect they are not engaged in warfare,
why do they have walls?
为什么有墙？
Why would, there are a lot of walls inside these cities.
为什么有墙
Why are there walls? Can anyone guess?
为什么有墙？能否给出???
Okay. Customs.
??????????????
Taxes. Okay? Meaning,
???????关??????????????????
this is again a value added, adding process center.
这又是一个增值，添加过程中心。
And the way they survive economically is by collecting tolls
他们的经济方式是通过收取关税和关税。
and customs on people who trade.
And the way they collect taxes is, when
236. And the way...?
you enter the city, you have to go to the capital.
]\}
You have to go to the customs house. And then
]?
you pay whatever is required of you.
翻译1
And then you can access the city.
翻译后...
Okay? And that's the way they centralized,
?
centrally controlled the economy and trade in the IVC.
中心化控制了印度河谷文明的经济与贸易。
These cities are amazing.
这些城市真是太棒了！
These are the first people to invent the sea toilet.
这些人先发明了海水冲洗的水槽！
The private sea toilet.
私家海厕
This is about the year 2800 BCE.
大约公元前2800年
Okay? So, when you go into these cities, you'll find
好的？当你进入这些城市时，便可见到
that in private homes, everyone has a private toilet.
在私宅里，每个人都有自己的厕所。
And then the feces is put into a sewage system
随后把粪便放入排水系统，
and the water flushes it out.
再把水冲洗出去。
Okay? That's pretty amazing.
好的？这很不错。
These are people who
这些人们...
are very concerned about the well -being of all its citizens.
这些人们很...
So, when we look at skeletal remains through DNA analysis,
翻译1
we've discovered the majority of the people ate about the same high quality of food.
翻译2
There wasn't these disparities between people,
翻译3
as you would find in other civilizations.
如同其他文明所见
At least half the people, we think, lived past the age of 55.
至少有一半的人口在 55 之后生活
That was an amazing achievement back then.
那是当时的惊人之作
In terms of innovation,
在创新方面，
they have research.
他们有研究。
They have reservoirs. They also have public baths.
他们有水库。还有公共浴池。
They also had really amazing things called wind towers.
...
I'm not sure if you've studied these wind towers, but they're basically air conditioners.
What they do is, these are high towers
...
and there is a hole on top.
在此处有一个空洞。
So, what happens is, the higher the air is,
在此处的高空气流动时，气流高处的气体更高，气流更高……………………………………………..
the cooler it is. So,
]\}We need to translate cues [266] and [267] and [268] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON with translations array.Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use natural Chinese. Let's translate each cue in order: [266]
this wind that's cool gets strapped into the wind.
...
So, the wind comes down and it pushes out the hot air from the other side.
This is what cools the houses in the summer.
...
This is a pretty advanced technology.
翻译成...??
Another really cool thing about the IVC is,
?……???
even though it covers a huge area,
?…..???
they have standardized weights and measurements.
他们有统一的重量和度量。
They have standardized weights and measurements.
Which means that every brick that they have is the same size.
这意味着每块砖块都一样大小。
Which means that
哪怕...??
their buildings, their structures,
...????
are extremely stable and resilient.
??
That's why, 5,000 years later, we still have their cities intact.
那就是为什么，五千年前的城市至今仍然完整。
You can actually go to the cities and live in them.
你可以去到城市里去，去上面…
That's how stable the technology was.
那种技术的…
So, this is a pretty advanced civilization.
所以，这是一种相当先进的文明。
Unfortunately, we don't have it.
不幸地，没能得到它。
We don't know what their writing system is.
我们还不知道它们的文字系统是什么。
So, if they had writing, and
所以如果他们有文字，且
we can't know for sure if they had writing,
我们可以在此时刻…
it was like Chinese in the idiographic language.
其在…
Meaning, it is not phonological.
意思是它不是音素的。
Their spoken language is not the same as their written language.
他们的语音语音语音语音语音语音语音语音语音语音语音语…
In other words, it is impossible for us to decipher their written language.
先前…
We don't have that
我们没有那样
many artifacts of writing.
许多写字的文物
We have seals with characters written on them.
我们有印章上写着字符。
But we don't have anything else.
但我们还没有其他东西。
And the reason could be, if you look at Egypt, they use papyrus.
“如果你看埃及的字形，…………………………………………………………………………??……………………外………??…??……………………………??…………??………………………………??……………………………………………??…??…中文………??……………………………i………??…………??…??…\{
Papyrus is stable,
?
or it keeps in the dry Egyptian air.
在干燥的埃及空气里，或许多字形…
If you look at Samarian culture, Mesopotamian culture,
如果你们有点儿…
they use cuneiform on clay tablets.
…
Which keeps forever.
哪一条保持永远。
But if they had a writing system, and they did write,
...
it would be on palm leaves.
Which degrades very easily in the jungle air.
哪一条在…
So, we don't have access to their writing.
...
This is problematic, because without access to their writing,
we don't have access to their religion.
我们没有接触他们的宗教。
We don't know what their religion is.
我...??
And one thing that you've learned in this class that's very important is,
]\}\{
religion, or mythology,
宗教，或神话，
it is the operating system of religion.
它是宗教的操作系统。
It is the operating system of the culture. It is the collective consciousness,
它是文化的操作系统。它是…
the collective worldview, that gives life to their culture.
集体的全局视角，给了他们文化的生命。
It explains why they do what they do.
它给了他方的...
And unfortunately, we don't know their religion.
其…
But, so,
翻译后可用????????????????????????????????????????
it's a complete mystery to archaeologists, to scholars,
?????????????……??…???…??……??…??………??…………………………………
as to why this very advanced civilization was very peaceful
????????…??………………………………………………………………
and very egalitarian.
...
We can only speculate. Any questions so far, before I continue?
]\}We need to translate cue 321:
Okay, so, I'm going to speculate as to why they were peaceful
...
and egalitarian. So, again,
??
the key is the religion.
What is the religion? Because that
will give us clues as to their mentality, their value system.
will give us clues as to theirmentality, their value system.
Right? We know that the Mesopotamian people,
their religion focused on struggle and achievement.
their religion focused onstruggle and achievement.
We know that the Egyptians, their religion focused on the afterlife.
我们知道埃及人...
Okay? This life that we live is,
好的，...??
what's important is not the here and now.
重要的是现在的事物不是现在的事物。
What's important is what happens afterwards.
重要 … … ??
Okay? And that's why the Egyptians built the pyramid.
好的？那就是埃及人建造金字塔的原因。
That's why they focused so much on funeral rites and on burial goods.
好的，...??
Alright? So, there had to be a religion in the IBC
好的？所以，伊布尔里卡里…??
that was different from the belief system in Sumer in Egypt
??????…??
that made it into a peaceful and
...
egalitarian civilization.
Okay? Alright. So, what is this religion and why were they different?
好的？好吧。于是…
My speculation is this.
我的想法是…
The key is to understand that this is a civilization based on trade.
关键在于理解这是一种以贸易为基础的文明。
And they've been traders ever since they were born as a culture.
从一开始就有了这类人类的古老文化。”
Meaning they were trading for at least 7,000,
翻译成中文：
8,000 years before they became a civilization.
...
Okay? And if you're a trader,
OK? 先后……
first of all, you're able to access the entire world.
...
So, we know for a fact they traded with Sumer
So, we know for a factthey traded with Sumer
and the Persian Gulf states.
...
Because we have, we have artifacts from the IBC in these places.
Okay? We know for a fact. We can speculate it.
OK? 先后…
They also traded with Egypt and
他们也与埃及...
with China just based on their technology and
with China just basedon their technology and
their trade networks.
So, this is a civilization based on trade.
翻译1
And as traders,
翻译2
they're able to see what's going on in Mesopotamia and Egypt.
他们能看到底格里亚和埃及的动向。
They know they built the pyramids in Egypt.
他们知道底格里亚里建造了古埃及的金字塔。
They know there's massive warfare in Sumer.
...???????????????
And I would think that
...????????...???
if you were a trader and you saw these things, you wouldn't be impressed.
Okay? In fact, you might be disgusted,
...
especially by the warfare in Mesopotamia.
This idea called the dialectic, right?
翻译结果
And I think this is a very important idea for
...
us to appreciate how history is often driven by the idea of the dialectic.
我们来回顾一下…
So, an example that
]\}
we have in today's world is, you look at Japan and China.
...
Okay? These are two radically different societies
好的？这两种截然不同的社会
that are next to each other.
好的，...
And the question then is, why are they still different?
又是...
I think the answer is because Japan knows China very well.
...
And a lot of cultural practice Japan
developed over the centuries have been in response
...
to what they see as failings or successes in Chinese culture.
到他们认为的中文文化的失败或成功。
Okay? Another example that
好的，...
Doug will appreciate is Canada and the United States.
多格会欣赏的是加拿大和美国。
The United States is probably the most belligerent nation in the world.
美国大概是世界上最具战斗性的国家。
Okay? They cannot get their hands off anything.
好的？ 他们可以把手放在...??
And then you go north, Canada,
...
and Canada and the United States share the world's longest border.
和加拿大与美国共享世界最长的边界。
Basically, Canadians are cousins of the Americans.
基本上，拉丁美洲人是相互相同的。
Okay? I mean, like, there's really no difference.
好的，...
We speak the same language.
我们说同一种语言。
We have the same cultural practices.
我们有同样的文化习惯。
But while Americans are the most belligerent nation ever in human history,
但当美国人是人类历史上最具战斗的...
Canadians invented peacekeeping.
可译为：...
Okay? The idea, like,
...
nations should strive for mediation
and peace.
和和平。
Okay? And I think a lot of Canada, a lot of Canadian values,
好的？我想…
especially its political system,
is in response to what it believes to be failings and successes in the American model.
在回应其认为的美国模型的失败与成功时。
Okay? You also have New Zealand and Australia.
好的，...
So there are many different examples of the dialectic going on in our global political systems.
在此处有多种不同的…
And I believe that's what happened
我认为这就是发生的事
with the IVC, where these traitors saw what's happening in Egypt
在...??…
and saw what's happening in Mesopotamia, and
??…
they were kind of disgusted,
他们在这段时间里有点儿…
especially by all this warfare in Mesopotamia.
...…………??…
Okay? Warfare back
??…??
then was pretty awful.
然后很糟糕。
And so in Mesopotamia, the way they fight is,
在马里亚里里…
they fight with these clay bullets.
他…
Okay? And you take a slingshot and you throw it at someone.
好的？然后你拿弹弓，往人投掷。
And these things kill.
这些小物件能投掷，能投掷…
They hurt. So think of David and Goliath.
先前……
Okay? And if you're a traitor,
好的？如果你是个叛徒，你会看到这场战争的进展。
you know, you'll see this warfare going on.
你会看到人们被砍头的样子。
You'll see people being, being beheaded.
And why are they doing this? They're doing it in the name of God.
...
Okay? Every city -state has a patron god
that it believes it must defend
...
and honor and protect.
和荣耀与保护。
And whenever there's a dispute, it's
当且...
because they feel their god has been dishonored by another city -state.
之...
So they go to war and they kill each other.
...
Okay? And again, if you're a traitor and you see this, you don't think this is a good thing.
OK? 这回又...??
And you go to Egypt and you see these pyramids,
And you go to Egypt andyou see these pyramids,
and these pyramids are, again, extremely impressive.
和这些古塔再次非常壮观。
But at the same time, you also need to see the consequences of these pyramids,
?
which is just massive inequality,
421. 这就是...
massive corruption, just massive waste.
421?
All right? So I think
全部好？所以我认为
that by trading with these two civilizations and other civilizations,
通过与这两种文明...
it reinforces the deep cultural values of the IBC people
and it basically compels them towards peace
...
and egalitarianism. Okay?
That's what I believe happened. All right?
现在...我想...我...??
Now, you could... There are other arguments.
现在，...我想...??
For example,
...
maybe these people are
just genetically peaceful and egalitarian.
...
But I've made the argument in this class that
from the onset of early human history, we were peaceful
...
and egalitarian people, but
and egalitarianpeople, but
different geographic circumstances changed our outlook.
...
Okay? So, for example, the people in the steppes,
OK? 这句...??
who we call the Anar people, because
438. 先后??
of the grasslands, because it is such a poor and
translations
rugged and unforgiving environment,
翻译结果
they're forced to be cattle ranchers.
他们被迫从事牧牛业。
They're forced to engage in cattle raiding.
Okay? And over time, their culture became very aggressive,
OK? 这句...??
expansionist, and
...
opportunistic. Opportunistic.
opportun...
Opportunistic just means they'll do whatever it needs to survive.
Opportun...
If they face a...
...
They'll trade with people if that's what benefits them.
他们会与人们进行交易，只要能给他们带来利益。
They'll kill people if that's what benefits them.
他们会在此时...
They are not that moral.
...
Okay? They're very opportunistic. And
OK? 先后…………………………………………………
I remember, as I said, these people with their cultural values
,
would go in and
...
conquer all of Europe in about 200, 300 years.
Okay? And they were called the Anar people.
OK? 先后……...……………………
Back in the steppes,
OK? 先后…………
these Anar people continued to evolve over time.
这些安拉人继续演变，时间里………………………………………………………………………………-??…??……………………………………1? 1..???…………??? ? … … 中文 … ?? … … … -… … 更好…… … ‐ … … -… … -… … 时间…… …古…… … 安…… … ??… … ? … 句… i… … … 翻… i… 繁… 地… 1… … … 1… … We need to produce JSON with translations array of two strings. The cues: [457]
And over time, they became even more aggressive,
and [458]
more expansionist, and more opportunistic.
more...??
Okay? Eventually, the Mongols, Genghis Khan and Mongols,
]\}We need to translate two cues: [459]
will come from this civilization.
...
Okay? So that's my argument to you.
And again, it's my speculation.
又一次，我的猜测。
It is because of the reaction of other cultures that
因为其他文化的反应，...】】\}We need to translate cues 463-465. Provide array of three translations. Let's translate. Cue 463:
convinced them to pursue a peaceful and egalitarian lifestyle.
? Actually cue 463:
Now, there are still inequalities in IBC.
...
We know there are classes. We know there's wealth inequality.
But relative to Mesopotamia and Egypt,
...
it was a relatively peaceful
???
and egalitarian society.
...
Okay? Okay,
any questions before I continue?
...
Okay, so the question is,
were they invaded the IBC?
他们在前面...
Okay, because as we discussed
...
in previous classes,
在前面...
when you're peaceful in a egalitarian society, we know that
?
old Europe, okay, before the Amna invasion,
老欧陆，好的，在阿姆纳入侵之前，是个和平且平等的社会。
was a peaceful and egalitarian society.
was a peaceful andegalitarian society.
You will eventually get invaded by other cultures.
...
Okay? And for the longest time,
there was a theory out there,
有一个理论在外面，
first proposed by,
有一个…………??
basically the Nazis, okay,
484: 1/2? 1/JSON? 1/..??..??
called the Indo -Aryan Invasion.
? 1..??..??
And the idea is, you have these white people
?..??..翻译??
sweep into India,
扫入印度，
conquer the people, and introduce civilization
征服人民并将文明带给印度人。
to the Indians.
Okay? This is called the Indo -Aryan Invasion.
OK? 这就是...??
Even though this theory has been discredited,
即使得方程式...??
there is a slight kernel of truth to this theory,
...???
okay, which I will explain to you.
好的，我会把它解释给你。
Okay, so, let me explain this theory and what happened.
好的，先说一下…
So you have the IBC, which is a very advanced civilization.
495 译文1
The problem with this civilization is,
495 译文2
their entire economy is basically based on trade.
他们的整个经济基本以贸易为主。
Right? Now, we know about,
“我”??
there's something called the 4.2 -kilo -year event,
...
which is basically a massive climate change around the world. And
the 4.2 -kilo -year event brought
???
basically an end to the Egypt O Kingdom. Right?
It also brought an end to what
503: 其...
we call the Akkadian Empire in Sumer.
...
A man named Sargon of Akkad conquered all of Sumer
and built the Akkadian Empire.
并且建造了阿卡德帝国。
And because of this drought, because of climate change,
并且建造了阿卡德帝国。”
his empire collapsed.
\}]
Okay? So in other words, trade networks
...
that the IBC is heavily dependent on
那一段文字的意思是：我先把“...”后面…
start to collapse.
...
Okay? And as a result,
OK? 这句...??
their cities now, which
???
are dependent on trade, start to depopulate.
514. 依赖于交易，开始脱落
Meaning a lot of people start to return
...
to the farms where they are from.
\}]
They start also migrating
...
to the rest of India, to the Ganges.
Okay? As well, because of this climate change,
好的，另外因为这天气变化
the IBC itself is being affected heavily.
...
Okay? So there's drought,
OK? 这句...??
the rivers are drying up.
...
Remember, like the Indus Valley Civilization, it's called the Indus Valley Civilization because
记得...??
it's dependent on the Indus River, among other rivers.
它依赖于印度河，其他河流中。
Okay? So there are some drought issues.
好的，先说个别的…
Also, what we learn in this class is
在这门课里我们学到的内容是
over time,
时间上...??
all civilizations face eternal tensions.
所有文明都有永恒的...
Okay? And
...
these eternal tensions can be divided into two major tensions.
这些永恒的矛盾可分为两大类。
The first tension is a conflict among the classes.
第一类冲突是类间的冲突。
Okay? So the idea of elite overproduction.
好的？那么精英过度生产的概念。
You have too many people striving for limited status.
你们有太多人去争夺有限的地位。
Right? And the conflict is mainly between upper nobility
对吗？而且冲突主要在于上层贵族与下层贵族之间。
and lower nobility.
对呀！
Okay? And so here in the IBC,
译文1
we can imagine the conflict might be between these families
译文2
that are large training houses
译文
against families that are small training houses.
对小型训练院的家族们
Okay? Or it could be like internally among the families.
好的，先前的那句…
Okay? But there's going to be some social tension going on.
好的，先前…
The other social tension that we discuss is the idea of rat utopia.
...
Where, and it's basically conflict between the old and the young.
在这里，基本上是老人与年轻人之间的冲突。
Again, the problem in the IBC is you have too many old people living for too long,
再一次，IBC中的问题是老百合久久。”
which means less opportunities arise for achievement for the young.
哪一…
Okay? And that creates conflict as well.
...
So what we believe that it also is
所以我们认为它也在此时发生了
that during this time, there was massive social tension
在此时，...
within the IBC.
在IBC内。
And some people would even say it was a revolutionary time.
在此时，...
Okay? When old customs and
好的？当时…
old mores were being overthrown.
好的，...
Okay? Because
好的？因为…
of climate change, the people in the Angelovo culture now are forced to leave the steppes.
好的，...
These are steps are no longer suitable for their children.
...
They should give up off off the oxus value civilization
and over time they will assimilate it into themselves okay
...
so the idea here is this is
not an intentional invasion okay it's not like you have a general in an army
...
and they go into the oxus value civilization and then
they conquer it okay it's more opportunistic
...
where at first you're trading and
as the oxus value civilization declines because
as the ox of ... …
of trade trading networks because
...
of the declining trading networks they will start to come in
and push out the people and
???
again the culture of these people it's very aggressive
再次...
so there are two strategies that
...
they were employed the first strategy is they might wipe
out villages okay these villages are depopulated anyway they come in
...
and they wipe everyone out which
...??...
means they kill everyone the second strategy is to come in they'll kill all the men
...????
and marry all the woman okay and
翻译
again this is a gradual
...
process of assimilation cultural conquest
but it's not a military invasion okay does
...
that make sense now after the internal culture and
the oxus culture merge this
...
creates a new civilization a new
culture called proto
...
-indo -iranian okay
???
which should give
?
off a
...
new outer
outer outer outer outer
...
Zoroastrianism comes from this
merger of the Proto
...
-Iranian culture into the Iranian plateau.
This is a process we call synchronization, by the way.
...
Where two major religions merge
Where two majorreligions merge
and share the same gods.
591-... 1/2? 2? ...
There are three distinct characteristics of the Proto -Indo -Iranian culture
? 1/2? 1/??
that becomes salient in the new Zoroastrian religion.
那在新古尔宗教里变得显著。
The first is the use of a ritual drink called soma.
第一种是使用一种叫做soma的仪式饮料。
Again, you don't have to know this,
再次，你不必知道这一点，
but I'm just telling you the cultural impact.
再来，给我方块
Soma comes from the Proto -Indo -Iranian culture.
Soma源自原始-印度-伊朗文化。
Second is the worship of fire, fire rituals.
第二点是火的崇拜，火祭仪式。
Fires are used heavily
火在宗教实践中被大量使用
in the religious practice.
火在宗教实践中使用
As we know, Zoroastrianism does use a lot of fire rituals.
如我们所知，梵语里有火焰的古典…
The last is horse sacrifice.
...
Meaning that warriors are buried with their horses.
战士们被埋葬时带着他们的马。
This is an emphasis on the warrior culture of these people.
这点体现了这群人战士的文化。
Okay? Okay? So that's what happens in Iran.
好的？
They become the Persian people.
他们成为波斯人。
We will discuss the Persian people at a later point.
我们会在后面讨论波斯人。”】\}We need to translate cues 606-608. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure Chinese natural. Let's translate: 606:
Okay? Not now, but I just want you to know this is what happened.
. Actually cue:
These people will also push into the IBC.
这些人也会向伊比克展开推移。
And over time, and this is a process that takes about 500 years,
大约五百年之内，随着时间的推移，伊比克人会向前方推移。
they'll push out the indigenous people.
...
Okay? And then
好的？然后这些人会向南印度迁移。
the indigenous people move into South India.
这些人会向南印度迁移。
Where they merge with the folk culture.
...
The animism of the local people there.
615. The animism...??
Okay? And guys,
??
what's amazing about this is this
?
process will create two major world religions
过程将产生两大世界宗教
that are still influential today.
它们仍在今天有影响力。
Okay? The first we know as Hinduism.
好的，先说一条。
Hinduism is the merger,
印度教是合并，Proto‑Indo‑伊尔兰宗教的同步与……………………………………………………………
the synchronization of Proto -Indo -Iranian religions.
And ...……………………………
And then the second is the integration of the local religion with the local IBC religion.
...??
Okay? And as the IBC pushes south,
好的？当IBc推向南方时，
this will create a new religion called Buddhism.
一百个…………………………………………………………………………………略…………………………………翻译…
Okay? All right?
...
But Buddhism is just the major one.
但佛教只是主要的那一个。
There are others that are being created as well through this process.
还有其他通过此过程产生的。
Right? The others are being Jainism and Shikism.
对了吧，佛教与之相同的佛教。”\}]\}We need to translate cues 627-629. Provide Chinese subtitles. Use terms: Buddhism=佛教? Actually
And again, these are the major ones.
...
Okay? That are still with us today.
Like basically this process created thousands,
...
tens of thousands of new religions.
十几万新的宗教。
All right? So this is what happened.
好的，都是这回事！
It's not a military conquest.
它是个别的…
It's not an invasion. But
它不是一次入侵。 但
it's a process of, you could argue, cultural genocide.
它是一种过程，你可以说是文化灭绝。
Okay? Where new people come in and over time, because they are aggressive,
好的？ 先来的人会在此时…
experiencing opportunities in culture,
经历了文化的机会，
they will eventually take over the culture.
他/她会在此时…
Okay? Mainly by the...
...
Marrying the local woman. Because the people who come in are basically males.
嫁给当地女子。因为来的人基本是男性。
Okay? They will marry the local woman.
好的，先前者先结婚。
And they will either kill or enslave the local man.
再接着…
And this is where we get the caste system from in India.
...
All right? So
this is a more subtle
...
explanation of the Indo -Iran invasion theory.
[648] 印度-伊朗入侵理论的说明。
Okay? And this is what scholars today accept happened.
[649] 好的，先前者先结婚…
And again, what's really important is to avoid generalizations
再一次，重要的是…
and simplifications.
...
Because this is a process that took about 300 years, 400 years.
因为这是一段历时约三百年、四百年的过程。
And there are different strategies employed by different people.
因为这是一段历时约三百年，约四百年。”
Some of it was peaceful. Some of it was violent.
一些是平静的，一些是繁忙的。
Okay? It was a mix. It's hard for us to generalize.
...
But the overall general effect is the creation of Hinduism
译文1
and Buddhism.
译前后两句的翻译结果
Which now are the two major world religions.
哪两大宗教现在已成形？
Okay? Any questions?
好的，先前…
But thanks for the question, Nicol.
...
Any more questions? Before I move on.
..
....
...
..... .
. That's right. .
...
Yep..
Okay. So, that's a great question Doug, okay?
Okay...
So, when you trade, there's always a problem of piracy and banantry, right?
...
So, how do you protect yourselves against that?
Okay. We know like Mesopotamia became violent
好的。我们知道，米索波特里亚成为了…
because it was being surrounded by violence, right?
...
The nomads in Arabia, the nomads in the Zagos Mountains were all pretty violent people.
阿拉伯半岛的游牧民众，扎格山脉的游牧民众，都是相当活泼的游牧民众。
You had to be because to survive, you had to be aggressive and opportunistic.
在此时，必须得以此来回顾，才可回到回到…
So, how is it the, sorry,
...
the IVC was able to, be peaceful yet at the same time trade?
And the solution is they set up colonies
好的，...
and trade partners in order to facilitate trade,
...
okay? So, we know for example, they traded heavily with the Oxus civilization.
好的？所以，我们知道，例如他们与乌克斯文明有大量贸易。
There were lots of trade agreements, long -term trade agreements.
有很多长久的交易协议。
We also know they had a colony within the Oxus Valley civilization,
我们也知道他们在乌克斯文明中有一个殖民，
okay? We know they traded heavily with a place called Dilman,
…
which is now modern day. Okay?
...
So, these are their main trading partners.
And so, you would think their trading partners were the ones
...
who were responsible for local security, okay?
谁负责当地安全，好的？
We can also suspect they also went to other places as well to seek new trading partners.
我们也可以猜测他们也去到其他地方去找新商机。
What's important about this world is this is still a relatively peaceful world.
在这片世界里，还是相对的好！
There's tremendous violence in Sumer, but that's still rare,
在苏玛里有大规模的冲突，但也很少见，?
right? And there's some unique, you know,
...】】】??
characteristics about Sumer that make it a violent people.
...
But in this world, and this is about 5,000 years ago,
但在这片 里 好 ??
people are still relatively peaceful.
...??
Organized warfare is still new
and rare in the human experience.
695. 发生在...??
And that's why I think the experience in Mesopotamia was
695???????????????????????????????????????????????????
so shocking because the idea
????..?????..??..????????..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..
that you could sack a city,
那你可以掳掳一座城
the idea that you could kill hundreds of people,
...??
give off ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice
冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰冰
ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice ice you can trust basically yeah okay
705: 冰冰冰冰...??
and any more questions before I continue
?
yeah I'm actually moving into Buddhism okay
呀！我正好去转入佛教啦！
and but any more questions before I continue okay
好啦！我先前往前进！
so the last thing I want to discuss is what is
the legacy of the IBC they were great
...
civilization are they completely lost to us what is your contribution to Western civilization
so
所以
the legacy of Egypt are the pyramids right we know Egypt because
...
of the pyramids the legacy of Mesopotamia are many
they invented a lot of things like
they invented alot of things like
writing cuneiform also they introduced world
写作符号写作符号
literature right the epic of Gilgamesh what
literature right theepic of Gilgamesh what
I want to argue now is the
我想要说点...
legacy of the IBC is in their
the ... ... ... … … … … … … i ... … 里 … … i … i … i…… ? ? … … i … i ... .. … I ... ..i…… … i…… … i…… … i…… .. … i….. … i….. … i…… i….. … … i…… i…… …………………………………………………………
special spiritual practice okay their spiritual values
...
so
所以
if you look at Hinduism
okay it's very different from Jorastinism
...
and that's kind of strange because
they're both proto indo -iranian religions right
它们都是原始印欧-伊朗宗教，对吧？
but let's look at very quickly at Hinduism and
but let's look at veryquickly at Hinduism and
it isn't believes the reality we
it … ... … … \{
live in is false okay
. .. .. ... .. ?? .. B….. .. .. .. .. .. ... .. .. B….. .. ?…?….. .. ...….. .. ..…….. .. -….. ..…….. ... ...…….. .. -……?…….. .. ?….. …….. 1?.. ..………?….. .. ..………?………………………………
the reality is called Brahmin
...
the true absolute reality
so
...
we live in this false reality as we
live in this false reality we collect
在此处翻译成…
karma karma is basically just an
翻译成…
accounting of your good deeds
...
and your bad deeds and
guess what throughout your life you're gonna accumulate more bad deeds than your argument than your good deeds
guess what throughout your life you're gonna accumulatemore bad deeds than your argument than your good deeds
and
your karma means your soul
your karma meansyour soul
called the admin is stuck here okay because
...
the Brahman it's pure you know you you can only return to Brahman to heaven if you're a pure person
so
所以
it will take many lifetimes for you to cleanse
...
your soul your admin in order to return
to the Brahman this process of cleansing
...
your soul it's what they
call Dharma okay Dharma
...
the right path
if you if the Dharma over thousands
...
of lifetimes if your Dharma is correct if
you have cheap Dharma you achieve what is called moksha
翻译成中文：
which is basically liberation moksha releases you your soul from the physical world
...
and also you return to the Brahman where
翻译成中文
you will live eternally in paradise okay that
...
is the one of the
basic ideas of Hinduism another really important
...
idea of Hinduism is this
idea of Hinduismis this
entire process is being meditated
...
or sorry mediated or gatekeep
by priests called Brahmins okay
...
so
you think being a good person is enough no it's not you have to listen to the Brahman
...
because only the Brahman understand the Brahman and the Brahman is the Brahman and the Brahman is the Brahman understands Dharma
and depending on who
...
you are your Dharma will be different
so
...
in Hinduism there's a
hierarchy okay at the very top are
...
of course the priest the Brahman because
they have access to spiritual knowledge below them are the warriors
...
and the Kings and
和王国的...
then below them are the farmers and the merchants
...
who keep the economy running
谁在维持经济运转
and that at the very bottom are the servants and
谁在维持...
the laborers okay now what's what's
...
really interesting about the
system is this
...
system can be differentiated by the color of one skin right
because remember the Polar Indo -Iranians they
have white skin the IBC culture the The people
...
who call the pro -Darwinians, no, sorry,
the pro -Darwinians, they have darker skin. So
]\}We need to translate cue 782:
the IVC people of the lower
...
class don't intermix with the pro -Indo -Iranians.
And so basically the pro -Indo -Iranians
...
accumulated and centralized power through the idea of Hinduism,
they're the priest class. So
...
that's a basic theory of Hinduism.
And again, Hinduism is an extremely complex religion.
...
I don't want to oversimplify it, but
I have no choice because I want to explain the differences, okay?
...
So in this system, who's really unhappy now?
In this system? Which group of people are very upset with this system?
...
Can you guys echo?
Can you applaud?
可 ? ?? ?????
Can you clarify what we've learned in this semester and answer the question,
?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ? ?? ...?? ?? ?? -??? ??????????????????????????????????????????????????..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..………… ?? ??? ??..??..??..…??…??……………??…..??…..…………………..??..??..……..……………..??..…..…..??……..……..??..??……..…..??..??..……..……………..??..…..??..???..??..??..……..??..??..?…..??..……..…………..??…..??…..??..……..??…..??..…
all these four groups, who's the unhappiest?
...
And who most wants change, or revolutionary change?
\}]
Excuse me? The lower nobility.
The lower nobility, and who's the lower nobility in this system?
The kings, okay?
Does that make sense? The kings actually in this system are the lower nobility.
The upper nobility are the Brahmins.
Because it's the Brahmins who control access
to the Brahmin, okay?
And so the kings must obey the priests.
So the kings aren't happy with this.
And so from this conflict,
you have the creation of Buddhism, right?
Remember, Sirhatta Gautama,
who was considered the first Buddha, he was actually a prince before he became a Buddha.
And the man most responsible for spreading Buddhism in India
and around the world, his name is Ashoka,
he was the king, the emperor of the Moran Empire.
And he was the one who
institutionalized Buddhism as state religion,
who sponsored missionary projects to China.
His highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest
highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest highest Nirvana.
You don't need the Brahmins to access
spiritual enlightenment. You can do it by yourself through
spiritual guidance by monks.
That's a major difference. As you can see,
Buddhism is, in many respects,
a revolutionary religion to overthrow
the power of the Brahmin class.
In response to Buddhism,
what did the Brahmins do?
Do you guys know? They created the caste system.
After the rise of Buddhism,
Hinduism started to implement what we call today the caste system.
Which is to say,
these classes must separate from each other.
They are not allowed to intermingle.
They're not even allowed to touch each other.
They're not even allowed to touch each other's food.
These two at the very bottom are what we call today the untouchables.
This system was developed by the Hindu priest,
the Brahmins, in response to the threat of Hinduism.
Now over time, because Hinduism,
like the Proto -Iranian people, are aggressive,
expansionist, opportunistic, they will defeat Buddhism in this struggle.
And the one way, one really important way,
is to defeat Buddhism is
by adopting most of Buddhism's practices.
So like yoga meditation, and also Nirvana.
The Hindu Brahmins will adopt whatever is popular in Buddhism.
Another thing that the Hindu priest will do is,
they will start basically assimilating
other religions as well. So
most Indians throughout its history
believed in their local folklore gods.
Eventually all these gods will be assimilated into the Hindu hierarchy.
That's why you have like a million gods in the Hindu religion.
Because they were all, over time, assimilated into the hierarchy.
And obviously, these gods are lesser gods.
The higher gods, the Holy Trinity, are Brahmin gods.
Okay? All right. So
now's the chance for Doug
to ask his question about Buddhism before I continue.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So maybe you get the chance to ask that.
Go back to the point about the IEP,
the Weston -Bowinger.
Yeah. So way,
way back a bunch ago, you were talking about the early Indo -European ideas.
That's right. Right? And there's been a lot of archaeological work.
That's right. To put that back together. Yep.
Do you know if there's been a similar process looking at the different Indian religions,
like Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism?
Yeah. And is there a certain common denominator that
perhaps could be taken back to the IEP?
Okay. Great question. Okay?
So what is the IVC religion, the portal religion?
Okay. I want to make an argument.
And again, it's speculation.
It's a very strange argument.
And most scholars probably will not agree.
I think the religion of the IVC is Proto -Buddhism.
And the reason why is,
if you look at Zoroastrianism,
and you look at Proto -Indo -Iranian,
the religion, there are a lot of similarities. Okay?
And Proto -Zoroastrianism actually fits into the larger Proto -Indo -European religion framework.
When you look at Hinduism,
you've got this strange idea,
a belief in karma, dharma,
reincarnation, impermanence,
Brahma, the ultimate reality.
Like this is not part of the Proto -Indo -European religion in anywhere.
Okay? So at the same time, Hinduism,
Buddhism, Jainism, and
Shikism all share this fundamental belief in the world
that this world is a false reality.
It's a reality created by our false beliefs.
And if we learn to tame our emotions,
if we learn to see the
underlying reality governing all human structure,
then we will be released from this world.
Okay? Now, where would that come from?
That must have come from the IVC because there would be no other place.
Also, it explains why these religions,
have such huge followings in India, right?
They don't have any followings anywhere else. Okay?
Like Hinduism is basically localized to India.
So is Jainism, so is Shikism. So
they are appealing to a fundamental sense of the world among Indians.
They're basically appealing to nostalgia. Right?
And where is this nostalgia from?
It must be from the IVC.
Okay? So I would make that argument.
I would make that argument. I would believe, I would bet that
if we're able to construct the religion of the IVC,
the proto -religion,
we would see a proto -Buddhism.
Okay? The beginnings of Buddhism. It would be very different.
Okay? Because Buddhism evolved over thousands of years.
But the underlying assumptions about the world,
basically the idea of oneness.
Okay? Okay?
The idea of false reality.
I think these two ideas would be very apparent in the IVC.
As they are apparent now in all four major Indian religions.
Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism, and Shikism.
Okay? Do you want to continue or?
No, no, no, no, no. I'm finished.
But like do you want to respond to my argument?
No, it's okay. Okay.
And I think that's a good argument. Are you guys following along?
Does it make sense to you guys?
In fact, I would argue
that
we as humans fundamentally have a nostalgia for these two ideas.
Oneness and false reality.
Okay? Because if you look at the West, okay?
If you look at us today, there are two ideas.
The most powerful today in Western civilization.
The first idea is Plato's Allegory of the Cave.
Right? The idea that we live in a shadow world.
And the truth is out there.
But we have to seek it. It's a very powerful idea.
Right? And it's very similar, by the way,
to the ideas found in Hinduism and Buddhism.
Okay? The Allegory of the Cave is the first powerful idea.
And then the second powerful idea is the idea of the Second Coming.
The return of Jesus.
Because what does the return of Jesus signify?
It signifies paradise on earth.
It signifies the destruction of our current reality
and the replacement of a new reality
that creates oneness,
completeness, and wholeness on earth.
So in many ways, I think that's a good argument.
This is very similar to what
the Indians are proposing as well. So
what this is saying is at a fundamental level,
everyone has nostalgia for a distant past.
And what is this distant past?
The distant past is the idea of animism.
So remember, 10,000 years ago, 20,000 years ago,
we were in the Ice Age.
We were hunter -gatherers.
And the way we saw the world was very different from the way we see the world today.
Okay? Back then, if you were a hunter -gatherer,
you could only think you were the same as the tree or as the animal.
Okay? It's the idea of oneness.
We're no different. We're all part of the life cycle.
We're all part of Mother Nature.
Okay? The Mother Goddess. All right?
We also believe we inhabit different realities at the same time.
Right? We live in this world, which is the material reality.
We're also inhabiting the spiritual reality as well.
And what we do spiritually matters a lot more than what we do materially.
Okay? So we can hunt and
kill animals as long as we pay the proper respects to the animals we kill.
As long as we contribute spiritually.
We contribute spiritually to the cycle of life
and death. Okay?
So I think that's where Buddhism comes from.
It comes from animism.
This Buddhism became reinforced
and became much more concrete
because it was experiencing a reality in Mesopotamia
and Egypt that
was abhorrent to the people experiencing it.
Okay? War goes against the human experience.
Inequality and corruption in ways goes against the human experience.
We fundamentally believe this to be evil and wrong.
Okay? So that
is my argument about the IBC.
Any questions?
Any comments?
You seem to believe that
human beings are incredibly benevolent
and kind until they're back to the state they've been trained to be.
Okay. That's a good question.
Do I believe that human nature is fundamentally benevolent?
I don't believe human nature is benevolent.
I believe humans naturally seek
a spiritual understanding of the world.
I think humans want to know why.
Why are we here? Where are we going?
Where do we come from? Okay?
We want to know why. We're also curious.
We want to explore the world.
Okay? So I think trade is not a new invention.
I think it's a very inherent thing to human nature.
I think the idea of globalization.
This was a globalized world like 5,000 years ago.
Okay? Extremely sophisticated, complex, globalized world.
So I think that's what makes us fundamentally human.
Okay? And you can say this is a good thing or a bad thing.
And I would say, well, it depends on the circumstance.
Right? But I think what drives us as humans is our curiosity
and
our imagination.
Okay? That's what I think being human is.
And sometimes this is a good thing.
Sometimes this is a bad thing.
Okay? Sometimes in the IVC this will lead to peace
and egalitarianism. But
this also is what drives the idea of the second coming,
which is what's driving the conflict in the Middle East today.
Okay? So it depends on the context.
It depends on the circumstance. If this curiosity,
this imagination is channeled effectively, then the idea of the second coming then I think that's a good thing.
If it's channeled opportunistically, then it's a bad thing.
Okay? Okay, but thanks for the question. Any more questions?
Okay. So this ends our Bronze Age unit.
Okay? So we looked at the three major Bronze Age civilizations,
Egypt, Mesopotamia, and IVC.
Okay? Next class we'll start the Bible.
Okay? The Hebrew Bible. All right.