Okay, so the story
so far is that 200,000 years ago,
we humans, Homo sapiens,
we were born in Africa.
And then about 50,000 years ago,
because of climate change,
we started to spread
around the world, okay?
We went into Europe, then into Asia,
then we crossed the Bering
Strait into North America
and South America. Then Asia
went to Australia, okay?
And 50,000 years ago, there's about
a million of us all around the world.
And the argument that I'm making you, that
I've made to you in this class
is that from the very beginning,
we were religious, okay?
We know from the Ice Age cave paintings.
We know because of places
like the Great Barrier Reef.
Go play at Tepe and kind of
Høøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøøø
is
animistic, meaning we believe
that we all come from one source,
the Mother Goddess, and
we are all the children
of the Mother Goddess,
including animals, plants.
And because of this,
we were a very compassionate people
that were egalitarian.
There was no difference
between men and women.
That was peaceful.
We were violent.
There was some violence, but
we didn't really fight wars.
And we were artistic.
We celebrated the Mother
Goddess through paintings
and through artwork.
And now the question then is,
if we were like this
for most of human history,
how is it that today we have war,
private property, and violence
against the Mother Goddess?
And patriarchy, where
men make all the rules
and women have little agency and power.
And so this week I will explain
to you how this happened.
Okay? So in today's class,
we will discuss really the
height of this civilization.
And this is what the anthropologist
Maria Gimbertas called Old Europe.
Okay? So to begin the story,
I want to tell you what
we discovered in terms of linguistics.
So for many hundreds of years,
many people have speculated
that maybe English, German,
Greek, Latin,
all came from the same language
that's been lost to us.
This is a language we call
Proto -Indo -Hungarian.
Proto -Indo -European. And
through decades of research,
linguists have been able
to conclusively prove
that all these languages that
we speak in Europe, okay, all come
from the same mother language,
the first language. But not
only that, but also Iranian,
and Indian,
okay, Hindi, okay,
all come from Proto -Indo -European.
So the question, so, okay, does
that make sense to you guys?
All right? So
we know this because there are many words
that sound the same in
many languages, okay?
So for example, father in
English is father, right?
But in Latin it's pater, okay?
That's where we get the
word paternity, okay?
From the father. Greek,
pateris, Persian, padar,
Hindi in India, pita, okay?
So the word father seems to come from just
one word in all these different languages.
Then you look at the word mother, okay?
Mother, matar, matara, madar, mat, okay?
Also sounds very similar.
So again, for hundreds of years,
people have speculated that,
um, um,
um, there is just one language.
And if you look at this map, okay?
So for example, the English
word for two, okay?
The number two. You can draw a schematic
that shows you how all these languages,
the word two, derived just
from one word, dua, okay?
So languages have been able to piece
together this Proto
-Indo -European language.
We've also been able to figure out
how this language spread, okay?
So there are two hypothesis.
Either the language spread from Turkey,
Anatolia or from Ukraine, okay?
Basically Russia. And
we know it spread all
around the world, okay?
So basically all of
Europe and including Iran
and India, okay?
So this is the first language of all
these languages, languages that we see.
we speak today in most of
Asia and all of Europe.
So any questions so far?
All right. Now,
the problem for linguists is
how do you piece together
the language, okay?
Because this language is lost to us.
So this language is lost to us.
And so what linguists did, okay,
and this is a very slow process is,
they basically looked
at all the words that
seemed to come from the same
word in different languages.
What they discovered is
that there's certain words
that are distinct to the first language.
So words like bull, cow,
ox, ram,
eel, lamb,
pig, piglet, sour milk,
why, herds, field,
dog, shear wool,
textiles, scratch plow, oxen,
yoke, grain, shaft, furrow,
wrestling, grinding,
pestle, households, okay?
What do you guys notice about these words?
Do you see patterns in these words?
What patterns do you see in these words?
Okay, so what these words tell
us is the culture and lifestyle
of the Proto -Indo -Europeans, okay?
Does that make sense? So from these words,
we're able to figure out four things
about the Proto -Indo -Europeans.
The first thing is that
unlike other cultures,
these people have a word for wheel.
In fact, they have five
different words for wheel.
And what this tells us, what we can guess
that these people, whoever they
are, they invented the wheel.
doesn't make sense. They have words
for wheel and other cultures don't.
So they were the first
to invent the wheel.
Second is that they have
words for dairy products,
cow milk. And this is important.
Why? Do you guys know why this is
important? Why is this strange?
Yes, okay, so they were
raising livestock, okay?
Okay, what makes it strange is
that for most of human history,
we were lactose intolerant.
Meaning we did not have
the ability to drink milk.
So these people, not only
did they invent the wheel,
but they changed their system.
Biological system so that
they became lactose tolerant.
They now have the capacity
to drink milk, okay?
Does that make sense? So
whatever these people are,
are the first people to drink cow milk.
Okay, the second characteristic,
sorry, the third characteristic
is they really don't have
that many agricultural terms.
Okay? So maybe they farmed, but
they weren't focused on farming, okay?
Whereas other cultures
were focused on farming.
Okay? That's the third thing.
The fourth thing is they
have words for horse.
And this is important because this
tells us that they were first to
domesticate the horse, meaning
that they could control the horse.
Okay? This is important
because throughout history,
horses, if they see a
human, they run away, okay?
Because that's the best way to survive.
If you see someone coming, you run away.
This, this is what we're going
to call excitability, okay?
Horses are excited.
So it took thousands of
years for these people,
the Proto -Indo -Europeans,
to domesticate the horse,
which means they could ride the horse.
Okay, does that make sense? So we
don't know who these people were,
but based on their language, we're
able to guess four things, okay?
So this is a theory. Now
what's interesting is
that archeologists start to dig
up, okay, and they dig up things.
And they start to discover
the linguists were right,
okay? By saying the language, the
language had four hypotheses. And
the archeologists were able to
provide evidence this is true,
okay? The most exciting thing is that
for the past five to ten
years, advances in genetics,
DNA technology, we've been able to look
at the DNA of these skeletons. And
we've been able to confirm
a lot of these hypotheses,
okay? Does that make sense? So what I'm,
what I'm telling you is
for the longest time,
we guessed that the Proto
-Indo -Europeans existed.
But now we have conclusive,
conclusive, scientific evidence
that they did exist and
who they were, okay?
Does that make sense? All right.
So wheels, okay?
So again, they have five, five
different words for wheels.
And we're able to know from
the archeological evidence,
the wheels were invented about 3500 BC,
okay? In this area,
okay, basically Russia.
And because wheels are part
of Proto -Indo -European,
then this language,
whoever starts to first speak it must
have been speaking it after 3500 BC,
okay? Does that make sense? All right?
There aren't that many agricultural
terms in Proto -Indo -European,
okay? We have a lot of words
for Proto -Indo -European.
milk okay to milk sour milk
buttermilk cheese cow okay
so whoever these people were dairy products
were very important part of their culture
and their diet this is
DNA DNA evidence that
shows us that these people
who if we call the Anaya
okay these people call
the Anaya they were
able to develop hormones
that allowed them to be
lactose tolerant okay in
about 4400 BC very few
people could drink milk
and by the time of the Anaya about a thousand
years later they could basically all drink milk
and because
they could drink milk what
happens to their body you guys
know what's the difference you guys know what's
the difference if you drink milk exactly okay
so we know from the evidence that
these people are taller than
everyone else in fact these people
because they drink milk and
they eat a lot of protein they
were on average 20 centimeters
taller than farmers
okay it doesn't make sense
you guys okay yeah go ahead
okay okay okay so
the drink the milk we drink today
is very different from the milk
that they drink before you understand
the milk they drink before came from cows
that were raised in grassland so
it's all in the grassland so it's all natural
the milk we drink today comes from cows
that are raised in factories and
we inject a lot of drugs and
hormones into these
cows did you understand
no no no no if you drink milk a
lot your bones will be healthier
and you'll grow taller okay that
that's just that's just biological
evidence okay does that make sense
but the milk we drink today we put
a lot of chemicals into the milk
and the sourcing of the
milk is from factories okay
and and and the reason why is we
want to make the milk cheaper
but it's worse for you okay so
in other words if you really want to be
healthy what you should do is go buy a cow
and drink from that
cow okay do you understand all right okay
so so are we clear okay so
we are clear okay so
we are clear okay so we are
clear okay so we are clear
okay so we are clear
okay so we are clear okay
so we are clear okay so we are clear okay
so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay so
we are clear okay so we are clear okay so
we are clear okay so we are clear okay so we are clear okay
so we are clear okay
so we are clear okay so
we are clear okay so we are clear okay
so we are clear 1500 BCE until
2200 BCE to domesticate the horse
because it's very hard to make horses
not run away when there's danger.
It doesn't make sense.
So this is a very long process,
but they were able to accomplish it.
The further evidence for
the domestication of a horse
is we've been able to
dig up skeletons. And
what we see is the skeletons
of the Anaya are different
from other skeletons
and it's because they ride horses.
That changes the curvature
of the skeleton.
Does it make sense guys?
So the evidence is pretty overwhelming.
Eventually they were able
to put all the pieces together.
They were able to put the
horse and the wheel together.
And as such they create the wagon.
The wagon meant they could
move from place to place
and they became what we
call nomadic pastoralists.
So have you guys been to Mongolia?
Have you guys been to Mongolia?
Yes, same.
But you see the way they
make a living is they have
like cows and sheep, right?
And they take the cows and
the sheep from place to place
to eat the grass, right?
And they're able to do that because
they're able to put all
the belongings into a wagon
and move from place to place.
Okay, does that make sense?
So these are the people
who
were the first speakers
of Proto -Indo -European.
And eventually, they're
able to spread the word.
They spread their language
all around the world.
Okay from Europe to India to Iran.
It doesn't make sense guys. Now the
question is okay we're able to confirm
that these people actually existed and
we are able to confirm that
they did spread the
language around the world.
Now the question the debate
is how do they do so?
Okay and there's two
sides to the argument.
argument. The first side,
the first side believes
these people were conquerors.
Okay, so think Genghis
Khan and the Mongols.
They went around, they were able to spread
their language by conquering other people.
Okay, so think Genghis
Khan and the Mongols.
Think of the European conquest of North
and South America where the
English and the Spanish and
the French went to North and South America
and eradicated the local population.
Okay, so that's the first belief.
The second belief is
that it was not violent.
Okay, it was just cultural diffusion,
meaning I came to your
country or your village
and I was able to influence you
and convince you that my
language is superior.
Okay, so we call this cultural diffusion.
So think of English where, okay,
China has not been conquered by the West,
but we want to learn English
because we think that
learning English will give
us more life opportunities.
Okay, does that make sense? So
there's two sides of the debate,
either one of conquest or
one of cultural diffusion.
And this debate went on for a long time.
Okay, and
for most of the time we believed
it was cultural diffusion.
So we believe that it was
cultural diffusion. But
now for the past five to ten years,
we have overwhelming
DNA evidence that it was in fact conquest.
It was a genocide. It
was a violent conquest.
And this is what I will
show you next class.
Okay, but
in today's class what I will show you
is the Europe before the conquest.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay, and then
next class we will look at
how Europe was conquered.
Okay, so this is the first class. This is
how Europe was conquered and how it was changed because of a conquest.
Okay, any questions so far?
Okay, so there's a quick question.
The question is, what's the difference
between conquest and diffusion?
Okay, the answer is this.
If I conquer a country, conquer
you, I eradicate your genes.
I kill you, okay?
Therefore your genes do not
come into the present day.
Whereas if it's diffusion,
your genes are still around.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So what I will show you next class is,
sorry, a lot of these
genes have been eradicated.
Therefore it must have
been a violent conquest.
Does that make sense? Okay. All right.
Let's now look at Europe
before the conquest.
And a lot of what we know about Europe
comes from a very famous anthropologist.
Her name is Maria Gambates, okay?
And we'll be spending a lot of time
today talking about her theories.
But what we know is, okay,
remember the Ice Age ended
about 12,000 years ago.
Okay? And this is how the planet is
warming, which allows for agriculture.
We also know that
agriculture started in Anatolia, Turkey,
and in Egypt and in Mesopotamia, okay?
Basically this region.
And the reason why is this
place was the first to warm up,
but it also had better soil
than other places, okay?
So they discovered farming in this region.
And in about 6500 BCE,
this region was the first to warm up. So
they started to grow. agriculture started to spread around the world, okay?
To Europe and then over to England.
Okay, does that make sense, guys?
Okay. Another question then is,
what propelled this migration
from Anatolia to Europe?
Can you guys guess? What
would propel this migration?
Hmm? Okay.
So, a good guess is war, okay?
But we don't have any evidence
of war around this time.
What's another explanation
why people wouldn't move?
Exactly, thank you. Climate change, okay?
The weather became a lot
cooler during this time,
make it harder for people to farm, okay?
Also, they've been farming for
a long time in this area, which
meant that the soil is
longer as good as before,
okay? So you had these
massive changes, okay?
And then you had these massive
migrations of families into Europe,
because Europe at this
time, it was becoming,
the weather was becoming a lot warmer,
which allowed people to start to
grow agriculture in this area, okay?
So in about 6500 BCE,
people started to move from
Anatolia into this area.
And because they were moving,
they brought with them
their religion, okay?
Remember like the religion of Goble Tepe,
and kind of how they were moving, right?
The Holy Act is one of the mother
goddess, giving life to everything, okay?
And because of that, we know
that the people in this area
were mainly egalitarian, peaceful,
and artistic, okay? Does that make sense?
Okay, what we'll study next class
is that there were two massive
migrations into Europe.
All caused by climate change.
The first migration are farmers, okay?
The second migration are pastoralists.
And what I will show you next class is,
we will look at the DNA evidence, okay?
So if you look at the DNA of people today,
what you will see is that about 4500 BCE,
most people in Europe,
their genes were mixed,
most people in Europe, their genes were
mixed, but the second migration was based on the genes of farmers who came from Anatolia,
as well as hunter gatherers who
were there originally, okay?
Does that make sense?
But then after 3000 BCE,
you have this green come in, okay?
And the green are the Yemnaya, okay?
The Proto Indo -Europeans.
And so I will show you
this next class, okay?
But I want you guys to
understand what happened, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay, so again,
this is a map of the migration, okay?
So agriculture was started in
about 9,000 BCE in the Near East,
Turkey, Anatolia, as well as Israel,
Syria, Jordan, then
it spread from about
7,000 to Europe, okay?
And then the purple is
the Yamnaya people, okay?
Who we believe were from
Ukraine, in the steppes,
and they spread around the world.
Next class, we'll discuss
who the Yamnaya were
and how they conquered the world, okay?
But first, I want to look at the farmers
who built Europe before the
conquest of the Yamnaya.
So again, Okay.
Maria Gumbutas, who
is an anthropologist
originally from Lutherania,
but who worked at Harvard and UCLA,
she's done decades of
research into old Europe,
okay? And her conclusion is
that
old Europe was
conquered by the Yamnaya people,
okay? And this is what
we know as the Yamnaya.
So this is what we know
as the Kurgan hypothesis.
So let me explain what
the Kurgan hypothesis is.
We know the burials of
the farmers is very different from
the burials of the Yamnaya people.
The major difference is this.
The people who are farmers
are buried together,
okay? But the people of the
Yamnaya, they're buried alone.
Not only are they buried alone,
but they're buried with weapons
and weapons.
with cattle and horses.
So what we can guess from this,
okay, we don't have evidence,
but what we can guess from this is that
the farmers were people who
did not have private property and who
were egalitarian, okay, and who were peaceful
because they didn't have any weapons.
And the Annihiler were the
complete opposite, okay.
These were warriors who
believed in private property
and which was male -dominated, okay.
Does that make sense? So this is what
we refer to as the Kirken hypothesis.
And for the longest time,
this is something that
Maria Gumbates argued and
she was laughed at.
Why was she laughed at? Why
would people laugh at her?
She's saying like, okay, before
these Annihiler came to Europe,
Europe was a place that
was basically governed by woman
and it was artistic, you know, it
was peaceful, it was egalitarian.
Why would people laugh at her?
Yeah, they don't believe
in her. Why? Excuse me?
Yeah, yeah. First of all,
in universities it's the men
who are professors, right?
It's the men who are scholars. So
there are many men who are like,
there's no way woman can be in charge.
They're idiots, okay.
Why would women be in charge?
They're stupid, they're useless.
It's men who are always in charge, okay.
That's one reason why they laugh at her.
What's another reason why
they would laugh at her?
Okay, there are also a lot of people
who who believe people are violent.
We've had wars always, okay?
The idea for like thousand years,
Europe was peaceful can't be true
because people are violent.
Humans are meant to go to
war against each other.
Okay? The third reason why
people would laugh at her is
we think we are motivated by money, right?
If you don't have money, then
why would you do anything?
Does that make sense? So,
Maria Gumbotas had this radical idea
that challenged the way
that men saw the world.
Okay? For men, men have
always been in charge.
There's always been wars,
and there's always been wealth and
money to motivate people
to work hard, okay?
And that's what men believe.
And Maria Gumbotas said,
no, that's not true.
For thousands of years, from 6500 B.C.
until about 2500 B.C., 4,000
years before they were conquered,
Europe was ruled by women,
and because of that, Europe was
peaceful, egalitarian, and artistic.
Okay? So this is a radical idea.
And again, what I will
show you next class is
this idea that was
laughed at for, you know,
decades, has now been
confirmed by DNA evidence,
meaning that this has been
proven true by science, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay, so
let's look at what Maria Gumbotas said.
And she's written quite a few books.
These are two of her most famous.
The Language of the Goddess
and The Civilization of the Goddess, okay?
So her main theory is
that Europe at that time,
their main belief is in a mother goddess who
gives life, gives life to everything, okay?
And so what she did was she went
and she dug up their graves
to look at their art,
and she studied their language
and their cultural practice, okay?
Does that make sense?
Any questions so far?
Okay. So this is from The
Civilization of the Goddess,
and we'll read this together, okay? And so
this is her main argument
about, Old European culture.
And the infamous infamous
infamous infamous
infamous infamous infamous
infamous infamous infamous!
infamous! infamous!!!
infamous infamous infamous infamous
infamous perception of all the sacredness
and mystery of all there is on earth.
So everything in the world is sacred
because it is blessed
by the mother goddess.
If there's a mosquito,
don't kill that mosquito because
it has the energy of the mother goddess.
If you are walking and
you see a bird,
a small bird, pick it up and heal it
because that comes from
the mother goddess.
Does that make sense?
This culture took deep delight in
the natural wonders of this world.
Its people did not produce lethal weapons
or build forts in inexorable
places as their successors did even
when they were acquainted with metallurgy.
So in other words, they had
the technology to make weapons.
They had the technology to build forts
and make war, but they chose not to.
Does that make sense? These people chose,
purposely chose, not to commit
violence against other people.
Instead, they built
magnificent tombs, shrines, and
temples, comfortable houses
in moderately sized villages,
and created superb pottery and sculptures.
This was a long -lasting
period of remarkable creativity
and stability in an age free of strife.
Their culture was a culture of art.
It doesn't make sense.
They spent all their
time and energy in producing these things.
They spent all their time and energy in
producing these things. They spent all their time and energy in producing these things. They spent all their time and energy in producing art to celebrate the mother goddess and to celebrate nature and to celebrate themselves.
This was remarkably peaceful and stable.
Does that make sense,
guys? Any questions so far?
What was amazing about this
culture is they invented writing.
Now for the longest time, we believe that
the Sumerians, which we will discuss
later on, the Sumerians who lived in Iraq,
we believe they discovered writing.
And we discovered that writing
came about for economic purposes.
So for example, if you are in Sumeria
and you need to build a temple,
what you do is you create writing.
So for example, here's
a play, and I say this.
So this is writing, right?
What does this mean? It
means like these two people,
this family of two, will
get two bushes of wheat
and two baskets of bread
for their work today.
Does that make sense? So we
thought that for the longest time,
people created writing because
or for economic purposes,
okay, in order to have an economy.
But what Maria Gambates has discovered is,
no, we actually created writing
before for religious purposes.
Okay? So for example, if I have a
painting, okay, and it goes like this.
Okay, so like this. And
what I'm saying is the
mother goddess blesses
this sculpture
with her life
and with the abundance of water in nature.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So writing is a way to communicate
with the mother goddess.
It's a way to make divine
and sacred our art.
Does it make sense, guys? Okay?
So these people were
so sophisticated, they invented writing.
Okay. Now,
I want to go over some of the
cultural differences between
that culture and our culture to
show how stark the differences are.
Okay? So for example, in today's culture,
when we think of snake, we
think of poison, danger,
right? We've been taught
that snakes are dangerous.
But in this culture, the snake was a
symbol of life energy and regeneration.
Because, you know, snakes
can shed their skin, right?
A most benevolent, not an evil creature.
Okay? So that's one major difference.
Another major difference between
our culture and their culture is,
in today's world, we think that,
white is good, black is bad.
Right? And we can't imagine
that
black is good, white is bad.
Right? But in their culture,
that's exactly what they believe.
Okay? Black did not mean
death or the underworld.
It was the color of fertility.
The color of damp caves and rich soil,
of the womb of the goddess
where life begins.
White, on the other hand, was
the color of death, of bones.
Okay? Does that make sense? So back then,
for most of human history, we thought
that white was bad
because it symbolized death, and black
was good because it symbolized life.
And we can't possibly
imagine that today, right?
Okay? The last thing I want to talk about, and
this is actually the most controversial thing, is,
back then, for most of human history,
woman had power and agency.
Okay? What I mean by that is, back then,
a woman's body was her body.
She could choose to do whatever
she wants with her body.
Does that make sense? In today's world,
if you get married, right,
if a woman gets married,
then we assume the woman's
body belongs to the husband.
Only the husband can sleep with her.
Okay? Does that make sense?
But for most of human history,
this was not true.
All right. So,
you look at sexual taboos today.
Okay? What are the sexual taboos to
shame woman into proper behavior?
Okay? So, for example, okay,
if a man sleeps with a thousand women,
we think, great, he's a stud.
He's good looking, he's rich, he's tall.
He's a stud. He's a stud, right? But, hey,
if a woman sleeps with a
thousand men, she's a slut.
She's a bad person.
She has no ethical,
she lacks ethics.
She lacks morality. She has no character.
Therefore, we must avoid her.
Okay? Why does this
make any logical sense?
Why is this true? Guys,
why is this true? Okay?
Yeah? How do you think about this?
Do you think that
this taboo is like something
that's going to
force women to control women?
Exactly. We have this, okay?
We have this prejudice because
men are considered superior
to women and therefore
men want to to control women and
the best way to do that
is by controlling the woman's
body it doesn't make sense okay
so this is just a cultural
prejudice there's no
biological evidence this
is true okay all right so
we have
a lot of evidence that
woman want sexual agency okay
women won't have sex
there's nothing wrong with
that okay so for example we
look at monkeys Reese's monkeys
and
females will aggressively
seek males out for sex okay
so it's the females that
are proactive you also look
at Bonobos monkeys okay
and Bonobos monkeys it's interesting
because they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very
aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're
very aggressive and they're very aggressive and
they're very aggressive and
they're very aggressive and they're very
aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive aggressive and
they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive
and they're very aggressive aggressive and
they're very aggressive
and they're very aggressive and they're
very aggressive and they're very aggressive and they're very aggressive and
they're very aggressive aggressive
and they're very aggressive
and they're very aggressive and
they're very initiate the sex.
There are some cultures where
it's the female that
will initiate the sex with the male.
So at Harvard and
UCLA they discovered
the plow agriculture,
these societies have lower levels
of female participation in politics
and the labor force. Meaning like before
where men and women did the same work,
both had the same political power.
But once men showed
that they could contribute more to
society, men started to have more power.
Does that make sense? So in other words,
differences between men
and women are not biological
constructs, they are cultural constructs.
And for most of human history,
men and women were equal.
Any questions so far? Okay.
The idea of black and white, it's
like white is good, black is bad.
It's a recent construct, okay?
It comes from the idea of race.
Okay? And race was invented
about 20 years ago.
Why? Because Europe was going
around conquering the world
and they needed to justify
why they were doing this.
And the theory is because
we're superior people.
Our race is better than your race.
Does that make sense? So race
is a recent cultural construct.
And it was to justify imperialism,
the conquest of other people,
for no reason, right?
Does it make sense? So,
all this is recent, okay?
Alright, there's a really fun book called,
sexual dawn, by Christopher Ryan, okay?
And what he argues is that,
for most of human history,
women had sexual agency, and
they They had multiple sexual partners.
And one piece of evidence is this.
Gorillas, right, they're
the biggest primates.
They're huge, right? Well,
it turns out their penises, when
fully erect, is only
four centimeters, okay?
Men, who are a lot smaller than gorillas,
when erect,
they are at least almost four
times as big as the gorilla penises, okay?
So the question then is,
why is this the case?
And one theory is
that when
women have multiple sexual partners,
the man with the bigger penis
will spread his gene forward.
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
And so this is evidence that
for most of human history, women
have had multiple sexual partners.
Okay? Okay.
So even when women had partners,
okay, a husband, they still
had sexual partners, okay?
And in some societies,
women have many husbands.
Usually brothers together, okay?
All right, let me ask you this question.
Why do they do this?
Right? Because we've been taught this.
We've been taught, okay, we
exist to spread our genes.
Right? You understand?
So if I marry someone,
only if I'm sure
that the offspring, the children are mine,
will I work hard to ensure
that the children are fed
and raised properly and educated, okay?
Does that make sense? So we've
been taught for a long time
that we first care about our genes, okay?
That's why men want to have as many wives
and children as possible, and
women want to find the wealthiest husband.
But before most of human
history, this was not the case.
This was not true. Why?
Why, guys? Okay,
so it has to do with the
idea of religion, okay?
So the first thing is that
we all come from the mother goddess.
We're all equal, right?
So it doesn't matter if my, if,
it doesn't matter if it's
my son or my friend's son.
They're all the children of the
mother goddess, and therefore
I have responsibility to
protect the children, okay?
Does that make sense? So
there is no concept of individual.
There's only a concept of community, okay?
That's the first thing. Second thing
is they really didn't understand genes,
okay? They didn't understand like, okay,
a child, a woman, a child.
A woman has 50% genes from the mother,
50% genes from the father, okay?
How they understood was, okay,
you have the woman, she gives life.
The man gives energy.
Okay, does that make
sense? Therefore what?
If you believe this, then what?
If the mother gives life,
the man gives energy, what?
What? Better energy to get better.
Right, but how would
you get better energy?
More men, right?
You understand? If men
are giving you energy,
the more men you have sex with, the more
energy you have. Does that make sense?
So, the man gives you energy. The evidence
is, if you look at the people in Melanesia,
they believe that semen provided energy.
And so you need a lot of semen.
So what would happen is that
when a woman married a husband,
what would happen is the members
of the husband's family would come
and have sex with her that
very night in order to get as much
energy as possible from the family.
Does it make sense, guys? Okay?
Any questions so far?
I know this is controversial, but
I'm just trying to show
you how our cultural
beliefs is radically different from the
cultural beliefs of people in the past.
Okay, does it make sense?
Okay, so one last piece
of evidence is this.
When you don't know
who your,
when the people don't
know who the father is,
everyone has a responsibility
to protect the child.
Okay, does that make sense to you guys?
Okay? So the story is this
Christian missionary,
he goes into a village and
he finds people just sleeping
with each other, okay?
There's no marriage,
there's no husband and wife.
People are just sleeping with each other.
And the priest says to them,
you people are shameless.
And one of the villagers replies,
you have no sense.
You French people love
only your own children,
but we all love all the
children of our tribe.
Okay? You understand?
So having multiple sexual partners is
a way to build community for everyone.
If you're a small
community, okay, maybe 15,
20 people, it makes
sense to make sure that
everyone loves each other and everyone
will protect all the children.
Does it make sense guys? All right, so
let me tell you a story
to illustrate this fact.
We know that in World War II, okay,
in World War II, American pilots, okay,
what they were doing for,
what they were doing is they were
sleeping with each other's wife,
okay?
Does that make sense? The reason
why they were doing this is
American pilots were
more likely to die in war
than any other soldiers.
Does that make sense guys? Therefore,
you slept with the wife of your colleagues
in order to ensure that if you die,
they would protect your children.
Because there's a good chance
you would die in war, okay?
You were afraid that if I died, who's
going to look after my wife and who's going to look after my children?
And the way you build intimacy
and community is by sleeping
with each other's wife.
So you became one big family.
Okay? Does that make sense guys?
Any questions so far? Okay,
so let's go to the next slide.
Okay, so let's go to the next slide.
I know this is controversial, I know
this is hard to understand, okay?
But we have evidence that
for most of human history,
woman had sexual agency
and power, and sex was a
way to build community,
okay? Does that make sense?
Yeah? I think this idea
is pretty much not true.
Okay? But I think it's true. But
you can use it as a
factor compared to the.
I mean, I already said it's true that
the idea is that you are,
but using it as a factor to,
to keep, using it as a factor to
to carry on. Okay.
So that's the question,
okay? So the question is,
is this backwards or is it primitive?
Okay. And what I want to show
you this semester is that,
okay, guys, there's no such concept
as backward and primitive, okay?
The reason why we care about
sex more than any other people
is the idea of private property, okay?
Private property.
Okay? So for example, if I have a wife,
I do have a wife, okay?
We have three kids, okay?
I want my three kids to inherit the money.
Right? But
if my wife goes to sleep
with other people,
then who gets the private property?
So in other words,
we have the idea of sex as shameful
because we live in a private,
we live in a patriarchy.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
Okay. Sorry. Let me explain
some more later on, okay?
All right. Let's move on.
All right. So I want to
conclude with this idea.
I want to conclude Maria Gumbutas argued
that old Europe was ruled by women or
women were part of the political class.
And because of that, Europe,
at that time, was more
peaceful and more stable
than at any other time in its history.
Does that make sense? So
another question then is,
why would women as a political class
be more effective than
men as a political class?
Okay? And there are
three reasons. All right?
The first reason is
women are more willing to
cooperate and collaborate.
It doesn't make sense.
So men are competitive.
We like status.
We like power. But women
are much more humble.
So women are much more
likely to compromise
and collaborate than men are.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
So if men are in control,
then men want all the power.
But if women are in control, then
women are much more willing
to share power with men.
Does that make sense? The other thing is,
let's just say, like, your community gets
in conflict with another community. Well,
what would happen is the women leaders of
your community would get together with the women leaders of
that community and you could
quickly negotiate a compromise.
Right? But men are competitive.
They like status. They like face.
So it's much more likely
that when men start to negotiate,
it becomes violent.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So that's one thing that
women are better at.
Women are better at
collaborating and compromising.
That's the first thing. Second thing is
that women have more
emotional intelligence.
Does that make sense, guys? Meaning, like,
men care about rules.
Right? Women care more
about you as a person.
Therefore, women are much better
at managing people.
Does that make sense? Okay?
The third thing is that
men can use violence
to coerce other people.
Women are not as physically strong as men.
Therefore, they have other
strategies for controlling men.
And the two main strategies are
gossip, okay? Basically talking
about you behind your back,
which forces you to conform.
But also sex. Okay?
So if the woman spreads sex evenly
among the men, the men
have no reason to fight.
And if someone, the man, does
something bad against the community,
the woman can choose to not
have sex with this man.
Okay? As a way to punish him.
But this is all very subtle
and nonviolent ways of
forcing people to conform
to the rules of the society.
Okay? Okay?
Does that make sense? Any questions?
This is confusing to you guys, right?
Okay? So, let's conclude, okay?
Before the conquest of the Yamaya,
all Europe was a peaceful
egalitarian society. Okay?
And a lot of the reason why is that
women were given higher status in society.
So it was women who made the rules and the rules
of the society and the rules of the society.
who were the most powerful and
the most powerful in the society.
And because of that, women are able to use
nonviolent ways to control society.
Making society much more
peaceful and stable.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
Any questions?
Excuse me? Okay, okay.
So the question then, the question is,
if people are not violent,
how do you control society? Okay?
And so, the way you can
control people is by,
is through the idea of shame.
Okay? Because everyone wants to get along.
Okay? All right.
So, all right.
Here's a fun experiment. Okay?
Here's a fun experiment.
What you guys can do is,
every time you walk the hallways
and you see a person wearing red,
like a girl wearing red, you
tell her, you look fantastic.
Okay? I guarantee you,
within like two weeks, all the girls
in the school will be wearing red.
Does that make sense? So
you're controlling people,
but you're not using violence.
You're using the idea of gossip,
shame, and flattery.
And that's what women do really well.
Do you understand? Okay?
Does that answer your question?
Okay. Any more questions?
Yeah, so you don't have to use violence.
You can also use flattery.
Okay? Right?
Any more questions?
Okay. So,
next class, what we'll do is
we'll look at the Yamnaya people.
Okay? Because the Yamnaya
people are violent.
They love war. They're patriarchy.
And they have private property.
The question then is, okay,
how do they come about?
Okay? What's their origin story?
And why would they come about? Why were
they so successful in conquering old Europe?
Okay? So that's a story we
will look at next class.