So in this class this semester,
I'm making three big predictions, right?
First is that Trump will win in November.
Second is that
United States will go to war against Iran.
The third big prediction is that
United States will lose this war,
which will forever
change the global order.
These past, so
last class we looked at one reason why
the United States would invade Iran,
which is the Israel lobby.
And in today's class, we'll
look at another reason,
which is the defense of empire.
America is an empire and
it must defend its imperial status.
So let's examine what an
empire means for America.
So from 1950 to 1980,
America's economy was mainly
focused on manufacturing,
factories, okay?
So manufacturing as a
share of GDP was 40%.
It made 40% of profits, okay?
And it employed 30% of the workforce.
So during World War II,
America had a lot of
factories to produce weapons.
And after World War II,
these factories produced consumer goods,
cars, electronics to sell to the world.
And this made the American workers
the wealthiest and
most well -educated middle
class ever in human history.
If you were a factory
worker from 1950 to 1980,
you had a really good life.
You worked 40 hours a week.
You had health insurance.
You could buy your own house.
Your wife didn't have to work.
You could have three to four kids.
You could have two cars.
Every year, you could go on
vacation to some place nice.
You could eat out once a week.
And then you retire and
have a very good pension.
So it was really the best life.
And so workers, they had to work.
And so, from 1950, 1980, in America,
were really the luckiest
people on the planet.
You were better off, actually,
being born into the middle
class in America than you were
being born rich in Africa,
or Asia, or South America, okay?
But then, after 1980, was something
called the Reagan Revolution,
and the introduction of,
what we call, neoliberalism,
And remember that we studied
neoliberalism before.
Neoliberalism is an economic philosophy
that believes in the
primacy of free markets
and deregulation.
So after that,
we now live in today what
we call a financial economy.
The economy has been financialized.
And so what does that mean?
It means that right now,
financial services account
for 22% of all GDP in America.
Manufacturing has gone down to 10%.
So it went down from a high
of 40% to now a low of 10%.
Financial services is now
twice as much as manufacturing.
Financial services bring in 40%.
Of all.
Profits. And
financial services employs 5%.
Of the total American workforce.
Okay? Now, let me explain
what these numbers mean.
What you're seeing behind these
numbers is a radical shift,
overhaul, transition in American society.
Let's just look at politics.
Politics. Governance. From this period,
1950 to 1980, American workers
had a lot of political power.
Because they were middle
class, they were confident,
they participated in politics for unions.
Today, most of this power has
shifted to the financial services.
Which basically means Wall Street.
And that means the economy. And
working for Wall Street are what
we call the
professional managerial
elite.
Okay? So these are people
who live on the coast.
San Francisco, New York,
Washington, DC, Boston.
They went to elite schools.
Okay? The Ivy League.
And they're multicultural.
And right now, they're the most popular.
They're the most powerful
political group in America.
And this has led to massive political
divisions within the country.
Okay? So it's the first major consequence.
Before, it was workers who
had a large say over American politics.
And now it is Wall Street,
the financial sector,
and the coastal professional
management elite.
And so government shapes policies that
favors the political system.
And so we have this multicultural
elite, financial elite,
over at the expense of workers.
Okay? So that's the first major shift.
But then you look at education.
And so what I mean by
that is that, you know,
if you went to a good school, a
good university in the 1950s and
1960s, your ambition was
to become a professor.
Right? Or maybe a scientist.
Or maybe an entrepreneur.
Or a corporate executive.
Okay? Nowadays,
most people who
graduate from these top
schools all want to go where?
Wall Street. And that's it.
Okay? Why? Because you make more money
on Wall Street than anywhere else.
Okay? So you're talking about
these PhDs in statistics
and artificial intelligence who
should be working in the field.
They should be working for IBM,
developing the latest technology.
Right? Instead, they're on Wall
Street working for a hedge fund,
gambling with other people's money.
Okay? So basically the
economy has gone from one
that is productive or
creative to one that is
entirely speculative.
Okay? So remember that
the financial services,
all it does is take people's money and
gamble with it or invest
in it to make more money.
Okay? It's not actually productive.
All it is is speculative.
Okay? And the smartest people in America,
the most well -educated, are
all focused on this sector.
Okay? And then
you look at the economy.
Okay? And
what has clearly changed is that
the economy in America has
become much more unstable.
So in 2001, there was the Internet crash.
Right? The dot -com crash. In 2008,
there was the financial crisis.
Right? The subprime crash.
And then after that, you have all the,
you have these banks going bankrupt.
Okay? I think like this past week,
three banks went bankrupt in America.
This should not be happening.
And the reason why this is
happening are all these bubbles.
Okay? So in other words,
all assets right now
in America overpriced.
Okay? Housing, stock market,
and people are gambling
that these asset prices will go
higher, which creates bubbles.
And when these bubbles burst, you
have volatility and instability.
And uncertainty. Okay?
So this is bad for the economy.
And then you have things like inequality.
Right? So
if you look at profits, if
you look at wealth generation,
the top 1% make much more
money than everyone else.
And this inequality is only increasing.
Okay? So in other words, you have
this inequality. Well, first,
the financialization
of the American economy
has been really bad for America.
And you can make the argument that it's actually
destroying the fabric of American society.
Okay? It's making politics
much more divisive.
It's making the economy
much more volatile.
The smartest people are engaged
in speculative activities.
Young people don't want to work.
They just want to buy Bitcoin. coin. And
you can also make the argument that
you're creating a rentier economy.
And the rentier economy just means that
if you are young, you can
never afford to buy a house.
You can only rent, which means that
you yourself can never go from,
you have no more social mobility.
So this overall is really bad for America.
Another question then is, how
did America get to this point?
How did it transition from a
manufacturing economy
to a financial economy?
And there are different
theories out there.
There are some economists who say that
this is just late -stage capitalism.
Okay? This is the natural
evolution of capitalism.
There are some who argue that
it is the neoliberalism or the
regular revolution that caused this.
Okay? When you take government, when
you cut back the role of government,
when you emphasize free markets, then
you have this situation.
The over -financialization of the economy.
Okay? What I want to show you today is
that you can't just buy a house and you
can't just buy a house and you can't just buy a house and you can't just buy a house and you can't just buy a house. The real reason is the transition to empire.
Okay? There's a really simple
explanation for why this is happening.
The reason is that after
the end of the Cold War,
1991, America became a global empire.
It could now set the rules of the game,
and it set the rules of the game
so that it would always win.
And then all money flowed to America,
which created all these asset bubbles.
Okay? So
that's the argument I'm
making to you today.
Okay? So are we clear
about what's happening?
Any questions so far? Okay.
Now I want to explain to you
how America became an empire.
In fact, I'm going to explain to you how
America became an empire. In fact, the most powerful empire in human history
because even though Rome was powerful,
it didn't really control the world.
Whereas America, the American empire
today, controls the entire world.
Okay? And so to understand
how America became an empire,
you have to go back to
the founding of America.
Okay? So in 1776, America
declared independence
from Britain. And at
that time, they had something called
the Declaration of Independence.
And the Declaration of Independence,
if you read the document, it's very clear.
It's what the founding fathers
of America said is that
we are founding a new society in America
based on God.
Okay? Now, the founding
fathers were Christians,
but they were special type of Christians
who believed in the idea of theism.
And deism is the idea
that, yes, there is a God,
and God did create everything,
but God is not interested
in managing human affairs.
God leaves us alone, which means that
we as humans are empowered to
create the world we want to create.
Okay? And the founding
fathers wanted to create
a new society based
on the idea of the human structure,
the structure of God, okay?
And what they believed is that
God gave human beings
three fundamental rights,
that all governments must
respect, okay? And so
the famous phrase is—do you guys
know the famous phrase— 'Life,
Liberty, and
the Pursuit of happiness.
That is the mission,
the purpose of America,
to ensure that every
American would have life,
liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.
And that's really the goal,
the role of government.
Life, to make you safe,
to provide security against enemies.
Liberty, the right to say
whatever you believe,
the right to believe whatever you believe.
So the tolerance of all
creeds, religions. The last
is the pursuit of happiness.
What does pursuit of happiness mean?
You guys know? So
Thomas Jefferson wrote the
Declaration of Independence, and
when he wrote the pursuit of happiness,
he had a very specific idea in mind.
What does the pursuit of happiness mean?
Which is what? Okay, so wealth, okay?
So in America, your fundamental right,
the fundamental purpose of your life
is to make as much money as you can,
to amass as much wealth as you can, okay?
And the idea here is that in this society,
in this new societies, there's
an experiment called America,
if we allow everyone
to pursue the
creation of wealth, then
America will become powerful, okay?
That's the idea. And it turned out that
this idea was absolutely correct, okay?
In a very short amount of time,
America industrialized very rapidly,
and at the end of World War II,
America became the most
powerful country in the world,
okay? After World War II,
it decided that
it can now export
its philosophy to the rest of the world.
So in 1944, there's something
called the Bretton Woods Conference,
okay?
And so in 1944, everyone knew that
Nazi Germany would be defeated, okay?
And Japan would be defeated,
which would make America,
Japan, would be defeated, which would make
America, Japan, would be defeated, which would make America, the most powerful,
the richest nation on the planet, okay?
Now, the Soviet Union
was a competitor, but
they didn't really matter, okay?
They had their own sphere of influence.
So America got together
with its allies in Europe,
and they decided what the new global
financial system would look like.
And the idea was that
with Bretton Woods, they
decided that the US dollar
would become the global reserve currency,
which basically meant that you could
buy anything with the US dollar.
Now, there were some
people at Bretton Woods,
some economists who
were afraid that
this would cause problems, right?
If you have a government which
was in control of the
global reserve currency,
that would basically
make the government God,
right? If they could just print
as much money as they wanted,
they could become like Midas.
If they touch something,
it would become gold, okay?
So some people thought it was dangerous.
And so the compromise is that
the US dollar had to be
backed by gold, okay?
The gold standard. In other words,
the US dollar was basically
like a receipt for gold.
If you had a million dollars, okay,
you could go to any American bank
and get a million dollars
worth of gold for it, okay?
Does that make sense? So that's
what we call the gold standard.
And for the longest, and so that led,
this Bretton Woods system led to
tremendous prosperity in America
and in Europe and in Japan, okay?
Then in 1971,
Richard Nixon did
something really radical.
He basically said we America,
we we're gonna go off
the gold standard, okay?
Remember that America
had spent too much money
on the space race, on Vietnam,
on domestic expenses,
okay? So they needed to transition
out of the gold standard.
But if you transition
out of the gold standard,
then how do you ensure the US
dollar is worth something?
How do you ensure the intricate
worth of the US dollar?
So they transitioned from
the gold standard to what?
Do you guys know? Oil,
okay, do you understand?
And that's what we call
the petrodollar. And
the idea here is that, look,
every economy needs oil to run, right?
You need oil as the basis of your economy.
And so after America went
off the gold standard,
these countries in the Middle East, mainly
Saudi Arabia, but other countries as well,
agreed that you could
buy oil using US dollars.
So the idea is, okay, before,
if you had a million dollars, a
million US dollars, you could change,
convert that to gold, okay?
And now you can convert it to oil.
And this is what we call the petrodollar.
And this is really the basis
for the value of the
US dollar today, okay?
So then what happened is that in 1991,
the Soviet Union fell,
and now America was in charge
of the entire global economy,
basically, okay? And so America at
that time said to everyone,
listen, let's focus on trade,
because trade will make
everyone rich, okay?
So let me explain the
theory of this, okay?
So America basically
wanted everyone to trade.
And the idea of trade,
okay, this is like Russia,
this is like China, this is like China,
this is like China, this is like America, China, South America.
The idea of trade is that each country
would focus on its competitive advantage.
What are you good at? And then
you would sell this competitive advantage
to other countries for what they're good at,
okay? And the theory here is
that if you do it this way,
then all countries will become rich, okay?
So let me explain why.
All right, so let's look
at, you know, US and China.
So what China is really
good at is cheap labor.
What the United States is
really good at is technology.
The idea is that the United
States and China trade.
China makes all these cheap
goods for American consumers.
But unfortunately,
Chinese consumers don't have enough
purchasing power to buy American technology.
So what happens is that
America gives China US dollars instead.
Trillions and trillions of US dollars.
Now, in theory,
what's supposed to happen is this money
trickles down to the average Chinese.
So that...
So that... The average Chinese worker,
his wages go up, right?
And when his wages go up,
what he can do now is buy
US products like iPhones.
And so over time, trade evens out.
Does that make sense? That's a theory.
That's the first theory.
The second theory is how capital moves.
And the idea here is that
capital is going to go to places.
Which allows it to grow the most.
Okay? And so the idea is that when
you have a globalized world, then
what happens is capital from the
United States moves to China.
Right? Because if you invest in
China, your capital grows the most.
You can buy a million dollar
house in the United States.
Or you can buy ten houses
for the same money in China.
So you're better off buying
houses in China, right?
Okay? So these are the two theories.
One is that trade will make everyone rich.
And second is that
capital will move from rich
countries to poor countries.
Okay? And when you actually
go to university and
you study economics, like Jack Wolfe,
then you actually have
to learn these theories.
But in reality,
these two theories aren't true.
Okay? Okay? Why not?
Why not? Why aren't
these two theories true?
So the first theory is that
if two countries trade, over time,
wealth trickles down to everyone in
that country, which makes everyone richer.
Okay? Is that true for China?
No, it's not. Okay? Workers' wages have
not gone up for the past 30, 40 years.
Why? Because of the idea of elite capture.
Elite capture. So
all the money is captured
by an elite group of people.
When that happens, okay,
they can't spend it.
They can't buy U.S. goods, right?
So the only thing they
can do is invest it.
Right? Now, according to this theory,
they should invest it
back in China because
if you invest it in China, right?
China should allow for more growth
than investment anywhere else.
Okay? But in reality, where
do they put their money?
In the United States. And
why would they do that?
Why? Exactly.
Okay? You don't put your money
where you make the most money.
You put your money where
it's the most safe.
Okay? That's why we have banks. So
because the United
States controls the U.S.
economy. The United States controls
the U.S. dollar. And because
people's wealth is expressed in U.S.
dollars, it makes the most sense to
put your money in the United States.
Okay? And this is not just true for China.
It's true for most countries in the world.
And that's why starting in the 90s,
you have all this wealth
amassing in the United States.
Okay? Does that make sense? So
everything in the United
States became overpriced.
Everything. Everything
became a speculative bubble.
Okay? So let me give you an example.
Let's look at equities.
Okay? Start market. Stocks.
In the year 1900, okay?
In the year 1900, if you look at
all the world's stock markets,
the largest was the U.K.
Okay? Because obviously the U.K.
is the most powerful country in the world.
It was the most powerful
country at that time.
Sorry. At that time, the U.K.
was the most powerful country. Okay?
So in a stock market, as a percentage
of the entire world, the U.K.
was the most powerful country. And the
entire global stock market was about 25%.
Okay? 24 to 25%.
The United States was second at 14.5%.
And you had Germany,
about 13%.
France at 11%.
Okay? So that was the situation
of wealth in the year 1900.
And this makes sense. Right? These four
countries are industrially extremely powerful.
Today, okay?
Today. The year 2024.
The United States has 60%
of all the world's stock wealth.
Okay? Who's second?
Can you guys guess? Who would be second?
Japan. Okay?
And what is the percentage
of global stock wealth?
Can you guys guess? A number?
United States has 66%.
60%. How much does Japan have?
Can you guess the number?
10% is a good guess, right?
It's actually 6%. Okay?
Do you see the disparity?
Number one is 60%.
Japan, number two, is 6%.
It's huge disparity.
How much is China? The world's
second largest economy?
3%. 3%. 3%. Do you understand?
All right? So, all this wealth that's
being generated around the world,
it can only end up one place.
Okay? The United States.
All right? So,
you have... And
that's what's pushed the
financialization of the U.S.
economy. Okay? Because this
wealth goes to the United States.
And someone has to pay for it.
Someone has to manage this wealth.
And this is the financial services sector.
So, people on Wall Street, and this is
very important, people on Wall Street,
they make their money based on
how they manage this wealth,
not on whether or not they
make money out of this money.
Do you understand? They
charge a management fee.
Okay? So, in other words,
they're not actually
incentivized to be concerned.
They're not actually incentivized to be
conservative and make sure that this money grows.
What they're incentivized
to do is design riskier
and riskier assets
and
investment opportunities
to attract more investment,
because then they can take
a management fee, a cut.
Okay? Does that make sense?
And that's what's led to so
much financial over speculation
over the past 20 years in the U.S.
economy. And that's what's led to so much financial
over speculation over investment opportunities And
one of America's biggest problems
is the growing national debt.
Okay? So, the government is paying for a lot
of government services just by putting money.
Okay? So, right now, the U.S.
national debt is about $34 trillion.
Okay? And this $34 trillion debt,
half of it is owned by foreigners.
Okay? So, Japan has about a trillion.
China has about $800 billion.
So, they buy U.S. treasuries.
Okay? So, America owes
Japan a trillion dollars.
America owes China $800 billion.
And then half of it, the
government owes to its people.
So, the two largest expenses are
the military and the pension system.
Okay? So,
$34 trillion is a lot of money.
Okay? And the U.S. GDP
is about $100 trillion.
So, the total debt is about
a third of America's GDP.
And this debt has interest. So,
this debt is growing about $1 to $2
trillion every two to three months.
Okay? And all this is
saying, okay, these numbers,
all they're telling us is
there's absolutely no way
that America can pay all this debt.
Okay? So, then the question then is,
if you're China and you're Japan,
why do you have all this debt knowing
that America can never pay you back?
Or America will at some point
default on this debt. Why?
Why does America, why does Japan and China
and other countries have all this debt,
U.S. treasuries? Knowing that
America can never really
pay back all this debt.
Why? Okay. So, there are many reasons.
Okay? The first reason is that in theory,
Japan and China can always take this debt
and buy oil with it.
Okay? So, this is again the petrodollar.
Okay? Okay.
So, the second reason is that even
though America's in debt,
it's still an empire.
It's still the greatest
military power in the world.
So, at some point, you feel
that the money is safe there.
Okay? Does that make sense? Because no one
can actually challenge America militarily.
And the third reason, and this
is the most important reason is,
there's no place for you to go.
You understand? What else?
What else? What else? So, where
else can you put your money?
Nowhere. Okay? So, that's
the issue right now.
And so, in theory, because
China and
Japan can buy oil with it,
and because
there's really no place for China and
Japan to put this money, in theory,
this system can go on forever.
Okay? So, it's possible that
maybe in 10 years' time,
the debt will go away.
It will be $340 trillion.
Okay? Who knows? Okay? So, in
theory, this could go on forever.
Right? Because America's an empire.
But then, what happened two,
three years ago is Russia invaded Ukraine.
Okay? Russia invaded Ukraine.
And why this is important is
that this is basically
Russia challenging China.
Why? Because Russia is challenging
the dominance of the American empire.
Okay? What Putin is really
saying to the United States is,
I think your empire is full of lies.
Your empire is based on nothing.
Your empire is based on the perception
that you are invincible in war.
Well, I'm going to invade
Ukraine and prove everyone wrong.
Okay? I'm going to show that you,
America, are in fact a paper tiger.
Okay? And so,
if Putin succeeds in his war in Ukraine,
then the fundamental understanding
of how the world works,
that America is an empire,
that America is invincible,
that the U.S. dollar is
safe, will radically change.
It will be destroyed.
It will be undermined.
It will be subverted.
Okay? Does that make sense? So,
that's why America needs
to stop Russia in Ukraine.
Okay? Can it stop Russia in Ukraine?
How's the war going
for America in Ukraine?
Pretty badly. Okay?
I mean, the war is almost over.
Okay. So, but
what America can do,
okay, which will solve all these problems,
is for America to transition from a
financial system to a political system.
Okay? So, America can transition from a financial
economy back to a manufacturing economy.
Okay? If America just does this,
America has nothing to worry about.
It doesn't have to worry about the debt.
It doesn't have to worry about Russia.
It doesn't even have to
worry about the world.
Okay? Because America is a
self -sufficient economy,
meaning that it has the
resources to sustain itself.
It doesn't really need to trade
with the rest of the world. Okay?
If America can return to
being a manufacturing economy,
then it can also be a self -sufficient
Then it will be invincible.
Okay? Now, the question then is,
can America re -industrialize?
Yes or no? Why not, Jack?
Because the politics
doesn't allow them to.
does not allow them to.
Exactly. But can you explain that?
Like, the financial system has,
you know, incredible power.
There's all these countries that
need to be a perpetual system.
And the economy is a perpetual system.
Yeah. And they won't
allow America to do that.
That's exactly right, Jack. Okay?
So, yes, the problem right now is the
very structure of American society
and politics and the economy.
Right now, the financial
sector has all the power.
And they don't want to go back to the time
when manufacturing had all the power.
Right? So, that's the first problem.
But let's just say, for the sake of
argument, that they agree to this.
Okay? What's your other problem?
If you want to re -industrialize?
. Excuse me?
. Okay.
But all the foreign investment
can just go into factories.
Right? But there's actually a really
big problem with re -industrialization.
Okay? So, as Jack says,
there will be political,
you know, political, you know,
political resistance to this.
Okay? But then you have a bigger
problem than this, which is what?
. Okay, guys.
The problem with this economy is
it creates a speculative mindset.
Okay? So, therefore, no
one wants to work hard.
No one wants to go to work
in factories anymore.
Do you understand? If
you're a young person,
you would much rather
spend your time investing
in Bitcoin than working in a factory.
Do you understand? Because
investing in Bitcoin gives you
the opportunity to become rich.
But if you work in a factory,
you have to work hard for 40
years just to buy a house.
Okay? Does that make sense? So, you're not
going to find people to work these factories.
That's a bigger problem. Okay?
And the third problem, of
course, is just investment.
How do you...
How do you build these factories?
You not only have to build
these factories, but
you also have to build logistics networks
to move goods from one place to the next.
Okay? So, in other words,
America could be industrialized,
but it's a pain in the ass.
Right? You're going to face a
lot of political opposition,
especially from the financial sector.
It's very hard for you to get
people to work in factories.
And plus, where's all this
money going to come from?
Okay? So,
if you can't beat Russia in Ukraine, and
if you can't re -industrialize, then
what can you do to protect the petrodollar
and your financial system?
Well, I have an idea. Okay?
Invade Iran. Okay?
Invade Iran. Now, why would you do that?
Okay? And the answer
is that, unfortunately,
of all the options out there, okay,
because America can't just sit back
and let its empire collapse, right?
Of all the options out there,
invading Iran happens to be
politically the easiest to do.
Okay? You're not...
You can't go fight a war against Russia
because Russia has nuclear weapons.
You cannot re -industrialize because there'll
be too much political opposition towards that.
Plus, it'll take you about 50
years to re -industrialize.
But if you invade Iran,
well, you accomplish three things.
Okay? The first thing
is you show the world
that you're still the top dog.
Your military is still invincible.
Okay? So, you're a foreign
investor in America.
You have a trillion US dollars.
You feel safe.
Okay? You don't think the
US dollar will collapse.
Okay? That's the first thing.
To show the world that
America is still the best.
To show the world the world's
foremost military power.
Therefore, the US dollar is safe.
Okay? Second is oil,
right? What is the US dollar based on?
Oil, right? Well, if you control oil,
then you don't have to worry about
people abandoning the US dollar.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
And it happens that the
Middle East produces...
40% of the world's oil.
And Iran is the world's
fourth largest oil exporter.
But when you take over Iran,
you also control Iraq as well.
You control that entire area.
Okay? And the third thing
about invading Iran is trade.
Okay? So,
that area, most of the world's
trade has to pass through that area.
Right? So, invading Iran would allow you
to control the world's shipping lanes.
Okay? So,
that would be the theory
behind invading Iran.
Okay? But
the motivation would be
to save the American empire.
Because if Putin wins in Ukraine,
then America is going to look weak.
It's going to look like a paper tiger.
Okay? And in this
situation, as the empire,
you have to act.
Today, you have a lot
of countries in Africa
who are rebelling against
the Western powers.
France, basically, and America.
Why? Because they think
that Putin is now in charge.
Okay? Why did October 7th...
Why did Hamas attack Israel?
I guarantee you that if it were
not for the war in Ukraine,
Hamas would not have done such a thing.
Okay? For the longest time
before the war in Ukraine,
there was a perception in the world
that America was militarily invincible.
No power,
no country could ever dare stand
up against the United States.
And by invading Ukraine, Putin
has proved everyone wrong.
Okay? The United States can be defeated.
And so what the United States
must do now is prove to the world,
nope, we're still militarily
the greatest power in the world.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
And again, it must do
so to protect its financial economy.
Otherwise, there's a very good chance
that this financial economy
will implode onto itself.
Okay? If China,
Japan, other countries pull out of
the war, they will be able to do so.
If they pull out of the U.S.
financial sector, okay? If
they sell the U.S. treasuries,
not only will America
face a sovereign debt crisis,
but it will lose access to easy money.
Okay? Easy money. And
the problem in America today is that
America is an empire
addicted to easy money.
Okay? People are so used
to just sitting around
and making millions of dollars that
they cannot imagine or tolerate a day
when they have to go back to working hard.
Okay? So it's this addiction to easy money
which will drive American,
which will drive America to invade Iran.
Okay? Does that make
sense? Okay, any questions?
..
...
............
.. managed okay so this is actually
very complicated okay because
again the financial
sector is very large but
if you have us dollars then
your options are you
can invest in the stock
market you can invest in um
houses okay the problem today is
because there are too many
rich people in the world
and
all this money is going to america
all assets are bubbles now okay
so the irony of all this is that
you feel that
your only option is to invest
in america but but when
you do this you're
actually losing value okay
and that's why the system is not really
sustainable everyone's going to america
and that's driving up all
these asset prices but
in the long term that
will destroy the american economy in the
long term um it'll create all these bubbles
that will destroy that will also
destroy individual wealth okay does that
make sense any more questions so
like if america reaches the war
in iran like other countries
will be even more confident in america
okay so so so
so jack asked a great question which
is like listen if going to if going to
iran is all about restoring confidence
in the united states well
if america loses the war
then that would destroy
even more confidence okay
and so
this is this is the problem of empires
empires have something called
hubris right imperial hubris
which means that
they cannot imagine the possibility
of losing a war okay
so why is that okay there are two reasons
okay there are two reasons the first reason is
that an empire what an empire
is it is a war it's it's a force
that imposes reality onto others okay
an empire makes you see the world
the way the empire wants you
to see the world okay does
that make sense which means there's
no feedback loop which means
that you cannot actually tell the
empire what you think it doesn't
your voice doesn't matter which means that
an empire it's not possible
for an empire to imagine
the possibility of it ever
collapsing you understand
if it could it would never collapse okay
that's the first problem second problem is
that okay let's do a thought experiment
if you had a choice if you had a
choice would you rather be smart
and strategic or stupid and
arrogant if you had a
choice in in an ideal world would
you would you rather be smart
and strategic or stupid and
arrogant okay the answer is stupid
and arrogant because it makes
you feel good okay stupid people
feel good about themselves
right smart people
get depressed they doubt
themselves they question themselves
and that makes you feel bad
most people in an ideal world
would want to feel good
about themselves always okay
so it so when
you are an empire you want
to be stupid and arrogant
because it makes you feel good
it doesn't make sense okay
but that's why empires collapse because
you're not going to be able to do what you want once they have too much power they become stupid
and arrogant and they refuse
to consider the possibility
that they could be wrong okay does that
make sense jack okay any more questions
okay uh the american empire has
been building for a long time okay
so you can make the argument that the empire
really started after after World War II,
because now America
controlled half the world, and
then it became dominant after the end of the
Cold War, when the Soviet Union collapsed.
And at that time, okay, before
the collapse of the Cold War,
America had to behave itself.
And the reason it had to behave itself
was it wasn't afraid of the Soviet Union,
it was afraid of communism, right?
That's why from 1950 to 1980,
they treat their workers
so well, because they were
afraid of a worker revolt, right?
So the real threat was not the Soviet
Union, the real threat was communism
as an opposing ideology to capitalism.
Unfortunately today, there's no
opposing ideology towards capitalism,
okay? And that's why America
can do what it wants.
It does not fear any enemies, it
does not fear internal revolt.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay, all
right, so I'll see you guys next week. Bye.