Okay, to review,
last class we discussed
three pre -historical sites,
right? Including Gobekli
Tepe, Jericho, and Kanahoyak.
And the argument I made to you last class,
which is the general scholarly consensus,
is that
what drove,
what compelled the transition
to agriculture was the religious
beliefs of the people at that time, okay?
So it was humanity's
religious impulse that
drove our transition into agriculture.
What I will show you today, okay,
my argument to you today is that
this religious impulse,
this need for religion,
this need to understand
why we are here today,
and what we must be doing,
and where we're going,
it's always been there, okay?
In fact, religion is what
makes us fundamentally human.
And to prove this case,
I'm going to talk about
Ice Age cave paintings.
So I asked you to look
at these cave paintings
that we found all around the world, okay?
They go back 30,000, 40,000 years.
And as you can see from those pictures,
they're beautiful, right? And
they're extremely creative, artistic.
And so I want to look at three questions
about the cave paintings today.
First of all, how were they painted?
They didn't have the
technology we have today, so
how did they paint these cave paintings?
Second question is, why did they do this?
Okay. Because when you're
in a cave, it's very dark,
it's very cold, and it's
very hard to breathe.
But they spent days in
there painting them.
So why did they do that?
That's the second question.
And the third question is, and
the hardest question is, what do
these cave paintings represent?
Or what do they mean?
So the first caveat,
the first thing I want
you to be aware of is that
there's absolutely no agreement
on any of these questions.
Cave paintings is something that
we have a lot of around the world,
but there's very little
evidence as to what they are,
what they represent, and
how they were painted.
So there are a lot of guesses, okay?
And the case that
I will present to you today is
my own personal interpretation
based on my research
and my understanding of the evidence.
But please be aware that
there are many different interpretations,
and the evidence is extremely unclear
about many of these things, okay?
So let's start.
The first thing you need
to understand is that
for most of human history,
it's been very cold, okay?
So the Ice Age only ended
about 12,000 years ago.
And we've seen a general
warming of the planet,
which has allowed us to adopt agriculture.
But before then, we're basically
living on a very cold planet.
Now, the history of humanity is this.
300,000 years ago,
we came into being in Africa.
But because the world was cold,
became very cold about 100,000 years ago,
that meant a scarcity of resources.
And that forced us to seek
food and resources elsewhere.
And so that drove our
movement into Europe,
which then drove our movement into Asia,
and then across the Bering Strait,
remember because this is all ice, right?
Into North America and into South America.
And then from Asia, we went
down to Australia, okay?
So we basically colonized Africa.
We colonized the planet. But
there were not many of us.
There was only about 1 million of us
around the world 20,000 years ago.
And the other thing to remember
is that in this process,
there were actually other
human beings in other places.
So the Neanderthals were here.
The Nesavans were here.
And we interbred with them until we
became the dominant human species,
okay? So does that make sense?
All right, so that's the background.
Now, let's look at some cave paintings.
Because this is in the Shovel Cave,
and this started about 30,000 years ago.
So these cave paintings
were a continuous process
where different people at different times went
to the caves and painted different pictures.
They might have added more things
to the pictures as well, okay?
But as you can see,
this is clearly
representing animals, right?
Bisons, rhinoceros.
The other thing that's interesting
about these paintings is that
there's really no focus, okay?
You see lions.
You see horses.
You see rhinos, okay?
It's almost like nature is
one interconnected picture,
okay?
These are lions,
This is Lacolle Cave
about 20,000 years ago.
And the most...
And a very famous artist, Papa Picasso,
actually was invited
into one of these caves,
and he said that, wow,
we learned nothing in 10,000 years,
meaning that they were just as good back
then as they are today.
Artistically speaking,
humans have not improved at all, okay?
So these are horses, okay?
This is Altamira, Spain,
which goes back to 34,000 BCE.
And you can see that
they're not looking for a realistic
depiction of animals, okay?
They're trying to imagine the natural
world in their own way, okay?
So another question then is, okay,
how did they paint these pictures?
So first of all, they mainly
used red and black, okay?
Red came from ochre,
which is a type of clay,
and black comes from a charcoal, okay?
So that's the coloring they used.
Inside a cave, it's very dark,
so they had to use lighting, okay?
So what they did was they got some
animal fat and put fire on it, okay?
So they could see some of the caves,
but not all of them, okay?
And then... So another question is,
why did they paint these pictures?
And a lot of the clue is this.
A lot of the clue is
this. One clue is where
we found these paintings.
We found these paintings in a
very special place in the cave.
We found these paintings in
the cave, a section of the cave
where the acoustics was the
best, the sound was the best.
So what this means is
we're fairly convinced
that these paintings were part of a ritual
which included music, because
we found these paintings in musical
instruments as well, flutes, okay?
So in other words, we think that
these paintings are like Gopalpepepe,
which is like maybe now and then
these hunter -gatherers would come into
this cave for a religious festival
where there's music, dancing, okay?
And they are watching
these paintings together.
So these paintings are part
of a religious festival.
In other words, these
paintings are not about art.
It's really about religion.
It's expressing the religious
beliefs of the people at
that time, okay?
So does this make sense, guys?
All right. Yes?
Okay, so I'm going to answer the question,
what are the beliefs right now, okay?
All right. So again,
no one knows what their beliefs are
because they wrote nothing down, okay?
They are preliterate.
We can't go back in time
and talk to them, okay?
So we have to use our imagination.
So let's imagine that
we go to a temple and
we go back in time to this time.
It's very cold and
our memories have been wiped out,
meaning like we've lost
the knowledge of today.
We've lost science.
We've lost what we learned
in biology class, okay?
So my first question
is, we're in this world
and what are things that amaze us
or make us wonder or make us in awe?
What are things that
capture our imagination?
Okay? Meaning like we see these things and
we're like, oh my God,
God must exist because
there's no way I can
explain what happened.
What are these things that we would see
and we would be surprised by,
marvel at,
basically be in awe of?
What are things about
our life that amazes us?
What's the first thing
that we can think of?
What's the first thing?
You're in this world,
right? Use your imagination. What's
one thing that's like, oh, okay,
there must be a God or there
must be some supernatural powers
that govern our world. What's the
first thing that comes to mind?
How about childbirth? Childbirth, right?
Does that make sense to you guys?
Because I'm a father, I have three kids.
And I can tell you, when
I first saw my child
being born, I was amazed.
Because you have this life
come out of nothing, right?
Okay? And if you don't, if you never studied
biology, you can't explain what happened.
So that's the first
thing that amazes about,
amazes us about being human.
Childbirth. Childbirth, right?
What's the second thing that would
amaze you if you were back here?
Child growing up. Okay,
so child growing up.
Yes. What else?
How about, yeah? Okay, how
about the stars, right?
It's late at night.
And remember, there's no pollution.
So you see out into the darkness,
and it's all stars glowing, right?
That's pretty amazing. So what
do you think these stars are?
You're staring out into
outer space, right?
And you see these stars
glowing brightly in the sky.
What are they? What's your
own explanation, really?
..
Okay, possibly, okay?
Possibly souls or other worlds, okay?
Planets, worlds. In other words,
the first thing that you recognize is
that our world is just one
of many worlds out there.
Does that make sense? All right?
What else amazes you about the world?
. Excuse me?
. Okay, recovery from disease.
Okay, so healing, right?
How do you explain healing, then?
. What thoughts save you?
. Oh, that God saved you.
Okay, all right, yeah, okay.
So there are some supernatural powers.
. But
another way to explain healing, okay, is
that you have a body and
you have a soul, right?
And the soul could be one of the stars.
So what's causing disease
in this world is the soul
and the body are in conflict.
And so healing is about
bringing the soul and
the body aligned together, okay?
. And we think this because
look at Chinese medicine, right?
It's the same idea, right?
Where the soul and the body
are in conflict, right?
And you want to align
the two in order to heal,
okay?
So other things that would
surprise you is nature, right?
The animals, the trees,
the vastness of nature, okay?
..
And the things that surprise us.
And they force us to
ask the question, why?
So now let's try to construct a theory
of how to connect all these things,
okay? All right, so we know
that the stars, there's
other powers out there,
right? There has to be gods or the
soul of really great people or
other planets or other worlds,
okay?. How does childbirth happen, then?
How does childbirth happen?
How does childbirth
happen? What is the womb?
It comes from the womb, right?
What's the womb, then?.
A portal, a door, right?
. So,
what the womb is, is a door, right?
portal that
the soul comes from another
world into our world.
Does that make sense? Then
how do people return to the other world?
If the womb is a portal
that allows souls to come into our world,
how do these souls return
to their world again?
But what do they do in death?
How do we...
so people die and then?
Burial. Thank you. Do you understand?
So this is symmetry, right?
The soul comes into our
world from the mother's womb,
from darkness, and then
for us to return the soul
back into the original world,
we bury this person in darkness,
and that carries that person
back to the original world.
Does that make sense? So
this is probably the simplest
explanation for how life and death works.
So there are these portals,
and what in nature most resembles a womb?
What in nature most resembles a womb?
A mother's womb. Like a cave, right?
You understand? A cave.
A mother's womb.
Like a cave, right? You understand?
A cave. So we can think that, okay,
we humans come from a mother's womb,
which is a cave, right? A tunnel.
But animals also come from a womb,
which is the cave, okay?
So the cave is a portal
into another world.
So why are we in the cave
celebrating animals?
Why are we doing that?
Why are we in
a cave celebrating animals?
What are we really doing?
We respect the soul?
We respect what?
We respect the soul? We respect the soul?
We respect the soul?
what else are we doing?
Because, why are we respecting their soul?
Yeah, we kill them, right?
So we kill them, and now
what are we trying to do?
Let them forgive us, but what
else are we really trying to do?
Once we eat them, what must we do now?
Excuse me? Yes,
bring them back, right? Do you understand?
So we kill them, we think they go
back into the spirit world, right?
So now we have to summon them back
from the spirit world into our world.
Okay, does that make sense?
So, in other words,
what this religion, what this
belief is really saying is
that we are all interconnected.
And for every action that we make,
we have to do something else
to compensate for action, okay?
So if we kill an animal to eat the meat,
then we need to ask forgiveness
and then bring this animal back into
the spirit world to maintain balance
and harmony in nature.
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
So, why is it in this world
there's balance and harmony?
Why do we think there's
balance and harmony?
Because what gives life to everything?
What's the force that
gives life to everything?
The mother goddess, right?
Mother nature, okay?
And so, if we think
that there's one force,
the mother goddess, that gives life to
everything, that means that for us, trees,
animals, us, are all equal.
We're all the children of mother nature.
We all have souls,
okay? And so, what gives us
permission to kill other animals?
Why are we allowed to kill other animals?
The other animals are
our brothers and sisters, right?
So what gives us permission
to kill the other animals?
Why are we allowed to do so?
Okay, because
mother nature, mother
goddess has a plan, okay?
Each thing on this planet has a function.
The function is to maintain
balance and harmony.
If we do not kill the other
animals, we will die, okay?
But also, if we don't
kill the other animals,
there'll be too many of them.
You understand? So, in other words,
the world is a cycle, it's a circle,
and each person,
each animal, has a part to play in that.
And as long as we play our part, then
the world will be harmonious,
and balanced, and perfect, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay?
Does that make sense, guys? Okay, so,
we have, actually, a
word for this religion,
and this word is
animism, okay? Animism.
And what animism is,
is it's a very it's probably the
first religion okay it's a belief
that each living thing whether it's a
tree a mosquito a person
or anything that's living
has a soul okay
and we're all interconnected because
we all have souls and so
we must maintain balance and harmony
and so
um many of the print of religions
okay if you go to talk to
native people in North America
and South America in Australia
they all have this belief but
also there are many religions
such as Buddhism which
also has this belief okay and we believe
that this is the first religion okay
so let's go over some evidence
that
this is in fact what
they believed okay you
so um a recent discovery
that we made is that
trees talk to each other you
guys do you guys know this
so what happens is that
trees there are maybe thousands
of trees in the forest
and their roots are connected
through mushrooms for fungi
and this allows us allows
them to share information
so for example what we know is that
if one tree in one part of
the forest lacks nutrients like water okay
the other trees will send nutrients to
that tree does it make sense okay
so it's it's almost like the forest is one
big brain or one big living organism
and they're all trying to communicate
with each other another thing
that we've discovered is that
if there are pests or insects
that attack one tree okay this
tree will automatically communicate
to the other trees and
these trees will start to prepare
for the pest or the attack okay
and the third thing which
is the most interesting is
that trees will recognize
their own children
so if the children these children trees
need nutrients the mother trees will send
the nutrients to the children right
away okay does that make sense
so this is something that
we've recently discovered
but when you think about it
if you're living back then
you can sense the you
can see sense almost health
trees communicate because
you're always in touch of nature okay does
that make sense all
right this is a cave painting
and you can see
that
these animals okay gazelles
they're going somewhere and
there are two beings here okay we believe
that these two beings
represent the mother goddess
because as we discussed last
class the mother goddess comes in
the form of a bird right the bird flies around
the sky the sky is the mother goddess okay
so it's almost like the mother goddess is
channeling or hurting the animals from a
spirit world back into our own
world what you also notice is
that these birds almost like humans okay
and so we what we think is that
the shamans dress up like birds
in order to channel the energy of the mother
goddess to control the animals okay Okay?
Okay, and there's actually
a lot of evidence for this.
So, this is clearly an animal,
but this is also a person who's an
animal, who's a human being, right?
Because of the figure.
So these are human beings, shamans, who
dress up like animals in order to
better communicate with animals,
but also to better communicate
with the spirit world, okay? And
this is actually a more clear picture of
shamans trying to access the spirit world.
Okay, are we clear so far?
So, from this religion, we can guess
that the people back then
were extremely compassionate.
They believed that
everything has a soul,
and every life is precious.
Okay? And one evidence for this is this.
This is a skeleton.
What's interesting about the
skeleton is that it's a dwarf, okay?
So there are some humans back then who
are born with diseases, or handicaps,
or physical deformities.
This person is a dwarf.
Now, this is interesting because
dwarfs aren't able to
communicate with humans.
They're not able to contribute
that much to your community, right?
So as a hunter -gatherer,
you need to hunt together to access meat,
to get meat, to feed everyone.
If you're a dwarf,
you're not really doing that much.
So in theory, because
it's such a harsh life,
being a hunter -gatherer, you
would think that they would
discard the dwarf, kill
the dwarf, or maybe
leave the dwarf. Leave
the dwarf behind, okay?
But from DNA analysis,
what we know is this.
This skeleton,
okay, this person had
the same amount of food,
the same quality of food as everyone else.
Meaning that even though
this person was not
contributing to the community,
everyone worked hard to make
sure this person was treated well
and was fed as well as everyone else.
And at the end of this person's life,
he was granted a elaborate burial,
okay? And we know this from the
archeological research, yeah?
Yeah, okay. Okay, does
that make sense, guys?
All right, so let me
ask you this question.
Let's make the assumption
that he was, in fact, a dwarf.
And that he was, in fact,
contributing to the community.
How could he contribute to the community?
How? They clearly thought he was special,
but what made him special?
If you're a dwarf,
you can't hunt, what can you do?
To me?.
Okay, okay, but
what else can you do besides food?
Why would they think he
was a special person?
What could he do that others couldn't do?
Yeah?.
Thank you, okay.
So maybe the religion back then
is that everyone is special.
Everyone's the same, right?
So if you're different,
it doesn't mean you're less special,
it means you're more special.
It means that the mother goddess
has given you a special power.
And maybe this power is to communicate
with the spirit world, okay?
So maybe the cave paintings, as you say,
were done by people like this,
who were in a constant state of
meditation, meditation, meditation.
But of course, that doesn't compare to the health
of the health of the health of the health of
the health of the health
of health of health
of health of health of health of health of
health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of
health of health of health of health of
health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health of health
of health of health of health of health of
health of health of
health of
of time into meditation
into religious practice
that enables you to communicate
with spirit world okay does
that make sense okay and not only that
but what we found is
that there are many burials like this okay
so this is a passage from
the dawn of everything
which is a fantastic book
okay by David grabber
and David Wengro they're
both anthropologists
and this is a fantastic book okay but
this is a passage from the book
so
Roman two is the dwarf he
goes back 10,000 years okay
and it was a pretty elaborate burial
and as this paragraph says we
know he ate exactly the same
food as everyone else okay he was
not discriminated against in any way
and the last passage here is neither is Romato in
isolated case okay we have many examples of this
when archaeologists undertake balance
appraisals of hunter -gatherer
burials from the Paleolithic
okay meaning the Ice
Age they find high frequencies of
health related disabilities okay
so the people who are
buried tend to be the ones
who are disabled they
have some form of disease
which makes us think that
maybe they're shamans okay
they were picked to be shamans
because hunter -gatherers thought
you're different therefore
you must be special therefore the
mother goddess favors you okay
and high levels of care until the
time of death sometimes their
funerals were remarkably
lavish which meant that
they were prioritized
by the community they
were highly valued by the people around
them okay the best explanation is well Well,
they were shamans. They were people who
could access the spirit world
and communicate with it, okay?
Doesn't make sense, guys. All right,
any more questions before I move on?
All right. Now,
another amazing thing that
we found about Ice Age cave paintings is
that they have symbols,
okay? So we saw pictures,
but a Canadian anthropologist
named Genevieve von Petzinger,
she went all around the world and
she documented symbols in these
Ice Age cave paintings and
she found recurring symbols.
For example, the hand, okay?
The hand is everywhere.
The spiral.
The quadrant. The triangle.
The circle, okay?
The asterisk. Let me
ask you this question.
Why would paintings have symbols?
Why would drawings have symbols?
Why can't you just draw the thing?
Why do you need to have symbols?
Okay so, so we think
that this is a written language, okay?
It's one of the first written
languages, which meant that
back then, they actually
had the ability to read
and write, okay?
so maybe this is a common language.
What are some other possibilities?
Why would you want to use
symbols in a painting?
Why? Why?
To keep the convent mysterious.
Excuse me? To keep the convent mysterious.
Okay, that's interesting.
Okay, to keep the convent mysterious.
And so, where do these symbols come from?
To keep the convent mysterious, right?
You have these symbols
and there's secret signs.
Where are the secret signs from?
From the
Another theory
is
that
this is the language of the gods, right?
As you say, to keep
the convent mysterious.
To keep it divine or holy or sacred.
Right? To keep it meaning. Okay?
Does that make sense? Okay?
What are some other possibilities?
Yes, exactly. Okay? Yeah.
So, this can also be a shorthand.
Okay? We call this shorthand. But also,
like, there's some things you can't draw.
For example,
love or energy or repetition or balance,
harmony, cycle. Right?
These things you can't draw. So, you
have to represent them using symbols.
Okay? So, there are many
different possibilities.
Which means this. Okay?
Let's just summarize what
the possibilities are.
What are the symbols in art? Okay?
The first is that maybe you're
trying to visualize an idea.
Okay? You can't draw energy or
life force or cycle or repetition.
So, you just have to use
a symbol to represent it.
Okay? Which means what? Which means that
each picture is a mythology.
It's a story.
Okay? Do you understand? The pictures
aren't trying to show you a picture.
They're trying to tell you
a story about the world.
That's why symbols are important.
Because in a story, there are ideas that
you cannot visually explain.
But of course, they're making things up that
haven't been expressed. It doesn't make sense?
Okay? That's the first thing.
Second thing is that
you're trying to visualize the
language of the spirit world.
Okay? So, this goes back to
making the concept of mysterious.
Okay? Why do we think this?
The answer is this? Okay?
We think that when they drew,
the way to access the spirit
world is to use drugs.
Okay? What we'll call psychedelics.
So, in other words,
there are certain plants
that are making things up that
haven't been That if you drink, okay,
it makes you see things and
The things they see are in fact
the symbols the geometric signs
so in other words, they went to the spirit
world or they think they went into spirit world
and then they're just trying to
Express the language of the spirit world.
Okay, does it make sense?
all right, so This is a complicated idea.
Okay, but I want to introduce this idea to you
like how we perceive or how we understand reality
So for most of human
history we thought that Oh
Reality was just reality and
we are trying just trying to see reality.
Okay reality something
that you must see and
Then along came a philosopher and
he's a very famous philosopher I want you I want
you to remember the name But his name is Immanuel
Kant Okay,
and he is considered the
greatest philosopher who
ever lived Immanuel Kant German and
his idea is this his idea is that
Reality is not something that
we experience or we see
Reality is something
that we Imagine that we
create with our mind
the example he uses is
time and space Okay,
the idea of time like one two three
four it does not exist in nature.
It's not It doesn't exist.
Okay. It's something
that we are my made up So
our reality is something
that we imagine every day
Okay, does that make sense?
Now what's really interesting is that
Immanuel Kant was writing
maybe over 20 years ago?
Okay, and today we have a new science that we're
going to be studying today It's called neuroscience
Okay neuroscience is
the study of the brain
and what's really amazing Okay, and
we will discuss this in
future classes is that
neuroscience has confirmed Immanuel Kant
Meaning like we now know
that the brain
Imagines reality, okay,
it projects reality.
It doesn't make sense So
what drugs do is they change?
The structure of your brain so
you you see a different reality
Okay, does that make sense guys?
So that's what drugs do and so when
they see a different reality,
maybe they're seeing symbols Okay,
so that's the second thing
about symbols in art.
The last thing is
These symbols are mysterious right and
Mystery makes things sacred and
divine right so back to childbirth
Childbirth is something that back
then they couldn't understand
Therefore they have to believe that
childbirth is sacred
and divine and therefore
Women are sacred and divine
because only women are
Able to give birth men
are allowed to give birth.
Okay, so back then we believe that
for most of human history either
We were egalitarian mean like
men and women were equal or
woman had more power than men
and Only in recent history
Do men have more power?
Okay, and how this happened?
I'll explain to you next week.
Okay, but just remember
like back then there was no
separation of sexes if anything
woman were considered
superior to men remember like
the God is a mother goddess a female and
therefore women
are more special than men and
they know this because
Women give birth not men.
Okay and Childbirth is mysterious.
Does that make sense? Okay, so
we understand symbols and art
as doing these three things now.
We have a more
comprehensive or complete
Understanding of why they did art.
Okay. The first reason is what they're
trying to do is trying to trying to
visualize their mythology Okay,
they're trying to take this
idea their understanding
of How the world works their religion
and they're trying to visualize it.
Okay, so art is basically religion.
There's no difference Second thing is
that They're trying to show
To themselves how reality works.
Okay, they're trying to show that
the under rely underlying
reality It's a soul or God.
Okay, does that make sense? the last thing
which is the most important is
they're trying to create a
common memory and imagination a
Language mythology that
they all share together.
Okay, and this is what we call society
Does that make sense? So in other words,
okay The argument I'm trying to make you
trying to make you the argument I'm trying to make to you today is one
religion has always been there
since the dawn of humanity
Okay, that's the first second
thing is that religion Okay,
that's the first second thing is that
religion Allows us to communicate with each other to be together in society
So the third thing the third thing is
Religion is what allows us
to be fundamentally human
What religion we could not be human.
We could not think we cannot
communicate we could not imagine
doesn't make sense guys It
doesn't make sense guys Okay,
any questions about this?
It doesn't make sense guys
Okay now let's look at a
quote Okay now let's look
at a quote It doesn't make
sense guys It doesn't make
sense guys It doesn't make sense
guys It doesn't make sense guys It doesn't
make sense guys It
doesn't make sense guys It
doesn't make sense guys It doesn't
make sense guys It doesn't make
sense guys It doesn't make sense guys It
doesn't make sense guys So when you go to university and you study sociology,
guess what? You'll mainly be
studying Imelda Durkheim, okay?
So this is what he says about religion.
Religion is above all, okay, first
and foremost, religion is
this, a system of idea by
which men imagine society of
which they are members, okay?
It's to create society.
And the obscure yet intimate
relations they have with it, okay?
Religion is a way for them
to understand the world.
All right? Does that make sense, guys?
All right. So
let's look at what he
says again in more detail.
Okay, so the great service that
religions have rendered to thought
is to have a system of idea.
Constructed a first representation of what the
relations of kinship between things might be,
okay? So what this is saying is that
religion allows us to construct
an understanding of the world, okay?
So basically, the first
religion was this, right?
And this is just a theory of the world.
This is important because
from this theory,
we are able to construct more theories.
All right. Given the conditions in
which it was tried, that
enterprise could obviously
lead only to makeshift results,
okay? Meaning that, okay, well, listen,
religion, it's all about guessing.
It's all about hypothesizing, okay?
So, you know, a lot of these
ideas aren't going to work out.
That doesn't matter. But then
are the results of any such
enterprise ever definitive
and must it not be taken up?
It has to be taken up
again and again, okay?
So our desire to know, our curiosity,
forces us to constantly
reimagined our religion.
Furthermore, it was less
important to succeed that to dare.
The fact that we tried was important.
What has, what was
essential was not to be,
was not to let the mind be dominated
by what appears to the senses, okay?
But instead, to teach the
mind, to dominate it and
to join together what the
senses put asunder. So
as human beings we're not trying to
see the world we're trying
to imagine the world.
That's what makes us human.
Going back to Immanuel Kant,
our ability to imagine reality is
what makes us fundamentally human.
As soon as man became aware that
internal connections exist
between things science
and philosophy became possible.
So from religion we develop
philosophy and science.
In fact you can say that
science today is our religion.
There's really no difference.
It's just an understanding of the
world based on our imagination
and some evidence.
Religion made a way for them.
It is because religion is a social thing
that we can use to create our own world.
It could play this role to make men
take control of sense impressions
and replace them with a new
way of imagining the real.
A new kind of thought had to be created.
Collective thought. So religion
is our collective consciousness.
It's what allows society
to come into being.
If collective thought alone had the power
to achieve this, here is the reason.
Create a whole world of ideals through
which the world of sense reacts to. If we can create a world of ideas through which the world of sense reacts to.
of ideas of health health health
health health health health health
health health health health health health
health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health
health health
health health health health health health
health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health health religion, there could be no society.
Without society, there
could also be no religion.
Okay? You understand?
So the implication of all this is that
as a human, first of
all, you are not alone.
If you are alone, you're not a human.
You're a human because
you live in society.
You're with other people. And
because you're with other people,
you must have a collective consciousness
or an idea you share together.
We call this thing religion.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Is this clear to you guys? All right.
Any questions? Anything
you are not clear about?
Do you see how all this connects together?
Okay? The cave paintings
is what started it.
Cave paintings is the
expression of a religion.
Then when the Ice Age ended, we
had the chance to settle down.
We created communities to
celebrate our religion.
That's what gave rise to activism. Okay?
And the religion that we use is
probably something like this.
Okay? The world is interconnected.
There's a mother goddess that
gives light to everything.
Okay? Any questions?
Anything you are not clear about? Yeah?
Okay. So
that's a good question. Okay?
So the question is monotheism.
Okay? So
the three major religions
of today are Christianity,
Islam, and Islam.
Okay? And Judaism.
Okay? They're all monotheistic,
meaning they believe in one God.
So this is actually a
very recent innovation.
Okay? So back
then, they wouldn't have a concept of
power hierarchy. Do you understand?
They wouldn't understand
that the mother goddess
is the greatest God of all.
Okay? They could only
think like the stars.
Right? There's no hierarchy in the stars.
They're all over the place. Okay?
So maybe the mother goddess
gives birth to our world, but
maybe there's another God that
gives birth to another world.
Okay? So they wouldn't
think in terms of hierarchy.
We think in terms of hierarchy
today because of monotheism.
But back then, they wouldn't think so.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
So maybe today,
you can think of a pyramid.
Okay? There's people at the top.
But back then, they would
think like it's a river.
Okay? We're all part of the river.
It's a cycle. It just goes in circles.
And there's no differentiation
or there's no power hierarchy.
Things go wrong when
there's conflict inside this river.
Okay? When people don't do things
they're supposed to be doing.
Okay? And what, and these things are what?
The world. What are things that
defy the mother goddess or go
against the mother goddess?
How about incest? Right?
How about killing animals without
making the proper sacrifices?
Right? So you just kill the animals, but
you don't go in the cave
to pray for their return.
Okay? So in other words, in this world, religion
is based on the fact that you're not going to die.
And this is basically ritual. And
this is something that we'll study next
class, how religion is just ritual.
Okay? Just, just habits
and practices and actions.
Any more questions? That's a
great question, by the way.
But monotheism is something that we will
look at very closely in future classes.
And it's very important because
it's a basis for our society.
Okay? Any, any other questions?
Yeah? I noticed that last class, God,
you can't really be
uncoversive because, you know,
Yes. Yes.
We can't live in a cave, though.
Right? You can't live in a cave.
You can only go there now and then.
There's no oxygen in a cave.
It's too dark. It's too cold.
You can't live there.
Right? So, you're right in
that, okay, if a cave were livable,
they could build farms around that cave.
Okay? So,
okay, that's actually a great question.
Besides caves, what are some
other portals in the world?
What are some other portals in the world that
have, like, spiritual energy besides caves?
In nature. In nature.
If you were back then, you would
think that this place is special
because it both connects
our world and spirit world.
And these places would
be mountaintops, right?
Mountaintops. Guess what?
Govle Tepe was on a mountaintop, okay?
Where else would there be portals?
Rivers, okay? Rivers.
Okay, does that make sense?
These are places that
people would think are portals into another
world and therefore they are special.
And we find that when they settled
down and built agriculture,
they did so on mountaintops
and they did so around rivers.
Okay? Does that make sense?
But not caves because you
couldn't actually live in caves.
Okay? Does that
answer your question? Yes.
Okay. Is it possible to live in a cave?
You can't live in a cave. There's
no food and it's cold and it's wet.
Oh, great question, okay?
So they lived outside in tents.
Oh, yes, but not in the cave.
No, no, you can't live in a cave.
There's no oxygen. Okay?
Any more questions? Okay.
So your question actually makes me think of
a point I want to end the class with, okay?
So today we think
that we are either economic animals,
economic animals or biological animals.
Okay? So the person who
introduced us, like
who introduced to us the idea that we
are economic animals is Karl Marx, okay?
And his argument is that we are
driven by our need to have money,
okay? And that's what we're doing.
That's what we believe today, right?
You're in school because you
want to get good grades so
you can go get into a good university
and then you can go get a good job, okay?
Now, there are other
people who believe that
we are biological animals
and these are people,
people are called evolutionary biologists.
They are inspired by Charles Darwin.
So the idea here is that
we are motivated by our
desire to spread our genes,
okay? So if I'm a man,
I want to sleep with as many
women as possible because
if I sleep with as many women as
possible, I spread my genes, right?
But if you're a woman,
you want to find a man
who will be loyal to you because
the cost of childbearing,
childrearing is very high, okay?
Does it make sense? So and
we'll be discussing both these
theories more for the next class.
Throughout the semester, okay? The
argument I want to make to you today is
that no, we are first
and foremost a religious animal.
We have the fundamental need
to understand why we are here.
We have a fundamental need to
connect with everyone, okay?
To connect with other people.
But that does not mean
that we are not economic and
biological animals, okay?
They all interplay together.
Do you understand? So
what we'll see later
in the semester is that
you might have a religion, but
this religion is not meeting your
economic and biological needs.
Then you have to either abandon the
religion or change your religion, okay?
But we'll also know that the
economic need is not enough.
You also need religion. So there
is an interplay between economics,
biology, and religion.
Okay, and that's what
drives human history.
This is something that we
will learn more about.
Next week, okay?
Sorry, next week. Okay?
So, yeah, any more questions? Okay.