Let's start class.
So last week we discussed the possibility
that Trump will become president
and we discussed that
if he does become president in a
second term there will be
a very strong likelihood
that the United States
will go to war with Iran.
Now the question today is
okay Trump wants to go to war
but will the US military agree?
Ultimately it is the Pentagon that
must implement this war and
if there is enough
opposition from the military
then
it is very hard for Trump to push a war.
I want to make the argument today that
the military will go along with the war.
And it has to do with what
happened in 2003, okay?
So let's go back to the last time that
America fought a major war.
It was the 2003 invasion of Iraq
called Operation Iraqi Freedom,
okay? So at that time, President George W.
Bush and his people,
Vice President Dick Cheney,
Secretary of Defense Donald Rumsfeld, and his
deputy, Paul Wolfowitz, they want this war.
And they go to the Pentagon
and say, listen, we want
this war, give us a plan.
And the Pentagon,
the generals,
they're very experienced
and conservative people.
And in general, when you fight a war,
there are three things
you must focus on, okay?
The first idea is mass force.
Mass forces. When you fight a war,
you want to overwhelm your enemy.
So when we say mass forces,
we basically mean infantry and armor.
Most wars are fought
using tanks and soldiers.
And the Iraq Army at
that time had about 370,000 soldiers,
okay? And in general,
the general rule of thumb when
you invade a country is you want
to have a three to one advantage,
okay? The reason why is
when you invade an army, when
you invade a country you
need to hold territory
and resupply your soldiers, okay?
So you need to advance but
you also need to hold territory
as well as resupply your troops
and have reserves, okay? So
the general rule of thumb is
that if you're going to If your enemy has
300,000 soldiers, you need about a million.
So that's the first principle.
Second principle is the idea of
you want to avoid encirclement.
The worst thing that can
happen to your soldiers
is if they become encircled by the enemy,
because then it becomes
impossible to defend yourself.
The third idea is
protect supply lines.
Most of war is actually just logistics.
How do you get oil and fuel
and weapons from here to there?
Supply lines. These are
the three major principles
that you must focus on
when you fight a war.
When the Bush government
asked the Pentagon for a plan,
the Pentagon went to the drawing board and
said to invade Iraq properly
we need about a million soldiers.
Okay? And
Donald Rumsfeld, who
was Secretary of Defense,
and his deputy Wolford said,
no we're gonna do it with
less than million soldiers.
Give us a plan with,
that requires less infantry.
And the Pentagon said, okay,
well we shouldn't do this
but the most we can do is about 900,000.
And Wolford said, nope, go lower.
And eventually, Rumsfeld
and Wolford said, I want,
we want you to fight this war
with a hundred thousand troops.
130,000 troops. Okay?
The Pentagon said to Rumsfeld
and Wolford, this is insane.
We will be outnumbered three
to one when we fight this war.
How are we going to avoid encirclement?
How are we going to amass forces?
How will we protect supply lines?
And Rumsfeld and Wolford, who are not,
by the way, professional
soldiers, they've never,
they've never really fought
a war before, they're like,
well we're going to try to defend ourselves because
we're going to try to defend ourselves because
we're going to try to defend
ourselves because we're going to
try to defend ourselves because
we're going to try to defend ourselves
because we're going to try to defend ourselves
because we're going to try to defend
ourselves because we're going to try to defend ourselves because we're going to try to defend ourselves because we're going to try to defend ourselves because we're going to try to defend ourselves
ourselves because we're going to try to defend ourselves because we're going to try to defend ourselves because we're going to try to defend ourselves because
we're going to try to
defend ourselves because
we're going to try to defend
ourselves because we're going because
the nature of war has changed.
What the US military specializes in,
what gives us the advantage is three
things, or three things, okay?
First is air supremacy.
We control the skies because
we have the greatest air
force in the world, okay?
But second, what's most
important is technological
omniscience. Omniscience
means to know everything.
We're god! The reason why is, listen,
we have satellites that
can see everything on the Earth.
We have technology that
allows us to eavesdrop on all
electronic communications.
When you talk on the phone, we can
hear exactly what you're saying.
We know everything on the ground.
That allows us to have the power of God.
Okay? That's the second thing. The
third thing is we have special forces.
So special forces are soldiers
who go into enemy territory
and they are able to target and
direct air power against the enemy.
Okay? And
we America have the best
special forces in the world.
And so
with these three things we
have a new doctrine of war.
We can fight war in a new way
that's never been fought before
but which will guarantee
that war will be quick,
we'll do it very quickly, cheap,
it won't cost that much
money, and third, decisive.
We will completely destroy our enemy.
Okay? Okay? Okay?
And the Pentagon was like,
you guys are insane.
This is not going to work.
This is a theory, guys.
Whereas this idea of mass
forces, avoid encirclement,
protect supply lines, we've been doing
this for like thousands of years.
This is just experience.
This is just history.
This is reality, guys.
This is just a fantasy.
All right? But Rumsfeld and
Wolfowitz insisted and they said,
you must fight this war this way.
And they insisted.
And it turned out that
this plan that the Pentagon,
most military planners thought is absurd,
insane, unrealistic,
worked 100% the way it
was supposed to work.
Okay? The Second Gulf War in
2003 lasted exactly three weeks.
Okay? Very quick.
The US military, with only 130,000 troops,
was able to destroy an army of 270,000
in three weeks. Okay? That's one.
Second is that
America lost at
most 200 soldiers.
And most of it was
through the friendly fire.
Okay? It was accidental. This is insane.
This has never happened before.
Only 200 American soldiers.
And the first thing that was most impressive was
the fact that the American soldiers died at most.
Whereas tens of thousands
of Iraqi soldiers died.
Okay? And the third thing
that was most impressive is
something called Thunder Runs.
Okay? This is just America flexing.
Okay? Or showing off. So
what was happening was
that America was so dominant
that you had these American
soldiers in their armored vehicles.
And they were able to destroy
an army of 700,000. Okay?
All of these automatic automatic automatic
automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic
automatic automatic automatic automatic
automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic
automatic automatic automatic automatic flip.
I'm so bored by this guy,
I'm going to do a back flip.
Thunder runs. So
these three things show
the incredible superiority
of this doctrine of shock and
awe.
So how is America able
to achieve all this?
Well, I mean the first thing
is the idea of air supremacy.
So one bomb called a
cluster bomb can wipe
out an entire tank division.
The reason why is that a cluster bomb
inside has about four forty bombs.
And these forty bombs
are equipped with GPS.
So what they can do is each of
these bomb can go and find a tank.
It will latch onto a tank
and blow the tank up.
So this one question is
a little bit complicated.
The first thing is, what does a cluster
bomb do? the bomb, which doesn't really cost that much money, can destroy an entire tank division
by itself.
The other thing is special forces.
So the theory is that special forces,
if we make them the central
core of our military,
that would have a devastating impact.
And it was true.
So what was happening was that
special forces could drive around
and look for military and
insulations by themselves,
which I'm like a few people.
And then they could order in an airstrike.
And then the planes
would blow everything up.
So shock and
awe was extremely effective.
But the problem is that
people don't really ask.
What did Sato do? What did
Saddam Hussein do wrong?
Why was it so effective
against Saddam Hussein?
And there are actually three
reasons to think
that what happened in 2003 was
not a revolution in military doctrine,
not a revolution in warfare, but
just a unique incident in war
that doesn't really tell us that much.
In other words, what was happening?
What was happening in Iraq
could not be replicated.
And there were three reasons why.
The first is that Saddam
Hussein had no air defense.
He had no air defense. He didn't have
weapons to counter America's air supremacy.
The reason why is that in 1991,
Saddam Hussein fought a war against
America called the First Persian Gulf War,
Operation Desert Storm.
And his army got destroyed
by American troops.
Then when
he hygiene hygiene hygiene
hygiene hygiene hygiene
hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene
hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene
hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene
hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene
hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene
hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene hygiene I can't stop it.
Okay. That's the first thing first thing
he learned second thing he learned is that
America probably does not
want to overthrow me because
If he over froze me it would
destabilize the country
it would destabilize the region you
would allow terrorists into the country
You would turn my people into
terrorists you would empower Iran
So there's no way that America could
overthrow me would want to overthrow me
So let me just focus my resources on
suppressing Internal dissent.
Okay, so he completely
forgot about America
So even when it was clear that
America was about to invade he still
did not put up any air defenses
because he didn't have Any air defenses.
Okay, but so that's the first
thing that was unique about
the 2003 war, okay, second thing is that
Iraq is a
desert That makes it ideal
for shock and awe right
Air power can go anywhere.
You have satellites
that can see everything
Special forces can just drive around
Okay, so a desert makes an
ideal situation for shock
and awe and the third
thing is just Surprise
No one in human history Has
tried to fight a war like this
Okay, and so no one knew
How what was going to happen
so an example is that
Special forces were in
Western Iraq blowing up
missile bases because
the concern was that
Saddam Hussein would direct all his
missiles his scuds against Israel,
okay, so so much damage
was being inflicted in
Western Iraq that Saddam Hussein
believed he was so confident that the
That the that the main American military
Was actually in Western Iraq when
in fact they were in Eastern Iraq
So he diverted all his
forces to Western Iraq
and left Baghdad completely
open to attack from the east
Okay so
! No one Had fought a war like this before
and no one knew what to expect.
Okay, but obviously you
can only do this once
Right. Okay.
So there are three special conditions
To make us think that
shock and awe in the 2003
Iraq war which is a one
-off it was unique.
Okay Unfortunately
The Americans Don't know this. Okay,
right the Americans are like well
all this does is Prove
our theory to be correct.
Okay, so over so after 2003
America focused its military doctrine
Its military on shock and awe, okay,
so the example is special forces
So before 2001 America had
about thirty eight thousand
special forces today is 73,000
That's a lot Because America
has a total army of 1.3 million
The budget for special
forces black ops, okay,
it was about two billion in
2002 thousand and today it's about
thirteen point seven billion.
So it's almost an increase of
Seven times which is a lot but
um, this is just the
public official number
because Special forces are black
ops they can operate outside
Supervision of The military.
Okay. So in other words their
actual budget is probably
Ten times possible hundred times
more than the official budget
right now
now special forces
I want to talk very briefly about
why special forces is a problem
Okay now traditionally
militaries have been very strict hierarchies
and There are good reasons for this.
Okay, you have to enforce order
and discipline, right, but
you're also concerned about the military
Overflowing the government, right?
That's always been a
problem throughout history.
So you must maintain complete control.
But when you do that
You create a
Lot of problems in the military
It is unable to act very quickly
to That's why you have special forces Okay
But in general you don't
want that many special forces
because again they're
outside the control of your
military, okay, they're independent
Sometimes of your military they have a
lot of like a lot of space to maneuver
and to be independent
Now why are special forces a problem it's
because the people who
volunteer for special forces are
different from you and me,
okay to put it very lightly.
So for example, let's look at
One of the top two special forces
in the world called SAS Okay,
this is British special air services the
most one the most elite certainly the oldest
special forces in the
world the other is Delta
and so
You volunteer for special air services.
You're applying. Okay
And their first test is
this the first test Okay,
there are many tests but the first test is
you have to run six marathons in five days
Okay, oh That's just beginning.
You also have to carry a
backpack of bricks
While you are running six
marathons in five days,
okay, and you're like, okay, that's hard.
Oh one more thing Hmm your
Running the marathon on a mountain
Okay, you understand you have to
run six marathons in five days
with a backpack of bricks
And you have to go on
a mountain somewhere.
Okay, so we even have that
first test there have been some
individuals who've gone crazy
Okay, you have to put them put them in
a hospital because they've gone crazy
But that's just to be
the first test the last
Test is always torture they would be
tortured To see how much they can resist
Torture, okay, because obviously when
you're captured the enemy's gonna torture
you to get information out of you, right?
What are you doing here?
Who is your commander? Are
there other comrades with you?
Okay, you always be tortured so
they also have to withstand torture
There's some other tests. So for
example in the French special services
one test is that
you will have to wear a
bulletproof bulletproof vest Okay,
and you will we have to hold a
Plate disk, right and then your
comrade will shoot a gun at you
Most people are like I'm
not going to do this.
Okay So in other words
The people who are special forces,
they're different from us physically
but they're really different
from us psychologically
They have a different mentality So,
one special forces was
interviewed by a reporter and
the reporter asked him, why did you
choose to become special forces?
And his answer is, well,
it's either I do special
forces or I go Rob -X.
One of the two. In other words,
special forces are individuals who
are addicted to risk
and violence.
And guys, in America,
there's 73,000 of them running
around the world trying to
protect the American empire.
Okay? So
special forces have increased
and it's really changed the
nature of the American military.
So it's good for America.
Because now...
Now, what Shaw and
all allows America to do
is be everywhere at once.
And you'll never see them.
Okay? So, for example, the example is
when Gaddafi was overthrown
in the 2011 Libya war.
Okay? That was special forces.
But we don't know this because the special
forces were hiding in the background.
Okay? Directing air power against Gaddafi.
So in other words...
What Shaw and all...
What Shaw and all really is, is
it's more than a theory of war.
It's ultimately a theory of empire.
America is an empire.
But unfortunately, most Americans
don't want to admit that.
Because being an empire means doing
bad things to innocent people.
And what Shaw and all allows...
What Shaw and all allows is for America to be
an empire without the guilt of being an empire.
Okay? You have special forces doing all the
work necessary in order to maintain this empire
without people actually knowing.
All right? So Shaw and
all is really a theory of empire
as opposed to a theory of war.
Okay? So does it make
sense to you guys so far?
Okay? Any questions so far?
Yeah? Okay.
So... Okay. So, Celine
asked a great question.
Are there... There's more special forces.
Is it because there's more people
who want to be special forces?
Or is it because America
needs more special forces?
The answer is both. Okay? So, again,
the... America...
America... After the fall
of the Soviet Union,
no longer had a peer competitor.
So the understanding of America is
that from now on, they will
have to fight rogue regimes.
Okay? So small nations that
don't really listen to America, and
these nations have to
be toppled very quickly.
Okay? So the examples would be Iraq,
Iran, North Korea.
Okay? The axis of evil.
Okay? So America started to shift
its doctrine to shadow wars.
Okay? Wars that you don't
really see, but which
would be effective in toppling
the regimes you don't like.
Okay? And so
a lot of the resources were
shifted into special forces,
and that allowed more people
to enter special forces.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay. All right. Any more
questions before I move on?
All right. Now the question
then is, all right,
shock and awe, where does this come from?
It comes from one of the greatest
disasters for America
called the Vietnam War.
Okay? So from 1965 until 1973,
there was a civil war in
Vietnam between North Vietnam,
which was communist, and South Vietnam.
Okay? And the war started in
Vietnam, which is basically a U.S.
controlled puppet state. Okay? And
America sent soldiers from 1965
to 1973 to protect
South Vietnam from insurgents and rebels.
And at the height of this war,
three million U.S.
soldiers had to be deployed.
Okay? Okay?
And at the height, in 1969,
500,000 soldiers, U.S.
soldiers, were in country to fight
against the rebels and the insurgents.
Okay? 58,000 U.S.
soldiers died in this war.
Three million, at least three million,
Vietnamese died in this war.
Two million of them were civilians,
innocent civilians. Okay?
Over 300,000 U.S.
soldiers were wounded.
Okay? They went home
without legs, without arms.
And they were traumatized.
And this was an extremely
controversial war in America
because they were trying to fight the
war using standard military doctrine,
mass forces. Right? So, the institute
did something called a draft.
So, if you were a young American, you
had to go fight in this war in Vietnam.
But you didn't know why you
had to go fight this war.
And chances are that
you would either die or you would
lose a body part in this war.
So, it became extremely
unpopular in America.
The other thing is that there were a lot
of journalists in Vietnam during this time.
And they were reporting on how America
was killing Vietnamese for no reason.
So, the most famous of these journalists
was the American journalist, Mr. Lee. And the most famous story is something called the My Lai Massacre where American soldiers
went into a Vietnamese village
and killed everyone there.
Okay? 300 people, 400 people.
Okay? And this was happening
actually quite a lot.
So, there was widespread anger
and protest in America at this time,
which ultimately forced
America to withdraw in 1973.
Okay? And...
The U.S. military was
very angry about this war.
Because the thing about generals
is they don't like to lose wars.
Okay? When they fight wars,
they want to win at all costs.
And they felt that they were
betrayed by the country.
They were fighting hard to
maintain the American empire,
to fight against communism.
And this was bringing the U.S.
military to a standstill. Okay? They're fighting
to maintain wealth, power, and prestige to America.
But the American people,
the American politicians,
the American democracy republic,
refused to make the necessary sacrifices
in order to maintain this empire.
And so, many American generals felt
betrayed by what happened in Vietnam.
Okay? Now, there's a very famous incident
during this war called the Pentagon Papers.
Okay? In 1971,
a group of
American analysts, okay, they were,
these were military analysts
working in the military.
They secretly got together
and they tried to compose
a secret history of the Vietnam War.
And this was called the Pentagon Papers.
This was meant to be classified.
This was not meant to
be read by the public.
But one of them, Daniel Ellsberg,
linked it to the
newspapers, Washington Post
and New York Times, and they published it.
And people were angry
by the Pentagon Papers
because what the Pentagon
Papers said is, one,
America has been secretly
fighting this war for a long time,
okay? So many presidents,
including Eisenhower, Kennedy, and
Lyndon Johnson, were expanding
this war without any reason.
Without public approval, without
congressional approval, okay?
So there was a lot of deception,
that's the first thing.
Second thing is that
the politicians,
the presidents, knew this
war was not winnable.
You couldn't win this war, okay?
And the reason why is that
these Vietnamese
peasants, they were unbeatable
because what they were doing was they
were digging tunnels underground.
And then when American soldiers were coming,
they would just pop out of these tunnels,
shoot at them, and then disappear
back into the tunnels, okay?
It was like as though they
could swim underground.
They were not beatable.
Second thing is that
they had an unlimited supply of weapons.
And you're like, wait a minute.
These peasants don't have
weapons, and the answer is,
they got these weapons from their enemies.
Okay? So the first thing is
that these soldiers, these American
soldiers, were in the jungle,
and they were carrying
backpacks of ammunition,
right? And sometimes
they would lose a fight,
or they would run away in the jungle,
because it's very hard to carry these backpacks of ammunition, right?
They would drop these
ammunition, and guess what?
You're now arming the enemy, right?
Because these peasants would pick
up these ammo and use it themselves.
Okay? That's the first
thing. Second thing is that
the US military dropped
more bombs on Vietnam than
in World War II combined,
okay? More bombs were dropped in Vietnam
than in World War II combined, okay?
Does that make sense? And about
20% of these bombs didn't explode.
And if they didn't explode, the enemy
could pick them up, and transform them.
They could import automatic automatic
automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic automatic second thing
and the third thing was that
the South Vietnamese army
was extremely corrupt
so they were taking these
American weapons and
selling it them to the rebels okay
so then the question then is you can't
really see this enemy they're everywhere okay they can swim underground
and if you're supplying them yourself so
no matter how much weapons you can bring
into this country how are you gonna win this war the other thing is
that these peasants were
getting angry at you because
obviously in this war you're
killing a lot innocent people right
who happens to be their brothers their
sisters their children their parents okay
so
as this war was dragging on the
Vietnamese were becoming more embittered
and more angry so
there's no way you were
going to win this war okay
that's that's a pentagon paper
second thing the third thing is okay
the question then
is is these American presidents
these American leaders
know for a fact that
this war cannot be won why were they fighting
this war why would they continue to flip this for
and
the answer is unfortunately the
answer is credibility
okay we don't want to
lose face guys okay we don't want to
lose face loose face if we
withdraw from Vietnam if we admit
that peasants were in pajamas can beat us
Soviet Union would laugh
at us China would laugh at
us the entire world would laugh
at us we don't be laughed at
so that's why we're
staying in this war okay
so
to summarize what the Pentagon
Papers said okay three things one is
that the American government
lied to the people
and
turn this into a major war that's
first thing second thing is
that America cannot possibly win this war
okay the third thing is
that America is only in this war
so
to avoid losing face that's it
there was no strategic purpose
there was no strategic objectives
from fighting this war it was just
like we don't lose face we don't
be laughed at that's it okay
so obviously when
the Pentagon Papers were released to
the public everyone was angry okay
and the anger was so tremendous
that America had no choice but
to ultimately withdraw from the war and
so the Pentagon felt betrayed by democracy
the politicians were more
concerned about winning
elections than about winning wars
okay people could protest
and
defy the military they refused to make
that sacrifices necessary to win this
war the media
could insult the military
so the
but so there are many in
the military who fought that
listen if we are to maintain
the Empire we need to divorce
the Empire from democracy
okay Empire democracy do
not get along if we want to
win a war our greatest
enemy is not the enemy
but democracy in America and
that's why you have shock and
awe right because
because they didn't think
because because because
because because
because because because because because
because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because
because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because
because because because because because
because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because because
because
to fight the war.
You can now escape the
shackles of democracy
in order to do what you must
to protect the American empire.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So shock and awe was really
a response to Vietnam War.
And what shock and awe means is that
the empire is no longer
burdened by democracy.
Special forces can go and
do what they must without any oversight
and consent from the people.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
Okay, so shock and awe is
really a fear of empire.
What America must do in order to maintain
its empire around the world.
Any questions before I move on about this?
Okay, so Suneen asked a great question,
which is, okay, I make the argument
that shock and awe only
works in Iraq, right?
And what would happen
in other wars? Okay, so
the thing about America
for the past 20 years is
it's been mainly fighting
wars in the Middle East.
And it turns out the entire
Middle East is a desert, okay?
Okay? So this shock and
awe policy has had
tremendous success in Iraq
and then in Libya, okay?
Because America overthrew
Gaddafi in Libya.
And it's also had some
success in Syria as well.
Okay? So from the perspective of America,
we're really only
fighting wars in a desert.
Shock and awe is fine. Okay?
But our next class, we'll discuss Iran.
And Iran is not a desert.
It's mountains. Okay? And I'll
show you that shock and awe
is not gonna work in Iran.
Okay? But that's next class. Okay?
Does that make sense? All right.
Any more questions? In Iraq,
after America had seen Saddam Hussein,
there was still a lot of
fighting after they won.
Yeah. They couldn't control it.
Yeah. So shock and awe is in a desert
in the middle of the country.
Yeah, okay. So Jack makes a great
point, which is, okay, yeah,
but most people would say
that America lost the Iraq war
because of the insurgency, right?
Okay. So, okay.
That's a great point. Okay?
You can make the point that
America, for the past 20 years,
have lost all wars in Iraq
and Afghanistan because
they have not been able
to control the insurgency.
Okay? But the problem with this is that
shock and awe, it's not
designed to stabilize countries.
Shock and awe is meant to
topple and destroy countries.
Do you understand? And so
the argument can be made
that the real intention of
shock and awe is to make sure
that no power in the Middle East can
arise to challenge America's supremacy.
Okay? So yeah, in Iraq,
the insurgents ultimately won,
but is Iraq a functional state?
And the answer is no, right?
Is Libya a functional state?
No. There's still a civil
war going on in Syria.
All right? So, but that's a great point.
Okay? And it comes down
to what is the ultimately,
what is the ultimate design
and intention of the empire?
Is it to replace regimes or
is it to destroy countries?
And you make the argument that shock and
awe is really designed to destroy countries
and not to replace regimes.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay.
So, what's important to understand is that
one of the theories of the invasion of
Iraq is to bring democracy to the country.
Okay? But the problem with that
is, from the start, they
did everything wrong.
Okay? So first thing is,
they really didn't have enough soldiers
to maintain peace, right, in the country.
So there's a lot of looting. So
the entire country broke down.
Second thing is that
during the air campaign,
America, America destroyed all the
infrastructure necessary for society, okay?
So including water supply,
including electricity grid.
Why would you do that if
your intention was to
bring democracy to the country, right?
The third thing is that the very first
thing the American government did
when they took control over Iraq is
something called de -bafflication,
okay? Which is to say that if you
used to work for the old government,
you're now out of a job.
Hey, the Iraqi military, they're
not going to work for you.
You're now disbanded. And
then the question then is, ha,
if your ultimate objective is to
bring democracy to the country,
why would you destroy
all political infrastructure
in the country?
Why would you destroy the ability for the country
to govern itself as well as to maintain order,
as well as to feed the population?
Why would you do that? Okay?
So an argument can be made
that the real intention
was not to bring democracy to Iraq, it was
just to destroy Iraq, to maintain American,
to maintain supremacy as well
as to teach others a lesson.
Don't mess with us, we'll
come and destroy you, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay,
but this is something we
will discuss later on, okay?
In another class, okay? All right.
All right, let's now
move to the last topic,
which is the theory of empire. So
this is not the first theory
of empire America had.
It's actually the second theory of empire.
Okay? The first theory
of empire was in 1991.
Remember that in 1991,
America launched
an attack against Saddam Hussein because
Saddam Hussein invaded Kuwait, right?
So at that time, 1991,
the Soviet Union had collapsed.
America was the only
hegemon, was the only power,
and it presented a new
theory of empire, right?
How America will rule the world, okay?
So the first idea is
limited strategic
goals or objectives, okay?
So for example, in 2003 when
America invaded Iraq,
its strategic goals
were pretty unachievable, okay?
It was basically like we're
gonna bring democracy and
peace to Iraq and the Middle East, okay?
Whereas in the Persian Gulf
War, led by the father,
right, George Herbert
Walker Bush, the first
and only goal was to remove
Saddam Hussein from Kuwait.
That's it, okay? We're not gonna go
to Iraq and topple Saddam Hussein.
We're not gonna inflict
punishment on Saddam Hussein.
All we wanna do is remove
him from Kuwait, okay?
That's the first thing. Second thing is
that, okay, we're gonna have to do this.
We're gonna have to do
this. America did so
with a coalition of countries, okay?
Dozens of other countries
were part of the war,
and America played a leading role, but it
also had to defer to its partners, okay?
So for example, countries
like Saudi Arabia,
who participated in the war, were like,
there's no way we'll topple Saddam Hussein.
We'll only stop at Kuwait, okay?
So the United States deferred
to its partners, okay?
And the third thing was,
and this is the most important is that
the ultimate leader
was the United Nations.
The United States had to go and
make a case to the United Nations.
The United Nations gave its consent
to the military action, okay? So
the United States made the argument
that this is not a U.S.
military action. It is a U.N.
military action, okay?
And so the important principle is to,
maintain the rules
based in national order.
Okay? So what America said at
that point is, yeah, I know we are
the greatest power in the world.
I know the Soviet Union has collapsed.
I know that militarily
no one can challenge us.
But with this power comes
great responsibility.
We must show humility.
We must show discipline.
We must show restraint.
Our priority will be to maintain
the national rules based order
because this will bring
prosperity, freedom,
and stability to everyone.
Okay? And that means that
if we use the military,
it will only because it's the last resort,
the last option, and only for
a limited strategic objective.
We will only do this if
we do so with partners.
And we will only do so
under the umbrella of UN authority.
Okay? So this is the
first theory of empire.
When you think about it, wow, great!
What a wonderful world, right?
Here's a question then. Why did America
not do this anymore? Why did
they switch to shock and awe?
Shock and awe is basically
unlimited strategic goals,
unilateral military action, right?
We, America, will do this by
ourselves. We don't need anyone.
Okay? And America is
just basically bullying.
We make the rules. Why
did America do this?
Why this transition from the
first theory of empire, which
is great, it would allow America
to rule the world forever,
to now the second theory of empire,
which is pissing the entire world off?
Why? Okay. So this is really
hard to understand, okay?
But let's use an analogy, okay?
So Jack is my son.
Okay? And I'm a billionaire.
I have $10 billion.
Why do I have $10 billion?
It's because one, I'm smart.
Okay? I'm smarter than everyone
else. Two, I work really hard.
Okay? And three, I bribe
a lot of politicians.
So I have $10 billion. But
I'm like 95 years old.
And I know I'm going to die.
Okay? So I invite Jack,
who's my son, to dinner.
And I say to Jack, Jack,
I love you and I want what's best for you.
I'm going to die very soon,
and you will inherit my empire.
Okay? And I want you to know
that you don't have to
worry about anything,
Jack, because I have 100 advisors who
control this empire,
who manage this empire.
And they are great.
They're experienced. They're loyal.
They're strategic. Every year, Jack,
they make 10% for us.
Okay? So $10 billion to make
$1 billion for us every year.
When I go, they're still going
to manage this empire for us.
And you know what? They're going
to give you, every year, Jack,
$100 million. You can
do whatever you want.
You want to go buy an airplane?
Do that. You want to go buy an island?
Do that. You want to
party with movie stars?
Do that. You can do whatever you want.
Okay? So,
Jack, as my last wish,
as my dying wish, I want you,
Jack, my son, who I love,
to promise me
that after I die, you will
listen to my 100 advisors.
Okay? So, Jack, do you promise me?
You promise me, right? And then, I die.
And then what is the first
thing that Jack will do?
The very first thing that Jack will
do is the first thing he will do.
Come on, guys. It's not hard.
Your first thing you will do,
okay, is fire everyone.
Get out of here. Okay?
What's the second thing you will do?
You're going to hire all your friends,
Jack. Okay? You're going
to hire all your friends.
Okay? And what's the third
thing you're going to do?
You're going to do
something really stupid.
Okay? You'll be like, you know what?
My dad only made $10 billion.
Those advisors only make 10% a year.
I'm going to invest in Bitcoin.
I'm going to invest in AI.
I'm going to invest in the Chinese stock
market, the Chinese real estate market,
and make $100 billion.
Okay? And then he loses all the money.
You understand? All right?
This happens all the time, guys.
Okay? Right?
Ask yourself, if your dad were rich
and he was about to leave
you a lot of money,
would you listen to professional people?
No. No. You'd be like,
no, I want to have fun.
Okay? So the question then is,
the first fear of empire,
okay, which said
that for America to maintain its empire,
it must demonstrate to the world humility,
discipline, and restraint.
Why did they get rid of
this and move to shock and
awe, which is like, we'll
do anything we want.
Why? Why? Why would they do that?
Because it's fun. Okay? Do you understand?
What is the point of having an empire if
you cannot blow things up for no reason?
There's no point. We have the
greatest military in the world.
Let's just blow things
up for like no reason.
Okay? All right? Now,
there are three fundamental
problems with shock and awe.
Okay? The first problem is that
you become over committed.
Do you understand? You believe that
shock and awe allows you to be God.
You can be anywhere at
once fighting all wars.
Okay? You're over committed.
Second is, you lack strategic focus.
Meaning that, you actually
don't have a plan.
You don't know what you
want to do with this empire.
You know you just want
to maintain this empire.
Okay? So you don't actually
have a strategy in place.
Okay? And the third thing is,
hubris. You don't think
anyone can challenge you.
You don't think you can lose a war.
Okay? And so, the idea of hubris is this.
Right now, America has this huge empire.
And it's refusing to spend the necessary
resources to protect the empire.
So for example, the US Navy. Okay?
In 1945, it had 7,600 ships.
Today, guess what guys?
That's 475.
These 475 ships must go around all around
the world to protect shipping lanes.
Okay? The US military,
in 1991, during the
first Persian Gulf War,
had 2 million soldiers.
Today, it has 1.3 million soldiers.
Okay? So, in other words,
if America ever fights a war, a major war,
it's going to have a lot of problems.
The other thing is that America doesn't
even have manufacturing capacity anymore.
Okay? It doesn't have
any factories anymore.
Okay? So, Which means that if it fights a war,
it can't fight a war for a very long time.
So, the example is that
for every ship that America makes,
China can make 300 ships.
Okay? America no longer has
this manufacturing capacity that
it had during World War II.
Okay? So, in other words,
why will the military agree
to the stupid war in Iran?
Because it's over committed.
It has no strategy. And
it's because it's arrogant.
All right? And the military is like this
because of what happened
in 2003, shock and awe.
It doesn't make sense
to you guys. All right?
So, next class, we will look at
what the Iran war will look like.
And I guarantee you that shock
and awe is not going to work in Iran.
All right? But I'll explain why.
Next class. Any questions
before we end for the day?
Okay. I'm going to go to the next class.
So, what's the difference between the analogy between the theory of the first theory
and the theory of the second theory?
Oh, so, Celine asked a great question.
What's the difference between the people
who believe in the first
theory and the second theory?
Okay? Okay. And the answer is this.
The people who believe in the first
theory came from an older generation.
Okay? This is the generation
that fought in World War II
and who fought the Cold War.
So, they understand what war looks like.
War is really bloody
and it's terrible.
And we must do our best to avoid war.
Okay? The second generation, 2003,
are individuals who
don't know what war is.
Okay? Like, if you actually
look at videos from 2003,
the war, it actually
looks like a video game.
You understand? You don't actually
see what they saw in Vietnam.
Okay? And the third generation, which
was all these soldiers losing their arms
and crying. Okay? I mean, the images
from Vietnam were just terrible.
It was hard for people to watch.
But, the Gulf War in 2003,
it was just a video game.
It was just like things getting blown up.
Okay? You don't actually
see the people dying.
And again, only 20 people died,
20 soldiers died in 2003.
Okay? So,
um, in other words, unfortunately,
America is headed towards disaster.
Okay? Because the people in
charge have no experience.
They don't know what war is.
And they don't know what
the horse of war is.
And they've inherited a lot of money.
And they want to enjoy the money.
Okay? They want to have fun. Okay?
Does that make sense? Okay.
All right. Great. So, I'll
see you guys next class.
Bye. Bye. Bye. Bye.