Okay, so we start Rome today,
and we will spend the next four classes
on the rise of the Roman Republic,
and then the rise of the Roman Empire.
So, Rome, traditionally,
we believe Rome was founded
in the year 753 BCE,
but we don't know, okay?
That's just what tradition says,
that's what the Romans believe,
but we actually don't know, okay?
So, around this time, Rome,
it's just like a small,
insignificant kingdom in
the middle of Italy, okay?
It was founded on a Tiber, this is Rome,
and it's part of Italy
called the Latin area, okay?
So, these people are known as the Latins.
Now, at this time, and
over the next centuries,
Rome would be a small,
poor kingdom, always.
It was at war with its neighbors, okay?
Primarily, the Sabins over here, and
then you have other tribes as well.
At this time, the dominant civilization
is what we call the Etrischians,
and
the Etrischians are the most advanced
civilization in Italy during this time,
and it is very similar to Greece,
in that there are different city -states,
and they trade with each other.
And because they are by the sea,
they are able to access cultures
and ideas and goods
from all around the world, okay?
Then across the Mediterranean,
you have a place called Carthage.
Here is Italy, Sicily, okay?
An island called Sicily.
Sicily is important because
it's basically the main island
of the Mediterranean, so
you're going to control the
Mediterranean Sea and the Tiber.
And to trade, you have to
control Sicily, all right?
So, across the sea is Carthage, and
Carthage is from...
It's a colony of Phoenicia,
which is in the Levant, okay?
And over the next few hundred years,
Carthage would become the dominant
economic power of the Mediterranean,
because they're very good at trade,
and they're very good at...
Sailing, okay? So they'll travel and
sail all around the world
and found new colonies, and
slowly they'll build up their own
little empire across the Mediterranean.
And they are, for the longest time,
the wealthiest city in Europe,
basically, okay? And
of course,
over here are the Greeks, right?
And we spend a lot of time... I'm
sorry. It's been a lot of time...
It's been a lot of time...
It's been a lot of time... It's been a
lot of time... It's been a lot of time...
It's been a lot of time...
that it did become, right?
So, what we will look
at the first class is
how did Rome become so powerful?
And the easy answer is, it's good at war.
It's really good at war. And then the question
then is, well, why is it good at war?
Why is it better than the
Greeks or the Carthaginians?
And the answer is, because
the Romans are not afraid to die,
and because the Romans have a different
conception of citizenship than the Greeks.
Okay, remember the Greeks
were extremely jealous
of citizenship. It was very
hard to become an Athenian.
It was very hard to become a Spartan. You
basically have to be born into the polis.
Same thing with the Carthaginians.
They were not as strict as the Greeks.
They were pretty inflexible as well.
They were very proud of being a citizen.
Rome, because it was the
poorest and smallest,
it had no choice.
If you wanted to immigrate to Rome,
they welcomed you as a citizen.
And as such, they could,
throughout its history,
draw on the vast manpower
pool in the surrounding areas.
Okay? And as such,
with their almost unlimited manpower pool,
they could eventually overwhelm the Greeks
and the Carthaginians and
become the dominant power in the
Mediterranean by about 200 BC.
Okay, that's the easy answer, and that's what
most historians and most scholars believe.
But I want to be more precise, okay?
I want to show you that
ultimately it's the value system
or what is known as the character
of these different civilizations,
that ultimately determine their fate
and future. Okay, does that make sense?
All right, so, so
about 500 BC, Rome becomes a republic.
And at this time, the Etruscan
culture is dominating Rome. In fact,
three out of Rome's seven
kings previously were Etruscan.
Okay? So culturally and
traditionally, speaking,
the Etruscans have this
huge impact on Rome.
But because Rome is very good at
war, it's slowly able to expand
and conquer the Etruscans and
basically control all of Italy, okay?
And because the Romans are
expansionists by nature,
they are a war -like people,
they are basically a war machine,
they now want to control Sicily.
They now want to control
Sicily. It's been a
war on the Entean,
Entean is the Enteanan dynasty,
Entean dynasty is the Entean dynasty
of Entean,
the Greek world is dominant
throughout the world.
So, Alexander conquered
most of the world, and
his generals now control
most of the territory.
And one of the successors to
Alexander, his name is Pyrrhus,
he decides this is an opportunity
for him to build his own empire.
So, he responds to the Greeks
who call for help against Rome.
So, Rome is threatening the
Greeks in southern Italy.
The Greeks are asking for
help from the compatriots.
Pyrrhus comes with an
army to help his compatriots.
And remember, at this time,
the Greeks have the best military in the
world because of the hoplite phallus.
And Pyrrhus is destroying the Romans.
Battle after battle,
Pyrrhus is destroying,
and decimating the Romans.
Eventually, Pyrrhus says this.
Wow, I'm winning so many wars.
I'm winning so many battles. And
if I continue to win battles,
I will be completely out of men.
I will have no more soldiers left.
Okay, and this is where the phrase
pyrrhic victory comes from, right?
You can win, but the costs of victory are
so high, you might as well
have lost, all right?
And so, what this means is, even
though the Romans were militarily
inferior to the Greeks,
the Romans weren't afraid to die,
and they inflicted so many
casualties on the Greeks
that the Greeks eventually
had to withdraw,
okay? And this will start many
centuries of war between the Romans
and the Greeks. Remember, at
this time, in the beginning,
the Greeks are wealthier, more numerous,
and more military
dominant than the Romans.
But eventually, because
of the Roman way of war,
Rome will eventually
conquer the Greeks, okay?
So that's the Greeks. Eventually,
the Romans went to Sicily, and
this brings them into direct
conflict with Carthage.
And this starts what is
called the First Punic War.
Now, there's a problem.
Carthage is a naval power,
Rome is a land power.
Rome has no navy.
So what Rome does is,
slowly over time, it
builds its own navy, and
at first, it sucks, they
lose a lot of ships,
and so the Romans build more ships, and
they get slaughtered by the
Carthaginians at sea, so
they build more ships, and more ships, and
more ships, and eventually, they overwhelm the Carthaginians.
And so, after 20 years of war, in
what is called the First Punic War,
Rome becomes a dominant naval
power in the Mediterranean.
Carthage becomes second.
Then something strange happens, okay?
Carthage, it is a trading
power, is a maritime power,
and while
it's able to dominate its neighbors,
okay, it establishes an empire in North
America, in North Africa, and in Spain.
It loses a lot of wars against
the Greeks and the Romans,
who are just better warriors, okay?
But then, the Carthaginians
produce a man named Hannibal Carba.
Hannibal Barca. And
Hannibal Barca is considered,
by many military historians,
to be the greatest general who ever lived.
As a military strategist,
Hannibal had no competitor, okay?
And Hannibal Barca, he
hates Rome with a passion.
He understands this. He understands that
Rome is fundamentally an
expansionist military power.
Rome will not stop until
it has conquered the world.
So even though, technically, Carthage,
Rome, and Rome are at peace,
eventually, Rome will come for Carthage.
So it is better to take a fight to Rome
first than to wait for Rome to come to you,
okay? Now,
Carthage at this time, it is
basically a republic like Rome.
And it's run by people called, by
something called Council of Elders.
Okay, and these are the words, okay,
the wealthiest citizens in Carthage.
And there's elements of democracy
and Arlacher as well, but
it's primarily republic, okay?
It's run by these people.
And these are merchants.
These are wealthy people. War
is bad for business, okay?
So they were not supportive of Hannibal
in his desire for war against Rome.
So Hannibal did two things, okay?
The first thing is,
he was in charge of civil mines in Spain.
And what he did was he conquered a
lot more, a lot of Spanish territory
for Carthage.
And so he was able to amass more wealth.
He took this wealth and he used it to
basically bribe the Council of Elders,
to leave them alone, okay?
And to support his military
adventures in Spain.
And again, these are business people.
If it's profitable, they will support you.
And then what Hannibal did was
he did something that
was unimaginable before.
He took his army and he
crossed the Alps, okay?
He crossed the Alps,
sorry, the Alps are here,
into Italy. He is now at Rome's doorstep.
And again, before Hannibal did this,
it was thought impossible
to cross the Alps,
especially in winter, with an army, okay?
But Hannibal did that.
He lost a lot of men and
elephants, war elephants,
in his crossing, but
he was able to cross.
And when he crossed, he was able to
summon a lot of allies to his side,
okay? Because Rome was at
war with everyone in Italy
and with the Gauls to the north
of Italy in France, okay?
So Rome had a lot of enemies.
And so Hannibal was able to replenish
his forces once he landed in Italy.
He was also a very charismatic speaker,
a great general, okay?
Rome heard about this,
and at first Romans were
shocked, but they weren't scared.
Rome is a war machine, okay?
So they decided to send
an army against Hannibal.
And army after army fell against Hannibal.
Hannibal was able to defeat
Roman, Roman soldiers
and armies using superior military tactics
and strategies, okay? Then the
Romans decide, you know what,
here's what we're gonna do.
We'll take two years off,
and we're going to build the
world's largest army, okay?
80,000 men. And at this time,
Hannibal had about 40,000 men.
And then we'll take
these 80,000 soldiers and
we'll just throw at
Hannibal and crush Hannibal,
and the war will be over, okay?
And that's the strategy. That's
just the Roman way, okay?
The Romans are not creative.
They are just brutal,
bold, and direct, okay?
That's just their way of war. And so
Hannibal meets his
80,000 soldier army at
a place called Cannae.
And they fight something called
the Battle of Cannae, in 216 BCE.
And this is the most famous
battle in human history,
okay?
Remember, the Romans outnumbered
Hannibal two to one. And
what Hannibal does is he decides on
a place to face the Romans, okay?
And in this place, it's a small valley,
and so even though the Romans
are numerically superior
because the valley is small,
they're forced to march in a straight
line, as opposed to in a wide line, okay?
If you have more numbers, you
want to march in a wide line,
but because of the geography,
they're forced to march in
a straight, long line, okay?
So they're marching this way.
Hannibal is uphill with his army,
and he does something strange.
He organizes his army not in a
straight line, but in a concave line.
Okay, like this, concave.
And the Romans look at this, and they laugh because
they've never seen anything like this before.
And they think it's a sign of weakness.
It means the military under Hannibal,
it's undisciplined.
They're just amateurs. This
will be over in an hour, okay?
So the Romans are marching
confidently against Hannibal.
They're attacking. On the
wings of both the Romans,
both armies are the
horsemen, the cavalry, okay?
So what happens as the Romans
march against Hannibal is,
Hannibal sends his cavalry
against the Roman cavalry,
and they overwhelm the
Roman cavalry, okay?
And now they're turning back in
to attack the flank or the back.
Meanwhile, the Roman attack, it's
so powerful, the surge is so
strong, that the Roman army,
the concave of Hannibal's army,
turns upside down, okay?
It turns upside down.
When it does so,
it traps the Roman army in a circle, okay?
Do you see this, okay?
Now they are inside a circle, and
the army is coming around and
attacking from the back, okay?
Militarily, we call this the
double envelopment strategy,
okay, double envelopment strategy.
And so the Romans are circled completely,
and what follows is the
greatest massacre in history,
militarily, until World War I.
The army of 80,000 that
the Romans sent lost almost 70,000 men.
70,000 men died that day.
And again, no military
would lose so much men
until World War I, when
they had much larger armies,
like millions of people, and when
they had machine guns, all right?
So this is like the
greatest military disaster
in human history up to this point.
The disaster is so great
that right now, Rome has lost 20%, okay?
20% of its adult male population.
To put that in context, in World War I,
the Germans lost anywhere between 10 to 15
% of their adult male population before
they were forced to surrender to the Allies,
okay? So Rome has lost 20%.
It's lost a third of the Senate.
The Senate is the highest
governing body of Rome.
So a third of their leadership is dead.
At the same time,
Hannibal is able to convince the Greeks to
start a second front against the Romans,
okay? So
at this point, the war is basically over.
And Hannibal sends
envoys to Rome and says,
listen, the war is over.
I'm willing to negotiate a peace treaty.
I'm willing to negotiate a peace settlement.
I am willing to negotiate peace terms.
And then something strange happens.
And this is unique in human history, okay?
The Roman Senate, they come together
and they discuss a situation.
It's bleak.
It's hopeless. But
there are Romans. Romans do not surrender.
So the Senate told Hannibal,
we will continue the war.
We will raise another army.
If you want to come attack us, come.
We will be ready for you.
And this is completely unexpected, okay?
Hannibal does not know what
to do. And this war continues.
And this, again, is 216.
This war continues for
another, another 15 years.
And then 15 years later,
the Romans have won. They destroyed
the Carpathianian presence in Spain.
And they've conquered, and they've,
Lenin and Africa
enforced Carpathians to surrender.
All right? Okay, so this is the mystery.
Why did the Romans not surrender?
And how were the Romans able
to defeat not just the
Carthaginians, but also the Greeks?
And also, like, everyone else?
Okay? Because at that time,
Hannibal basically united the entire
world against Rome, against Rome and Rome.
In the end, even though
it was very costly, right?
They did win. So that's a mystery.
Okay? So, um,
first thing we need to understand is,
traditional military doctrine about
who wins wars, it's basically wrong.
Traditionally, we understand
the military about three things.
Okay? Manpower.
How many soldiers do you have?
Technology. How good are your weapons?
And resources. How wealthy are you?
Okay? Traditionally, we've
understood war making,
um, like,
if you're good at war, you
will have these three things.
Okay? Lots of soldiers,
lots of technology,
and lots of money.
And if you analyze it this way,
then Rome should be no
match against Carthage.
Right? Carthage is a lot wealthier.
Uh, it has more technology.
It has the greatest general in Hannibal.
But then at the same time,
the Athenians should not have
been able to defeat the Persians.
At the same time, Alexander the Master of Persia
should not have been able to defeat the Persians.
In fact, throughout human history,
we have a lot of instances,
cases where smaller armies have been
able to defeat much larger armies.
So think of Genghis
Khan. Think of Muhammad.
Okay? So clearly this is wrong.
But if this is wrong, what is a better
way to understand military strength?
Well, I would argue how
strong a military, uh,
is, is based on three criteria.
The first is cohesion.
Do the soldiers like
and identify with each other?
Are they united? Okay?
Cohesion. Second is
the idea of discipline.
How well trained and experienced are they?
And the third is devotion.
How committed are they to winning?
Okay? So
if you want to see how powerful
a nation is militarily,
you have to ask yourself
these three questions.
Are they cohesive? Are they disciplined?
Are they devoted? Okay?
And I would also argue that
each nation has a certain
culture, a certain value system,
which makes, which gives
it a certain character.
And this character will tell you
if they are likely to win a war, or not.
Okay? All right.
So let's examine briefly
the characteristics
of Rome as opposed to the
Greeks and the Carthaginians.
Okay? So let's, let's do a table.
Let's just say, okay, you
have, you have Greeks,
you have Carthage, you have Rome.
All right. We know a lot about the Greeks.
And there are three major concepts
that define Greek culture.
Okay? All right.
So the first question is,
what makes you a good person?
For the Greeks, it was the idea of erite.
Okay? Erite just means excellence.
You could be an asshole.
You could be a jerk.
But if you're erite, like you have
talent, then you're a good person.
Okay? And the erite that
the Greeks are most concerned about
is the ability to speak well
and the ability to fight well.
Okay? That's erite.
So I'm going to give you a question.
The question is, what is the thing
that matters to you? Okay? The
most valuable thing in your life.
Well, why do you fight?
Well, for the Greeks, it
was the idea of freedom.
Okay? And for them,
the idea of freedom means the ability to
speak your mind in front of your peers.
Okay? The freedom of speech, basically.
And the last question for the Greeks is,
what is the purpose of life?
Okay? And here the Greeks
have an easy answer.
It's eudaimonia. Remember,
eudaimonia is Greek for flourishing.
You can only be happy as a person if
you are achieving your true potential,
if you are flourishing as a person.
Okay? So,
that's Greek culture. And
if you think about it,
this explains why the Greeks were the most
creative civilization in human history.
Right? So, they're very creative.
At the same time, they're
also very selfish.
And that's why they were
never able to come together
except in times of national emergency,
like when the Persians invaded.
And only then, but even then,
only a few of the Greeks in these states came
together and some even joined the Persians.
Okay? So, the Greeks are
notorious for being creative
but also for being selfish.
So, that's Greek culture. Now,
let's look at the Carthaginians.
Okay? Now, unfortunately,
we don't know anything
about the Carthaginians.
The reason why is Rome wiped
Carthage out of history.
Okay? Rome destroyed Carthage,
killed everyone, and erased Carthage
from the history books. But, we do know
they are a
mercantile empire, meaning
they are focused on trade.
We also know that in
their political system,
it's the wealthiest citizens who have the
most money and the most political power.
Okay? And so, they are basically
a merchant culture, a merchant,
mercantile culture. And from that,
we can make certain guesses
about their value system.
Okay? So, what is good
for the Carthaginians?
It's the idea of being lucky.
Right? You succeed in
life if you're lucky.
That's how business people are, right?
And that's why they're very superstitious.
The Carthaginians are notorious
for being extremely
religious and superstitious.
And one example of this is,
of all these major civilizations,
the Carthaginians are known
for practicing human sacrifice.
In fact, in times of war,
they will even go as far as
practicing child sacrifice,
killing children, killing children
and sacrificing them to the gods in
return for divine favor in times of war.
Okay? So, they are known for
focusing on fortune and luck.
Okay? What do they care about?
They care about their
own interests, right?
What's profitable? What's
their purpose in life?
Accumulating wealth. Right?
Does that make sense? Because
these are business people.
They're merchants. So,
that's how they structure
their society and their culture.
And that's why, for most of their
history, they were extremely wealthy.
Okay? They were notorious
for being extremely clever
business people who made a
lot of money for themselves.
Rome, let's look at Rome.
Okay? What is good for them?
What's a good person? The answer is piety.
Piety just means duty to the gods,
to the city, Rome, and to your father.
Okay? They believe
heavily in filial piety.
The best person was someone
who practiced piety. Okay?
What did they think was most
valuable in their lives?
It's the idea of liberty. Okay?
But liberty is a different conception
for the Romans than for the Greeks.
Remember, for the Greeks, what
mattered was the opportunity
and the ability to speak your
mind in front of your peers.
Okay? That's what freedom was.
The Romans believed liberty
was about receiving the law,
the institutions, and the history of Rome.
But it is only by respecting
the law could you be free.
Otherwise, we'd all just be savages.
Okay? That's the conception of liberty.
Now, the last question then
is what's the purpose of life?
And for the Romans, what really mattered
to them is the idea of re publica.
So, re publica.
This is Latin. And
it's translated as usually public
virtue for the public good.
Okay? And this is where we
get the term republic from.
And so, for Romans, the highest honor,
the highest privilege, the
purpose of life was to serve Rome
and make it stronger and better.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Setting for political office
and being head of the military was the
highest honor Rome could bestow on you.
That was the entire point of life, point
of your life.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
So, if you, if we just do
a compare and contrast,
we could easily figure out, oh,
it's the Roman ethical system that
will allow them the most cohesion,
discipline, and devotion
in their military.
And therefore, over time,
we can see that over time,
in a war, the Romans should be able
to defeat both the Carthaginians
and the Greeks. Okay?
Does that matter? Sorry,
does that make sense to you?
Okay. Any questions so far?
Is this clear? My argument?
Carthaginians. Yeah.
Okay. All right.
So, Rome,
in the Third Pentecost
War, from 149 to 146,
they would go and destroy Carthage.
They would burn it to the
ground. And then they would just,
they would burn all the books
that Carthage ever produced.
So, we don't have
anything written by them.
But, we have a lot
written by Greeks and Romans.
Right? Because the Greeks and
Romans were always in conflict
with the Carthaginians.
And, what's interesting for us is, that the Romans
before all the conflict started in about 300 BCE,
the Romans and the Greeks had nice
things to say about the Carthaginians.
Okay? They were good fighters.
They were brave. They
were very prosperous.
Carthage was like
the wealthiest city in the world.
Okay? They were, they had all
these praises for Carthage.
And after, when war started between
the Carthaginians and the Romans,
then they focused on,
like, child sacrifice.
The Carthaginians were
offended by the gods because
they practiced child sacrifice,
which was barbaric, and that's
why the gods smited Carthage.
Okay? Remember, back at
this time in human history,
we didn't believe in human agency.
Everything was, was ordained by the gods.
Okay? So, if Carthage was destroyed,
it's because the gods will it.
Why did the gods will it? Because the
Carthaginians practiced child sacrifice.
Okay? And that's what the
Romans and the Greeks insisted.
Of course, that means we have to be
skeptical of what they say, right?
But at the same time, we've done a lot of
archaeological excavations around Carthage,
and we have found human remains
that show signs of human sacrifice.
Okay? So,
we have the, we have,
we also, Carthage comes
from Phoenicia, right?
We know a lot about
Phoenician culture. Okay, so,
we've lost a lot of information about Carthage,
but we're able to piece them back together
slowly. Does that make sense?
Yeah. All right. Okay, but again,
unfortunately, we know nothing
about their culture, right?
We don't know nothing
about their literature,
about their mythology, about their
religion, because it's all been destroyed.
The writing has all been
destroyed by the Romans.
Okay. So,
these three characteristics that
define the Roman identity, right?
Piety, liberty, and Okay,
and repubblica,
I want to explain them slowly, okay?
So, what the Romans really did well
is they,
they basically created
history as mythology,
okay? So, the Greeks separated
mythology from history.
Mythology is what the Greeks did,
history is what humans did, okay?
So basically the Greeks invented history.
The Romans, they basically elevate
their history into mythology.
Their history became their religion.
So let me explain what I mean by that.
So there are legends
that surround the founding of Rome.
So Rome was supposed to be
founded in 753 BCE by Romulus.
And there are legends surrounding Romulus.
There are lots of legends
surrounding Romulus.
But the idea is this. There was a king
and he was overthrown by his brother. And
the brother banished the
king's daughter to a temple
to be a virgin for the rest of her life.
But then she got pregnant.
And so the brother says to the king's
daughter, why are you pregnant?
And the daughter says, I was
visited by a woman who was a virgin.
I was visited by Mars, the god of war.
And he impregnated me.
The king's brother obviously
does not believe her.
So he banishes her.
And he orders for the twins who
are born to be killed.
But as a case with these legends,
the person charged with killing
the twins takes pity on them.
And somehow they... They are
left to die in the woods.
A she -wolf, a wolf, comes and
nurses them before another
shepherd comes and adopts them.
Okay. Eventually they realize who they are
and they help the king
overthrow the brother
and take back the throne.
Now the brothers are asked to go and
basically found their own city.
So they go to Rome. And
it's all just healing.
They go to Rome.
And they decide this is the
place to build their kingdom.
Because there's a river, the Tiber.
And there are all these hills
that provide good defense.
Okay. The problem is this.
They're twins. There's two
of them. Romulus and Remus.
So and only one can be king.
So they're... So they get into a battle.
And Romulus kills Remus.
Okay. And that's the founding legend of...
of... Rome. And from this legend
we can sort of understand or...
make some extrapolations
about the Roman psychology.
They believe that violence is
at the core of human existence.
Right? I mean, like...
Sometimes you have to
kill your own brother.
And that's the right thing to do
because that is ordained by the gods.
Okay. So that's the first legend.
Second legend is this.
Romulus has to build Rome
and he becomes a very open person.
He welcomes immigrants into Rome.
And he grants them citizenship
and status right away.
Okay. Rome becomes a nation of immigrants.
Eventually, their rise
startles their neighbors.
And their neighbors go
to war with them at once.
The Romans are so good at war that
they fight back their neighbors.
Their neighbors are called the Sabines.
The Sabines decide, listen.
We can't put them in war.
But at the same time,
Rome only has males.
Right? Rome only has males.
So, we will just isolate Rome.
Our daughters will not marry into Rome.
And in 20 years time, Rome
will have no population.
Okay? Romulus hears of this
plan and he devises a strategy.
What he does is he
organizes a huge festival.
Invites all his neighbors. So
fathers bring their daughters.
To attend this festival.
At this festival, the women are kidnapped.
And they basically raped. That night,
Romulus visits every one of these women.
And apologizes for what has happened.
And promised that they
will be safe in Rome.
That they are now citizens of Rome.
And therefore, they will be protected
by him personally, the king.
The fathers and the brothers are
obviously very upset about this.
So they organize this huge army.
And they march against Rome.
The Roman citizens come
out to face them in battle.
Okay? And just as they are
about to clash in battle,
the women come and run between them.
And beg the new husbands and their
fathers and brothers not to fight.
At this point, Romulus appears and
says he will make everyone
a citizen of Rome.
Okay? And by doing that,
he basically does that.
He will double the population of Rome.
Alright? Again, from this legend, we
can understand the Roman psychology.
Which is, everything can be sacrificed
in the pursuit of Roman glory.
And basically, to ensure
that Rome survives.
Okay? Because what matters is Rome.
Okay? It's the cult of Rome.
All that matters is the survival of Rome.
Morals don't matter. Nothing matters.
So, after this, Rome
starts to grow slowly.
And this is a period
known as the Seven Kings.
So, there are seven kings who rule Rome.
And they do so for a very long time.
About 200 plus years.
And most of them are
very, very good kings.
Except the last king.
His name is Tarchanus.
Tarchanus Superbus.
Okay? Superbus is Latin for arrogant.
So, he's often referred
to as Tarchan the Proud.
Okay? So, Tarchan the Proud, he is,
as his name suggests,
a very arrogant king.
What makes him arrogant is his hubris.
He refuses to listen to the nobility.
In fact, those in the nobility who
challenge his authority often get killed.
Okay? All right?
He has a second son.
And this second son, he's a jerk.
He likes to abuse his power.
And one thing that he enjoys
doing is raping the woman of Rome.
There's one woman who's
notorious, or who's famous,
for her virtue.
His name is Lucretia. And
the prince thinks raping her will be...
the most fun. Okay?
Because she will be the
most insulted by this.
So, he rapes her. And then
she goes and confronts her husband.
Okay? Her husband. And
her husband has a friend.
His name is Lucius Brutus.
Lucius Brutus happens to
be the nephew of the king.
And he is very much opposed
to the tyranny of the king.
And Lucretia says to her husband
and to his friend, Lucius Brutus,
I've been raped. Will you
promise me to avenge my honor?
And the husband and Lucius
Brutus see she's distraught.
Okay? And so they sue her and
promise her they will do
everything they can in the morning.
And Lucretia, she doesn't
really believe them.
So what she does is she takes
a knife out from her dress.
And she stabs herself in the heart.
And she dies before them. Now,
they are honor bound to avenge her death.
And so what Lucius Brutus does is
he calls a meeting of the nobility.
And they decide together
to overthrow the king.
The king is out campaigning for war.
He's basically at war. And what they
do is they lock the gates of Rome.
Now, the king is furious.
Okay? And so
what the king does is he decides,
he's going to go back to
Etrusca, where he's from.
And he's going to rally
his friends, the kings.
Okay? Because if the Romans can overthrow him,
well, other people can overthrow their kings.
Right? So this is a bad president.
So he's going to organize a huge
army to march against Rome.
Meanwhile, Lucius Brutus,
he's instituting the republic.
Okay? Now, the king, the
thing about the king is
that all powers are invested in the king.
These powers include military, judicial,
deciding cases, legislative, making laws,
administrative,
bureaucratic, right?
And religious. Okay?
So these are the five
major duties of the king.
And this is where his power comes from.
So what Lucius Brutus and
the Romans do is they separate
his powers not into individuals,
but into institutions. And these institutions
that are now elected by the people.
Okay? This is the heart of republicanism.
So, the military will
now run by the council.
The council is basically
the head of the state.
Okay? And again, he's elected. The
judicial is run by the praetor.
Legislator is the senate.
Administrative is the adile.
And the religious is the pontifex maximus.
And again, he's elected. And again,
they're all elected by the people.
Now, what's important to understand
is it's usually nobility
who are in these offices.
But back then, there wasn't much separation
between nobility and ordinary people.
So nobility are what we call patricians.
The patricians. And the ordinary
people are what we call the plebeians.
And honestly, there was
not much difference.
The patricians are... This comes from
the long history of the nobility.
They're the oldest families... Like, the
families who have been in Rome the longest.
Okay? The oldest families. And
they were wealthy, but not that
much wealthier from ordinary Romans.
So, maybe you have one cow, right?
Well, I have three cows. Also,
the people could go visit each
other's homes without any ceremony.
Okay? So, you could be the head of state.
You could be the council. But if I'm an
ordinary person, I can just come to your house and have dinner with you.
Okay? There were no doors.
There were no guards.
There was no separation.
Okay? So,
Lucius Brutus instituted a new system
where the king's powers were divided
among different institutions.
And now,
people didn't have to obey the king.
They had to obey the republic.
And the republic was three things.
The laws. The history.
The traditions. And institutions.
Okay? That's the republic.
And this system, unbelievably,
incredibly, will not
change for about 500 years.
So it's pretty stable. Now what's important
to remember is, these are not innovations.
The Romans just basically copied this
from the neighbors, the Etruscans.
So the Romans have a republic.
The problem with a republic
is everyone's equal.
And so you come from a privileged
background, you find this very annoying.
So now there's a conspiracy
to bring back the king.
And this conspiracy was discovered and
everyone was caught and imprisoned.
It turns out, Lucius
Brutus has two sons, okay?
He has two sons, and they were
both part of this conspiracy.
They were tried by the Senate,
and they were all sentenced to death,
including the two sons of Lucius Brutus,
okay? The problem is this.
The problem is,
The council has to
oversee the execution of the prisoners.
Whose council? Lucius
Brutus' council, okay?
So, Lucius Brutus has to oversee
the execution of his two sons.
Now, if Lucius Brutus
is like, you know what,
I'm gonna resign my office, or,
hey, you know what, I'm sick,
everyone would be like, we understand,
take the day off, don't
worry about it, okay?
Instead, Lucius Brutus showed up for work,
and he oversaw the execution
of the two sons, okay?
of his two sons. All of
Rome came to the execution.
Okay, it was a public event.
Everyone was watching the
face of Lucius Brutus.
Okay, we know the two sons are gonna
die, they're gonna be beheaded.
But everyone wanted to see
Lucius Brutus' reactions.
He was crying for our execution.
These are his two sons, right?
He has no more sons.
This is his legacy now.
And his two sons are about to be killed.
In fact, he's the one charged
with killing his own sons.
He has to do it, he has no choice.
So everyone's watching him.
And throughout this process, he's crying.
His tears are flowing down his face.
He can't help himself. But
he's still standing still, and
he's still slowly ordering
the execution of his two sons.
And the Romans are just shocked.
They're just shocked
by this public display.
Okay, this is the idea of devotion, right?
You are so devoted to Rome
that you're willing to
sacrifice your own children
to ensure its survival and its glory.
Tarchinus, Tarchin the Proud, hears
about this, and he gets really angry.
So he allies himself with kings,
and they march against Rome.
Lucius Brutus is counsel, he's
in charge of the military, so
he marches his army
against Tarchin the Proud.
One of the sons of Tarchin the
Proud sees Lucius Brutus, and
he charges ahead, because
he wants to kill the man
who insulted his family.
Lucius Brutus sees the
king's sons running,
they're both on horses, right?
Running, galloping towards him,
and Lucius Brutus gets angry,
and he says, so he charged ahead as well.
Lucius Brutus froze his spear, Javelin,
the king's son, the prince
froze his spear as well,
and they spear each other
to death and they both died.
Okay? And
so Lucius Brutus is at
this point considered the greatest Roman
who ever lived. And for most of Roman history
he'll be considered the greatest Roman
who ever lived until Julius Caesar.
Okay? And
it was in the memory and
honor of Lucius Brutus
that they would assassinate Julius Caesar.
But we'll discuss this next class.
Okay. So
the king's army is overwhelming the Romans
and the Romans have to
flee back into the city.
There's a drawbridge that
connects Rome to the mainland.
Okay? So there's the river Tiber crosses
it and the river flows through the city.
And the Romans have to flee back into the city.
So they get scared and they run all into Rome.
So they get scared and they run all into
Rome. There's a garrison that's supposed to be protecting the bridge,
but they see the army coming,
the army marching towards them,
they get scared and
they run all into Rome.
One guy, his name is Caucasus,
he decides, I can't run away, because
I run away, the army just marches
into Rome and kills everyone.
So he descends, he decides
to make a last stand, and
it's it's just one guy
there's one random guy okay
and
what he does is he starts
shunning insults at
the enemy army he's like you guys are
slaves we're Romans we will always be free
and the enemy army and
like their spouses of them okay
they have absolutely no idea what's
going on this is one guy on a bridge
shining insulting insulting them okay
so they they freeze eventually they
realize oh this guy is just distracting us
because his friends the other soldiers
are trying to cut down the bridge
so
they run to him at this point to
up to other Romans okay two
officers run besides cockles
and together the three of them
hold off the invading army together
okay with their shields they fight
for their lives eventually the bridge
is about to be cut down okay the two
officers are going to be shot down
and they're going to be shot down and they're going
to run away and cockles makes the last stand and
the bridge falls and
what cockles does is before it falls
completely he jumps into the Tiber
and he survives he doesn't drown
so
this tells us hey anyone can be
a hero of Rome right it loses Brutus
he's the king's nephew he's nobility
but cockles he's just an ordinary Roman
who had the courage he had the
devotion to fight for Rome okay
and by doing so with his devotion
he's able to save Rome by himself
so
Rome right now is surrounded
by this huge army
and one young man his name is Musius
and
he's a Roman nobleman
okay he goes to the Senate
and he says to the Senate, listen,
we're being surrounded by an enemy army,
they're huge, we're starving to death.
I have a plan to win this war.
I'm going to swim across the Tiber,
sneak into the enemy camp and kill
the enemy king and this war will end.
The Senate gives Musias his approval and
Musias sneaks into the enemy camp.
It's payday, which means the soldiers
are getting their wages, right?
Musias sneaks into the front and
he sees on the podium
there are two individuals
who are giving out wages to the soldiers.
They both look like the king.
One's a king and one's a secretary.
They look the same. Musias doesn't know
who's the king and who's the secretary.
You know, at this point, an
ordinary person would be like,
I'll come back later, okay?
Like, let me
figure it out, let me spy first and
figure out who the king is and then
when a better opportunity
arises, I'll kill the king.
Musias is like, it's 50 -50,
man, so he takes his knife,
rushes to the podium
and stabs one other man
who happens to be the secretary, okay?
So, he's arrested and the king
is now interrogating him.
He wants to know if there
are other spies in the camp.
s s King says to Musias,
tell me the truth or I
will burn you alive,
okay? And he shows Musias the
pyre, okay, with this huge pyre.
Musias says, I am one of
a hundred young Romans who
have pledged their lives
to kill you to free Rome.
He's lying. This is not true.
You kill me, there'll be 99 more, okay?
We are not afraid of you. You say you will
burn me if I do not tell you the truth?
Now what he does is he puts
his hand into the fire.
His hand is burning,
okay? And he holds it together.
And what makes him hold
it together is what he
sees is the face of Lucius Budus as he
orders the execution of his two sons,
right? Because
ordering the execution of your two
sons is a lot harder than burning.
Than burning your hand alive, okay?
Than burning your hand. And
the king, he looks at this and he thinks,
the Romans are the craziest
bastards I have ever met.
Screw this, I'm going home.
And he lets Musias go.
And the war is over.
Okay? And
that's how the Roman Republic
survived the invasion
and became the Republic.
Okay? So this is the history of Rome.
And this history is something that
can be taught to anyone
who becomes a citizen.
If you are a Roman, it's because
you believe in this history.
Believing in this history, knowing
this history is what makes you a Roman.
Okay? So that's the first concept.
Piety. Loyalty to Rome.
Second concept that
makes Rome unique or powerful
is the idea of liberty.
Okay? What Cogles did, what Musias did,
what Lucius Budus did was
preserve the liberty of Rome.
Remember, what liberty means is respecting
and following the laws, institutions,
and history of Rome.
Because that's what makes Rome.
That's what allows you to have freedom.
Okay? And that's why, in 216,
even though Hannibal had defeated the
Romans, the Romans refused to surrender,
because surrendering would mean
surrendering their liberty, right?
Because Hannibal would
impose peace terms, that
would, that would make, basically,
Rome into a clan state of Carthage.
It would lose their liberty, right?
If you don't have liberty,
your life isn't worth living.
Give me life or give me
liberty, okay? liberty.
The third element of Roman greatness
is the idea of rep this right Republica.
So what this means is every nobleman
if you have the ability
you want to serve Rome.
So what they did was this they turn
Roman politics into a
competition to produce the best man.
It was basically a meritocracy. So
once you have the financial
means, you stood for election
and this system was
basically a meritocracy.
You first stood for
election to become an adile
and then you become a praetor
and then you became a council.
Once you were council, you had the
opportunity to win the highest glory.
What you could do is become a
governor of a faraway province
and if you are governor
of this faraway province
and you can win more territory for Rome
then you'll be given
something called a triumph.
Triumph is a big parade
where you're celebrated
by all the Roman people.
That's what every Roman
soldier aspired to,
to become a great general who
would receive his own triumph
because he's won new territory for Rome.
Okay and that's why even
though a third of the Roman
Senate was wiped out by Hannibal,
they didn't give up because
the other people were like okay now
here's my opportunity to prove myself.
Right and one of these young
people his name is Scipio,
he would go on and
lead an army into Spain, conquer Spain and
then lead an army against
Hannibal in North Africa.
In Carthage and destroy Hannibal.
Okay, because
the point of life is
to receive the triumph
and if you receive the triumph then
you will be remembered by
Romans in their history, which
is what gives your life meaning.
Okay, alright so do we understand this?
Okay, so do we understand this? Go on,
move on,
move on, move on, move on, move on, move
on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on, move on,
move on, move on, move on, move
on, move on, move on, move on,
move on, move on, move on, move on,
move on Judas's Buddhist
over for the king,
and he established the Roman Republic.
The Roman Republic is
now a nation of laws.
His two sons are princes, and
they lost their privileges, so
they partake in this conspiracy
to bring back the king, right?
This conspiracy was discovered, and
as punishment, they were
all sentenced to death,
because they wanted to destroy the
republic and bring back the king.
Does that make sense? So,
what the story, and again, we don't
know if these stories are true.
They're probably not true, okay?
What this story is telling us is,
if the founder of the Roman
Republic can sacrifice
his family in order to make
sure the republic survives,
well, you can as well, okay? No sacrifice,
every sacrifice must be made
to ensure Roman greatness.
That's basically the message, right?
Any more questions?
That's a great question,
okay? So, how do we know
this? The answer is this,
for most of this time, this
is what we call oral history,
okay, so this is, you know, mythology,
and it was basically passed
from generation to generation.
This oral history was
written down in books,
okay, on the, But because
Rome was at war so much,
Rome was conquered once
and Rome was burned down, and so we
lost a lot of the written history.
Now the problem with oral history is there
are different versions of oral history.
So there are different
versions of these stories.
And then a man named Livy,
during the time of the Roman Empire,
when it was first founded, he sat down
to write the official history of Rome.
And this is where we get
all these stories from.
And again, we don't believe
these stories to be that true.
Lucius Brutus was probably
a real person, but
whether or not he did these
things, we don't know.
It's debatable. But
what matters is, this
is what Romans believed.
Do you understand? What matters is what they
believed as opposed to what really happened.
And this is what creates
the Roman identity.
Great. Any more questions?
Okay. So, yeah, I mean,
that's basically it, okay?
This is what made Rome great, and
that's what allowed them to
come back from the defeats
that Hannibal inflicted on them
to eventually win the war.
Okay? Any more questions?
Okay. I have a question about...
I'm talking about how Rome
built an 80,000 -year army.
80,000 army against Hannibal, yes.
Yes. So, the Roman army...
Okay. That's a great question, okay?
So, like, you want to know more about
Hannibal's invasion of Italy, right?
Okay. All right.
So, Rome... What Rome is able to
do is offer citizenship to anyone.
Anyone who fights for Rome. And Rome has,
for the longest time, been
fighting its neighbors, right?
Once it conquered its neighbors,
its neighbors promised to send
soldiers to Rome in times of war.
So, Rome is able to draw on soldiers
from all around the Italian peninsula.
Okay? That's the first
thing. Second thing is
that when
Hannibal invaded Italy,
he was doing so with many Gauls, okay?
Who are the invaders of Italy.
And these Gauls have traditionally
been the enemy of the Italians.
So, when Hannibal did so,
Rome's neighbors rallied
to Rome's support,
to support Rome. Okay?
Because they saw the Gauls and
Hannibal as invaders who
threatened their culture.
Okay? That's the second
thing. The third thing is...
Okay. Hannibal had an
invading army, right?
But he had no organizational
and logistic support.
He had no food supply.
Because he was basically doing
this on his own initiative.
Carthage is too far away. Okay?
And Rome had the best, like,
navy in the Mediterranean.
So, there was no way that
Carthage could resupply Hannibal.
Sorry. There's no way Carthage
could resupply Hannibal, right?
So, Hannibal was forced to spend a
lot of his time foraging for food.
Do you understand? And that's
ultimately why he lost the war.
Because it's possible for
you to win all these battles
because you're a military genius. But
you still have to feed your soldiers.
And what Rome did after the Battle of
Canaan was they recognized this fact.
They recognized that Hannibal's
main problem was logistics.
And they started to not...
They decided we will never fight
Hannibal in a battle again.
We will cut off his food supply.
Okay? And so, Hannibal had to spend
most of his time foraging for food.
Meanwhile, Rome could rebuild
itself by freeing its slaves. Okay?
And by recruiting more
neighbors to join their cause.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay. That's why...
That's why armies don't win wars.
Nations win wars. Does that make sense?
So, another thing that
you need to understand is
while
Hannibal was winning glory in Italy,
the kinds of elders in Carthage, were
they happy about this, do you think?
These are business people,
right? Are they happy about this?
They're not happy about this.
Because one, they're not happy about this.
And the other thing is, one, it's going to cost them a lot of money to continue the war.
And listen, Italy is poor.
So, there's no profit to be
made from conquering Rome.
Okay? That's the first
problem. Second problem is,
if Hannibal were to win glory in Italy,
he would come back and become
the king of Carthage, right?
Does that make sense? So,
Hannibal was being undermined
by Carthage itself,
even though Hannibal was
trying to save Carthage.
Does that make sense? And
that's what makes Rome unique.
Rome has been united
for most of its history,
whereas most places like Greece and Carthage
were divided into different political factions.
And that's what caused Carthage
to ultimately be undermined.
So, ultimately, Rome was able
to come back from the defeat
and defeat Carthage, because
Carthage, again, saw Hannibal
as big a threat as Rome.
Okay? This would be costly for Carthage,
because after the war is over,
50 years later, Rome,
a Roman senator named Cato
the Elder, he visits Carthage
because he's curious what's happened
to Carthage after the end of the war.
And to his dismay, and
to his shock, Carthage
has become a great power.
It has become wealthier than ever before.
Okay? 50 years of peace means that
Carthage is able to accumulate
more wealth than ever before.
It has so much wealth that
it is able to pay off the indemnity
that Rome imposed on it.
Okay? It's basically able to pay Rome off.
And Cato the Elder,
he is traumatized by this.
He goes back to Rome and says,
we have to destroy Carthage.
Okay? There's a huge debate in the Senate.
He says, listen, if we
let Carthage survive,
Carthage will always be a threat to us.
And the other senators were like, listen,
Cato, I know you want to destroy Carthage,
but remember, Carthage threatens us.
If we destroy Carthage, we, Rome,
will no longer have an enemy.
We will no longer have a threat.
We will change as a people
if we destroy Carthage.
But Cato the Elder insisted. Eventually,
an army was dispatched
to destroy Carthage.
The Romans have a habit of always
blaming the enemies for starting a war.
Okay? So they didn't want
to instigate the war.
So they made up these dumb excuses and said
that Carthage was violating the peace treaty.
And the Romans said to Carthage, listen,
if you surrender all your weapons, you will not be able to destroy Carthage.
We will go away. The
Carthaginians believed the Romans
and thought if they surrender
all their weapons, they go away.
The Romans got all these weapons.
They were like, we
didn't expect this, man.
So the Romans said to the
Carthaginians, you know what?
We also need you to move your city
from the coast 10 kilometers inland.
Okay? And at this point,
the Carthaginians knew.
Rome was going to destroy Carthage.
So there's a three -year siege.
And then at the end of it, Rome conquered
Carthage, killed everyone inside,
enslaved others, burned all the books,
and wiped out Carthage from history
as well as the history books.
Okay? So that's a Roman mentality.
Devotion means all or nothing.
Okay? You don't surrender, but you
also don't show mercy to your enemies.
Okay? So Hannibal was right.
Rome was a threat to Carthage.
But because Carthage has a merchant
culture run by business people,
they could never recognize the threat.
Does that make sense? All right.
Any more questions?
Good..
Public virtue. Yeah. .
...
Okay. So why do people
want to come to Rome?
Well, the fact of the matter
is that for most of history,
people didn't want to go to Rome.
Because Rome was considered a,
like for example, the Greeks
didn't want to go to Rome
because they thought Rome was uncivilized.
But Romans wanted to go to Athens because they
thought Athens was the height of civilization.
The Carthaginians certainly
didn't want to go to Rome.
Okay? Rome was like Macedonia.
So basically like North Korea even.
You can even say it's like North Korea.
Okay? It's a militaristic
society that's barbaric.
Right? The Greeks like to watch theater.
The Romans like to watch gladiator
shows or lions eat people.
Okay? So for most of its history,
people avoided Rome.
When becoming a republic,
you had no choice but
to go to Rome because that's
how you could build your career.
It was the capital of the world.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So another way of saying this
is there were many people
who wanted to be Greek because
they were attracted by the culture.
Nobody wanted to be Roman.
The Romans made everyone into
a Roman through the conquest.
Okay? So
the Romans were repugnant in many ways.
Okay? They just were a repugnant people.
Okay. Any more questions?
Okay, great. So next class, it's a
fun class, we do Julius Caesar. Okay?