Okay, so today we will finish the
Greeks by discussing Aristotle.
And a lot of what I will say
today will be controversial.
So feel free to challenge me.
Feel free to ask for clarification.
Feel free to ask any questions.
So here's my argument.
Aristotle is a paradox.
He is one of the mysterious
figures in world history.
He's one of the most famous, but
he's one of the most mysterious.
He's a paradox for three reasons, okay?
The first reason is he is considered
to be one of the greatest
philosophers in human history.
He's next to Plato. He's
certainly as influential as Plato.
But what is unique about him
is we do not have anything,
originally written by him, okay?
We have no text that
we believe was personally written by him.
And that's unique in human history, okay?
We say Shakespeare was a great writer and
we can prove it or show
it by reading his text.
We believe Aristotle is a great thinker,
a great writer, but we have no evidence,
no text, to show us this is the case.
We believe so, okay?
So this is the first paradox.
The second paradox of Aristotle.
Second paradox of Aristotle is
he was a very prolific writer
and thinker. In fact, we believe he,
there's about 200 works
attributed to Aristotle.
What is unique about his work
is the range of his
thinking and his research.
So he's written a book on politics,
right? What is the best political system?
He's written a book on poetics,
theater, basically. What
makes for a good tragedy?
He's written a book on ethics.
What is a good life?
What makes a good person?
He's written a book on rhetoric.
How do you convince the
audience that you are correct?
He's also written books on physics.
He's written books on metaphysics.
He's written books on physics.
He's written books on biology.
Okay? The range is just incredible.
We have no analog in
human history like him.
He's simply unique in the
range of his curiosity.
Second paradox. The third
paradox is most problematic.
We know that Aristotle studied
under Plato for 20 years.
And so we also believe that Aristotle
studied under Plato for 20 years.
Aristotle was Plato's most famous student.
The paradox is Aristotle's understanding
of the universe is radically
opposed to Plato's
understanding of the universe.
Okay? And that's, again,
is unique in human history.
You would think the best student would carry
on the master's work or at least build on it,
right? But Aristotle,
his understanding of the universe,
is in conflict with Plato's work.
In fact, you could also argue that
Aristotle is negating Plato's worldview.
Okay? So let me explain how.
So we know Plato. We know that for Plato,
there is a god, and it's
called the form of the good.
And the form of the good
is what is the best.
It's eternal, perfect,
and immutable.
Okay? Now,
the form of the good
emanates other perfections.
What he calls the form of the ideal.
Okay? So these are concepts like
justice and beauty and reason.
And then these concepts
manifest themselves
in forms like horse,
right? Or a woman.
Okay? And these are
like the ideal, perfect,
immutable, eternal manifestations.
Okay? So there's only one
horse. It's up in heaven.
Everything else is a copy of this
horse or imitation of this horse.
Okay? So we live in a shadow realm.
Okay? A shadow realm where
everything is imitation.
Okay? This is our reality.
It's a shadow reality.
And that's why art and poetry
and theater are so important.
And that's why music and
theater are so bad. Because
they are really an
imitation of an imitation.
Okay? So this is Plato's hierarchy.
So from this hierarchy and
this world view, we can
make certain extrapolations.
Okay? The first
extrapolation is for Plato,
what is good is if you approach or
return to the form of the good.
What is evil?
What is bad is if you move
away from the form of the good.
Okay? Right?
So poetry is evil. Mathematics is good.
Okay? Now, why is mathematics good?
Because mathematics is what allows
you to approach the
form of the good.
All right? So let me give
you an example of this.
Okay? Let's say there's a circle.
Right? What Plato argues is
no matter how hard you try,
you could never,
ever draw a circle in this world.
Okay? Because a circle has an edge.
So it's like literally impossible for
you to create something without an edge.
Right? You're like, well,
I can draw on the computer.
But if you go at a microscopic
level, you will always find an edge.
Okay? So how do you create a circle?
Well, you create a circle by
imagining it in your head.
Okay? So you draw a circle.
So what you're really doing
is you're imagining the circle
because you're accessing
the realm of the forms.
You're approaching from the good.
Okay? So it's only pure,
it is only through a
process of pure thought,
pure philosophy, pure mathematics that
you can actually start
to understand this world.
All right? That's Plato's
understanding of the world.
Aristotle has a completely
different understanding.
Okay? So Aristotle starts with this.
That God's a prime mover.
Okay? So the prime mover,
just imagine a big bag.
Right? Something explodes.
Boom. It moves.
And it forces other
things to move as well.
So what Aristotle is saying is
everything is really in motion.
Okay? Everything is change.
Because it was all caused
by the prime mover.
And in Plato's, sorry,
in Aristotle's world,
what is good is the good.
But what he's saying is if the thing
that changes moves towards its purpose.
Okay? Or the word he uses is called telos.
Telos. Okay?
If you're moving towards your purpose,
you are doing good in this world.
If you're moving away from your purpose,
you're doing bad in this world.
Okay? So the example is a soldier. The purpose
of a soldier is to fight and win wars.
So if you go fight and you do
your best, you're doing good.
But if you run away from
a war, you're doing bad.
you're doing bad, okay?
So this is Aristotle's worldview
and as you can understand,
as you can see,
these two worldviews cannot harmonize.
They are in conflict with each other.
You have either one or the other, okay?
So let me highlight the three major
differences between these two worldviews,
okay?
And again, I need to emphasize this.
I am not an expert on Aristotle.
I'm not an expert on Plato, okay?
So I am committing oversimplifications.
Scholars who are experts will
hear this and be outraged, okay?
But for the purpose of this class,
I feel these oversimplifications
provide clarity, okay?
Alright, so the first oversimplification
is Plato is what we call a rationalist.
Aristotle is what we call
an empiricist, alright?
So these are two big words, but
the rationalist is just
someone who believes that
you can access the truth
through pure thought, okay?
Mathematics. An empiricist is someone who
believes you can only access
the truth through observation
and what we call induction,
okay? Inductive logic, alright?
So if I see a woman wearing a dress
and I see a woman wearing
a dress, and a third,
I'm like, okay,
well from this I can
logically deduce or induce
that all women wear dresses and that's
what separates women from men, okay?
So for Aristotle to seek the truth,
you have to observe and
you have to induce, okay?
So that's the first major difference.
Second major difference is Plato
is what we call a dualist.
And I'm going to give you a little
bit of a background on that.
Aristotle is what we call a materialist.
A dualist is someone who believes
that there's a body and a soul, okay?
And if you believe
there's a body and a soul,
you also believe the soul
is more important because
the soul is eternal, whereas
the body will decay and die.
Aristotle, he's a materialist, so
for him the focus is on the body
and what happens to the body, okay?
There may be a soul, there may not
be a soul, he doesn't really care.
For him it doesn't really matter. What
matters is what happens to the body, okay?
The third major difference is Plato
believes in the idea of a mutability,
okay, or a call eternity.
For Aristotle, almost
nothing is a mutable.
Most things are a mutable, okay?
The only thing that's a really a mutable is
really God, but everything else is mutable.
It will change over time.
And so, for Aristotle,
the concept is infinity.
Things will always change, things will
always move, there's no stopping movement.
But for Plato, things are eternal,
there's a grand design,
and nothing that changes really matters.
It doesn't really affect the grand design.
So for him, it's eternity.
So these are the three major
differences between Plato and Aristotle.
Now what's really interesting for
us is this conflict between Plato
and Aristotle is what will inform the philosophical
debate for all of Western civilization.
So there are two major
camps in Western philosophy.
There is the rationalist camp,
so people like Descartes, and then there are
the empiricists, so people like David Hume.
And for most of Western history,
philosophers like Descartes will go back and
forth between these two extremes, either the
Platonic ideal or the Aristotle reality.
Does that make sense? Is this clear?
Any questions? Sure,
go ahead. Yeah, so
that's a great question.
And for Plato, okay, what we,
like our lives, the reality
we live in is not real.
It's ephemeral. Whereas the form of
the good, that's what's concrete.
That's what's eternal, okay?
So I mean, like, I understand
that's counterintuitive to us,
but the reason why it's kind of
counterintuitive to us is because we're mainly influenced by Aristotle, right?
We live, we are materialist, right?
Science is materialistic.
But back then, and I would say back
then in Plato's time, and
for most of human history,
it was assumed that
our world was transitory,
or transient, or ephemeral, okay?
And it was a spirit world, okay?
That was real. And that was eternal.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah, I think so.
Okay. Okay. Again, this is
oversimplification, okay?
Like, if you go to a scholar
who understands itself,
I will probably, he'll
probably criticize me, okay?
But I'm saying that for the purpose of this class,
and for our understanding of Western civilization,
this will do, okay? Just understand there's
a major conflict between Plato and Aristotle.
This will go on for thousands of years.
This will inform the debate
in Western civilization, okay?
This is the fundamental
debate in Western philosophy.
All right? So let's go back to,
let's summarize where we are.
Aristotle is a paradox, right?
We have nothing that he wrote originally.
The range of his work is just incredible.
It's unique in human history.
And then lastly, even though
we know Aristotle sat under Plato
for like 20 years, at least,
Aristotle came up with a very different
conceptualization of the universe.
In fact, it is indirect.
It's an indirect conflict with
Plato's understanding, okay?
So how is this possible?
How are these paradox,
how can we resolve these paradoxes?
Okay, so I'm gonna make an argument.
And I will slowly make this argument,
but it is a controversial argument, okay?
My argument is that Aristotle
was not a philosopher.
He was not a thinker.
He was not a writer.
What he was ultimately,
is what I refer to as a censor.
Censor. You can also use
words like synthesizer, okay?
Or editor. Or systemizer, okay?
But basically, nothing that
he thought was original to him, but
he decided what would be political
convenient for the moment,
okay? That's what we mean by censor.
And it's my argument that,
you know, I'm not a thinker.
But let me make my argument that we
understand Aristotle's censor, then
these three paradoxes go away.
We can explain away these paradoxes.
All right, so let me make my argument.
Okay, my first piece of evidence is,
We need to compare and
contrast the life of Phippus Sacc
and the Macedon and Aristotle.
And when you do that, Okay?
And you put their lives side by side
into a! interesting parallels emerge okay
so let's look at their lives very simple
aristotle he was born in year 384.
philip ii was born in year 383.
that's about the same age right
now philip ii he's a prince of
masson his father is the king right
aristotle his father was the court
physician to the king he was
the king's personal doctor
right so from these two pieces of information
what can we guess about philip and aristotle
they grew up together
right does that make sense
aristotle's father was the personal
doctor the king philip was the son
of the king it would make sense they grew
up together it would make sense to be educated together all right
second thing that's interesting
is from 367 to 3 348 okay
aristotle went to athens to study in plato
now around the same time
okay in the year 369 to 365
philip went to thebes to study military innovation
under the best generals in greece all right
and here i would extrapolate and
say the teenagers they're going
to further their education right
and learn the best scientific and
military innovations in order
to bring back the mastodon and
this happens all the time right
in the 1980s china sent its best
and brightest to america
to study science okay
so we can also surmise that
even while they were away
they were still in contact
with each other all
right now in 359
philip became regent or
basically king and from
then on he started this massive military
campaign to conquer all of greece
now one thing that
was interesting about philip's
conquest of greece was
that
the athenians didn't
really oppose him okay
and this is one of the great mysteries
historians struggle with why is it
that philip ii he's going around
he's conquering all these places
that are in conflict with athens and
athens doesn't really resist all right
and athens and athens and athens
and athens and athens and athens and
athens and
athens and athens and athens and athens
and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and
athens and athens and athens and
athens and athens and
athens and athens
and athens and athens and athens and
athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and athens and to democracy,
and that's why we must oppose him.
So we can surmise that
Philip was bribing these Athenians to
support him, and that's why there's
so little Athenian resistance to Philip.
If that's the case, then
who's the middleman?
Who's the person who's in contact
with these Athenian aristocrats?
Aristotle, right? Why, because remember,
Aristotle was at the academy for 20 years.
The academy in Athens at that time
is like Harvard, Oxford today, right?
It's where all the rich
and powerful go to study.
So for 20 years,
Aristotle was in contact and
became friends with the most
powerful individuals in Athens,
and that's why when Philip needed
to negotiate with the Athenians,
it would make the most
sense to send Aristotle.
Okay, does that make sense? And
then we know that Philip
united Greece in 338,
and then 335, three years later,
Aristotle started a new school in Athens,
a competition academy
called the Lyceum, okay?
So what is the purpose of the Lyceum?
So that's what I will discuss
next, but does that make sense?
There are direct parallels between
the lives of Aristotle and Philip.
Okay? And we can guess
or extrapolate or deduce
that Aristotle and Philip were
very close throughout their lives,
and they were helping each other.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay, so now the question then
is, why was Philip going around
conquering all of Greece?
Well, Philip had a vision for the world,
and it's something we call
the Pan -Hellenic Project.
Okay, so a Pan -Hellenic Project.
Alright, so at this time
and throughout most of its history,
Greece was divided into city
states all around the world,
mainly in mainland Greece, but
also across the aegean in
Asia Minor, Anatolia, okay?
Across all these different islands and
into North Africa and
across the Adriatic,
also into Italy as well, okay?
So you have this sprawling Greek world.
And there were many who believed
that this Greek world
should unite together
because there's a common ancestry,
all right?
So it was a dream of
many philosophers that
a great man of history would arise and
unite all of Greece by
basically defeating Persia.
And Philip II said, hey,
that's a great idea,
and it should be me, okay?
But the problem is
the Pan -Atlantic Project
assumes a common Greek identity, and
it didn't really exist at that time.
In fact, Greeks probably had more
power over the Greek people and
more common with their local
cultures than with each other, right?
So if you were a Greek
living in Asia Minor,
you were probably more
Persian than you were Greek,
okay?
So in other words,
Philip needed someone, a censor basically,
to create a Greek identity,
right?
And the way you do that
is by taking all this vast universe
of knowledge that the Greeks created and
you create an encyclopedia
or a series of textbooks
that define what it means to be Greek,
right?
You standardize and you
systemize Greek knowledge.
Does that make sense? And so
that's probably what
Aristotle was doing when
he started the Lyceum.
He had lots of students, okay?
So he was like a chief on the Greek, like
standardizing the Greek and the Hebrew.
Yeah, so throughout history,
all conquerors did this, okay?
Because that was the only, because by
standardizing and systemizing knowledge
was the best way for you
to co -opt the elite
and to showcase your legitimacy, okay?
Otherwise, the intellectual elite would
think of you as a barbarian conqueror,
all right? And the best way that
you co -opt the intellectual elite is by
showcasing a new
systematic knowledge, okay?
Does that make sense? All right.
So, the problem is
that in 336,
Philip was assassinated
and his son, Alexander,
came to a throne, came to the throne.
And as we discussed last class,
Alexander had a very different
vision from the Greek and the Greek,
and he wanted to become his father. His
father wanted to unite the Greek world.
Alexander wanted to conquer the entire
world to show he was superior to his father,
okay? And unbelievably, incredibly,
he was able to do so,
conquer most of the world
in about 10 years' time.
So now, suddenly,
you have this sprawling empire
all around the world, okay? So
let's just sketch out how
vast this new empire was.
Okay, so you have, you
know, Greece and Macedon.
All right, okay? So
that's the Greek homeland.
Thank you. That's the
Greek homeland, right?
But hey, over here, you have Anatolia.
This is Mesopotamia.
Over here is Afghanistan.
Oh, sorry, sorry, it
should be Iran, sorry.
Iran, Afghanistan.
And you also reach as
far as Pakistan, okay?
And down here, you have the Levant,
and you have Egypt, all right?
This was not supposed to happen.
Philip and the Panhellenic Project,
imagine like their conquest
would extend up around here,
okay, because you're
uniting the Greek world.
Alexander went too far, and now you're,
you've conquered most of
the known world, okay?
Then Alexander died, and then
the empire was divided
into three major fragments.
Over here, you have something
called the Antigonid Empire,
okay? The Antigonid Dynasty, okay?
So that's one piece of the empire.
Down here, you have Ptolemy, okay?
Ptolemy was one of Alexander's
general, and he took over Egypt.
And over here, you have something
called the Seleucid Empire,
founded, of course, by the
general Seleucus, okay?
And over here, you have other
smaller kingdoms as well.
So you have this vast empire,
and this is something that
was unplanned and unexpected.
Now that you've conquered these places,
your concern or your problem
is, how do we conquer them?
Govern, okay?
So you need a new culture.
And so these different generals
adopted different strategies.
So for example, here,
the Persian culture is
extremely well established,
and the Seleucid king
and his hearers decided a
process of localization,
okay? Or another word we
can use is synchronization.
Synchronization, okay?
Meaning two different religions or
two different cultures come together
and coalesce together, okay?
So throughout the Seleucid Empire, it
was really a process of synchronization.
The Greeks adapted
themselves to local customs
and to local culture, okay?
At the same time, the
Greeks were conquerors.
So they still needed to maintain
a coherent identity, okay?
So it made sense for them
to adopt a lot of Aristotle's work.
Remember, Aristotle was
creating a panhellenic identity
and so he basically
created a lot of textbooks,
he basically created a encyclopedia.
So it made sense for them
to import Aristotle's work.
Also it's important and remember,
Aristotle was Macedonian
and
a a a along this time Greeks did not
consider Macedonians to be Greek.
This is why it's called the Pan -Hellenic
project, not the Pan -Greek project.
Also Greeks were very
condescending towards Macedonians
because they saw Macedonians
as barbarians. So
it was in the best interest of these new
Macedonian conquerors to exaggerate or to highlight
the intellectual contributions of Aristotle.
Does that make sense? Ptolemy's
Egypt was very different.
Egyptian culture has been
around for thousands of years
and the Europeans are very
proud of their culture.
This is a problem because
you're very proud of your local
culture you don't like foreign rulers
and this is something that
the Persian Empire struggled with
throughout the centuries that it passed.
The Persians dominated Egypt. The
Persians were famous for their openness
and tolerance. Basically you are
allowed to practice your own religion
and they're very supportive of that.
The most famous example
are the Jews, right?
The Persians supported in
rebuilding the Second Temple.
We'll get to the Jews later on.
But because the Persians were so
supportive of local culture in Egypt,
the Egyptians rebelled against
Persia many many times.
So Ptolemy and
his hearers didn't want
to make the same mistake.
They wanted to impose a new culture
on the Egyptians in order to show
that they were superior
and therefore more divine than Egyptians.
So Ptolemy did many things
that started this process.
The first thing that he did was he
stole Alexander's body from Babylon.
Where he died and brought
it back to Egypt.
Because Egyptians saw Alexander as
a god, as a son of a god, right?
So to establish legitimacy in Egypt,
Ptolemy went on a military expedition and
stole the body of Alexander which
started something called
the War of the Diochi,
basically the successor wars.
That's the first thing he
did. The second thing that
he did was he established a
new capital in Alexandria
called Alexandria.
Ok? So this was mainly a Greek city.
It was a new Greek city
founded by Alexander and
this is where they house Alexander's body.
The third thing that he did
was he started to sponsor
something called, we
call today the Museion.
Ok? The Museion is the root of the English The
Museion is the root of the English word museum.
But the museum was really the
world's first research university.
So Ptolemy and
his hearers brought together the greatest
Greek scholars in the world to basically
continue the work of
Aristotle to standardize
and systemize Greek culture so
that they can impose it on
the local Egyptian culture.
Does that make sense? And
the most famous aspect of the
museum is the Library of Exandria.
And Ptolemy spent a lot of money
on the Library of Exandria,
mainly by going around and
collecting original manuscripts.
So a representative went to Athens.
And he went to the library
of Exandria. And said,
we at the Library of Exandria
would like the original copies,
the original manuscripts for Aeschylus,
Sophocles, and Euripides,
the three great playwrights.
And the Athenians are like, we can't do
that because they're like gods here, okay?
We're not gonna give you
original manuscripts.
And the Egyptians said,
all we're gonna do is we're gonna take these
manuscripts back to the Library of Exandria
where our scribes will copy them out,
okay? That's all we're gonna do.
And then we'll give it back to you.
And as a guarantee, we're gonna give
you like 15 talents of silver, okay?
And that's like a billion
dollars back then.
The Athenians have never
seen so much money.
So Athenians will say, well, okay,
well, if it's just to
spread Greek culture,
we can actually deal with that, okay?
So we'll take the deposit, 15 talents,
and we'll give you the manuscripts.
The Egyptians took the manuscripts,
placed it in the Library of Exandria,
and said, hey, Athenians,
keep the money, okay?
Because the Egyptians under Ptolemy were
focused on turning the Library of Exandria
and Exandria into the intellectual
capital of the Greek world,
all right?
And so what happened was that
after Alexander died and
his generals took over,
the Panhellenic project really became
what we call the Panhellenistic project.
Okay? It went from uniting the Greek world into
spreading Greek culture all around the world.
And that's why we have Greek
culture still with us today,
okay, because of this process.
So, let's go back to the
Original Paradox, all right?
Why – there are three paradoxes, right?
The first paradox is why do we have
nothing original from Aristotle?
The answer is because Aristotle
didn't write anything original.
He stole every fucking thing.
thing from other thinkers and
had his students copy it
out in manuscript form.
It doesn't make sense.
Second is why are his works
so diverse? Why is the range so great?
The answer is because he was trying to
capture the essence of Greek knowledge.
He was trying to unify Greek
knowledge into an encyclopedia for
dissemination around the world.
The third thing is, the
most interesting thing is,
why is Aristotle's philosophy
so different from Plato's worldview?
That's a really interesting question.
Why are they so different?
So let's switch our
perspective and ask ourselves.
If you were king of Macedon,
if you were Philip Alexander,
what's your problem
with Plato's philosophy?
You have a problem. What is it?
Any guesses? You're
Alexander, you're Philip.
You really hate Plato. Why? Why?
Well, the problem with Plato is,
you go to Plato, you're Alexander, you go to
Plato and says, I want to conquer the world.
Right? Plato would say, what's the point?
It's all not real, Alexander.
You're just wasting your time.
You can conquer the world, but all
you're doing is conquer a shadow.
What's real is the form of the good.
Right? Alexander, study mathematics,
man. Okay?
Do more math. Stop going around
and killing people.
Do more math. Right and
we know what Alexander would do here.
Alexander would probably
cut off Plato's head.
Alexander and Philip hate this thing.
This thing is idiotic.
I want to conquer the world, but this
philosophy is telling me it's pointless.
What matters is mathematics.
What matters is a
philosophy. philosophy. Now,
let's now compare
this with Aristotle's
prime mover theory.
What Aristotle was saying
is, everything is motion,
and what is good is if
you fulfill your purpose.
Now, if you're Alexander or
Philip, this makes more sense.
I'm Philip, my purpose is
to unite the Greek world,
and the more I unite,
the more good I'm doing
for this world, right?
Also, if you're a king,
you want your citizens,
your soldiers, your workers
to work hard, right?
Well, for Plato,
working hard is just useless.
You're imitating an imitation, right?
When you create art.
But here,
working hard is what gives you purpose.
It's what gives you happiness.
Okay? So
Aristotle also promoted
two major concepts.
The first is erite.
The second is eudaimonia.
Okay? Erite is just excellence.
Okay? Alexander has erite because
he is an excellent general.
When you have erite and
you are achieving your purpose,
then you achieve eudaimonia, okay?
Which is just flourishing or happiness.
And that's the purpose of life, to
have erite and to achieve eudaimonia.
So work hard. Fight for Alexander.
Support him as he conquers the world.
Because he's making the world better.
Okay? Does that make sense?
I have a question about that.
So if I'm a soldier and
my purpose is to be a good soldier,
am I not approaching the
form of the good that
there's this ideal soldier out
there and the closer I can get to
that, the more engaged I am
in the face of the world?
Okay, that's a great
question. Yeah, thanks, Doug.
Okay. All right. So the question
then is, if I'm a soldier and
I'm a soldier, and I'm,
you know, working hard and
winning battles, am I not
approaching the form of the good?
And the answer is, for Plato, it's not.
The reason why is, what do you do
in this material world is pointless.
Okay? Because this material
world, it's not real.
So whatever you do is not real.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So what you need to do is
return to the form of the good.
But your body can't do that.
Your soul can do that.
So your use of the body is pointless.
You have to use your soul.
You have to use your mind. All right?
Therefore, you have to be a good person.
Therefore, you have to engage
in philosophy and mathematics.
And that's how you return
to the form of the good.
Your use of the body,
you're just deluding yourself.
Okay? All right?
And if you engage in art,
you're just deluding yourself.
Then you are deluding others.
And that's more evil. If you're
Alexander and you're conquering others
and forcing them to believe your fake philosophy,
then you're committing the most evil in the world.
Does that make sense? All right?
All right. So, yeah.
All right. So
this is my theory of how to best resolve
the three paradoxes of Aristotle.
Okay? Does that make sense? There's basically a
censor who is working for Philip and Alexander.
And he was trying to develop a pan
-Hellenistic identity in order
to unite the world they conquer.
Okay? So that's my argument.
Any questions about this overall argument?
Does it make sense to you guys? Okay?
I've got a few questions.
Go ahead. Yeah. Thank you.
Go on. All right. Go ahead.
So one of the questions is how
do you know you're going to.
So I'm going to ask you a
question. That's a good question.
Yeah. Okay. All right.
So how do we know he didn't
write any of his works?
Okay. The answer is this.
When you write something,
you're actually manifesting your thought.
Right? But your thought
comes from your personality.
So if you look at any work of genius,
it's original and unique.
Okay? Does that make sense? In other words,
if you read Shakespeare, guess what?
There's no other Shakespeare in the world.
If you're trying to imitate
Shakespeare, you look like an idiot.
Okay? Homer is unique. Plato is unique.
There's no point in
trying to imitate them.
You can't do it because you are not them.
Okay? Now, when you look at Aristotle,
there's something unique about Aristotle.
So, you know, when you read Plato, the Republic,
there are certain ideas that stand out.
Like, how to go to the cave.
Right? There's certain phrases
that capture your imagination.
That doesn't exist with Aristotle's texts.
Okay? They're written like textbooks. So
the argument for the longest time was
Aristotle did write his own books,
but they were lost to us. And
his students had to reassemble his
thinking from their own memory.
Okay? So, yeah, that's how we know.
But this is generally agreed upon.
We have nothing that Aristotle wrote.
Aristotle wrote originally. Okay?
So maybe the follow -up question then
would be, is it possible
that his ideas were for the empire?
And they could have been co
-opted by forces of that.
That's right.
And is that as much of a.
Is that.
Yeah. Okay. So thank you, Doug.
Okay. Yeah. So, yeah.
So, there are many different
possibilities of how Aristotle can become
so influential. Okay?
The first possibility is,
as I argue, he was actually
a partner of Philip's.
That they were both trying to
promote the pan -Hellenic project.
Okay? That's the first possibility.
But then the possibility is, as Doug says,
he was just a philosopher.
He was a student of Plato's.
He was very smart. And he
was a very good teacher.
And after Alexander and
his generals conquered the world,
they needed a symbol of
Macedonian cultural superiority.
And they just decided upon Aristotle
because it was most convenient.
Right? So that's another possibility.
Okay?.
Just from the part
there about Aristotle's.
I think that kind of sounds up to me.
I mean, I'm not sure.
I'm not sure. But he rejected
too much onto his dad.
But his dad was a physician, right?
. That's right..
If that's your approach to the world,
you are looking for much
more materialistic.
If you're looking for.
. Right?
. But you need much more.
...
Yep.
Yep, exactly.
So, yeah, so it is entirely possible
that Aristotle was a materialist
because that was just
his personality, right?
The influence from his father,
who was a physician, okay?
But that creates another
problem, which is if you are
so opposed to Plato's
understanding of the world,
right, because you're a materialist and
he's a dualist, why were you studying under Plato for 20 years?
Does that make sense?
Does that make sense? So
that creates another problem.
All right, so another thing
I want to point out is,
okay, how we have Aristotle's works today,
there are three different
possibilities, okay?
The first possibility is that Aristotle,
in his lifetime, he
organized his students and
created this encyclopedia, okay?
It's no different from professors
at universities today, right?
Professors who are scientists, they
actually do very little of that.
They have the original research.
They have the students do it.
They're the ones who supervise
the entire process, okay?
So it's possible, that's
the first possibility.
Aristotle was supervising the work
of creating a Greek identity.
The second possibility
is after Aristotle died,
his students started to remember, recall
his lectures. And that's why so much
of his work is fragmentary, okay?
We don't have complete manuscripts. And the third
possibility, okay? And it's a very important one.
The third possibility is
Aristotle is a fiction
created by scholars at
the Library of Alexandria,
okay? So it's really the scholars at the
Library of Alexandria who created Aristotle.
And they did so by
synthesizing all this work.
And then they gave it to,
they accredited it to,
attributed it to Aristotle in order to
create the legend of this philosopher,
okay?
Does that make sense? Yeah.
Okay. So let's have an
argument about Confucius.
Let's have this discussion
about Confucius, okay?
But I want to very quickly
talk about the Greek legacy.
Because even though we can argue back
and forth about Aristotle and
his providence, what is not
debatable is the profound influence
that Aristotle had on the world, okay?
We can argue if Aristotle was the
original writer or the original thinker.
But what is not debatable is the tremendous
influence he had on the entire world,
okay? So there are three aspects of
the Greek legacy I want to discuss.
The first aspect is the Greeks
created a new way of being human,
all right?
So let's look at the major thinkers.
You have Homer. You have the playwrights,
Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euboides.
And you have the philosophers,
Plato and Aristotle.
Plato and Aristotle. Alright.
So the Greeks created a
new way of being a human.
Alright. Alright.
Alright. Alright. Alright.
Alright. Alright. Alright. Alright.
Alright. Alright.
Alright. Because
the point of listening to Homer
was to enter Homer's world
and become Achilles or Odysseus.
And through this process, you
became a different person.
And therefore, you learned empathy,
but you also expanded your imagination.
Okay? So that's what
Homer did for the Greeks.
Then you have Aeschylus,
Sophrates, and Eupodes.
And what they did that was different is,
rather than think
directly at the audience,
they had the characters face each
other in a dialogue, in a debate.
Okay? And by doing this,
what happens is you
create the capacity for perspective
and inner debate.
Right? Because before, you were part of...
the story.
Now you have to step
back and judge the story.
There's a debate going on.
You have to switch perspectives in
order to understand the characters.
And this creates the capacity
for an inner monologue.
Okay? And a debate in you.
And then you have Plato and Aristotle.
What Plato did that
was unique was he took all
the dialogue in the play.
And he transported it onto the page.
But now, you're reading it by yourself.
And you have the benefit of time.
Okay? And so,
this creates a capacity
for reason and reflection.
Okay? You can sort of reason out
if the words make sense to you.
You are no longer influenced by the
crowd or the emotions of the actor.
You can just look at the words themselves.
And judge them on their own merit.
You also have the capacity now to reflect.
Meaning, you can go back to the words
over and over the course of your lifetime.
To constantly reflect on
their meaning and logic.
Okay? You understand?
So, when you add these
three things together.
Homer created the capacity
for empathy and imagination.
The playwright created the capacity
for inner debate and perspective.
The philosophers created the
capacity for reason and reflection.
You now have a new human mind.
Okay? And when you study all of them.
This is what we call a
liberal arts education.
Alright? And guess what?
Our greatest thinkers came to
us through the liberal arts.
Alright? Alright? Alright?
Alright? Alright?
the greatest thinkers
of the past 20 years,
they all, what was common about
them is, they all read the Greeks.
And that was just their education.
Alright, so this is the
first legacy of the Greeks.
A new way of being and seeing.
Okay, does that make
sense? Second thing is,
now that you have this Greek world,
the Greeks need to establish
a cohesive cultural identity.
And they did that
by promoting a Greek education.
Okay, but not only that, but
they had to bring in local
people into this education.
So one major function of
the Library of Alexandria
was to standardize and
systemize Greek knowledge.
And they did this by
standardizing the text.
Okay, so there are different
texts that were written by Homer.
The text of Homer that
we have today was developed by the
people at the Library of Alexandria.
Standardization. They also did
something called commentaries.
So commentaries are basically
like teacher handbooks.
They teach you how to teach this stuff.
And they create like footnotes and
chapters and page numbers,
codices, indexes.
Okay, so the point was
to make Greek education
available and accessible to anyone.
All right, and what this means is, we
in China now can actually read Homer,
Issylus, and Plato for ourselves.
Even though we are not culturally Greek.
And that's the benefit of
the pan -Hellenistic project.
All right. And
the third major benefit
is Greek knowledge meant
a global development.
Revolution. And innovation, okay?
And what I mean by that is, remember,
Greek knowledge is being
spread all around the world.
And then they're interacting
with powerful local cultures.
And through the process
of synchronization,
new forms of knowledge are being created.
Okay? So
the Greeks spread the knowledge to India.
And now it's interacting with
local Indian philosophies.
And religion, including new ideas.
Right? So
the most famous synchronization
is in the Levant.
Greek knowledge was
being spread to the Jews.
Okay? And so when you put the
Greeks and the Jews together,
you have a new idea that
would forever revolutionize human history.
And it's called Christianity. All right?
So Christianity would not
have been possible if it
were not for the work of Aristotle.
Okay? All right.
So those are the three major
legacies of the Greeks.
And so it is,
I think it's perfectly fair to say
the Greeks were the most influential
and consequential
civilization of all time.
They were certainly the most creative. No other
civilization even comes close to their creativity.
All right? Okay.
So that's it. Any questions?
Okay. So…
Okay. So we are finished with the Greeks.
Next class we start a new unit on Rome…
Roman history. All right?
So… Great.