Okay, so I want to summarize
and review what we have learned so far.
So the main message is
that for most of human history,
we have been peaceful, egalitarian,
and artistic. So
about 200,000 years ago,
our species, Homo sapiens,
were born in Africa.
And then 50,000 years ago,
because of climate change,
we started to spread around the world.
And throughout most of our history,
we have been hunter -gatherers.
And we don't know.
We don't know that much about our history.
We can only guess. But
based on the available
archaeological evidence, we were,
for most of the time, peaceful,
egalitarian, and artistic.
Okay, so peaceful does not
mean we were not violent.
There is lots of evidence that
there was in -group conflict.
So, for example, we discovered that
the people in burials were
people with skull fractures.
So there has been violence, but
there has been no evidence
of organized warfare.
That comes much later.
That's the first thing.
The second thing is that
we were egalitarian,
meaning that there was
no difference in status
and power between men and women.
Men and women were considered equal.
There was no hierarchy, meaning that
there were people who were considered
more wealthy than other people.
We know because
we could not find any
evidence of hierarchy,
meaning larger houses, meaning
groups with special privileges.
Now, there are individuals
who might have higher status.
And we know because
they were buried more
elaborately than other people.
So, for example, shamans, right?
Shamans were their religious leaders, and
as such, they were quoted higher
status than everyone else.
Okay? And the third thing is artistic.
So, as we know, they were
engaged in cave paintings.
They built monuments in order to
celebrate and worship their religion.
So for them, art really
was about the expression
and celebration of their religion.
Okay? So, for most of human history,
we were peaceful,
egalitarian, and artistic.
And we know that today,
we are not peaceful.
We are not egalitarian.
We are not that artistic. So what changed?
Next week, I will explain
to you what changed. Okay?
Basically, a new group of people
called the Yamnaya came into being,
and they had a different
religion that celebrated warfare,
patriarchalism, and the like. Okay?
And eventually spread all around Europe
and Asia, and they conquered everyone, and
they created a new history of humanity.
That's next week. Okay? So
I want to explain the
evidence for why we think
most of human history,
we were peaceful,
egalitarian, and artistic.
Okay. So something else
that we discuss in class is we don't want to be a
group of people who are not happy with what we do.
We don't know what their religion was,
but we suspect that it
was animism and shamanism.
Okay? Remember that animism is the belief
that we all come from the mother goddess,
from one source of life, including trees,
animals, and humans.
So every living being has a soul.
Okay? And the other thing is
that we are not religious.
Okay? And by religious we mean
that the soul is permanent.
You can't ever kill it.
Okay? The body and the soul are different.
So it doesn't really
matter if you die because
your soul will go somewhere
else and maybe come back.
Okay? So death was not a big deal.
And the third thing is that
there's a spirit world or another world
which is more real than our world.
Okay? Our world is just a manifestation,
a physical manifestation
of spiritualporteriality.
of the spirit world, but what
matters is the spirit world.
And the last thing is that
there's an order to the universe.
We have a part to play.
So for example, we can kill
animals to feed ourselves,
but we must pay tribute to these animals
before and after we kill them in order
to maintain the harmony of the universe.
Okay? So
that's what we believe the
religion of early humans
were everywhere in the world,
okay? Including in China,
including in Europe.
This is Gopalatepe, and
you can see that this is a T -pillar
and it's meant to represent a human.
And inside the T -pillar is an animal.
So basically, the T -pillar
represents a human being.
And the animal is the manifestation
of the animal spirit in us.
And we believe that this
is a religious festival
that they would have
before they went hunting.
And the evidence for this
is that at this site,
we found a lot of animal bones.
Okay? So does that make sense, guys?
Alright. So again, this
is all just review.
This religion goes back a long time, okay?
So this is 40,000 years ago.
We found this small figurine, okay?
It's a very small figurine
in a cave in Germany.
And this dates back to 40,000 years ago.
Okay? So remember, 50,000 years
ago, we started to leave Africa
and venture into Europe
and around the world, okay?
So this goes back to the
beginning, the dawn of humanity.
This is a flute, okay?
That goes back to the same time.
So at the beginning, this is a flute.
And at the beginning of
humanity, we were religious.
We celebrated our religion through music
and through art and through shamanism.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
Yes? It's a figurine.
It's a doll. Okay?
So they believe that
these dolls have religious
qualities, right?
Okay? Does that make
sense? It's like paintings.
It's like paintings. So remember,
they also have these cave paintings where
they're celebrating the mother goddess, and they're
celebrating the fact that life is a circle.
After you kill the animals, their
soul goes back into the spirit world,
and then through proper tribute
and worship, you can bring them
back into this world, okay?
Okay? This is a shaman
dressed as an animal.
Okay? So now the question then is, okay,
if we cannot go back in time
and observe the religion,
how do we know what the religion is?
And the answer is we have a field
of study called anthropology.
Okay? Anthropology.
Anthropology is a study of other cultures.
Okay? And if our theory is right,
then we should be able
to find other cultures
that are still alive today
that practice this religion.
And what we've discovered is that
if you go to places
in the jungle in South America
and in Africa, in Australia,
they do practice this religion.
Okay? So
understanding the religion gives us
tremendous insight into the thinking
and religion of early humans.
And that's what we will do today.
Okay? To truly understand
what early humans thought
and how they understood the world.
Okay? Does that make
sense, guys? All right. So
the first passage we're going
to look at is from a book
called The Wayfinders.
By Wade Davis.
Okay? This is a great book.
If you guys ever have a
chance, please read this book.
Okay? It's extremely
well written. Wade Davis,
he's an anthropologist, Canadian.
And this recently came out.
Okay? So he spent a lot of time
traveling around the world to explore
and to understand indigenous peoples,
people who are native to the land.
And they've been there
for a long, long time.
So this is what he says about a tribe.
This is a story about a
tribe in the Amazon forest.
Okay? In the beginning,
before the creation of seasons,
before the ancestral mother, Romi Kumu,
woman shaman, opened her womb,
before her blood and
breast milk gave rise to rivers
and her ribs to the mountain
ridges of the world,
there was only chaos in the universe.
Spirits and demons known as He.
Prayed on their own kindred.
Bread without thought, committed
incest without consequence,
devoured their own young.
Romi Kumu responded by destroying
the world with fire and floods. Then,
just as a mother turns over a warm
slab of maniac bread on the griddle,
she turned the inundated and
charred world upside down,
creating a flat and empty template from
which life could emerge once again.
As woman shaman, she then
gave birth to a new world, land,
water, forest, and animals.
Okay? So this is what
we call a creation myth.
And every single civilization,
every single people have a creation myth.
So let me ask you this question, okay?
Why? Why do you need a creation myth?
What's this creation myth
doing? What does it explain?
Okay, how the world forms, okay?
But there's something much more
important than that, which is what?
Excuse me? Who are we?
Where we come from?
Yes. But there's something,
yes, it explains all that.
Who we are, where we come from, okay?
That's what all creation myths do.
What else is this myth doing, which
is very important for us? Okay.
So it's telling us how the
universe was formed, okay?
Okay. What is in here
that's very important
and which is important for
society to function well?
Okay. So the woman shaman
is the mother goddess. Well,
what's in this page page page page page
page page page page page page page page Paragraph that's very important in order for society to function.
What do you need for society to function?
You need rules and laws right so
what this creation myth is doing what
all creation myths is doing is build
Explaining to you the legal structure
of your society why you
can't do certain things
Okay, so for example you can't
commit incest Okay, you can't eat your young
people you can't kill the young people okay?
Why because that's what evil people do
You understand? So
what this Christian myth
is doing is it's basically
Explaining the legal system the rules
and why we have them We have these rules
because they're evil they
represent the evil spirit
Okay, does that make sense guys?
Okay The other thing that you will
notice about this creation myth is
that it's very sophisticated
and very elaborate
Okay, so
this is a visualization of their understanding
of creation as you can understand.
It's very
Complicated okay Does that make sense?
Why is it complicated?
Why is it complicated why is
Is this so complicated?
There are reasons for it why?
Why is it complicated?
Okay, so one thing that you
will learn in this class is that
What's really important is for you to
believe that your religion is correct, okay?
It is just correct as science
and what makes people believe
That your religion is correct Yet
you have to accomplish three things.
Okay, the first is grandness
Meaning that is come huge Okay,
it's vast and
as you can see this is a vast religion
of vast cosmology of how things started
So grandness is very
important then you have you
then you then you need completeness
And the idea of completeness is That
Everything that you see in the world
must be explained in this cosmology.
Okay, so what this is doing is
explained to you how everything
Started okay, where everything comes
from so completeness is important.
The last thing is
unity Meaning that there's a
beginning and there's an end
Okay, as you can see there's a
beginning and then there's an end.
Okay So this is something that we will learn in
this class as we explore other religions including
Judaism and Christianity where
for religion to be powerful for it to be
Authoritative you need these
three ideas grandness completeness
and unity. Okay, does that make sense?
All right, let's keep let's keep on going
All right
so thus
For the people living
today in the forests of
the para Parana Okay This is the Amazon
forest the entire natural
world is saturated with meaning
and cosmological significance Okay,
they feel that everything
around them has life
and it's all connected.
It's one unified whole.
Okay every rock and
waterfall embodies a story
Plants and animals are but
distinct physical manifestations of
the same essential spiritual essence
And we all come from the woman Shaman.
We all come from the
mother goddess Therefore
we all have the spark of life in us
and therefore we must be respected Okay,
the plants and the animals all must be
respected as much as we are respected
at the same time
Everything is more than it appears
for the visible world is only one
level of perception
behind every tangible form
That everyone means concrete physical
Okay every planet animal is an incredible!
! is
a shadow dimension,
a place invisible to ordinary
people, but visible to the shaman.
So in other words, our
world is a world we can see.
But there are other worlds,
the shadow dimension,
which is more real, which
captures our essence,
where the soul resides.
That's more real. And it's
the job of the shaman to see
and communicate with this world.
This is a realm of the He spirits,
a world of deified ancestors
where rocks and rivers are alive.
Plants and animals are
human beings, sap and
blood the bodily fluids of the
primordial river of the Anakana.
Hidden in cataracts behind the
physical veil of waterfalls,
in the very center of stones are
the great malakas of the He spirit,
where everything is.
Everything is beautiful. The
shining feathers, the koka,
the calabash of tobacco powder, which
is in itself the skull
and brain of the sun.
Okay? Now, reading this,
what can we say about their religion?
What can we say about their religion?
That would be surprising to you.
Okay, first of all, it's
very imaginative, right?
It's very imaginative.
They have a vivid imagination, okay?
The other thing is that it's
extremely sophisticated
and complex.
So, one major prejudice
that we might have of
these people is, well,
they don't drive cars, they don't have
cell phones, therefore they must be stupid.
Therefore, they must
be stupid. But clearly,
from our understanding of
their religious beliefs,
they're actually extremely imaginative
and extremely sophisticated.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
All right. So,
this is their shamans
in religious practice.
Okay? What can we say about this picture?
What stands out about this picture?
What surprises your...
What catches your eye about them?
What can we say about their
beliefs based on this picture?
Okay, yeah. So,
there's a lot of...
There's a lot of
thought put into what they wear, right?
Okay? So, again, sophistication.
Their clothing, the way
they dress, suggests
that this is a very
sophisticated religion.
Okay? It's not like they
just put on anything.
It's like it seems they
put a lot of care and
thought into what they wear.
Okay? That's the first thing.
Okay? That's the first thing. Okay? Okay?
Okay? Okay?
Okay, yeah, I mean, he probably
has a higher status, okay?
And he stands in the middle,
okay? What else? Excuse me?
Okay, so you're right in like,
okay, if this is a tribe and all
they're trying to do is hunt
and eat food, none of this
makes any sense, right?
But the main argument that I've
been trying to tell you is like,
no, their first priority
is their religion, okay?
So everything they do has a
religious significance to it.
We don't know what it is.
They don't really speak our language.
But for them, everything that
they do must have a
religious meaning, okay?
So it's their religion that says, okay,
we're going to do this, okay? So
the other thing I would say is,
you can see there's some
organization in order to it, right?
So as you say, the person, the
elder stands in the middle, okay?
And these two, can you see the symmetry?
Okay? It's clear that they are doing
a religious ceremony. And because
this religious ceremony
requires their bodies to
be a certain way in relation
to each other, it requires,
them to dress a certain way.
It requires them to say
certain things, okay?
Clearly, they are in prayer of some sort.
We call this the idea of ritual.
Ritual is just the expression of
religion in everyday practice.
In other words,
their lives are extremely ritualized.
Meaning, what they do
every second has a ritual.
Okay?
different kids. Okay?
Does that make sense to you guys? Right?
So for example, you come to school and you
think your life is very ordered, right?
Because maybe at 8 o
'clock you start class.
And then when class starts,
the teacher takes attendance.
Okay? That's all ritual. And then
at 8.45, the bell rings and then you go
off and get some water or something, okay?
If you want to go to the restroom,
you have to raise your hand.
This is all what we call ritual.
So your lives are extremely ritualized.
And the thing about ritual
is behind the ritual,
there has to be a belief system.
Okay? So for us, the school,
we believe the system is set up
so that you learn how to do well in life,
right? You learn how to be on time.
You learn how to respect authority.
You learn how to read books.
Okay? So
this society is exactly the same way
where every minute of
their lives there's order
and structure to what they do
that has meaning and purpose.
Okay? Does that make sense to you guys?
Okay. So
let's talk about their ritual.
Okay? Okay. It is to the
realm of the He -spirit
that the shaman goes in ritual.
So the shaman is responsible for
entering the world of the demons
and negotiating and
communicating with them.
That's his role. That's why he
has his power and authority.
Contrary to popular lore in the West,
the shaman of the Barazana never
uses or manipulates medicinal plants.
His duty and
sacred task is to move in
the timeless realm of the He,
embrace the primordial powers and
harness and restore the
energy of all creation.
He is like a modern engineer who
enters the depths of a nuclear reactor
to renew the entire cosmic order.
So if,
for example, plants are dying.
Outside, what does this mean?
If plants are dying outside,
what does this mean?
The animals and plants are dying.
How can we fix the problem?
Why are bad things happening?
Bad things are happening
because the spirits are unhappy.
Does that make sense? So therefore,
you must go into the spirit world
and understand why the spirits are unhappy
and fix it.
And that's the role of the shaman.
And what this is saying is this.
What this is saying is that
our world doesn't matter guys.
Our world is insignificant.
What matters is the spirit world.
Because the spirit world is
what controls everything.
Does that make sense guys?
Okay? Among the Barasana,
such renewal is a fundamental
obligation of the living.
In practice, this implies that
the Barasana see the earth as potent,
the force as being alive
with spiritual beings
and ancestral powers.
To live off the land is to
embrace both its creative
and destructive potential.
Human beings, plants and
animals, are not the same.
They share the same cosmic origin and
in a profound sense are seen
as essentially identical.
Responsive to the same principles,
obligated by the same duties,
responsible for the collective
well -being of creation.
There is no separation
between nature and culture.
Without the forests and the
rivers, humans would perish.
Without people,
the natural world would
have no order or meaning.
All would be chaos.
The norms that
drive social behavior would
have no order or meaning.
It would also define the manner in which
human beings interact with the
wild, the plants and animals,
the multiple phenomena
of the natural world,
lightning and thunder, the sun and
the moon, the scent of a blossom,
the sound order of death.
Everything is connected with each other.
We are all equals. Does
that make sense guys?
This is what we call animism.
Alright, so let's talk about hunting.
This is something we
talked about last class.
If we are the same as animals
and plants, what allows us,
what gives us permission
to kill other animals?
And this passage explains it.
When men go to the forest to hunt or fish,
it is never a trivial passage.
You cannot just go and hunt.
You need permission. First,
the shaman must travel in trance to
negotiate with the masters of the animals,
forging a mystical contract with the
spirit guardians in exchange
based always on reciprocity.
Reciprocity means give and take.
If I give you a present,
you must give me a present.
The brasarana compared to marriage for
hunting too is a form of courtesanism.
It is a form of courtship in which one
seeks the blessings of a greater authority
for the honor of taking into
one's family a precious being.
Meat is not the right of a hunter, but
a gift from the spirit world.
To kill without permission is to
risk death by a spirit guardian,
be it in the form of a jaguar,
anaconda, tapir, or harpy eagle.
This is something that we
discussed in the cave paintings.
Why did they spend so much time
painting the cave paintings?
They were painting these animals.
We said it's because
they're trying to pay
tribute to the animals.
If I kill you,
I must thank you for taking
your meat to replenish myself,
but I also must ask for your forgiveness.
Otherwise, the animal's
soul may seek vengeance.
Does that make sense? This is
the essence of the religion.
If we hunt, we must first seek the
blessings of the spirit guardian.
We must pay tribute to
the spirit guardian.
That's what explains the kata hoik.
The bull and
the people must pay tribute to all
the animals before they go hunting.
You also look at the cave paintings.
They have all these cave paintings.
What they celebrate is not themselves.
What they celebrate are the animals.
They celebrate the animals
that give them life.
They give them nourishment and
meat. Does that make sense?
You can see this in
caves all around Europe
and around the world.
As the ritual begins, the
kata hoik is a ritual.
As the ritual begins, time collapses.
There are two series of dances separated
by the liminal moments of the day,
dawn, dusk, and midnight.
The shaman, during the ritual,
needs to communicate with the
animals in the spirit world.
To do that, he changes from
fish to animal to human being
and back again, transcending every form,
becoming pure energy flowing
among every dimension of reality,
past and present, here and
there, mythic and mundane.
His chants recall by name every point of
geography met on the ancestral
journey of the anaconda.
As you can see, before the hunt,
the ritual is extremely elaborate,
sophisticated, and complex.
Its main purpose is to celebrate
the unity of the animal.
The ritual is to ask for
forgiveness as the hunters
go kill the animals.
Does that make sense? Again,
this explains
the shaman's
change into animals in order to
better communicate with the animals.
This explains all the cave paintings
and how 40,000 years ago,
they were creating dolls of
shamans dressed as animals.
Because for them, this is what is true.
Does that make sense, guys?
Any questions so far before I move on?
Are you guys clear about what's going on?
Okay? Alright.
Now, let's move to Africa.
Okay? We were in South America,
and they're still there today.
If you want to go visit
that tribe, you can do so.
Okay? Now, let's go to Africa.
And in Africa, there's a group
of people called the Pygmies.
Okay? The Pygmies. And
there's a very famous book by
a British anthropologist by
the name of Colin Turnbull.
Okay? And he discusses how the Pygmies
practiced their religious beliefs.
At the very center of the
religion is something called the Molimo.
Okay? Which is a trumpet -like instrument.
And the Molimo allows them to
communicate with the forest.
It allows them to communicate
with the spirit world.
And that's how they resolve every issue.
Okay? And
the Molimo also captures the sound
and spirit of the forest.
Okay? Alright?
So, even though
we are in a different part of
the world, we're in Africa, and
even though the Pygmies have different
religious beliefs than the people of the Amazon,
what you will discover,
what you will notice is that
essentially, it's the same religion.
Okay? The same idea that
we are part of nature,
and that
our job is to help nature
maintain balance and harmony.
Okay? Okay.
Okay. So, what I want to do now,
okay, is compare and
contrast the way we think today
and how they thought before.
Okay? So, let's read.
I had no idea of how far we
had come or in what direction.
So he's following the group of
Pygmies around as they hunt.
But I knew we had left
the camp far behind.
It was the first time
I had seen the Pygmies.
I had known a group of
Pygmies to be so silent.
Normally, unless hunting,
they are deliberately noisy.
But now, just at the time that
leopards would be prowling
about in search of food,
they seem unwilling to disturb the
forest or the animals it concealed.
Just the opposite, in fact.
It was as if they were
a part of the silence
and the darkness of the forest itself. And
were only fearful lest any sound might
betray their presence to some
person or thing not of the forest.
They stood there, quiet and still.
And it struck me with a sudden shock that
not one of them carried a spear or bow
and arrow. As they peered into the dust
and cocked their heads first on the side,
then on that, satisfying themselves
that we were really alone,
it seemed that they felt themselves so
much a part of the forest and
of all the living things in it,
they had no need to fear anything
except that which was not of the forest.
One of them said to me later, When
we are the children of the forest,
what need have we to be afraid of it?
We are only afraid of that
which is outside the forest.
So, what I want to do now is,
by analyzing this passage,
explore how our minds are
different from their minds.
So our mind is what we consider modern,
and their mind is what
we consider pre -modern.
What's the first major
difference between I,
the British anthropologist, and
how we think, and how they think?
What's the first difference
you notice from this passage?
First of all, what is the word that
tells us that he doesn't really
understand how these people think
and behave? What's the word
that tells us he doesn't
really understand these people?
This is actually a great SAT question,
if you guys plan on taking the SAT.
There's a word in this passage
that tells us he is actually,
he is actually, he doesn't really
understand how these people think and feel.
What's the word? Shock, right? Shock.
So he's surprised by their behavior.
Why is he surprised? What confuses him?
Anyone? Why? Yes, exactly.
Why does that surprise him?
Exactly. So here's the
first big difference.
Why do we think that nature is dangerous?
Why do they not think nature is dangerous?
Why? Why, guys?
That's exactly right. He thinks nature
is dangerous because they're leopards.
They're predators. They don't
think nature is dangerous.
What's the difference?
What's the difference? Okay, the
first major difference is this.
Our minds think that
we are separate from nature, okay?
Man versus nature.
But they think they are
part of nature, okay?
So let me ask you this
question. Why do we fear nature?
Why do we fear nature? What makes us fear
nature? If I put you in a forest, you're afraid.
Why? Yes,
okay. Why are you afraid of the unknown?
Okay, you don't know what you encounter,
but why does that make you afraid?
Okay. Why? Why would the
unknown make you afraid?
Why? What is it that we are obsessed with?
Hmm? Jimmy?
Okay. We're obsessed with control, right?
We have to control everything.
We want to know something because
we want to control it, okay?
We like animals in the zoo, right?
We do not like animals in the forest.
We can control animals in the zoo.
We cannot control animals
in the forest, okay?
So, we're obsessed with control.
Why aren't they afraid of nature?
What's their attitude? What
are the pygmies' attitudes?
We want to control nature, but they...
They what? Therefore they...
Therefore they... Okay,
the word is trust, right?
Trust. They don't have to control
nature because they trust nature.
They believe the leopards
know them and they know
the leopards, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay.
So, that's the first major
difference between our world
and their world.
We've been taught that
nature is our enemy or
nature is outside us,
whereas they believe that
they are part of nature.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
Alright, let's move on. Alright.
So, this is about
their religious practice, okay?
So, they have a meal together and then
they sing
or they use the malomo to make
noises and they sing and dance, okay?
Everyone ate his fill
as and when he pleased.
A couple of the older
men saying they would
wait until the youngsters
had finished before they ate.
But they did not wait for long.
I was told, however, that everyone
had to eat just as no adult male
was allowed to sleep, but to sing while
malomo was singing was in progress.
Apparently, one of the greatest
crimes that a pygmy can commit,
if not the greatest, is to be found
asleep when the malomo is singing.
One of the men stood up and
miming, as all pygmies love to do,
he showed how they used to
search for sleeping men,
a spear under each arm,
and how if they found one,
they would spear him in the stomach
and kill him completely and forever.
I was told that then his body
would be buried under the komalamo,
okay, the komalamo is a great fire in
which they practice their religion, okay?
And nobody would be allowed
to mention his death,
even to remark on his absence.
The woman would be told that the malomo
itself, the great animal of the forest,
had carried off one of their
number, but like the men,
they would ask no questions and would
never again mention the missing men.
Okay. So in this world,
the greatest crime you can
commit is not to kill someone,
but to sleep during the religion.
Can someone explain why that's the case?
In this world, okay, the pygmy world,
the worst thing you can do is sleep.
Why is that the case?
Okay. Let's just say that
we're having a class,
and one of you is sleeping, okay?
And I get so angry
that I want to kill that person.
Why would I want to do
that? What's my logic?
It's disrespectful of what?
Okay, it's disrespectful
of my authority, that
is true, but then I just
ask a person to leave my class, right?
Or I shout at that person, but
I want to kill that person.
Why? What's happened?
Okay. Okay.
What is a classroom? What is a classroom?
Okay. A place to study.
What else? What are we doing now?
Yeah, but what is class?
What is classroom?
What allows a classroom to exist?
Hmm? What is the ritual we're practicing?
Okay, so a classroom, you can
understand as the collective experience,
okay? A classroom happens when
everyone is participating in it.
Does that make sense? That's
why we take classroom alive.
So why would I be angry
if one of you is sleeping?
But why does that matter?
......
If you're sleeping,
what are you telling me?
... Yeah, it's not a classroom.
It's not real. This
discussion is not real.
It's pointless. You understand?
So that's what's happening here.
Their malemo singing, the ritual,
it's meant for everyone to recognize
that the religion is real.
It's more real than reality.
Okay? But if you're sleeping, you're
saying, no guys, this doesn't matter, okay?
What we're doing does not matter.
And therefore, what you're doing is,
you're not committing
violence on one person,
you're committing
violence on the community.
You're committing
violence on the religion.
You're insulting the forest.
You're insulting the god.
Does that make sense? And that's
the word for the worst crime.
Because reality happens.
This religion is only possible
if everyone believes that it is true.
If you're sleeping, it means
you don't think it's true.
And therefore, you are,
first of all, rejecting
the community, right?
You're telling everyone,
you're all idiots.
Okay? Second is that you might
endanger the community because
you're insulting the forest.
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
So for most of human history,
people take their religion
extremely seriously.
So seriously that they
think it's more real than
reality. As long as everyone
believes in it, it's true.
But if someone doesn't believe in it,
then we have to kill that person.
Because if he doesn't believe in it,
then it might cause our religion to die.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Any questions so far?
Any questions?
We're all clear, right? Okay?
And what I'm trying to show
you is the power of religion.
Okay? How once we have
the religious imagination,
we can create things that are
actually for us more real
than reality. Okay? So
that's the second thing that's different
about us from other human beings.
For most of human history,
we were spiritual.
Okay? We were spiritual meaning like
we believe like the world of spirits,
our soul, it exists.
Okay? Today the word we use is
materialistic. Materialistic.
And the idea of materialistic is this.
If we cannot see it, okay, it's not real.
Okay? God can't be real
because we can't find it.
The soul can't be real
because we can't measure it.
Imagination can't be real because
we don't know where it comes from.
Okay? Does that make sense? And obviously,
okay, obviously, this idea
of materialism is wrong.
How can you say the
imagination doesn't exist?
But unfortunately, we have structured
our society around this idea.
All of science, okay, when you go to
science class, they teach you this.
Okay? If it's real, you can measure it.
You can see it. You can feel it.
But for most of human history,
we didn't believe that.
We thought like, okay,
there is a spiritual world
and that matters just as much as reality.
Okay? In fact, it probably matters more
than reality. Okay?
So, this is making
sense, right guys? Okay.
Okay. For a month,
I sat every evening at the Kamal
Molo listening, watching, okay?
If I still had little
idea of what was going on,
at least I felt that ear of
importance and expectancy.
Every evening, when the
woman shut themselves up,
pretending that they were afraid
to see the animal in the forest.
Every evening, when the man
gathered around the fire,
pretending they thought
that the woman thought
that the drain pipes were animals.
Every evening, when the trumpet dropped,
the drain pipes imitated leopards
and elephants and buffaloes.
Every evening, when all this
make -believe was going on,
I felt that something very real and
very great was going on beneath it.
Something that everyone else
took for granted and about
which only I was ignorant.
Okay. Clearly, he does not
understand these people.
What word tells us he does
not understand these people?
He doesn't know what's going on.
Why? What word tells us this?
Excuse me? Why is he ignorant?
There's a word in here that tells us he
doesn't understand these people at all.
This word shows that
there's a chasm, okay?
A huge difference between
the pygmies and us.
What is this word? It's a
word that the pygmies use.
What word would the pygmies not use here?
They'd be insulted by this word.
What's the word? You use it
over and over again, right?
There's a word here that's insulting.
No. What word here
in this passage would the
pygmies find insulting?
No. What word here
is insulting? So if
another teacher comes into
my class and he says, wow,
your class is a lot of fun.
I'd be insulted. Why?
I'd be insulted. Why? No.
Wow, you guys have so
much fun in this class.
I've been insulted, why?
Excuse me? Yeah, this
is not studying, okay?
This is not serious academic work.
This is playing. It has no significance,
no meaning, right?
So what word implies that here?
It repeats itself over and over.
Pretending, right? Pretending.
We think they're playing.
What do they think?
We think they're pretending.
We think they're playing.
What do they think? They think
it's all true, do you understand?
For them, their religion is
more true than this world,
okay?
That's a power of the human imagination.
You can imagine a world, and this world,
as long as many of you
are imagining it together,
it's more true, more powerful,
more real than this world.
That's a power of religion, okay?
What we call the religious imagination.
And we'll see this over and over
again in human history, okay?
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
So we've been taught that
oh, you can't see it.
It must be pretending.
It must be make -believe.
But for most of human
history, for most people,
this is not playing.
This is not pretending. It's true.
It's real. It's what allows
us to be close to God,
okay?
God is real. This world
we live in, it's not real.
Okay? Does that make
sense, guys? All right.
Okay, so let's look at the last paragraph,
and then we'll finish for the day.
He went on to tell that
the pygmies called their malomo whenever
things seemed to be going wrong.
It may be that the
hunting is bad, he said,
or that someone is ill, or,
as now, that someone has died.
These are not good things,
and we like things to be good.
So we call out the malomo, and
it makes them good as
they should be, okay?
So this is very similar to the
shaman going into the spirit world
when things are bad, okay?
Things are bad because
the spirits are unhappy.
Normally, everything goes well
in our world, in our forest,
but at night when we are sleeping,
sometimes things go wrong
because we are not awake.
To stop them from going wrong.
Army ants invade the camp.
Leopards may come in and steal
a hunting dog or even a child.
If we were awake, these
things would not happen.
So when something big goes wrong,
like illness or bad hunting or death,
it must be because the
forest is sleeping and
not looking after its children.
So what do we do? We wake it up.
We wake it up by singing to it.
and we do this because we
want it to awaken happy,
then everything will
be well and good again.
So when our world is going well,
then also we sing to the forest
because we want it to
share our happiness, okay?
Do you understand? So this is like
them going to the spirit world
and communicating with the spirits.
So it's almost the same religion, okay?
Maybe the details are different,
but the idea is the same.
The idea is that we're all interconnected.
Animals, plants, humans, all the same.
This is not the real world.
The spirit world, the forest,
they're the real world.
And for us to maintain our health
and our happiness and our safety,
we must always communicate
with this other world
and make sure they're happy.
Okay, does it make sense? And
because of this belief,
it means we shouldn't go to
war with other people, okay?
Because then that causes mayhem
and chaos in the spirit world.
Our job is to maintain harmony
and balance in this world.
We're caretakers, okay?
It means we should not be
in conflict with each other.
We should be egalitarian.
We should be equal because
we're all from the same mother goddess.
We're all from the same
forest. We're all from...
woman shaman, okay?
It means we have to be artistic
because we have to celebrate
and worship the spirit world.
Does that make sense? So again,
for most of human history,
we were like this.
And even today, in a lot of cultures
around the world, they're still like this.
So now the question is,
what changed? Why do we have war?
Why do we have... Why
do we have hierarchy?
Why do we have patriarchy?
Why are men superior to women?
Why do some rich people
have all the power, okay?
This clearly goes against
this religion. And
what I will show you starting next
class is the beginning of a new religion
and how this new religion that
worships wealth,
power, and war conquered everyone, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay, any questions?
Before we break...
Anything you're unclear about?
Okay. Okay. Okay.