Okay, let's start class.
We're continuing the
United States Iran war.
As I've said in the previous class,
the United States will invade Iran.
We don't know when, it might be two years
from now, it might be six years from now,
okay, but eventually it will happen.
And in today's class,
I want to go over some of the reasons
why the United States will invade Iran.
And I believe that
there'll be three major reasons, okay?
The first major reason is the United
States must defend its empire.
Second major reason is that
the United States will be
pressured by its allies,
mainly Saudi Arabia and
Israel, into invading Iran.
And the third reason is the Israel lobby,
okay? So in today's class, I want to
explain to you what the Israel lobby is.
But first, I need you to
understand what Christianity is,
okay? So remember that Christianity,
it's a religion about a man,
Jesus, who we know very
little about, okay?
We think that he was born in 4 BCE,
and then
he died in 31 BC,
sorry, CE, Common Era.
Okay? So we know that he is
from a place called Galilee.
We know that the Romans crucified him.
And that's about it, okay?
What his believers say is that
he is God come to earth,
and he was preaching a gospel or a message
that God is returning, the
kingdom of heaven is coming.
And after he was crucified,
he was resurrected.
Okay? And then he went to heaven.
And what's really important is that
Jesus will eventually return,
okay? And this is called
the second coming.
Okay? This is the second
coming of Jesus, and when
he comes, he will bring heaven onto earth,
and we will all live forever in peace.
Okay. So that's the story of Jesus.
Then the question then is,
what is the story of Jesus?
Why this religion become so popular?
So popular in fact that
today about 2 billion
people believe in it.
Okay? It's the most popular, most
powerful religion in the world.
And at first, the appeal
of Christianity is
that it was a revolutionary religion
that promised a better world
to the world's oppressed.
Okay? So if you look
at the early people who
followed Christianity, it was slaves,
peasants, women.
Okay? People who were
marginalized in society.
And the idea of Jesus is that
a better world is coming where
everyone will be equal.
Okay? The meek shall inherit the earth.
So if you think about it,
Christianity is appealing
because it's a new world. Because what
it is, it's a free lottery ticket.
Okay? Does that make sense?
It's a lottery ticket.
It costs you nothing.
And hey, if it's right,
then you go to heaven.
Okay? So at first, Christianity was
an extremely revolutionary religion.
And its basic characteristics in the
beginning were it was revolutionary.
It was egalitarian. Okay?
It was anti -authority.
And it was anti -authority. And it was
anti -authority. And it was anti -authority. And it was anti -authority.
And so these individuals who
before were outcast from society,
okay, like criminals, Jesus promised hope,
salvation, and redemption.
Okay? So before, if you were a criminal,
there was really no way for you
to redeem yourself in society.
And Jesus is the promise of your salvation
and redemption. Okay? And that's why
it was so appealing to a lot of people.
It became so popular that
it became the official
religion of the Roman Empire.
Now, there's a problem.
Okay? Because remember,
Christianity is a revolutionary,
egalitarian, and anti -authority religion.
And now, it's become an empire.
So, you know, there's a problem.
And so, they had to develop new
theories to reinvent Christianity
as an establishment religion.
And as we discussed last semester,
the person who did it was Augustine.
Okay? Augustine.
Remember that last semester, we
read City of God and Confessions.
And City of God and Confessions,
it's really to adapt Christianity
as an establishment religion.
To reduce its revolutionary nature.
Okay? So, is this all making sense to you?
And one problem that
Augustine had was the
idea of a second coming.
Okay? That the world will end.
He had a major problem with
this idea for many reasons.
Okay? But the first reason is
that, you know, if the
world's going to end,
why do we have to do anything?
Why can't we just drink and drink?
And party and play video games every day?
Right? What's the point of working?
That's the first problem.
Right? The second problem is,
well, why is Jesus coming back?
It's because the world sucks.
Right? Well, who's in charge of the world?
The Catholic Church is
in charge of the world.
You understand? So,
Jesus is coming back to destroy the
authority of the Catholic Church.
That's not good. Alright?
So, for many reasons,
Augustine basically said,
okay, the second coming,
don't worry about it.
Okay? Jesus will come back
whenever he wants to come back.
But before he comes back,
we, the Catholic Church,
will take care of everyone.
Okay? Alright.
So, why is this important?
This is important because
from Augustine onwards,
we've had divergent
understanding of the world.
We've had divergent understanding
of what the second coming means.
Okay? For people who believe
in the second coming,
the term we use is premillennialism.
Premillennials. Okay? Because
the second coming promised
a thousand years of peace.
Okay. Premillennialism is this.
Okay? Pre means before.
Right? So, when Jesus comes back,
we're going to have a new world.
When he comes back, he will give us a
thousand years of peace and prosperity.
Okay? Do you understand?
Before he comes back.
Okay? When he comes back, he will give us
a thousand years of peace and prosperity.
And what Augustine said is, no, no, no.
No. That thousand years
is just a metaphor.
It's not actually going to happen. In
fact, it's already happened because
the Catholic Church is giving us this
thousand years of peace and prosperity. Okay?
So, he's called a millennialist,
which means no. Okay?
That thousand years is just a metaphor.
It's not really going to happen.
Okay? So, that's a second big idea.
Now, as we know,
because all power became
concentrated in the Catholic Church,
there's a rebellion against the
Catholic Church called the Reformation.
Okay? The Reformation.
And the idea of the
Reformation is
God did
not mean for his authority to
be established in the church,
to be held by priests.
God is meant to speak to all
of us through the Bible.
Okay? So, what the major difference
between the Catholic religion
and the Protestant religion,
is Catholics are not
allowed to read the Bible.
They don't read the Bible.
Whereas Protestants must read the Bible.
They must seek meaning and
guidance from their
interpretation of the Bible.
Okay? And because
of the Reformation,
you now have thousands,
tens of thousands of different
religions spawning up.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
So, you have different religions
and you have different descent.
So, let's look at England.
Okay? England. So, England is a king.
And before,
the Catholic Church was supposed
to have authority over the king.
And of course, the king did not like that.
So, he supported the Reformation and
he changed the Catholic Church into
something called the Anglican Church.
Okay? Or the Church of England, which
he would have authority over.
But once the Reformation started,
again, you are not
allowed to read the Bible.
And because of that,
you have thousands of new
religions coming up in the Bible.
But curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious
And eventually this led to something
called the English Civil War,
where the dissenters, the
Puritans, killed the king.
But then the king was reestablished.
And so this led to decades and
decades of fighting in England.
So one way that
the king tried to resolve this conflict
is by sending all these
dissenters to America.
Okay? To America.
And the idea is this.
These dissenters believe that
the Bible is a supreme authority.
The Bible asks us to do
certain things, okay?
Because it's written in the Bible. For
example, you're not allowed to drink.
You're not allowed to dance.
You're not allowed to have any fun.
You must focus on your
own spiritual improvement.
Okay? You're not allowed to have slaves.
And so... Because they
believed these things,
they were constantly in conflict
with the establishment,
okay? With people in power.
And so the king was like, guys,
if you really believe in
these things, go to America.
Why? Because there's nobody in America.
So you can build your
own kingdom of heaven.
You understand? Okay?
So this is the origin
of the United States.
The United States was founded
as a Christian nation.
Which put the Bible as
a supreme authority.
Okay? Does that make sense?
You guys probably don't know
this about the United States.
You think the United States,
it's a non -religious, secular,
multicultural nation that
believes in science, right?
That's what it looks
like from the outside.
But inside its soul, its history,
it is a Christian nation.
Dedicated. To achieving the
kingdom of God on earth.
Okay? And using the Bible
as the supreme authority
and guide to achieve
this kingdom on earth.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So... These people in America,
these are sinners, okay? One question that
they always ask themselves is...
Why isn't Jesus back yet?
Okay? The second coming.
Why isn't the second coming back yet?
And different people have
different explanations.
Okay? And so
from this group come two more groups.
Okay? You have some people
who are called the post -millennials.
Okay? And post -millennials believe that
Jesus will come back after
we establish a thousand years
of the Christian church in the world.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So we have to prove that
we are worthy of God.
God's not going to come back
and establish this for us.
We have to do it ourselves. Okay?
So these are people called post.
Which will say that Jesus will
come after the thousand years.
But then you have another group called...
Post. Dispensationalists.
I don't even know how to
spell this word actually.
Okay. Anyway,
dispensationalists are historic.
Okay? All right. So
now the pre -millennials are
split into two other groups.
So the historic pre
-millennials are people
who believe what the early
Christians believed, which is
that Jesus is going to come back.
Don't worry when he's coming back.
Just be a good person and
he'll come back eventually.
Okay? It's not up to us to ask
when he's coming back.
He's God. Okay?
He has a plan. He knows what he's doing.
Just be patient guys. Okay?
That's the historic pre -millennials.
And then you have another group
called the dispensationalists.
Dispensation -less pre -millennials.
Okay? And what they believe
is something different.
They believe that...
Oh. In the Bible,
if you read the Bible very, very closely,
it tells you how
and why Jesus will return.
Okay? What the Bible says is that
there must be a nation called Israel.
Okay? And Israel is a nation of Jews.
And then Israel has
something called the temple.
The temple. Because
that's where God resides.
Okay? It must have a temple.
And then what will happen,
according to the Bible,
is that the antichrist, okay, or Satan,
lives. Okay?
And then there'll be an antichrist, okay,
Satan, who will be the great deceiver.
He'll pretend to be God.
Okay? He'll pretend to be
Messiah, but he's really Satan.
Okay? And then he will launch a war
when
all the nations of the world
will try to attack Israel.
And at this point, Jesus will come back
and he will destroy the antichrist,
he will save Israel, and
he will usher in a
thousand years of peace.
Before... And then a thousand years
later, you'll have the last day.
The last judgment. Where
God will judge us to be
either worthy or not worthy.
If we are worthy, we'll live on forever.
If we're not worthy, then
we'll burn in hell forever.
Okay? Okay?
So there are different variations of this.
Prophecy, what they believe.
Okay? So in other words, the historic...
Historic premillennials.
What they believe about the coming
of Jesus is it's a promise.
Okay? Jesus promises to return.
He's God. He will keep his promise.
He's probably very busy
right now with other things.
So don't worry about it, guys.
Okay? Let's just be patient and
trust in Jesus.
Okay? That's what they believe.
But the dispensationalists...
Premillennials believe that
the prophecy, it's a plan.
Okay? It's something that
we must achieve to bring Jesus back.
And if we do what the
Bible tells us to do,
which is to say to have Israel
as a nation run by the Jews,
to have the temple,
and then to face the antichrist,
then Jesus will come.
Okay? And then the Jews will return. Okay?
Does that make sense? Okay.
Now, so
these are the four different
views of the end times.
Okay? You have the historic premillennials
who believe that Jesus
has promised to return.
Let's just wait, guys.
Don't worry about it.
You have the dispensationalists,
premillennials
who believe that we have to
work hard to bring Jesus back.
Okay? And then you have the amillennialists
who are like, okay, we're going to do this.
We're going to move back to where
Jesus curiously
curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious
curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious of the four different beliefs.
Even within each belief,
there are variations, okay?
Because again, there
are two billion people
who believe in Christianity, and
they all believe
something different, okay?
Does that make sense? All right,
are we clear about the
four different ideas?
Any questions? Okay, so,
okay, okay.
Okay, so you don't actually
have to remember this, okay?
But all I'm trying to show you is that
even within Christianity,
there's a debate, okay?
But there's a concern, an obsession
as to when Jesus will return
and how he will return.
Okay, does that make sense? All right, so,
so, this is important.
Now, most Christians,
most Christians don't believe in
dispensationalist premillennialism, okay?
In fact, most Christians believe
that dispensationalist premillennialism
is actually pretty evil.
Why? Why would it be evil?
We shouldn't, we should not,
we cannot believe in
dispensationalist premillennialism
because it's evil. Why?
As a Christian, why would
you think this is evil?
What's the problem with believing that
there's a plan in the Bible?
Why would that be anti -Christian?
Okay, so, this is hard, okay?
But the idea is that
with this plan, you're
trying to manipulate God.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay,
you're trying to force God to return.
And you shouldn't do that. If you
believe in God, then you will trust God.
And you will try your best to be a good person,
which is what the Bible asks you to do.
And when God returns, it's
none of your business, okay?
It's not our concern. So,
the dispensationalist
premillennialists are
an extremely controversial minority
within Christianity, okay?
Okay? Most Christians don't
actually believe this.
And they find that a lot of
these beliefs to be evil.
And maybe even blasphemous, okay?
You're insulting God with
this sort of thinking.
Okay, the problem is
that of all these groups,
the dispensationalist millennials,
premillennialists, are the most organized.
And they're the most fanatical.
They really believe
that this is true, okay?
We know that throughout history,
those who achieve their
objectives are people
who tend to be the most united and who
are the most fanatical in
achieving their objective, okay?
That's the first point.
Second point is that
this sort of belief
thrives... in a time of massive
uncertainty and inequality,
like the time that we are
living in today, where
inequality is growing, where there's
more instability and uncertainty.
So in other words, there
are more and more people who
believe in dispensationalist
premillennialism.
Does that make sense? Okay.
All right. So
why this is important is that
dispensationalist
premillennialists, as Christians,
have done a lot to cause
conflict in the Middle East.
Okay? So they're the ones
who are actively encouraging
conflict between the
Palestinians and the Israelis.
They're the ones who want
Israel and Iran to go to war.
Why? Why are they actively encouraging the
dispensationalist premillennialists to go to war?
Why are they encouraging conflict between
the Palestinians and the Israelis?
Why are they encouraging a
war between Iran and Israel?
Why would they want a war
between Iran and Israel?
Well, Israel is already back.
Why? Because it's part of the prophecy.
Do you understand? It's
part of the prophecy.
The prophecy is that
Israel must first be,
must be reconstituted as a nation.
Okay? This happened in 1948. And then
Israel must go to war with other nations.
Okay? Does that make sense? So
these Christians are actually
promoting war between Israel
and its neighbors.
Okay? Does that make sense?
All right. Okay.
So now the other thing,
is that after the Reformation, okay,
they developed a new theology
called Christian Zionism.
Christian Zionism. Okay?
What is Christian Zionism?
Christian Zionism is the belief
that as a Christian,
you must support Jews in
the return to Israel.
Okay? So,
because remember that
Israel as a nation was
only founded in 1948.
And then
basically in
about 70 CE,
the Romans burned down the temple.
Okay? So for about almost 2000 years,
really, the Jewish people have
not lived in, sorry, sorry, sorry.
The Jews were not in control of Israel.
Okay? For about 2000 years.
And there are Christians who believe
that it is our responsibility,
it is our duty to help Jews
take control over Israel.
Okay? And they believe this
for many different reasons.
So Christian Zionists, some may believe
that that's what the Bible says.
God promised Israel, to the Jews.
Okay? So
Christian Zionism intersects with
dispensationist premillennialism.
Okay? There are Christian Zionists who
believe that, okay, for Jesus to return,
we also, we need Israel back
and we need Israel to be in
conflict with the Middle East.
Okay? So in other words,.
The Middle East. The Middle East.
Okay..
Okay. All of them.
All of them. Okay? So,
so Christian Zionism,
I mean, you can make the argument
that it's a pretty evil idea.
Why? Because they're using
the Jewish people as a tool,
as a mechanism in order to
achieve what they believe,
which is the return of Jesus. Okay?
Does that make sense?
Because Christianity believes
that if Jesus returns,
then all Jews,
then Judaism as a religion
will cease to exist.
Two -thirds of all Jews
will die in the battle,
and the rest,
a third, will immediately
convert to Christianity.
Okay? So you can make the argument that
Christian Zionism, it's a pretty cynical,
and a pretty evil idea.
Okay? And then
from Christian Zionism, we
have the idea of Zionism.
Okay? And
Zionism is the belief among certain Jews
that, two things, okay?
One is that
the Jews are the chosen people of God,
and that Israel is a promised land.
And therefore,
Jews must return to Israel.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay? But what's important is,
before Christian Zionism came along,
Zionism was not, Jews
didn't really think this.
Okay? So it was the Christians who
supported this idea of Zionism.
And even when this idea came about, which
was about 20 years ago, it was
an extremely unpopular religion,
an extremely unpopular idea.
And the reason why is,
Jews didn't think they
were a race of people.
They felt they were a religion.
Okay? They felt that, okay,
I'm in Iraq.
Well, guess what? I'm an
Iraqi like everyone else.
I may have a different
belief, but I'm still Iraqi.
Okay? They didn't put,
the religion above their
nationality or their race.
Okay? Do you understand?
And Zionism is like, no,
being a Jewish person is a race.
And therefore, you must return to Israel.
Okay? The problem with all this is
that, in Israel,
Palestine, it was mainly Arab people.
Okay? So there were
very few Jewish people.
And in fact,
Zionism couldn't convince anyone
to come to Palestine.
Okay? But then of course,
the Holocaust happened.
And after the Holocaust,
many Jews start to go to Israel.
And in 1948,
they established the state of Israel.
Okay? And the Christian Zionists,
and the, the dispossessionists,
premillennials, were very happy
with the establishment of Israel,
because they feel that,
we've achieved the first step
in this plan to bring Jesus back.
Okay? Okay?
Does that make sense? Okay? Um,
So, to summarize, the
main message is this.
Okay? Here's what you need to know.
First is that,
there are many Christians who believe
that Israel and
the Jews must be used as a
tool to bring Jesus back.
Okay? That's the first thing.
Second thing is that,
America was founded as a Christian nation.
Therefore, its soul is Christian.
Its first leaders, were,
uh, Christians who believed
in Christian Zionism.
Their descendants now control
the military
and the foreign policy
apparatus of America.
Okay? The second thing, okay?
And the third thing is that,
uh, Israel, as a nation,
um, thinks
that it can use Christian Zionism in
order to advance its
geopolitical interest,
which is to basically, um, gain
control over the Middle East.
Okay? Do you understand? And
that's what's driving the
conflict between Israel
and Iran. Does that make sense?
Okay? What's driving the conflict
between Israel and Iran is,
America believes it has a
religious responsibility to
protect Israel against Iran.
In fact, if there's a war between Iran and
Israel, that's a good thing,
because it's gonna drive
this prophecy and the return of Jesus.
Okay? And
then, and people in Israel
are like, you know what?
If we go to war with Iran,
America is gonna fight for us.
So, why not?
Right? We don't have to fight this war.
America is gonna do it for us.
So, why not fight this war?
We lose nothing. We gain
everything from this war.
Okay? So, um, the idea is
that all this is driven
by a religious worldview,
understanding the world. Okay?
And over time,
this worldview is gonna
become more popular
in America. Okay?
Does that make sense? Right?
Okay, good. Any questions about this?
Anything that's not, that's
not clear about what I just,
what, what, what, what I just
explained? Do you mean
to clarify anything?
Okay. So, to explain what you just
said. Okay? So, why, like, do we,
like, do we get to,
to a nationality state?
In terms, in terms of,
like, the the the the
the the the the the the
the the the
the the the the the the the
the the the the the
both curious curious curious
curious curious curious
curious There's no race.
There's no race to the idea
of Christianity, right?
You can be Chinese and Christian.
You can be American and
Christian. It doesn't matter.
And that's what the Jewish
people say as well.
I can be Chinese and Jewish.
I can be American and Jewish.
Because being Jewish is a religion.
But the idea of Zionism is that
being a Jewish person is a race.
In fact, you are directly descended
from the Hebrews in the Bible.
Which is complete nonsense.
This is not true, okay?
So, Zionism is the main
political belief of Israel,
right? Why does Israel exist?
Because Israel is the promised land
that God gave to his chosen people.
And this was a promise that
dates back at least 3,000
years to the time of Abraham.
And it's written in the Bible.
Therefore, it must be true. Okay?
Does that make sense? Alright.
Any other questions? Okay,
that's a great question, okay? Alright.
So, I'm making the argument
that Christian Zionism
and
dispensationless premillenism will over time
become more popular religions in the world.
Because they are not
just in America. Okay?
And the question, and then
Charles asked like, well, why?
Okay. Let's go back to the
founding of Christianity.
Why did Christianity become so popular?
It became popular because
it was in the Roman Empire, okay?
At that time, there was
something called the Pax Romana.
Which meant the Roman peace.
Okay? Which meant that the
Romans controlled everything.
Therefore, there were no wars.
Therefore, there was no war.
People were at peace, right?
And you think that's a good thing, right?
The problem is that if there's peace,
then you have massive inequality.
Okay? Because war is a mechanism back
then of social mobility.
Right? War killed people.
And if war kills people, that creates
opportunities for the people who are alive.
But if there's no war, then
what happens is if I'm a rich
person, guess what, guys?
I become more rich.
If you're poor, what happens?
You become more poor. Okay?
So as a poor person, what do you think?
You think that life is hopeless.
Life is pointless. There's no future.
There's no hope, right?
And so Jesus comes along
and says, listen, if
you believe in me, then
I will bring the King of heaven onto earth
and I will destroy inequality.
Heaven will be the same. Okay?
So again, back then it was like this.
There was a free lottery ticket. Today,
we live in something
called the Pax Americana.
And the Pax Americana, same thing
where for the past 70 years, there's
been peace around the world, right?
Very few people have died. But all that
means really is that
inequality has increased.
Fewer and fewer people have money.
Okay? Guys, billionaires make no sense.
Do you understand?
Why should a few people
have all the money?
That makes no sense. Because
money is meant as
a mechanism of exchange
and transaction, right?
You use money, you
should spend your money.
If it's all in the bank,
what's the point of that?
Okay? So having
billionaires is a bad thing.
And if you go to America, you'll find
that there are many young people
who feel that life is pointless.
Okay? So they're looking for alternatives.
You understand? And
this idea of dispensationalist
premillennialism,
which is like what's happening right now
in Israel will lead to a better world,
that's kind of attractive to you.
You understand? Right?
Audience Member 2
Why is it that you're like this?
Well, because you're poor
and you're stuck being poor.
Guys, imagine you are a
delivery person in China, in Beijing.
Okay? You're like a kuai di yuan, right?
What hope do you have for the future?
Your life is pointless and hopeless.
No one's going to marry you.
Even if someone marries you, you're
going to have to live with them.
You can't have children because you can't
afford to have your children go to school.
You can't buy a house.
You can't afford anything.
You're stuck being a delivery person for
the rest of your life. Do you understand?
Do you know how many delivery
people there are in China?
Millions and millions. Okay? You have
millions and millions of young men
who have no hope in the future.
Right? Audience Member 2 Why
is it that you're like this?
Yes, because Jesus is coming.
And he's going to destroy
the world we live in.
Audience Member 2 Why is
it that you're like this?
Because you're a delivery person in China.
That's exactly right. Christianity
is a free lottery ticket.
It costs you nothing. And
if you win, you win big.
Okay? Audience Member 2 Why
is it that you're like this?
Because you're a delivery person in China.
You're stuck being a delivery person for the rest of your life.
Why is it that you're like this? Because
you're a delivery person in China.
Right? What does it cost you?
It costs you nothing, right? Okay?
Do you understand? That's why it
will become more popular over time.
Audience Member 2 Excuse
me? Audience Member 2
Right. So what you do
is you support America.
You support Israel. You
support the war against Iran.
Right? But you want more
conflict in the Middle East
because the conflict in the Middle
East will drive the prophecy,
right? Do you understand?
That's what you want. You want
more war. Audience Member 2 But
what good
does peace do you? Sorry to interrupt you
curious curious curious curious curious curious curious curious
Peace just means like tomorrow,
you'll still be poor and hopeless, right?
But war, it's an opportunity
for a new world.
Exactly, right?
So all this inequality is
making people much more extreme
and desperate, right?
Which will lead people,
more people to believe in
dispensationalist premillennialism, okay?
The government, of course,
does not want any instability.
But what can the government do about it?
You're absolutely right, okay? So the
government could provide social welfare
to poor people, but where
would the money come from?
Right. You understand?
Oh. Okay.
Fine. Okay, who's more dangerous to you?
A few rich people or
millions of poor people?
Millions of poor people.
No. Because they're not enough.
No, no, no, no, no.
A few rich people are much more dangerous
than millions of poor people, you understand?
Millions of poor people.
Millions of poor people united.
That's right, united, right?
Poor people don't know how to unite.
. That's right.
..
Yeah, but, but, but.
. Right, okay? Okay,
so does this make sense?
Okay? Right?
So this is the, so I mean it's hard
because this is religion, okay?
And we're not religious. I'm not
religious, you're not religious.
So we don't understand how
religious people think, okay?
But remember that on this planet
Earth, most people are religious.
And they take their religion
very, very seriously.
Okay? Do you understand? They're
willing to die for the religion.
Because they think that if I die
for my religion, I'll go to heaven.
Excuse me? Okay.
All right. So, so.
That's exactly right.
Do you understand? Okay?
All right. Because you're
not giving people any hope.
And religion gives people hope.
Okay. So, listen.
In the real world, the
poor will always lose.
The rich will always win.
No matter what happens.
That's right. That's
why they're poor. Okay.
Okay. Okay. Okay.