Good morning. So
today we start the Bible,
which will be the final unit
before the semester break.
Hopefully this will be the most
interesting section we do.
It's certainly the most important, because
the Bible is the most important book ever.
And it is driving a lot,
it has driven a lot of history, and
it's driving a lot of history today.
So if you want to fully understand
the conflict in the Middle East,
what's happening between Israel and Iran,
what's happening in
Palestine, you cannot do so
without a full understanding of the Bible.
At the same time, the Bible is,
because it's so important,
the ideas around it
are very controversial.
There are billions of
people around the world who
believe the Bible is the Word of God.
It's Holy Scripture.
Every word in the Bible comes
to us from the divine,
the divinity himself.
And obviously, that's not what I believe.
More so, I'm going to make
arguments in this class
that go against not only the
traditional understanding of the Bible,
but also the mainstream academic
understanding of the Bible.
So to be fair,
to you,
I want you to be very
skeptical of what I say.
Come to class with doubting my authority,
doubting my understanding of the Bible.
So feel free to challenge me, and I
want you to challenge me, because
what I will say in this class
will be extremely controversial.
Okay? So, let me give
you a brief introduction.
I'm going to give you a brief introduction
to the Bible. And then I'll explain some of the history behind the Bible.
Okay? And this overview
is going to be very broad,
very general. But
it will help structure our understanding
of the Bible for the next few classes.
Okay? All right. So the Bible.
The Bible is Greek for books.
And it really means library.
So the first thing you need
to understand is the Bible,
it's a collection of different things.
Different works by many
different authors. So
there's no worldview or consistency
or continuity in the Bible.
You can find whatever you want in the
Bible, because it's such a, it's a library.
It's a huge collection of ideas.
There's about 2,000 pages. Okay?
So there's very few people who
actually read the Bible in its entirety.
There are people who might read, there's
a section of the Bible. Okay? But
most people will receive
their understanding of
the Bible from authorities
like priests or rabbis.
Okay? The Bible itself is
divided into two major sections.
The first section is what
we call the Hebrew Bible.
And so this was originally
written in Hebrew.
And this was, this is the major,
this is the book of the Jews.
Okay? What do the Jews believe?
They believe in the Hebrew Bible.
The Hebrew Bible itself is divided
into three major sections.
The first is, so, so
the Hebrew term for the
Bible is the Tanakh.
Okay? So you may hear some
people say the Tanakh.
It just means the Hebrew Bible. Okay?
The Tanakh is T and K.
And this is the Hebrew
term for certain ideas.
The T stands for Torah or teachings.
So this is the laws of
the Jewish tradition.
Okay? For example, the Ten Commandments.
Right? Second is N,
which means prophets. Or,
and the prophets themselves are
divided into minor and major.
So in Rome, the people
who are most admired are the generals.
Right? Julius Caesar, Pompey.
In Greece, the people who are
most admired are the Jews.
The people who are most admired are
the poets, Homer and the playwrights.
In the Jewish tradition,
the people who are most
admired are the prophets.
These individuals who
speak the truth of God.
They're social critics.
And they're people who
challenge the authority of the
kings in order to promote the laws
and teachings of God.
Okay? Does that make sense?
The prophets are the people
who are most admired in
the Jewish tradition.
And the third RK is writings.
So basically, things that don't really
belong in teachings and prophets,
but which have some cultural or religious
significance to the Jewish people.
Okay? So this is the Hebrew Bible.
And then we get to the New Testament, which
is something that only Christians believe.
Alright? So
Jewish people do not accept anything
in the New Testament. The New
Testament calls
the Hebrew Bible the Old Testament.
Okay? Why?
Because the Old Testament
is the promise of salvation.
Right? The promise of Jesus Christ.
The New Testament is the
promise of salvation.
The New Testament is the deliverance or the
fulfillment of this promise in Jesus Christ.
Okay? It's the coming and
the work of Jesus Christ.
The New Testament itself is
divided into many different works.
It's a lot smaller than the Old Testament.
So there are the Gospels.
The Gospels is Greek for the good word.
And the good news is
that Jesus is on earth.
And he's here to deliver us
from our sins and our suffering.
There's letters, mainly
by someone named Paul.
And these are the work of Jesus'
apostles after the death of Jesus.
They go around the world. They
promote the Gospel of Jesus,
the good news. Okay?
And this is about what they do.
And then there's something called,
there's some other books as well.
The major one is called Revelation,
which is about the end of the world.
And it's the idea of the second coming.
How even though Jesus is dead,
he will return and he will bring peace,
eternal peace to the world.
Now, from the Bible,
in the interpretation of
the Bible comes the Koran.
And this is the basis for Islam.
Okay? So eventually we'll do all three.
The Hebrew Bible.
The New Testament. And the Koran.
But we'll start with the Old Testament,
the Hebrew Bible. Okay?
So, the Old Testament, the Hebrew
Bible, is what we'll start with.
And to do so, I will have to
teach you a lot of history.
And this history will be extremely broad.
Okay? But over time, I
will be more precise.
I will go into specific details about this history
in order for you to better understand the Bible.
Okay? There are three ideas
about the Hebrew Bible
that Jews believe,
that Jews today believe,
which are not true.
Okay? The first idea is the Hebrew Bible,
the Jewish religion, has
always been monotheistic.
Meaning, the Jews have
always believed in one God.
His name is Yahweh. And
he is the God of the Jews since Abraham,
who is the patriarch of all Jewish people.
Okay? That's what Jews believe.
I will show you this is not true.
In the beginning, Jewish people,
like everyone else, were polytheistic.
Okay? Polytheistic is a modern idea
that has been used for a long time.
And it has been retroactively
put back into Jewish history.
Okay? So that's the first
myth that I will correct.
The second myth that I will correct is
that
Jewish history, or the Jewish religion,
has been continuous for
at least 3,000 years.
Possibly 4,000 years. Okay?
And what I will show
you is that's not true.
And so there have been many
major changes to the religion.
And these changes are so drastic that
you can argue these are
very different people.
Okay? So the Israelites,
the people who founded the religion,
are very different from the
people we call Jews today.
And I will show you why
in the next few classes.
Okay? That's one really important
idea you need to understand.
The history of the Israelites
and the Jewish people are not continuous.
Alright? Okay?
Does that make sense? Okay.
Any questions so far?
Are you guys following along?
Okay. Um...
Yeah. So...
And the last idea is...
The Bible, or the Hebrew Bible,
it's a historical record.
And what I will show you is...
We've been trying for at least 300 years,
200 years, to prove that the
Bible is a historical record.
There are archaeologists
who have spent fortunes,
their entire lifetimes, looking
for things like Noah's Ark.
Looking for people like Moses.
Can't find them. Okay?
And this tells us,
pretty conclusively, that
the Bible is not a historical record.
It is a work of our imagination.
Okay? It is a literary work.
Now, it's a very powerful literary work.
And that's what explains its relevance
and its power today.
Okay? I will explain why it's powerful.
But I want you to remember,
it's not a historical work.
It is a literary work.
It's a work of our collective imagination.
Alright? Okay. Now,
I'm going to talk a little about the
broad history of the Israelite people.
Okay? Um...
So, in the Bible, what it tells you is...
Maybe about 2000 BCE,
there's a man named Abraham.
And he's from the city of Uruk.
Okay? In Mesopotamia.
Or is it Ur? Okay, it's one of the two.
Sorry. Um...
And then God, Yahweh,
thought Abraham was the
best man in the world.
So, God, Yahweh,
made a covenant with Abraham and said,
You are the most righteous and
dignified man I have
ever seen in the world.
And I will make you a father
of a new nation called Israel.
Okay? And these people will become,
eventually, the Israelites.
And the greatest king of the
Israelites is named David.
And then David...
And then God says to David,
David, you are the greatest
man I've ever seen.
I love you as you love me.
Therefore, I will make your house,
the house of David, eternal.
Okay? You, the house of David,
will reign over Israel
for all of eternity.
I will make Israel into
the mightiest of nations.
Okay? So, that is what
it says in the Bible.
The historical record is
a lot more complicated.
Alright? So,
let's start in the year 1200 BCE.
Okay? And this is towards
the end of the Bronze Age.
Right? We're about to enter the Bronze
Age collapse, which lasts about 400 years.
At this time, let's look at the world.
Israel is in a place called the Levant.
And the Levant has always been important
because, as we discussed
in previous classes,
Levant was one of the first
centers of agriculture.
So, Jericho is in the Levant.
But it's also important
because the Levant is
where three major
civilizations and empires meet.
Okay? They are the crossroads
or the nexus of empire.
These three empires are Egypt, which
again, for most of its human history,
has been the wealthiest and
the most powerful nation.
Okay? Over here is Mesopotamia,
which is the cradle civilization.
This is where
human civilization first
developed mathematics,
writing, astronomy, architecture.
Okay? And up here are
the Hittites or Anatolia.
Anatolia, again, is extremely wealthy.
So, the Levant is sort of sandwiched
between three extremely aggressive,
wealthy, and
powerful nations that are very powerful.
And the Hittites are extremely
advanced and sophisticated. So,
the Levant has
always been a colony
of either Egypt or Anatolia.
It's not been very
independent for very long.
And it can't be because
it's at the edge of empire.
But because of its position, okay,
the Levant is what we call a nothing part.
Or a meeting place.
So, every culture, every language,
every religion that
was imaginable at this
time met in the Levant.
Okay? Mainly for trade purposes.
Right? Because, again, Egypt and
Mesopotamia are extremely wealthy.
The Levant, you can go across the
Mediterranean into all of Europe
and into Northern Africa.
Okay? So, the Levant was really the
center of the world for the Hittites.
For most of its history. And so, it was
a meeting place, mainly for traders.
Right? At this time,
Levant was divided into
different sections.
A province called Canine
was a province of Egypt.
And Canine was special to Egypt
because the Egyptians loved two things.
They loved wine. They loved olive oil.
And the Levant was very good
at harvesting both wine,
good wine, and olive oil.
So, but
the Egyptians didn't really
like to go outside Egypt.
So, the people administrating the
Levant were local elites tied to Egypt,
but also foreign mercenaries.
And these foreign mercenaries
were from as far as Greece.
Okay? And we know this because
we've discovered Greek pottery
that dates back to this period.
Okay? These foreign mercenaries would then
intermarry with the local women.
Because as you can imagine,
these are young males.
Okay? You also had lots
of nomads living in the Levant
because of Arabia.
Right? Okay?
Lots of nomads. People
we call the Bedouins.
You also had people living in the hills.
All of the Levant, the hill people.
And you have these cities. Okay?
The Canaanites. You also
had, believe it or not,
Egyptian priests living in this area.
Why would they live in this area?
Well, because they had a certain religion
that
was considered heretical
or controversial in Egypt.
So they had to leave to
practice their religion.
Or maybe they were a
little bit more religious.
Or maybe they were priests who
got into a political struggle.
And as such, they were
exiled to the Levant.
Okay? So, does that make sense?
The Levant, it's not
at this point a nation.
At this point, it's
really a meeting place.
A melting pot of cultures,
languages, and religions.
It's as diverse as can be.
And historically, this has
always been the case. Right?
Then, what happened, of course,
is the Bronze Age collapse.
The thing about the Bronze
Age collapse is you
have this massive migration
of people looking for food.
Right? These are called the Sea Peoples.
They're basically like pirates. And
there are these massive waves of
Sea People attacking the Hittites.
Attacking the Levant and attacking Egypt.
And again, these are like refugees. Okay?
This is a forced migration.
And they're trying to feed their families.
They basically overrun the Hittites.
They destroy the cities of the Levant.
And they almost destroy Egypt.
But Egypt, because it's so wealthy,
it's able to hold off the Sea People.
Eventually, what happens
is, the Sea Peoples
and Egypt come to an agreement and say,
Listen, stop attacking us and
we'll give you land in the Levant.
You can settle down there.
You can grow your own food.
You can feed your families. Okay?
And this place is what we call Philistia.
And these people are
called the Philistines.
So these are basically the Sea Peoples.
Mainly Greek, actually.
There are a lot of Greeks
among the Philistines.
But this creates a problem
for everyone in the Levant.
Because now you have a foreign presence
that
is very aggressive and expansionist.
Okay? So now,
the people in the Levant
need to come together
and fend off this threat
from the Philistines.
They also have these neighbors as well.
These other cultures. These other people.
They keep on attacking them. Okay?
So these are extremely diverse people.
And so
what they agree to do is elect a
king to lead them in war
against the Philistines.
And this person is named Saul. King Saul.
Alright? And King Saul
is a very good king.
He's a very good military
leader. He's helping the people.
He's helping the people in the Levant fend
off the Philistines and aggressive neighbors.
Okay? So this is a military alliance.
King Saul employs a lot of mercenaries.
And one of these mercenaries
is named David. David.
David is an extremely capable,
charismatic soldier.
Who develops a following.
David, as you can imagine,
because he's very charismatic,
is also very ambitious.
And eventually, he has
a falling out with Saul.
Okay? David is Saul's best
general, best soldier.
But David is too ambitious.
And Saul sort of suspects David.
So what David does is he runs off
and joins the Philistines.
Okay? He's not fighting
for the Philistines.
What's really important
for us to understand,
and I know it's a hard concept.
But borders and alliances
and allegiances are
extremely fluid at this time.
If it benefits me, I'll fight for you.
But if it doesn't benefit
me, then I'll betray you.
Okay? There are different
factions within all alliances.
Okay? So the Philistines are divided
among different ethnic groups.
The people in the Levant are divided.
The people in the Levant are divided
into different political factions.
You have these hill people.
You have these nomads.
You have these foreign mercenaries.
And they're fighting
for different reasons.
So these alliances are always shifting.
Okay? So David goes off and
fights for the Philistines.
King Saul and his sons are
eventually killed in battle.
And David sees a political opening.
So he turns back into Levant.
And he starts to politically
maneuver to be the new king.
Okay? And
his power base is in
a place called Hebron,
or in south the Levant.
But the house of Saul is still around.
And so there's a civil war now going on.
And eventually David triumphs.
And then David's able
to unite these people.
And he creates a new nation
called the Philistines.
Israel. All right?
And then Israel is able,
under David's leadership,
is able to
basically put down
any aggressions from its neighbors.
And they're able to build an empire.
A small empire. Okay?
Nowhere near Egypt.
But it's an empire. All right?
So. This is what we know from
the archeological record.
But David is so charismatic that
when he dies, his son Solomon is not
able to hold the empire together.
So what happens is Israel
divides into the northern kingdom
and Judah.
Which is where the house of David is.
Okay? Now again,
the Levant is a very
important strategic location.
So as these empires,
major empires, start to
consolidate the power,
they want to take over the Levant.
Okay? So the Assyrian Empire comes in
and destroys the northern kingdom.
And then
eventually the Babylonian
Empire will come in.
And destroy Judah.
Okay? The Babylonians will
take the Israel elite.
Basically the royalty.
And force them to go to Babylon.
Where they will be held as hostages.
Or captives. Eventually,
what will happen next is
the Persian Empire will come
and defeat Babylon.
And what they do next is very interesting.
They decide they will
release these Israelite elite.
Have them return to Jerusalem and Israel.
And have them govern the Levant.
Based on. And have them govern the Levant.
Okay? Does that make sense? And
it is only at this point
that we get the term Babylon.
And the Jews. Okay?
This is a Persian idea.
The Jews. Before they were
called the Israelites.
And this is about 500 BC.
Okay? 500 BC. And
now we have a radical
departure from the tradition.
Okay? And so I'll explain
three major differences.
And then I'll explain, I'll go into detail
about these differences in future classes.
Okay? The first major
difference is Israel.
Under the Israelites. It's
a polytheistic religion.
They have one god, Yahweh.
But Yahweh. But they also
have a pantheon of gods.
Which is the same. Which is
true for every other religion.
Right? There's a pantheon of
gods. Yahweh is at the top.
But they also celebrate other gods.
Like Baal and Asherah.
Okay? We know because they're
written down in the Bible.
So we know at this point, Israel is
still a polytheistic religion. But
after the Persian Empire
returns them to Judaism,
they became a monotheistic religion.
Or the beginnings of a
monotheistic religion.
Why? Because when
the Jews are released from
captivity by the Persians.
Their religion merges with
that of the Persian religion
called Zoroastrianism.
And Zoroastrianism is
a dualistic religion.
Okay? Meaning there's good and evil.
So that's the first major difference.
At the beginning,
the Bible was very much
a polytheistic religion.
And then after the
Israelites became the Jews,
it became monotheistic.
Okay? Second big difference is this.
Second big difference is during this time,
the people with the power
in Israel were the kings.
Okay? The monarchy. But
after 500 BCE,
the Jews decided they
didn't want any kings.
And they couldn't have kings because
their overlords are the Persians.
Right? So the center of
power became the priesthood.
Okay? The priests.
The people with the absolute
authority are the priests,
not the kings.
There are kings, but the kings
are not subservient to the priests
who speak on behalf of Yahweh.
Okay? Because now it's
a monotheistic religion.
And then there's one other difference.
The other difference is, remember,
at this point they're
polytheistic and they're kings.
Okay? Which means they are tolerant.
They're welcoming of
other religions, right?
Because you're polytheistic.
But also, as kings,
you need to establish diplomatic
alliances with other countries,
who have different religions. Right?
So when you marry someone from
another political dynasty,
you also are marrying into that religion.
Does that make sense? So
Israel, under the kings,
is a very tolerant religion.
But if you're run by priests,
right, you become intolerant.
Because you insist that
your religion is the best.
Okay? And
that's why, after the
Persians lost control,
and the Greeks came in to the Levant,
this is the Seleucid Empire.
Okay? The Jews rebelled
against the Greeks.
Because the Greeks were polytheistic, and
the Jews considered themselves monotheistic.
Okay? They refused to
acknowledge the culture
and the religion of the Greeks.
And then things got really
bad when the Romans came in.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay, so this is the history
of the Jewish people.
Up until the birth of Jesus.
Okay? Any questions so far?
Do you guys understand what's happening?
Excuse me? Okay.
So how did the Bronze Age collapse?
Okay, we talked about this. Okay?
We don't know why it collapsed.
The, um, the, um, the, um, the, um, the, um,
the, um, the, um, the, um, the, um, the, um, the,
um, the, um, the, um, the, um, the,
um,
the, um, the, um, the, um, the,
um, the, um, the, the, the,
the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
the, this
area. If you go east to Mesopotamia,
where the Assyrian and the
Babylonians are, they're fine.
And it's the Bronze Age Collapse
that allow the Assyrians
and the Babylonians to eventually become
world powers. So
the Bronze Age Collapse was
not a global phenomenon,
it was a localized phenomenon
to the Mediterranean.
But why the Bronze Age
Collapse is important is
because the Bronze Age Collapse
will give us Greek civilization,
Homer and Plato, okay?
It will also give us the Bible, right?
Because if you look at this history,
Israel would not have come into being
without the Bronze Age Collapse.
Egypt or the Hittites would
continue to control the Levant.
And it's important to
understand the Greeks
and the Bible are the basis, the two
fundamental pillars of Western civilization.
You understand? That's why Westerners are
so fascinated by the Bronze Age Collapse.
Because in their minds,
the Bronze Age Collapse is part of God's
divine plan or design to
create classical Greece
and the nation of Israel
so that
his vision for the world can
be achieved through Jesus.
Okay? Yep?.
Yeah, that's fine. Yeah. .
Okay. So that's a good question.
So the argument I'm trying to make up,
maybe it's not a good argument, but I'm trying to make it clear to you is,
the Bible says Abraham is a
patriarch of the Israelites.
But the historical record,
the archaeological record is,
we barely have evidence of David.
We have absolutely no evidence
of anything before David.
Okay? So
I think David is the founder of
the nation of Israel, not Abraham.
Next class, I will explain to you why.
They constructed this mythology.
Okay? All right?
But first, I want to give
you a broad overview.
All right? Next class, I will
explain to you where these ideas,
Abraham and Moses, came from.
It will make sense when
I explain it to you.
Okay? But do you guys have any
more questions before I go on?
. Yep..
..
..........
.
..
... a
a a a
And at this point, there are
many divergent religions.
Okay? But
what happens is Babylon
conquers Jerusalem,
and then the Jews are sent in exile.
So now the religion is sent overseas.
And the religion is detached
from the culture and the people.
Does that make sense? And what
we know is when you do that,
when you detach the religion and
you put it into a place
that has no interactions with
the local people and the culture,
it becomes much more fanatical.
It becomes much more
focused and fanatical.
Do you understand? Okay?
Do you understand?
Because if it's in Israel
and there are different cultures,
the religion has to be tolerant
and pleased.
And to be to these different
factions among the people.
Okay? Does that make sense? But
once this religion goes off to Babylon,
it's now divorced from the
people, from local reality.
So the elite can design it in a way that
they think is most appropriate.
And we call that fanatical.
Does that make sense? So
an example of this, okay,
it's a bad analogy, but
maybe this will help you.
Right now you're not sure
what it means to be Chinese.
So you want to change to
Chinese. You're Chinese, but
Chinese in China is a very fluid,
very diverse identity.
When you go off to America, right,
then you have much more concrete,
much more clear understanding
of what it means to be Chinese.
Your Chinese identity
becomes much more formed.
Does that make sense? The
same thing with religion.
Within Israel itself,
the religion is constantly changing.
It's very fluid. But when
they're off to Babylon,
they have to use the religion to
survive as a people, as an identity.
And so it becomes much more formed,
much more concrete.
Does that make sense? And then
what happens is, now
that it's much more concrete,
it now interacts with Zoroastrianism,
which is the religion of the people.
The Persians. And
at this point, the religion
becomes basically what it is today.
Okay? So I'm sorry,
I don't think I've explained
this clearly to you, but
I want to wait until we
get to this period, okay?
Right now I'm just giving
you a broad overview.
Any more questions before I begin?
Before I continue?
Okay. Thank you.
All right. Now I want to talk
about the Bible, okay? Because
the Bible
is the mythology.
It's a collective memory
of the Israelites.
Okay? And so
I'm going to discuss why the Bible
was first created in this class.
And what I will explain to you is,
the Bible was first created in
order to explain the person
with the person with
the person with the person with the person
the person with the person
with the person with the person
with the person with the person with the
person with the person with
the person with the person
throne okay usually kingship
requires ruthlessness
but
the problem is when
you're ruthless you have
a legitimacy problem right
so the way that most
Kings resolve this issue
is by sponsoring
writings or an
apology to explain why he or she is king
and the answer usually is because
God willed it so because
I had no choice in the matter I'm not
ambitious I was not at all ambitious
but
the circumstances forced my hand to
save my people to do God's work I had to kill
my brother I had to kill my enemies even
though I myself am NOT a violent person okay
that's usually how the apology goes okay
so remember back at this point the very
idea of writing it is new
it's a new technology
but it's also very expensive technology
meaning you need to buy the materials okay
which which are rare but
you also need the people
to be able to write okay
and they're also very
expensive you basically need it
to be able to support a team of
scribes to create any work of fiction
so writing back then is like moving on to
the next chapter of the book so you need to be able to support a team of scribes to create any work of fiction so writing back then
is like we movie making today
it's a very expensive endeavor
that was usually sponsored by the king
in order to justify or
explain why he is king in order to
create legitimacy doesn't make sense
so
the Bible was created first
as an apology for David
and
explains why the house of house of
David is now in charge of Israel
but as we know the Bible is
a very expensive thing and
it's not a very expensive thing and it's
not a very expensive thing and it's not a very expensive thing and it's not
a very expensive thing and
it's not a very expensive thing and
it's not a very expensive thing a very expensive
thing a very expensive thing a very expensive
thing a very expensive
a very expensive a very
expensive a very
expensive a very expensive
a very expensive a very
expensive a very
expensive a very expensive are
in charge of the Bible, the priest class,
are interested in promoting their own
interests. Mainly in the points of ritual.
It doesn't make sense?
Like, what are rituals?
Why do we need them? Why
are priests important?
Then you have people at this point,
in the Babylonian captivity, looking back
at the history of Israel,
and trying to figure out why
the house of David collapsed.
And their answer is
because the Israelites refused
to follow the will of God.
Because the Israelites became
polytheistic, or they became immoral.
Okay? Does that make
sense? In other words,
the Bible at this point are
divided into like four
major factions, or schools.
The school that supports
the house of David,
the legitimacy of the house of
David, is called the J school.
Okay? The J school.
Don't worry about this.
I'll explain to you next
class what these things mean.
The people who support the northern
kingdom as legitimate house
of Israel is called the E school.
E. The school
that supports the
power of the priest is
obviously called the P school.
Okay? For priest. And then
the school that tries
to go back in history
and examine why
Israel fell, and
which believe it's because
the Israelites betrayed God, these
people are what we call the D school.
Okay? The D school.
So E, G, P, and D.
And these are just four
of the major schools.
There are other schools
as well. All right?
And so at this point, the Bible is,
divided into like four major schools,
or documents, controlled
by different factions.
When the Persians take over,
okay, they insisted, you
need one religion, guys.
You need one document. And so
all four were put together
to create the Bible. Well,
the way they did it was very interesting.
All they did was just put them together.
Okay? You understand? So,
you have, so if you read the Bible,
it's like A, B, C, D.
A, B, C, D.
Okay? So one line is from the E school,
the next line is from the J school,
the other line is from the P school.
It's very confusing to read.
If you don't understand this history, it
is impossible for you to read the Bible.
I'm not sure if you've tried to
read the Bible, it's not readable.
Okay? So why would they do this?
Why would they just put all four texts together,
about the Bible, without major editing
or revisions? Why?
Do you guys know?
Why would they do that? It's very, I mean,
they just made a complete
mess of the Bible.
But why would they do that? Okay.
Okay. So let me explain.
The first major reason is most people
didn't read or write back then.
So, the Bible itself didn't really matter.
What mattered was the oral
explanation of the Bible,
controlled by the priest class.
Does that make sense? The
people didn't read the Bible.
So, how the Bible was actually
written was not that important.
It was important for the priest
to have access to the Bible,
but the people didn't
actually read the Bible.
That's the first reason. The
second, more important reason is
because the Bible is political
real estate. And I want you
to remember this idea, okay?
It's the most valuable political
real estate in the world.
Everyone wants to be in the Bible because
to be in the Bible gives you legitimacy.
It gives you power. Right?
So, if you're a king and
you have four sons who
all want to be king, well,
your best solution is to divide the
kingdom among the four sons, right?
Same with the Bible. You have four extremely
powerful schools and political factions.
So, the best way to resolve the issue
is just to say, listen,
we'll put you all in the
Bible together, okay?
Like, and you, when you merge them,
it's a lot easier
than if you just try to do it by order,
okay? Like, E school goes first, then J
school, then P school, then D school, okay?
They just put them all
together. Does that make sense?
Okay, so, this is a very important idea.
The Bible is the most, is the most valuable
political real estate in the world.
Everyone wants to be in there. And,
what ideas are, you can find in there,
will ultimately shape human history.
Okay? Any questions so far?
Before I, before I continue?
All right. So, the last thing
I want to talk about today is,
is, is the apology of David, which
is the beginning of the Bible.
Okay, um,
so, when
kings come to power, they have
three major problems, right?
The first major problem is legitimacy.
What gives you the right to be king?
Okay? Second problem
is the idea of identity.
Okay? And, this is a huge
problem for the Israelites,
because the Israelites,
it's a multicultural entity.
You have people speaking different
languages, different cultures.
They practice different cultures,
they practice different religions.
So, now you need to create an identity
that everyone accepts. Okay?
The third thing is differentiation.
You need, not only for
these people to get along,
but you need them, you need
to get along with each other.
you need to get them to
divorce their former culture.
Does that make sense? Because you
have Egyptian priests in there.
And, you have to tell these Egyptian
priests, you are now Israelites, and you're not Egyptian anymore.
Okay? And, the example
that we use for this,
um, is Augustus Caesar,
and the writing of the Inead.
Okay? Remember, the Inead, it's a
book about a character named, Ineos.
And, it provides political
legitimacy to Augustus Caesar,
because Augustus Caesar is a
direct descendant of Ineos,
who is the founder of Rome.
Also, what the Inead said is,
Augustus Caesar is the end
point of Roman history.
Everything before Augustus
Caesar led to him.
Augustus Caesar is like the Jesus of Rome.
Okay? He is the salvation, he
is the redemption, of Rome.
Okay? That's what the Inead does.
Okay? Second thing about the Inead is,
it creates a new Roman identity, that
focuses on piety,
loyalty, over liberty.
Remember the problem, for Augustus
Caesar was, Romans didn't like kings.
Well, now he's a king. So,
how do you get people to obey?
Well, you tell them, piety is
more important than liberty.
Alright? The third idea,
is, the Inead,
remember, it's anti -Greek.
The problem for Rome at
that time was, Greek culture was
vastly superior to Roman culture.
And, so
a lot of Romans were adopting Greek
cultural practice, like Mark Anthony.
And so, the Inead said,
Greek culture is like a Trojan horse.
If you let into your city,
Greek culture will, corrupt
you, and destroy you.
Okay? So, guess what guys?
Every king, has to,
resolve all three issues.
Okay? Legitimacy, identity,
and differentiation.
And that's what David, is
trying to do, with the Bible.
Okay. So, let's, so I'll
give you, three examples.
Three stories from the Bible,
that, are, illustrate,
David's, quest for legitimacy.
Next class, we'll talk about,
identity and differentiation.
And how the Bible achieves that.
Okay? But, this class,
I want to focus on, legitimacy.
So, now that, David is king,
a lot of people don't
think he's legitimate.
Why? Because he, ruthlessly, is, a king.
David, tried to, usurp
the throne, from Saul.
Right? Saul is the king that
everyone, picked, or elected.
And he was a good king.
He was good at war.
He was someone that, most people,
liked. And David, took,
stole the throne, from him.
Okay? So now, what is David's problem?
Now that he has a throne. Others
will try to steal it from him.
Right? Because, if you David,
are, if you set the precedent, if you,
um, steal the throne, then others are now,
empowered to steal the throne from you as well.
Okay? So the first thing the Bible
does, the apology for David does, is,
show us, David,
loved Saul. He was not at all ambitious.
He cared, only, for the
well -being, of his king.
Okay? And so one story,
that illustrates this.
There are actually many, many
stories in the Bible, that does this.
But one story that
illustrates this, is this.
So, Saul thinks David's
trying to kill him.
So he's, chasing after
David, with his army.
Okay? Trying to kill
David and his followers.
One, one day, Saul is alone in a cave,
praying to God, for deliverance.
David sees Saul alone, and
he sneaks up behind Saul.
Then, he takes his sword, and cuts,
David's hand. And David, but
David, a piece of Saul's clothing.
Okay? And then David disappears.
Saul leaves the cave, and then
David rushes to him and says,
Saul, my king, I beg of
you, give me a second.
Let me explain to you. Back then,
in the cave, I could've killed you.
This is a piece of clothing to
prove I could've killed you.
But I didn't. Because I love you.
Because I'm loyal to you.
I would never kill you.
And then Saul says, Oh,
this is, this is proof,
that David is going to kill Saul. you
were you never meant to kill me okay
and this is a story in the Bible
obviously this story
cannot be true okay but
this is what the Bible trying to
do it's trying to first show us
that
David is not all ambitious in fact the
entire apology of David is focused on
the lack of ambition of David okay
so that's the first story let's look at the
second story okay the second story is this
soul is dead and
his son was a young man comes
into a throne there's a
gentleman Abner okay Abner
who was loyal to Saul but now
that soul is dead and
David is very popular among the people
Abner sees the political winds changing
and Abner tries to align
himself with David so
Abner writes a long letter
to David and saying listen
I will swear loyalty to you and
we'll end the civil war
between the House of Saul and
the House of David you
will unite israel and
then David writes back and
says yeah come to my come to
me well I'll give you a fuse and then
we'll be friends and so Abner
comes David gives him a fuse
and then
as Abner leaves he runs
into David's general named Joab Joab
and And Joab and Abner
go a long way back, okay?
They were friends, they were enemies.
Abner killed Job's brother.
And in an act of anger,
Joab stabs Abner to
death, and Abner is dead.
And once Abner is dead, the house
of Saul basically gives up,
and David is able to unite Israel.
Okay? Now it's a story in the Bible.
David is so
angry by this that
he curses Job, and
he gives Abner a great funeral.
Right? Because
David does not want to betray his friends.
Why is this story wrong
or completely made up?
It's not made up. But it is.
It's what we call spin, right?
Clearly, Abner and David
had a feast together,
and clearly Joab killed Abner.
But why is the Bible version of
this event wrong or incorrect?
It can't be true. You guys know?
Okay, this is hard, okay?
Okay, but the reason is this.
If you're David and you're king,
which person in the world
are you most afraid of?
If you're the king, there's a person in this world
you're most afraid of or you're most suspicious of.
Who is that person? Hmm?
Abner. Okay, yeah, he
is suspicious of Abner.
But in general, you should
be suspicious of Joab, right?
Because Joab has access to your army.
Abner is your enemy, but
Joab has access to your army.
So if Joab wants to betray you, he could.
Okay? So in other words, because
David is most suspicious of Joab, if
Joab were ever to act independently,
then David would need to kill him.
Does that make sense?
And in this circumstance,
Joab acted independently.
David told Joab Abner
was an honored guest.
And Joab didn't care.
He was angry about the
death of his brother.
And he kills Abner. This
cannot possibly be true.
You understand? Joab had to kill Abner
because he was ordered to by David.
Right? Now,
why would David want Abner to be killed?
Because in his mind, he thinks,
oh, if Abner can betray the house of Saul,
he can also betray the house of David.
He is an ambitious man.
And why would he think like that?
Why would David come to this conclusion?
Because he himself is like that.
Do you understand? He
himself betrayed Saul.
So he's very, very careful
or cautious about people
who betray their leaders.
Right? Abner betrayed the house of Saul.
And it was very likely that he would
betray David at some point as well.
And so David had to have him killed.
Right? But he could not say this publicly.
Because if he were to say this publicly,
it would show he in fact knew this
because he betrayed Saul.
Does that make sense? The logic of this?
Okay? But you can see how
wonderful the spin is.
It's almost impossible to
see the truth from this.
Right? If you're a person, you know, okay,
David, you know
that Job killed Abner.
And you were told the story.
You would believe the story.
It's just because Abner
was angry that he killed.
Sorry, it was just because
Job was angry he killed Abner.
You would believe that. Right?
But you think about it, it can't be true.
Okay? Now, I'm going to
give you one more story.
And this story is actually even harder
to figure out because of the spin.
Okay? Okay. Now that
David is king of Israel,
Israel has many enemies.
So his armies are always at war.
Okay? One day,
David is on the
rooftop of his house.
So, and this is, Israel
is not a very rich place.
Okay? So these are not
palaces. They're just houses.
Okay? And so David is
strolling on his rooftop. And
across from him is a
woman named Bathsheba.
Bathsheba. Bathsheba.
And she's bathing naked.
And David is overcome with lust.
He's like, I must have this woman.
Okay? And he's king. He orders
his servant to go get her.
She comes. They have sex.
Okay? The problem is, we have
sex, but she gets pregnant.
Okay? The problem now is,
Bathsheba's married to a man
named Uriah the Hittite.
Right? And
Uriah the Hittite is one of
David's best soldiers, and
he's fighting for David
and Israel somewhere else.
So David's like, oh,
this is a problem because
once Uriah comes home and
he finds Bathsheba has a new child,
he's going to know it's not his.
So either he's going to kill her, or he's going
to figure out it's David to come kill him.
Okay? So David, being very
clever, has a solution to this.
He invites David.
He says, Uriah, back home.
Okay? So Uriah comes home from the war,
and Uriah thinks, oh, the
king has called for me.
Therefore, it's an emergency. Okay?
So he rushes back. And
David meets Uriah at his house,
and David says, listen, Uriah,
you've been doing such a great job.
You're such a great soldier.
You're so loyal. I want
to give you a vacation.
Go home and be with your wife.
And Uriah's like, okay.
So David leaves the house with David and
leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and
leaves with David and
leaves with David and leaves with David
and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and leaves with David and
leaves with David leaves with David and
leaves with David leaves with David leaves with David to go home.
So then David tells Uriah,
you're such a great soldier,
you're so loyal, I'm so
happy and proud that you fight for me.
And he gives Uriah a letter
to his general Joab,
okay? And the letter
instructs Joab to kill Uriah.
Joab will send Uriah with his
soldiers out in the battlefield,
and then at the last minute,
Joab will recall his soldiers
leaving Joab by himself
and at this point the
enemies will swarm Uriah
and kill Uriah, okay?
And that's what happens. And
once Uriah is dead,
David marries Bathsheba,
and they're about to
have a child together.
At this point, David is visited
by a prophet named Nathan.
And Nathan says to David, I
want to ask you a question.
And David says, sure, go ahead.
Nathan says, let's imagine
there are two shepherds.
There's a rich shepherd with a hundred sheep,
and there's a poor shepherd with two sheep.
There's a traveler, a foreign guest,
who comes into town, and the rich
shepherd wants to honor him with a feast.
The rich shepherd steals the poor
man's shepherd to feed the traveler.
Who's in the wrong? And David says,
of course the rich
shepherd is in the wrong.
He's indignant. He's angry.
How could a man be so unrighteous
as to steal another man's sheep?
And then Nathan says, you,
David, are the rich shepherd.
You have violated God's law.
You are in the wrong. And as
punishment, God will take away
your son or your child with Bathsheba.
And that's what happens. And
David goes into more trouble.
And David goes into
mourning. He is distraught.
He's depressed. And he
writes a lot of poetry.
So this is a very powerful story.
And this is a story that has
captured the imagination
of everyone for thousands of years.
But it's complete spin.
This is not what happened. How do we know?
First thing is this. Nathan says to David,
David, you have stolen a man's wife.
Therefore, you are in the wrong.
What's the problem with this logic?
What is David's crime, real crime?
Guys, he killed Uriah.
Right? You understand?
You've forgotten this fact.
He had Uriah killed. That's a real crime.
He killed Uriah. Yeah,
he slept with Bathsheba.
That's bad. But it's much
worse if you murder someone.
Okay? So another question then is,
why would he murder Uriah?
Why not just talk to him honestly
and say, Uriah, I'm sorry.
I love your wife. I had sex with her.
I'm sorry. Why did David
have to get Uriah killed?
Why was Uriah killed?
Yeah, because the army is loyal to Uriah.
Right? So why would David fear Uriah?
Because Uriah is a popular, brave soldier.
Just like David. And
David uses popularity in order
to usurp the throne from Saul.
Right? Therefore, David thinks,
Uriah could do the same thing to me.
Therefore, I have to get him killed.
In other words,
this Bathsheba thing must have
come later to disguise the fact
that David killed Uriah because
he feared Uriah's popularity.
Does that make sense? Right?
Do you see how clever this story is?
The historical truth must have been
David feared Uriah's popularity.
And he needed to get rid of Uriah.
So he could conquer this plan.
And then, after he killed Uriah,
he needed to explain to his army,
who loved Uriah, why this happened.
And then David was like, Oh, because
I fell in love with his wife.
I couldn't control myself. I'm just a man.
Okay? God is God.
I'm a man. I'm a king.
I can't be God. I can't
control my emotions.
I can't control my feelings. I can't
control my emotions. Does that make sense?
But the irony of this is
because David is working
so hard to disguise his ruthlessness,
he's creating very powerful literature.
He created a very powerful story that
has captured the imagination
of readers for a long time.
If you think about it, if you
think a lot about the story,
it unleashes a lot of ideas in you.
Okay? You have to ask yourself,
What is man? What is God?
Are we capable of
controlling our emotions?
So in other words, this story
is extremely well constructed
that inspires you to
imagine your own personal
and emotional
and moral life.
Okay? We call this literature.
Right? So,
guys, it's no coincidence
that today
the Jewish people are the most
creative people in the world.
When you go to America for university,
most of your professors are Jewish.
Most of the best thinkers
in the world are Jewish.
These past 200 years, there have
been three revolutionary thinkers.
Karl Marx, Albert Einstein,
and Sigmund Freud. They're all Jewish.
Who are, who are stepped,
who are, who
have been raised in the
Jewish tradition of asking
deep questions about what
it means to be human.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay. Any questions?
About this? Okay.
So, I think that's it.
Thank you. Okay.
That's a great question. Okay? So,
the question is, why would people
believe this apology of David?
And, well, the answer is most, most
didn't believe the apology of David.
Okay? Most were very clear
about David's ambitions.
But, when you're king,
you need to
impose your reality on others.
Okay? So, this is a very important
question. This is why this is written.
And so, it was written for people
who were part of David's
political coalition.
Do you understand? His enemies
wouldn't believe this, right?
But, it was meant,
it was basically meant to
appease or convince those
who want to believe David.
Does that make sense? Okay.
Spin. And it's, it happens today, guys.
When you watch the news, it's spin.
And, so, most people will
believe the media, right?
There are some people who
will never believe the media.
Like, I don't believe
anything the media tells me.
Whether it's Chinese
media or American media.
I, I know a lot of history to understand.
The media is, is distorting reality.
Okay? But,
most people, will, will
believe this because,
they have absolutely no
interest in not believing it.
Right? David's king, if you don't believe
it, then you have to, then you have to believe your king is a murderer.
Okay? So, David's king is a murderer.
Does that make sense? Yeah?
Yeah? Echo? What's the mainstream
understanding of the story?
Oh, yeah.
That's a good question. Okay. I, yeah.
This is really important. What's the
mainstream understanding of the story?
So, the mainstream understanding
of the story is, it has to be true.
Why? Because it puts David in a bad light.
You understand? And, it
shows the genius of David.
Because David, is wrestling,
with his own morality.
David is being honest.
Right? So, the mainstream
understanding is, David is a poet king.
He's a man, who prays constantly,
and, engages in a process
of self -reflection.
And that's what makes David great. Right?
He's constantly praying to God. In fact,
the Bible just goes on endlessly about this.
How, David is constantly
in communication with God.
And, in this communication,
he's praying, and asking for,
light, for, for truth
in his own weaknesses.
Okay? To be delivered from his,
failings as a man. And the Bathsheba,
Bathsheba story, is epimantic,
about this. Because, why
would a man, make this up?
Right? Well, I've told you why.
But, most scholars don't see that.
Most scholars think, okay,
well this, Bathsheba story,
puts David in the worst
possible situation.
And, he's in the worst possible
light. Therefore, it must be true.
And therefore, it shows
us David is a poor king.
Who is constantly thinking
about, his own moral failings.
And so, he's an
inspiration, to his people.
Okay? That's the mainstream understanding.
Okay? Any other questions?
Yup? That's right.
I was wondering, how do you
know, that David is a poor king?
That's right. So, how did
the story, tell David?
Oh, okay. So, the question is,
if people at that time,
were mainly illiterate,
why was this written down?
Or, how would they know the story?
Okay. So, the idea is this.
First of all, this was
written for the elite,
for the people around David, to
know, what story to tell people.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So, this was, you know, written
for internal consumption,
and this was to, basically,
preserve David's historical legacy.
So maybe, 20 years from now,
when everyone's dead, when
people who knew Uriah, and
Bathsheba, were dead, well, what,
what is truth now? The truth
is, what's been written down.
Okay? That's why they're saying,
history is written by the writers.
Right? History is not
written by the winners.
History is written by the writers.
Right? Okay. Does
that make sense? Okay. Any more questions?
Okay. Great. So, next class,
we'll continue the Hebrew Bible.
Okay? Because, it starts
off as an apology for David,
but it evolves into a
much larger mythology.
Right? So, that's next class. Next class.