Okay, so
today we will be discussing how
Greek culture spread around the world
and how it can dominate the Western world
and became the basis of
Western civilization.
Now, normally,
Westerners understood this
process as one of diffusion,
meaning that Greek
civilization was the best,
and so everyone wanted access to it, okay?
So it spread because Greek
civilization was the best.
Historically, that's not
true. What happened was that
Greek civilization spread
through a process of conquest,
primarily by Alexander the Great, okay?
So, the question I want
to answer today is,
how did Alexander the Great,
conquer the world?
Because Alexander the Great
himself is not Greek.
He's Macedonian. So he's
like a close cousin,
but he's not considered culturally Greek.
He's from a place called Macedon,
okay, which is north of Greece.
And for most of its history, Macedon,
the kingdom of Macedonia, was poor,
it was weak, it was divided.
So how was it possible that
Macedon, the kingdom of Macedon,
would conquer the world
and not Sparta or Athens,
which for most of Greek history
were the dominant powers, okay?
So, for me to explain what happened,
I need to explain to you two
thought experiments, okay?
So, we're going to do two thought
experiments to develop the
analytical tools in order to better understand
the process of military conquest, okay?
So, let's do a thought experiment.
There's a father and there's a son, okay?
And they're both business people.
They started business. The
father starts with nothing
and he makes $10 million, okay?
Which is a great accomplishment.
The son takes his business
and expands it, okay?
And he turns $10 million,
the inheritance, into $10 billion,
okay?
And this happens a lot.
So, who is the most,
more impressive of the two,
the father and the son?
The father is more impressive because
he started with nothing, right?
It's much harder to build something from
nothing than it is to expand something,
okay? The problem though is that
we, in society, in history,
in the media, we celebrate the son because
$10 billion is a lot of money, okay?
Does that make sense?
So, it's a father who
does all the work and
builds the organization
and the capacity for growth.
It's a son who expands it and
gets all the credit, okay?
And this happens a lot in history.
Now, what we're going to do is we're going
to think about the qualities of a father
and a son that allow
them to succeed, okay?
So, what can we say about the father?
How was he able to build a great business?
He is what? And
the first thing we can say
is he is innovative, right?
Meaning he has a new idea
that allows him to capture markets,
okay? Now, it's possible
that he stole the idea,
but that also shows
that he's not a genius.
It shows that he has
wisdom and judgment, right?
So, he's innovative or he has wisdom
and judgment.
Okay, does that make sense? That's
the first major quality of the father.
He's very innovative, okay?
Or he's wise and has good judgment.
Second quality about the
father we can say is that
he's a very effective
manager of people, okay?
Because remember, he has nothing. So,
he has to build loyalty among his workers.
He has to find workers, he
has to recruit workers, and
he has to make them work
hard for him, right?
So, what can he do to find good workers
and ensure they work hard
for him and build a business?
Why would you want to go work for
someone and work hard for him?
Well, they pay you well.
They pay you good money, but a
lot of people pay you good money.
What's different about this business?
Good, okay. So, the vision, right?
Or the dream. So, the
business has a vision
and a dream that compels you, okay?
You see the potential for growth, okay?
So, not only is the father innovative,
but he's also a visionary. He's a dreamer,
and that's what attracts you to him, okay?
The other thing is that he's fair,
meaning that he promotes talent,
right?
You want to work for someone who
will treat you fairly, who
will be honest with you.
So, if you work hard, he'll tell you,
wow, you're working really hard,
thank you so much, okay?
But if you're not working so hard, then he
might give you some feedback on how to improve,
okay? And that's very hard to do because
normally, what do we humans want to do?
So, a good boss would promote talent,
and most people would do what?
Promote his or her friends, right?
Promote people that they like.
Promote people who suck up to them, okay?
That's the natural human instinct.
So, in other words, the father,
he's almost like selfless, okay?
He's always thinking
about the greater good,
which is really the
company or the business.
So, he's going to work
harder than everyone else.
If you come to work at 7 o 'clock in the
morning, he'll come in at 6 o 'clock.
If you leave at 10 o 'clock at night,
he'll leave at midnight, okay?
He's always working harder
than you to show that
he is the most loyal to the company, and
that's what makes you loyal
to the company as well.
Does that make sense? So, these
are the three distinct qualities
of a good business person, a good founder.
Innovative, a good manager, a good
manager of people by sharing the vision,
by communicating the vision,
and by being fair to people,
by promoting talent, okay?
And also selfless, very disciplined, okay?
Will work very hard in order
to achieve the greater good,
to ensure the company succeeds.
Now, it turns out that
these personality traits are consistent
with extremely successful people.
Okay? So, when
we study other great leaders,
for example, Genghis Khan, Mohammed,
then we will recognize they all share
very similar personality traits.
And I want you to remember
the three distinct qualities
that make them great world leaders, okay?
The first is they are strategic
to the point of visionary.
This means they have a vision
of what the world should be.
And then they have a long -term
plan on how to achieve that, okay?
They're very strategic. The second
thing is they are innovative
to the point of revolutionary.
Okay? So, what they understand is
if you want to change the world,
you must destroy the status quo.
You must change the way
society is structured, okay?
And they're willing to
do that, even though
they know it will be a very bloody
process involving lots of wars,
okay? That's the second quality that they
have that's different from everyone else.
The third quality is they
are extremely disciplined
to the point of selfless.
Okay? They are fanatical and
obsessed with achieving their vision.
They won't eat, they won't sleep
until they achieve their vision.
For them, it's all about
achieving the vision
and the greater good as
opposed to personal happiness.
All right, does that make
sense? So, this is a pattern
that we'll see over and over again where
the great world leaders that
have changed history forever have
possessed these three distinct qualities
that make them unique.
They have the same characteristics
And so, Genghis Khan,
Mohammed are two examples,
but also like Napoleon
and Julius Caesar, okay? Basically,
all the great world conquerors in
human history have these
similar characteristics.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Now, the sun is very different, okay?
So, if the father succeeds
because he is innovative,
how do you rank him in rank?
No, he's not, actually.
How do you rank him in rank?
How do you rank him in rank? How do you rank
him in rank? How do you rank him in rank?
How do you rank him in rank? How do you
rank him in rank? How do you rank him in rank? How do you rank him in rank?
How do you rank him in rank?
You have ten million dollars.
You can go to the bank and
say I have a great business Can you lend me a
billion dollars so I can buy out my competitors?
Okay. Now when you do that, that's risky, but
that's how you expand very quickly, right?
So the first thing about the son that's
very different from the father is he succeeds by taking risk
That no one else are willing to take.
Okay, that's the first thing
Who does he promote? His
father promotes talent.
Who does he promote? Who
does he want around him?
Exactly wants his friends.
Okay, so he's gonna promote
loyalty All right,
if you listen to him if you're
obedient to him if he likes you
then he will promote you Okay, the father
is very different the father will not do
that because if you do that
that's gonna hurt the internal
structure of your company,
right and The father is selfless.
What does the son care about?
What drives him?
What does he really care about what sort of the
father is motivated to build a great company,
right? He wants to achieve his vision.
What drives the son?
Usually it's idea of personal glory.
Okay He's very selfish
You understand he wants to be remembered
He wants to be famous He wants
to be admired and respected
Okay, the father cares about the vision
the son cares about the personal glory
Why would the son put personal
glory first and first?
Think about his psychology
What drives him what does he want to prove
Exactly exactly you understand
he's greater than his father.
It's insecurity because
Everyone will say to him you
are where you are because
your father built a great organization
So for him he must prove he's
better than the father by
Expanding and by winning
glory for himself.
Okay, does that make sense? And
again, we will see this pattern
in human history all the time and
We will you I want you
to remember this because
this describes perfectly
the relationship between
Philip II of Macedon,
the man who actually built the
greatest military in the world,
and Aksum the Great, who
will take this army, the
greatest army in the world, and
conquer Persia.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Alright? So over the next two classes,
I will show you, Philip,
how this relationship
between the father and son
describes very well the personalities
of Philip and Alexander.
Okay? Alright?
Does that make sense? Okay?
So, and this repeats
itself throughout history.
This makes sense to you, right? You will see this
in life, you will see this throughout history.
Okay? Now, the other thing
I want us to look at,
another thought experiment is,
throughout history, what we discovered is,
poor countries often
conquer rich countries.
And for us, that's very confusing.
Because normally we think, if you are
rich, you have a very strong military,
you have advanced technology,
and you have a lot of resources, right?
And therefore, it's very
hard to be conquered.
But we see this throughout history
all the time, where poor nations,
poor countries,
quickly conquer rich nations.
Okay? So, how can we explain this?
And to explain this, we'll do
another thought experiment.
Okay? So let's compare North
Korea with South Korea.
Okay? And these countries
are same culture, right?
Same people, but they are night and day.
North Korea, we know, is poor.
South Korea is rich.
North Korea is primitive,
meaning they are not,
they don't have that much
advanced technology.
South Korea is very advanced, right?
Technologically advanced, right?
Think of Samsung, the
phones, the cars, and
the phones they produce, and the
computers they produce, right?
A very advanced country.
The last thing is that North
Korea is a dictatorship,
and South Korea is a democracy.
So, if we were to take a snapshot of
North and South Korea today, right?
Then we could easily predict
that in 20 years' time,
North Korea would be poorer, South
Korea would be richer, right?
Okay? But that may not happen.
What is South Korea's problem?
What is South Korea's biggest problem?
Do you know?
It's not having children. In fact,
it has the world's lowest
fertility rate at 0.8.
Okay? And it's women who
refuse to have children.
And not only that, but South Korean culture
is becoming more and more anti -family.
They hate kids. There
are lots of restaurants,
lots of places that refuse to let kids in.
Okay? So, this is a very
weird state of affairs, right?
What's driving the low fertility rate?
Do you think? Usually.
Why are young women
refusing to have children?
Because? Yeah, right. Inequality, right?
If you feel that if you're just a normal
person, the rich have all the resources,
it's very hard for you to advance.
So, why have children? Okay?
Now, North Korea doesn't
have this problem, right?
Because it's poor.
Therefore, it has equality.
And because it has equality,
people there are united, right?
They're not divided, they're united.
And what else? They're obedient, right?
They listen to what the
government tells them to do.
And last thing is they're hungry.
They will work very hard for very little.
Okay? Do you understand? So,
it is possible that in 20 years' time,
North Korea overtakes South Korea.
Because its people are willing to work
harder than the South Korean people.
Okay? Does it make sense? So,
evidence for this is that right now,
North Korea is sending weapons and
soldiers to the war in Ukraine.
Does it make sense? So, when you do that,
you make a lot of money for yourself, right?
And so, with this money, you
can upgrade your military.
And then what you can do
is threaten South Korea.
Okay? North Korea can say to South Korea,
our military is now
stronger than your military.
And what will South Korea do in response?
What do you think? North Korea is like,
we're going to come and invade you.
What will South Korea do in response?
Someone wants to attack you, right?
So, how do you get this
person not to attack you?
Exactly. Do you understand? Alright?
Give them money. So, North Korea
doesn't even have to attack South Korea.
North Korea just has to
threaten to attack South Korea.
And South Korea will give them
a lot of money not to attack.
Do you understand? And
by doing that, right?
North Korea becomes richer
and more military advanced.
South Korea just becomes poorer.
Do you understand? And
because North Korea,
the army is fighting in
other places like Ukraine,
it's developing all this
experience and expertise that
will allow it to eventually
overwhelm South Korea.
Does it make sense? So, in
this thought experiment,
it's possible that
North Korea can eventually
conquer South Korea.
Okay? Does it make sense? And
this gives us an understanding of why
Macedonia, Macedon, was able
to conquer all of Greece.
Even though Macedon was by
far one of the poorest places
in Greece at that time.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Because the people are hungry,
united, and obedient.
Alright? Any questions so far?
About this? Okay?
So, I want you to remember
these two thought experiments.
Because they will help us
explain a lot of history.
And I will refer to these two thought experiments
some more as we go along in the course.
Okay? Alright?
But does this make sense to you so far?
Great. Alright.
So now, let's focus specifically
on Philip II of Macedon.
How was he able to conquer all of Greece?
Given that his nation, Macedon,
was poor, weak, and divided.
Okay? Alright.
So, King Philip, okay?
He was born in 383 BCE.
Okay? And I want to talk about the world
of Greece and
Macedon at the time of his birth.
Okay. So, around this time,
there are three major powers in Greece.
Okay? There's Athens.
Remember that even though Athens
lost the Peloponnesian War,
it's still very wealthy and it still
has the best navy in all of Greece.
Okay? So, it's still a major power.
Then you have Sparta,
which for most of Greek history
was considered the best military.
Right? And then you have... Sorry.
Let me try to use another...
Okay. So, the map.
Okay? So, this is Sparta
here to the south.
This is Athens. And then to the
north is a place called Thebes.
And what's interesting is at this time,
Thebes has become the
most dominant military
in Greece. Primarily
because Sparta and Athens
decimated each other during
the Peloponnesian War.
Okay? So, because of
the war, Thebes has...
became the dominant power
in Greece at this time.
Okay. And then to the
far north is Macedon.
Okay? The Kingdom of Macedon. Now,
Macedon is very poor, weak, and divided.
So, let me explain why it is.
First of all, it has a geography problem.
The nation is divided between
agricultural farmland to the south
and mountains.
And then to the north.
Okay? So, most of its land
can't even grow crops.
And where it can grow crops,
its farmers are just peasants.
Okay? Now, the problem is that
there are lots of tribes in the mountains.
And the way they make their
living usually is by coming
and raiding your farmland.
And there's nothing that
you can do about it because
if you go chase them, they
go back to the mountains.
Okay? So, that's the first problem.
The economy is very divided.
And it's very... And the people
don't have that many resources.
Okay? That's the first
problem. Second problem is
Macedon is completely
surrounded by hostile powers.
Okay? So, you have the
Kingdom of Phrase over here.
And that's a long -term enemy.
And you have Illyria over here.
Okay? And these are
warlike mountainous people
who live in fortresses.
It's almost impossible to invade them.
And it's easy for them
to come and attack you.
Okay? So, they're a huge problem.
To the south is a place called Phycelae.
And they have one of the
best militaries in Greece.
Okay? They're known for their
cavalry, their horsemen.
And then, of course, you also
have Thebes, Athens, and Sparta,
which also want to play a
role in controlling Macedon.
Okay? And over here, of course,
across the sea is called Persia.
And for some of its history, Macedon
was actually a province of Persia.
Okay? Persia actually conquered
or subjugated Macedon.
So, Macedon is always being
threatened by a more superior power.
And it keeps on losing these wars.
Okay? The third problem it has is
that it's a kingdom.
It has a king. And the
king has many, many wives.
And why would this be a problem?
Exactly. Okay? There are a lot of sons,
and they fight over who will be king.
And the thing is that
these sons are always supported by
another foreign power. Okay? Because
the foreign powers want Macedon
to be always in conflict.
Okay?
So, for most of its
history, Macedon was poor,
weak, and divided.
And then Philip II changes all that.
So, he's born in 383.
And then from 369 to 365,
for about five years,
he's a hostage in Thebes.
The reason why is Macedon
lost the war to Thebes.
And to ensure that Macedon does
not rebel against the Thracians,
Macedon had to send hostages.
And so, Philip was a hostage in Thebes.
But he's a prince. So, he's treated very,
very nicely in Thebes.
And he can do whatever
he wants. The thing that
he wants to do is he wants to
understand why Thebes
is the dominant military
power in Greece at this time.
And he learns from the
best Theban generals.
They become his mentors.
Okay? So,
what makes Thebes so
effective is the idea of
the sacred ban of Thebes.
This is the secret to the power of Thebes.
Okay? These are 300 soldiers
who
spend every day training to
be the best soldiers they can.
And in many ways, they're
like special forces.
Okay? And
this is modeled off Sparta, right?
The difference is this.
The difference is in
Sparta, only citizens,
only aristocrats can be soldiers.
But in Thebes, these 300
people were volunteers.
They were commoners who
wanted to be soldiers. And so,
the first thing Philip learned in
Thebes is anyone can be a soldier.
Not just the rich. Okay?
With proper training,
anyone can learn to be a great soldier.
That's the first thing he learned.
Second thing he learned is when
you have an elite group of soldiers, it's
really about how to use them effectively. Okay?
So, the traditional warfare in Greece
at this time is called a phallax.
Right? The hoplite phallax.
Okay? So, remember, it
is like a moving wall.
They move together slowly.
Slowly. And try to crush the enemy.
Okay? The innovation
the Thebans did was say,
we're going to do a slant.
Okay? The reason why
is when you do a slant,
you can put the 300 sacred bands
first against the best
soldiers of the enemy.
Okay? And we know that in a fair fight,
these 300 will always destroy
the first soldiers of the enemy.
But when you do that, there's
a massive psychological effect.
And so, what happens is the
phallax breaks formation.
And if the phallax breaks formation, and
people start running away, they're all dead.
Okay? So, that
is the major innovation
of Thebes at this time.
Okay? And
from the best generals of Thebes, okay,
Philip understood the
importance of discipline.
He understood the importance
of discipline in an army.
And this is new. Okay?
Because in Greece, remember,
the Spaniards had discipline,
but most armies, like the Athenians,
they were citizen soldiers.
They did this for fun. They
did this as a civic duty.
They did this part -time.
Okay? So, they weren't really
training when they weren't fighting.
Now, when you train,
you develop discipline.
With discipline, you have
three major strengths.
Okay? The first major strength that
you have is the idea
of mobility, speed. And
what this means is your army can
march much faster than other armies.
Okay? So, maybe this is important
because maybe you want to attack a city.
Right? If you get there really fast, and
you're able to siege
a city and destroy it,
the city cannot ask for reinforcements.
Okay? Because reinforcements
will come too slowly.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So, this is a major innovation,
the idea of mobility.
Okay? Second is the idea of coordination.
Coordination. So, different military
units are able to work together.
And this is really important. So,
in Greece at this time,
there are maybe two different land forces.
Right? There's a phalanx,
and there's a cavalry.
Right? And they do their own thing.
Okay? But with discipline,
you can actually get
them to work together.
And if you get them to work together,
you create something called
the anvil and hammer strategy.
Okay? Anvil and hammer.
Okay? So, the idea of an anvil
is you put something in place.
Okay? And the hammer is you
just knock that thing apart.
Okay? So, in this attack,
the cavalry becomes the hammer.
The anvil is a phalanx.
So, with discipline, the phalanx is able
to lock the other enemy army in place.
Okay? And then what happens
is the cavalry sees this,
and they stream in from the
back and destroy the enemy.
Does that make sense? It's called
the anvil and hammer strategy.
And the Thebans used it, but
Philip started to use it as well.
And you can use this with discipline.
Okay? If every soldier knows
his or her role in the army.
And with coordination, you can
also have the idea of flexibility.
Okay? So, remember the Greeks thought
using the hoplite phalanx and that's it.
But what Philip understood is,
hey, if I have coordination,
I can change my strategy and
tactics according to the enemy.
Right? So, he had different units.
He had archers. He had shield bearers.
Okay? People whose job
was to hold shields.
He had phalanx. And he had cavalry.
And in response to different enemies,
he would change his strategy
using these different units.
Okay? Does that make sense?
And so, as over time,
this army, if you have these
three things, mobility,
coordination, and flexibility,
you'll be invincible.
No one could beat you. Okay?
Because the very idea that
an army could do this at
that time was unheard of.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
So, that's what he learned in Thebes.
It is possible for you to
transform your army in a way
that makes it highly disciplined.
And once you have discipline,
it will become invincible.
Okay? So, he became resolved
to take all this education
and transform the Macedonian army.
Okay? He got his chance in 359.
Okay? The reason why is his brother died.
And the brother's son,
his nephew, was too young.
So, he became regent. Okay?
He became the sort
of placeholder before the
son can become of age.
Okay? But once he became regent, he basically
became de facto king for his entire life.
And as regent,
he was determined to transform
the Macedonian military.
And at this time,
the Macedonian military was
getting destroyed by everyone.
Okay? Illyria attacked
and destroyed the army.
Thrace attacked and destroyed the army.
Okay? The Macedonian
army was a complete joke.
And he became determined to transform it.
And what he recognized is,
if I want to transform the army,
I need to turn it into a meritocracy.
Okay? Meritocracy.
So, traditionally, because
in Macedon, you have a nobility,
it's always the, like, all
decisions are made by social status.
Okay? So,
a person rises according to his
social status as opposed to his merit.
And Philip was determined to change that.
And the thing that he did that
was extremely controversial
was he made the cavalry,
which was full of nobility,
equal to the infantry,
which was made of commoners, peasants.
So, in this new system, as long
as you perform well in battle,
you'll be promoted.
Okay? And one of the people
he promoted very heavily
and who would become his
most successful general,
his name is Parmenion.
Parmenion. Okay? I want
you to remember this guy.
Parmenion. Okay? Because he would
basically become Philip's partner in war
and his greatest general.
Even though Parmenion, he was not,
he was born into lower nobility.
He certainly had some money.
But Philip treated him as a partner.
And he allowed Parmenion
to lead armies on his own.
He was not afraid that
Parmenion would rebel.
Okay? He trusted Parmenion.
Okay? So, Philip was a tremendous,
tremendous,
he had tremendous understanding
and judgment of people.
He knew who to trust.
And he knew how to use people effectively.
The other thing that he did that
was very important was he
needed to make the army loyal
to him. And
what he understood is if you
want the army loyal to you,
you need to do three things.
Okay? The first thing is you
need to fight with them.
You understand? He was not in
the back watching the battle.
He was in the front leading the battle.
He was training with them every day.
He trained harder than everyone else.
In fact, in one battle,
Philip lost an eye.
And he had many battle wounds and scars.
Okay? And so because of that,
his soldiers were
fanatically loyal to him.
Okay? And also because
Philip was fighting with
his soldiers every day,
he did not want to risk
the lives of his soldiers.
You understand? He was very strategic.
He would not put his
soldiers in harm's way.
And so his soldiers became
even more loyal to him.
Second thing that he did was
he ate and drank with them.
Okay? These common soldiers, he would spend
his time just eating and drinking with them.
And that told the soldiers,
hey, you know what?
We're equals. We're friends.
And I'm willing to listen
to your complaints.
Okay? Here's your opportunity
to complain about Commander.
Here's an opportunity
to complain about me.
I'm willing to listen to you.
Okay? Does that make sense? And
the third thing was he was
an excellent communicator.
He would give speeches
explaining his vision.
Right? He wanted to make Macedon great.
He wanted Macedon to
conquer all of Greece.
And then conquer Persia.
He wanted glory for his country.
Okay? But not only that, but he
praised people like Parmenion.
Okay? He used his speeches
to praise soldiers
that were good examples.
And obviously that made
Parmenion feel really good.
Right? And that made him
even more loyal to Philip.
Okay? So Philip,
over time,
was able to build a strong,
loyal, unified,
disciplined army using his strategies.
Okay? So the other thing
that Philip did was he started to,
while he was starting to build his army,
his enemies were still attacking him.
Right? And what he did that
was kind of intuitive was
he built a strong army.
He basically negotiated. Understand?
He used diplomacy. He understood that
having the best military is just a...
Sorry. Sorry.
Let me rephrase this. Having smart diplomacy is
just as good as having the world's best military.
Right? Does that make sense? Because remember,
at this time, it's basically Game of Thrones.
Every nation is at each other's throat.
Okay? And they hate each other.
Okay? So Sparta hates Thebes.
Thebes hates Athens.
They really didn't get along. Okay? So
what Philip could do was use
diplomacy to build alliances
against other enemies.
Okay? So he was using diplomacy a lot in order
to buy time for him to train up his army.
Okay? He would also marry the
princesses of other nations.
Okay? As part of his diplomacy.
So Philip was known as a great strategist.
But much more importantly, he
was known also as a diplomat.
Someone who knew how to negotiate and
deceive his enemies.
Okay? So after he started
to build his army,
he started to make his move.
Okay? The first thing he did was he
basically secured his northern frontier.
He got into these wars with his enemies to the
north and he secured his northern frontier.
That's important.
Okay? Because he wants to move
into the south eventually.
But he needs to make sure that
he's not attacked from behind.
Okay? So that's the first thing he does.
Second thing that he does is in 347,
he invades a city called Amphipolis
and he conquers it.
This is important because
Amphipolis has gold mines.
Okay? Now he has resources.
He has money. And with his
resources, he can pay his soldiers.
Because his soldiers
are training every day.
They're not farming.
They're training every day.
So he can now pay them.
He can now buy the loyalty of the nobility
and
he can stir national settlement
in Macedon by building projects,
by building roads. Okay?
He can improve the economy.
Okay? And the last thing that he does with
the money is he starts bribing everyone.
Okay? He basically starts
bribing the nobility of Athens,
other nations to support him.
Okay? So he's being very
strategic and very clever.
In 356, his son in here, Alexander the
Great, is born to his wife Olympias.
Okay? And
the last major event is in 338
BCE is the battle of Tyrrhenia.
Tyrrhenia. This is the last
battle between Philoctetes.
This is the battle between Philip
and the people who opposed him.
So in Tyrrhenia, the two nations that
opposed him are Thebes and Athens.
But at this time,
the problem is the great
generals of Thebes have all died.
Okay? And Athens felt basically glad
they were stalkers to support him.
So Athens didn't really
put out a great army.
And this battle of Tyrrhenia,
Philip II with his like
modern, highly disciplined,
loyal army destroyed everyone.
Okay? He crushed Thebes.
He crushed Athens.
And he united all of Greece.
So he destroyed all, the
entire army of Athens.
And he almost destroyed Thebes.
But what happened was,
when it was clear that
Thebes was about to lose the
battle, the sacred band of Thebes.
Okay? Stood in the way.
Okay? They basically sacrificed
themselves so the other army,
the other soldiers of Thebes could escape.
Okay? And
so the sacred band of Thebes
was forever destroyed.
And the irony of course is,
it's the sacred band of Thebes
that taught Philip how
to build a great army.
Okay? And in his last act,
he destroyed the sacred band of Thebes.
And now he united all of Greece.
Now that he united all of Greece,
his ambition now is to take
his army and conquer Persia.
Okay? So what he did was,
he sent his great general
Parmenion into Persia.
Okay? Remember in Anatolia at
this time, which is today Turkey,
there are lots of Greek colonies
that are under Persian rule.
And for the longest time, they
wanted to be free of Persian rule.
Okay? So Parmenion went
over with a vanguard,
about 10,000 men, to begin the invasion.
Okay? And
Philip was about to go over
and lead the invasion, but
his daughter was about to get married.
Okay? So he had to attend
the wedding. At the wedding,
he had one bodyguard.
Okay? Because at the wedding,
there'll be lots of
Greek diplomats, right?
So he wanted to appear approachable.
So he didn't have his
entire bodyguard in place.
He had one bodyguard. Okay?
His bodyguard took his sword and
stabbed him in the rib, killing him.
And then his bodyguard was
killed by the other bodyguards.
So Philip was assassinated before he
could launch his invasion of Persia.
Okay? And when he died,
it was like 337.
Okay? Okay?
So Philip was really in
the prime of his life.
He had like 30, 40 years
of military conquest to go.
Okay? He died very young.
And his son, Alexander, who was like 18,
19 at this time, he now became king.
It was Alexander who would
lead his army into Persia
and conquer all Persia and
move all the way to India.
Or like the... Or Pakistan, really.
Okay? So for the longest time,
historians do not know what happened.
How is it possible for this great man,
Philip II, to be assassinated
in the prime of his life?
All right? Now, there
are three explanations.
There are three major explanations.
The first explanation is it was Persia.
Persia knew that Philip was about to invade,
and so they hired the bodyguard to kill him.
Okay? That's the first explanation.
Second explanation is it was personal.
So the story is very complicated, but
apparently the bodyguard
and Philip were lovers.
Okay? They were homosexual
lovers. And then
Philip found someone else, and
the bodyguard became very jealous.
So it's a very complicated story.
Okay? It was personal. And then
there's one more explanation.
The other explanation was it
was the mother of Alexander,
Olympias. And Alexander.
Okay? Right?
So these are the three explanations.
So if you want to, and like, honestly,
we'll never ever know what happened.
Okay? But if you want to evaluate a
murder, you always look at two things.
Look at opportunity. Who
has the chance to kill him?
You look at motive. Okay?
You understand? So if you look at these
two things, you look at opportunity.
Let's evaluate all three possibilities.
Persia. Okay. It had the motive,
but it didn't have the opportunity.
You understand? How could it
access Philip's inner court?
Right? And Philip's not a dumb guy.
He would know exactly who to
trust and who not to trust.
And usually, if Persia
was afraid of Philip,
what they could do was
basically give Sparta
and Athens all their
money to attack Philip.
Right? So I don't think it's Persia.
I think most people
agree it was not Persia.
Okay? Second possibility
is it was personal.
And that's kind of strange.
Right? Because Philip,
he's very good at inspiring
loyalty from others.
He's also good at reading people. Right?
So I don't think it was personal.
I mean, it could be, but
I don't think it is.
Okay? And this leaves us with the
possibility of Olympias and Alexander.
And here, it makes sense because
they both have both the
motive and the opportunity.
Okay? So let me first explain motive.
The motive is very easy to understand.
If Philip were to die,
Alexander would become king.
Right? And
this is at the height
of the glory of Macedon.
They have the world's greatest military.
They conquered all of Greece.
Persia is an easy target.
Okay? And maybe they were afraid that
if Philip goes to Persia,
it would be too late.
The other problem is Philip is
an excellent judge of character.
And what's clear about Alexander,
from a very early age,
is he was a very violent young man.
He couldn't really control his emotions.
You have Philip, right?
You're kind of like, I don't know.
Do I really want this guy
to be the heir to my empire?
Could he manage the empire?
Plus, remember, Philip
has a lot of wives, right?
So over time, he could have new sons.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So the motive is very clear.
And the opportunity makes sense
because they're all one family, right?
The bodyguard is in constant
communication with Olympias.
Okay? And what gives evidence?
What provides evidence for this?
So what we're trying to do is,
after the death of Philip's
bodyguard named Pausanias,
Olympias actually made a monument to him.
Okay? And
next class, when we look
at the life of Alexander,
we will see a lot of evidence
that suggests he wanted his father dead.
Okay? Maybe he didn't participate
in the killing of his father,
in the plotting. Of the assassination.
But he clearly wanted his father dead.
Okay? And next class,
we will discuss this.
Alright? So, does it make sense to you?
Okay? And again,
what we will understand is this
pattern of a great man emerging, who
creates a revolution that
transforms the world,
it will repeat itself in this way
many times, including with Muhammad.
Okay? And with Genghis Khan.
With Napoleon. With Julius Caesar.
Okay? But they all have this
sort of similar personality,
and they're all working within
a similar social context.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Any questions so far about this?
That's right. Hostage.
That's right. So, why would they inform so
much knowledge of him,
when would they break up,
when would they stop him,
when would they do it again?
That's a great question, okay. So,
the question, why do they treat Philip
so well, and why do they
give him so much knowledge?
And the answer is, first of all,
no one thinks Macedon
will ever be a threat.
Do you understand? No one
takes Macedon seriously.
It's like today, no one would
take North Korea seriously, right?
You understand? Everyone
thinks in East Asia,
the major powers are China and Japan.
And everyone thinks North
Korea is a complete joke, okay?
This place will collapse
in five years' time. So,
no one during this time ever
thought Macedon could ever challenge
Sparta or Athens or Thebes.
Okay? No one did. Okay?
So, it's just overconfidence.
Second thing is,
if you're a...
If you're the Thebans, you want...
Your enemies are Sparta and Athens, okay?
So, you want to build allies.
The best way to build allies is by building
strong relationships with weaker nations
who then rely on you.
And the best way to do that is by
indoctrinating the future leaders of
that nation, right?
Like Philip. So, basically,
they want to treat him nice,
so Philip would be thankful to Thebes.
They didn't realize Philip
had other intentions.
Okay? And it's impossible because
Philip is one of these individuals,
these men who we call
great men of history.
They stand outside of history.
They are in many ways not human, okay?
They don't behave the way
normal humans behave, right?
Normally, if you're a prince, you
just want to have a good time, right?
You just want to enjoy your wealth.
You want to promote your friends, right?
And you want personal glory.
But Philip wanted to change the world.
And so, you can't possibly
predict that, right?
Okay, does that make sense? Alright.
Okay, great question, though.
Okay, any more questions? Oh,
great, great question, okay,
the phalanx. Alright, okay,
so, Philip not only
learned military strategy,
from Thebes, but he was
also a military innovator.
Okay? So, he made a lot
of changes to the phalanx.
So, the phalanx, it's very strong, but
there are a lot of issues with it, okay?
The first major issue with
it is it's not very mobile,
because everyone's carrying heavy armor.
So, the first thing that
Philip did was he made,
he lightened the load, okay?
So, he had his soldiers wear less armor.
Then the question then is, well, if you wear
less armor, then how do you protect yourself?
And the answer is two
things, okay, that he did.
The first thing he did was
he made the spear very long.
It became a pike, okay?
So, it became very hard to
reach the phalanx, because
the spear was in the way, okay?
The pike was in the way.
And the other thing that
he did was he added a new
unit called shield bearers.
Okay? So, the shield
bearers were on the flanks,
were on the sides to
protect the phalanx, okay?
So, that's how he improved the phalanx.
And so, when the Macedonian phalanx came
into contact with the Greek phalanx,
the Macedonian phalanx proved superior
because of these innovations, okay?
Remember, they were lighter.
They could move around faster.
And they had longer spears, okay?
So, they could maintain
distance from you a lot longer.
And also, they had these shield bearers who
were mobile and could adapt to situations, okay?
So, if they were mobile, they
could adapt to situations, okay?
So, if one part of the phalanx
was being threatened, then
the shield bearers could converge on
that and like basically leak the dam.
Does that make sense? Right?
So, what made Philip so,
such a genius was he
was very flexible, okay?
He was always looking at
what happened at battles
and making adjustments in
order to become stronger.
And that's why his soldiers were so loyal
to him, because he was such a great general.
And he put the lives of his men first.
First and foremost, okay? And what we will
discover in the next class is Alexander is the complete opposite.
He's always risking the lives of his men.
Does that make sense? Okay.
Any more questions? But
that's a great question.
Yeah. Sorry. Sorry. I obviously don't have
enough time to go into all the details, okay?
There's a lot of changes, okay? But
the phalanx is a major innovation.
But it could have been well -developed.
Yeah. Yeah. So,
what's the difference
between the phalanx and
the phalanx?
Well, you have the
shield bearers in place.
What about above you?
Excuse me? Above you.
Above you? Yeah.
Okay. Well, they have helmets
and they have shields as well.
Okay. Do you understand?
The shield is really mobile. That's right.
Yeah. So, the shield bearers were really
the secret sauce of the Macedonian army,
okay? Because the shield bearers
were meant to resolve any issues
that might arise in battle.
Yeah. But yeah.
So, do you understand how this works?
Okay. But you have the flexibility because
these are extremely disciplined
and loyal men, okay?
And what we'll discover is, when
we get to Alexander is, even though
Alexander was bold and aggressive.
He would make mistakes.
But the loyalty and
discipline of the Macedonian army would
compensate for a lot of his strategic mistakes,
okay? Does that make sense?
Great. Any more questions?
Okay. So, was this interesting for you?
Yeah. Okay. And this is clear, right?
Because again, the thing about this class that's
different is we build on all this knowledge,
okay? We will see how military
strategy changes over time.
And we'll see how the Greeks,
the Macedonians, will
influence Greek culture, okay?
All right. So, next class, we
will do Alexander the Great.
Okay? Bye.
Bye. Bye. Bye.