So this will be a fun class today.
We are doing the Great Pyramid.
Okay, so
the Great Pyramid was
built about 2500 BCE,
that's 4500 years ago,
by a pharaoh named Curfew.
And it was one of the
seven great wonders of the ancient world.
It's the only one that's still standing.
From 2500 until 1400 CE,
which is about 4000 years,
it was the tallest
man -made building in the world.
Okay? Okay? The Great Pyramid,
the direction is true north,
meaning you can actually use the pyramids
as a compass to tell the directions.
Let's look at the architecture
of the Great Pyramid.
So the center is something
called the King's Chamber.
That's where the King's mummy
rests in the sarcophagus.
There's a grand gallery that gives
you access to the King's Chamber.
And then a slope.
And then it's a pyramid structure.
And on the top of the pyramid
is what is called the Ben -Ben.
Or the Pyrrhonion.
Okay? The Pyrrhonion.
Okay? And it is extremely significant
culturally and religiously in Egypt.
Because in Egyptian mythology,
the religion, the creator god, Atum,
he's known as Atum, he's also
known as Ra, the sun god,
first came into existence on the Ben -Ben.
So imagine a large dark ocean.
And there's nothing. And then
suddenly emerges a mound.
Okay? Called a Ben -Ben.
And that's where comes
the creator god, Atum.
Or Ra. Okay?
That's one legend. The other legend
is from the dark ocean of space,
comes down a Ben -Ben.
And on top of it rests Atum.
Okay? So this idea of the
Pyrrhonion, the Ben -Ben,
it is central to the idea of
creation in Egyptian mythology.
So this is an extremely powerful
and
beautiful monument to Egyptian culture.
Architecturally, Napoleon,
who visited the Great Pyramid,
he calculated that
if you took all the stones
from the Great Pyramid,
you could actually build a wall
around the perimeter of France.
There's more material in the Great
Pyramid except for two structures.
The first structure is
the Great Wall of China.
There's more stone in
Okay? There's more stone,
there's more material in
the Great Three Gorges Dam.
Also in China. Okay?
And it took about 26 years
to build this pyramid.
So today, in today's class, I'm
going to look at three questions.
The first question is,
how did they build this?
Because it's still with us today.
You can actually go to Egypt
and visit the Great Pyramid.
Second question is, why
did they build this?
What was the purpose? And
the third question is,
why did they stop building the pyramids?
Okay? So those are the three
questions we're looking at today.
How was it built? Why was it built?
And why did the Egyptians
stop building the pyramids?
So, how it was built is an
extremely controversial question
that has plagued historians
and Egyptologists
and archaeologists for hundreds of years.
Okay? And
originally, a Greek historian,
Herodotus, proposed the idea
the pyramid was built in steps.
Okay? So it was first a
step pyramid, and then
using pulleys, they pulled the stones up.
Okay? And it was the accepted
idea for the longest time.
There was no better idea.
But architecturally,
that has been disproven.
Okay? It can't work that way. Then,
about ten years ago, there was a French
architect named John Pierre Houdin.
Okay? H -O -U -D -I -N, Houdin.
And he's an architect.
He's never been to Egypt.
Doesn't speak Arabic. Never studied Egypt.
But his father and
him were very interested in how
the Great Pyramid was constructed.
So he came up with this theory.
And they've run computer simulations
and discovered this to be true.
There's also a lot of physical evidence
to suggest this theory is true.
Okay? So this is how they
built the Great Pyramid.
What they did was,
they first constructed an external
ramp in order to build the base.
Okay? So you now have the base.
And then from the base, what they did was,
they built two structures.
Okay? And this is what
they call counterweights.
Okay? So these counterweights
are like pulleys, which
allows them to pull
the stones up, up high.
Okay? And then
surrounding these two structures is what
they call an eternal spiral ramp.
Okay? To carry the stones up.
And so what they did was, they basically
built the pyramids from the inside out.
And then once they built the structure,
they covered it up with limestone.
So that it reflects in the sun.
Okay? If you actually were living with
a person, you would have a limestone.
But if you were living back then, and
you saw the pyramids from a distance,
you would think it was the star that
has come down on the planet Earth.
Okay? So
that's how they built the pyramid.
But then this raises another
interesting question,
is how they come up with this plan.
And how were they able to
do this without blueprints
and without basically writing,
or modern engineering techniques?
And the answer is, if you think
about it, what they did was,
they built a model right
beside the pyramid,
which allowed them to figure out
how to build a larger pyramid.
Okay? But,
inontologists still believe
this was not possible,
because they believe that
Egyptians didn't have the intellectual
capacity to imagine this to be true.
Okay? And I'll show you later
on that they actually did,
that we underestimate their imagination
and their intellectual capacity.
So that answers the first question
pretty easily, how is it built?
A more controversial
question is why was it built?
And for the longest time,
the accepted theory is this is a tomb,
a tomb. The reason why is Egyptians
believed in the afterlife.
And so the theory is
this pyramid is designed
to ease the Pharaoh's
transition into the heavens
where he would become a star or a sun.
And so the common phrase is this
is almost a resurrection machine
where the Pharaoh goes up to the sky
and then after a few centuries,
he reincarnates inside the pyramid.
And the structure is
meant to accomplish this.
And again, this is the generally
accepted theory today.
But there are three major
problems with this theory
which basically makes it,
which basically discounts it.
The first major problem is
there are about 100 pyramids
in Egypt. 100 or more.
We don't know, okay?
We have not found a mummy
or a body inside any
sarcophagus inside the pyramids.
So this is a problem.
If this is a tomb,
why is there no body?
We can't find the body, okay?
So that's one problem.
Second problem is this.
For this to be a tomb, this implies
that the Pharaoh, because the
Pharaoh's so divine, right?
They are basically the
emanation of God on earth.
This means that when they
come to the planet earth
and they come to Pharaoh, their
priority is to build their own tomb,
right?
Does that make any sense? They come
to earth and they're like, okay,
well I'm gonna die so I wanna get
out of here as soon as possible
so let's build our tomb, right?
Now the problem is that this would imply
that the Pharaoh sees the
Egyptian people as his slave.
You exist in order for me to live.
And so,
but the problem is that
in Egyptian mythology,
gods are considered
benefactors of the human race.
So for example, Atum -Ra, he is the one
who gave life to the
world, but then his son,
his descendant Osiris, another
god, gave civilization to Egypt.
And then Horus, the son of Osiris,
gave the institution of
kingship to Egypt. So
these gods come to earth in order
to help the human race
develop in some capacity.
So it doesn't make any sense that
the Pharaoh's primary purpose when
he's on earth is to create a tomb
because that's a very selfish reason.
Does that make sense?
And the third problem with
this is just pure logic.
If you're a Pharaoh and your
primary concern is the afterlife,
resurrecting yourself, and
the pyramid is a primary
means of accomplishing this,
and it takes about 26 years or
30 years to build a pyramid,
how can you be sure that
you won't die before the pyramid is built?
Right? That's a problem.
So these are three logical problems.
But again, Egyptologists insist that
it is a tomb, primarily because of the way
that Egyptians understand the afterlife.
So here's some evidence
to suggest it is a tomb.
This is considered
a writing of a Pharaoh to
his son about the pyramid.
So this is what he says. Make
your grave well furnished
and prepare thy place in the west.
The west is where they go off to die.
Look, death counts little for us.
We can conquer death. Look,
life is valued highly by us.
We want to become immortal.
The house of the dead,
meaning the tomb, is for life.
So the pyramid is what
will make us immortal.
So this is, again, highly debated today.
So logically speaking, it
doesn't make sense that
the pyramids are a tomb, but there's a
lot of evidence to suggest it is a tomb.
And because of this debate,
different theories have been
proposed as to the purpose of the
pyramid. And there are lots of
really strange theories out there.
OK? Lots of really strange theories.
One really interesting theory was
proposed by a man named Nikola Tesla,
the founder, the creator
of electricity, basically.
And his idea was this.
He studied the architecture of the pyramid
and he proposed the pyramid
was a battery system,
OK, in order to create free
clean energy. And the theory is this, OK?
The theory is, first of all, if
you look at the King's Chamber,
the sound frequency in it is F sharp.
And F sharp is also the
frequency of planet Earth.
OK? So it seems like the pyramid
is attuned to the planet Earth.
Second of all, if you look at
where
the pyramids are geographically,
it's true north.
OK? It's put in a place that
matches the directions
of the Earth. And so
the theory is the direction of the pyramid
is capturing the energy from
the electromagnetic field
that the Earth generates.
OK? And the third explanation is inside
the pyramids are granite stones
and outside are limestones.
And this is a perfect way
to trap and store energy.
OK? So think of a solar panel where
the Sun and the Moon reflects
light onto the pyramids
and this energy stored inside the pyramid.
Okay? And so this is a great theory.
And again, there are lots of
people who believe in this because
this is actually much more plausible
than the tomb theory.
But the problem with this, of course,
is it doesn't work scientifically.
And also you have the question of, if
they produce all this free, clean energy,
what are they using it for? Okay?
So this leads us with a big question.
Why did they build the Great Pyramid?
And today I want to propose
to you another solution.
The solution is this.
My belief is the Great Pyramid
was designed as Egypt's Manhattan Project.
Okay? The Manhattan
Project, as you know, uh,
was a World War II project in
order to build the nuclear bomb.
And you can argue, nuclear bomb is
humanity's greatest invention ever.
It took about 130,000 people
over five to six years
working in the United
States, in Canada, in UK.
And these are the best scientists
in the world at this time.
Okay? Working collectively in
order to create the nuclear bomb.
And you can also make the argument that
there are many working on the project
who
believe the Manhattan Project was
about bringing peace to Earth,
eternal peace. It was ultimately about
mastering the secrets of the universe,
channeling the power of God
in order to create eternal
peace, to bring God on Earth.
And you can also argue that
because we've had no major
war, after World War II,
fingers crossed, they were right.
Okay? So that's my argument to you.
The Egyptians conceptualized
and created the Great Pyramid in order
to harness the power of God
in order to create eternal peace on Earth.
To bring an end to history.
To bring an end to pain,
suffering, and death. Okay?
So, before I provide the evidence,
let me explain this theory in general.
Okay? And again, this is my theory.
It's speculation. It's imagination.
But I think it makes sense. Okay?
So let me explain the theory to you.
The trick is the body of the pharaoh.
The mummy. Okay? Now,
if the pharaoh, was divine, and the
Egyptians believed he was divine,
then after his death, the body
would be sacred and divine.
Right? But knowing that,
if you think about it,
after the pharaoh dies,
he would ascend to the heavens
and become a star or a sun.
Right? The body then
becomes a portal or a mechanism for
you to communicate with the pharaoh
while he's in the heavens.
You can also argue that,
the body, the mummy,
could be a mechanism for you
to channel the pharaoh's powers on earth.
Okay? So, imagine this.
You have the sarcophagus.
The mummy is inside.
Okay? Okay?
And then, you have the grand gallery.
And inside the grand gallery,
what are people doing?
They are there praying and
worshipping the pharaoh.
Which then
draws the energy from
the stars onto the earth.
And then, because of the limestone,
this energy is
reflected across Egypt.
So,
the entire nation can bask in
the divine energy of the pharaoh.
Okay? So, Nikola Tesla said,
that this was a battery
in order to channel free,
clean energy to power Egypt.
Well, what if you change this
to divine energy instead?
The pyramid was a battery to channel
divine energy in order
to power Egypt. Right?
Now, let me discuss, if you are a woman,
if you are a worshipper
in the grand gallery,
what are you experiencing?
Okay? Well, first of all,
you are experiencing the collision,
the nexus of life and death.
Right? Because the pharaoh, he's dead,
but he's still alive for your faith.
Even though you're mortal,
you are now in communication with God.
Okay? So, this is a
nexus of life and death.
Okay? This grand channel,
sorry, this grand gallery, if
you actually have such a visit,
it in Egypt,
okay, you'll recognize that
this almost looks like a womb.
Okay? All right? So,
it's almost like you're
inside a dark space that's
taking you back to the
point of your birth.
Right? But it's also, you
can also be seen as a tree.
A tomb. A place where
you're being buried. So,
this is also like another collision
or conflation or nexus of being born
and dying.
If you were outside and
you just saw the pyramid,
again, you would think of it as
a star that has landed on earth.
Right? So, this is a conflation,
a nexus of heaven and earth.
It's a collision, a nexus
of myth and reality.
You can also make the argument
that through divine worship,
what you're really doing is you're reversing
the great bang, sorry, the big bang.
You're reversing the big bang. You're
bringing it into this one space.
And you are creating oneness,
wholeness, and completeness.
You have achieved the union and
the unity of all things through
your faith in the Pharaoh,
which gives you divine
energy to be born anew,
cleanse of your sins,
and to cleanse others of their sins,
to create a moral Egypt.
Okay? Does that make sense?
All right, so that's the theory.
So now let me explain the
idea of eternal peace.
Why would the pyramid
create the idea of eternal peace?
Well, the first reason is even
though Egypt was an empire,
a dynasty at this point, it
was still divided culturally.
Okay? There were at least four different
cultures scattered around Egypt.
And they all had their own mythologies.
They had all their own
religious practices.
They had their own faiths.
All right? So the point of this pyramid
was to unite all these faiths
into one singular object
in the worship of the Pharaoh.
If you were an Egyptian citizen,
if you were in Egypt and
you looked at the pyramid,
you could not help but
think, this is God on earth.
Okay? This centers your faith
and it forces your obedience and your submission
to a higher authority, which is the Pharaoh.
Okay? That's the first reason, unity.
Second is the idea of awe.
So let's just say
you're a powerful army and you're an
enemy and you want to conquer Egypt.
Well, you send your scouts to Egypt
and they see the pyramids, right?
The Great Pyramid. What are they seeing?
They're seeing God on earth. Okay?
So you're not going to
attack God on earth.
You're going to run away. So it creates
a sense of awe around the world.
All right? The last thing is
the domination of nature.
So through divine inspiration,
Egyptians are able to
summon the Great Pyramid.
And it shows the God's
ability to control nature.
Why is this important?
Because the source of Egyptian
wealth and power is the Nile River.
Okay? The Nile River.
And basically, it's the Nile River that
has made Egypt the wealthiest country
in the world for thousands of years.
Okay? So the thing about the
Nile is if it's in a good mood,
you live a very good life
because the Nile just floods,
just floods the banks
and leaves this rich soil
and then you just throw some seeds in it and
then you can grow all these crops very easily.
Okay? It's a very easy life.
And you can become very wealthy that way.
So if it's in a good mood, then
you are a very happy person.
But if it's in a bad mood, for example,
it doesn't flood or it floods too much,
you could die of salvation
or of drowning. Okay?
So it's very important for you to be
able to control the moods of the gods.
And that's what the
pyramid is meant to do.
The Egyptian word for Egypt is Kemet,
which basically means black earth.
So the source of all life
in Egypt is the soil,
the black earth.
Okay? So let's go back to this quotation.
And now we can actually
understand it in a different way.
Right? Make your grave well furnished
and prepare thy place in the west.
That's fine. Now, look,
death counts little for us.
We're gods. We're pharaohs.
We will never die, so we
don't worry about death.
We don't have to worry about dying.
Okay? Look, life is valued highly by us.
What is life? Life, our
humans, the Egyptian people.
Our concern as pharaohs is for the
well -being of the Egyptian people.
So that's our primary responsibility.
Okay? The house of the dead,
the pyramid, is for life.
The pyramid is our legacy
to the Egyptian people.
It is our benevolence.
It is our generosity. It is
how we will make Egypt eternal
and stable and prosperous.
Okay? So that's my theory
of what the pyramid is.
It is really the Manhattan Project.
An attempt by the pharaohs
to bring eternal peace.
Okay, any questions about this
idea before I elaborate on it
and present the evidence for it?
Any questions about this?
You guys don't find this controversial?
Are you confused by any of this?
Do you want to challenge me
before I present the evidence?
Okay, all right. So let me start
presenting the evidence, okay?
So the first piece of evidence
is, again, Egyptian mythology.
All right? So in Egyptian mythology,
and it's very different from other
mythologies we'll study in the future, like that of Mesopotamia,
the gods give everything to the people.
Okay? The people don't really do anything.
Ra gives life.
Osiris gives civilization.
Horus provides the kingship.
Okay? So the Egyptian understanding
of the relationship with the gods is basically
if they worship the gods well enough,
the gods will always reward them.
Okay? So the idea, like, the,
you know, the gods will make the people
build tombs doesn't really make any sense.
Okay? It makes more sense.
The pharaoh is helping the
Egyptians achieve eternal peace
by inspiring them to build the pyramid.
Okay? The second thing is
the architectural quality
of the pyramid.
Now, there is a misconception,
a myth, that pyramids
were built by slaves.
They just had slaves, they used slaves,
but they never used slaves
for religious purposes.
Right? Because slaves, you
can't really trust slaves.
So it was tens of thousands of laborers
who built the pyramid together.
And it's a complete mystery to people
how they're able to achieve
such a miraculous building.
Okay? And so the answer is this.
Let's think about for
the past thousand years.
The most impressive buildings in
the world are usually churches,
temples, mosques, right?
So that just demonstrates
the power of religious devotion
in the act of creation. So
if the Egyptians saw the
pyramids as the ultimate temple,
as bringing God on earth,
you can imagine every one of them would
work very hard in order to do their best.
Does that make sense? Okay?
The third is the idea of
the cult of the skull.
So around this time, and
throughout the world,
people practiced ancestors of worship.
So the way they did that usually is
maybe they have an ancestor
who was well regarded.
They would keep a skull around.
They would decorate it
with clay and ochre.
And they would use this skull as
maybe a portal into the outer world,
into the spirit world, in order to draw
inspiration, to draw good luck from this.
Okay? So the idea that
they would use the Pharaoh's body as
a portal into the heavens is a very,
would be a very common idea at that time.
All right? And then
you have cave paintings.
So remember way back, way
earlier in the semester,
we looked at Ice Age cave paintings.
Inside, so these paintings inside caves.
And we discussed these paintings
were a means of religious worship,
of bringing the spirit
world into our world,
connecting the two, okay,
in order to celebrate life and hunting.
Okay? Then you have a place
like Gopalapet Thetple,
which is considered one
of the earliest temples.
Okay? Remember it is a religious
monument on top of a hill,
okay, which,
would be also another way for you to
connect our world with the heavens.
And for your worship, draw
divine energy from the heavens.
Okay? So this, in other words,
there's a pattern of humans
trying to connect the spirit world with
our world through religious worship.
And the pyramid represents
the ultimate temple.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So the pyramid is a continuation
of this sort of religious devotion
and worship and religious practice.
Okay? All right.
Okay. Any questions before I move on?
Okay. So now the last question is,
why did they stop building a pyramid?
And there's a very good reason why
they stopped building a pyramid.
Because remember, this pyramid
was about creating eternal peace,
pleasing the gods, unifying the world.
Right? That's a theory.
The problem is this theory doesn't work.
Because in about 2200 BCE,
the 4.2,
4.2 kilo year event happened.
Okay? Think of this as a mini ice age,
where for about 100 years,
there's a drought in Egypt.
Well, that's a problem, right?
Because the entire point of the pyramid,
why people sacrificed themselves so
hard to work on the pyramid,
was to prevent a drought in Egypt.
Right? It was to control the Nile.
And they failed. So this creates,
first of all, a crisis of faith.
Okay? A crisis of faith.
Many now are forced to reject
their faith in the Pharaoh.
And now you see the
rise of the priesthood.
Okay? And other gods as well.
So the first major reason why they stopped
building the pyramids is a crisis of faith.
Second problem is, in order
to build the pyramids,
you need a pyramid economy.
Okay? A pyramid economy.
And what the pyramid economy represents
is centralized planning, right?
Centralization. The Pharaoh
and his palace are able to
coordinate all the resources
of the state in order
to create the pyramids.
We need to build the pyramids. And we know
that when you have a centralization,
you have three problems.
The first is inequality. So if
you're part of this planned economy,
you do very well for yourself.
Okay? But if you're not,
then you become poor.
Okay? So inequality is a huge issue.
But you also have a problem of corruption,
where people in the system,
they want to steal because
it's just easier to do.
Okay? And the third problem is just waste.
It's not very efficient. So
basically, a pyramid economy
is just a complete waste of resources.
All right? And the third problem is this.
Okay? And this is actually a much more...
Okay? This is a huge problem.
Okay? This idea of a
nihilistic religious belief.
What this religious saying is,
life doesn't matter.
It's death that matters.
It's death that allows us to be
like God, to be eternal. Right?
In order to ensure our
ascent into godhood,
one, we have to be close to the Pharaoh.
Okay? We have to be loyal to the Pharaoh.
But two,
we have to ensure we obtain
a lot of wealth in our life.
Okay? So basically,
what Egypt was doing during the pyramid
economy was taking all its grain,
all its resources, and then
selling it overseas in order to
bring back precious metals that
they could put in their graves so that
they could take these precious metals,
gold, jewelry, into the
afterlife with them.
Okay? So basically,
they were just taking all this
tremendous wealth of Egypt,
almost unlimited wealth of
Egypt, and just squandering it,
gambling it away, basically, and then,
they were just taking all this precious wealth and the promise of an eternal afterlife.
And they really didn't care
about the here and now.
They didn't care about
building a great nation.
They really weren't concerned about
ensuring everyone was well off
and prosperous and happy in a nation.
Okay? So you had an elite who
was concerned about abusing
the power in order to steal
as much money as possible in
order to ensure a good afterlife.
Okay? And this is the three major reasons
why they stopped building the pyramids.
Okay? One, because it's a crisis of faith.
It doesn't really work.
Second is, the centralization creates
inequality, corruption, and waste.
And third is, religious
belief can only lead to
the corruption of the state and tyranny.
Okay? So,
I answered those questions. Any
questions before I continue?
Okay.
think of the scale of
time that the Egyptians,
they struck against.
maybe, do you use this
as part of the and think of that
in terms of the space of the time that
they're going to be even at 200 years,
can you imagine if you could
imagine every year the color of
that map? Right.
So, yeah, that's a great point.
Okay? So, you're actually
right that even though
they stopped building
pyramids, this civilization
could go on for another 2,000 years.
And it was still for the majority of that,
a very prosperous, stable nation.
That was basically the
hegemon of the Western world.
Okay? So, this is the Old Kingdom.
That's what they, the Old Kingdom
focused on building the pyramids,
but the Middle Kingdom and New Kingdom
would also have a lot of glory as,
as well. So, I don't mean to denigrate
the society. Okay?
I'm just pointing out some
logical flaws in the society
that will lead to their
eventual decay.
Because, even though
the Old Kingdom will collapse,
the society is very resilient.
So, as I said,
the Old Kingdom will be replaced by the
Middle Kingdom after a large civil war.
Also, they will make changes to society
that will make society much more stable.
And the main reason for
the major change is to
take all the centralized
powers of the pharaoh and
then devolve it into the priesthood
and creating a priest bureaucracy.
Okay? Which is very much like the
Confucian bureaucracy in China. And
they will also start importing
new ideas from overseas.
So, I apologize if I'm implying
that this is the end of Egypt.
It's not. After the Old Kingdom,
after they stopped building the pyramids,
they started building the pyramids you will have a new flourishing of creativity
and innovation in Egypt.
But, they stopped perceiving the
pyramids as the end of beyond.
Whereas, and the point I want to make is,
during the Old Kingdom, they did perceive
the pyramids as the Manhattan Project.
Okay? They really thought if we build this
thing, then there will be eternal peace.
And you can also make
the argument that the
Israelites were not because
there's the Tower of Babel story, right?
The Tower of Babel story where
the humans are erroringly
trying to build a
tower up to heaven to be with God, right?
And you can argue that's
what the pyramid is.
And God laughs at them and mocks them and
they never succeed and
then God punishes them by
making them speak different languages.
Right? I have another question.
Sure. Sorry, it might be
really hard to answer.
So, it seems to get to around
the common narrative of the.
Did you know like the Egyptians
spoke themselves about the
pyramids at that point?
There's no motivation that
they've gone and lost them.
Did they have a different Okay.
So, this is a great question, okay?
What do the Egyptians remember
about the Great Pyramid?
So, Herodotus was writing
about 400 B.C., okay?
And this is about 2,000 years
after the Great Pyramid.
And Herodotus travels around Egypt and he's
a basically a historian, he's a journalist.
He wants to know how they
built the Great Pyramid.
And what he discovers is
the Egyptians don't know.
Not only do they not know,
but they don't even
know how to rebuild one.
Okay? If you ask the Egyptian in
400 B.C., can you build a pyramid?
They've lost their expertise. Okay?
And so, let me elaborate on this.
When I talk about the pyramid economy,
I'm talking about three things.
I'm talking about specialization,
right? Just massive specialization,
including how to carve granite,
how to move granite,
how to do measurements, okay?
You have specialization going on.
Then you have something
called industrialization.
Which is basically creating
a memory of this knowledge.
And you do that through, by passing
this knowledge to your sons
and your grandsons and to,
maybe in a guild or workshop, okay?
And then you also have systemization.
Which is to say, you have to
bring all these pieces together.
Okay? So, the pyramid economy
was extremely complex because you
need all three things to happen
at the same time. Specialization
and systemization.
You can also argue the man who created this
system, the pyramid economy, his name is Imhotat.
Okay? And he's revered in Egypt as
a divine figure.
Okay? I mean, he was a, basically,
grand vizier to the Pharaoh.
He was royalty, but he was a man.
But he was able to
contribute so much to Egypt
that they deified him, basically.
Okay? And you can argue
like his major contribution
was in creating this pyramid
economy that are all three elements.
Specialization, institutionalization, and
systemization. Okay?
Because it's actually very hard
to put the pieces together.
You need writing, a writing system.
You need a financial system.
You need a lot, a lot of elements.
Okay? I'm making this sound a lot easier
than it really is.
Okay? So, that's the first thing.
Very complex. Second thing is, remember,
for the Egyptians and for the Pharaoh,
the pyramids represented God and Earth.
Right? So, there has to be
mystery and secrecy around
the building of the pyramid.
Right? So, as I said,
what makes the most sense is for them
to build these models around the pyramid
so that these working teams would
know where to go at what time.
Okay? But after they build the pyramids,
it would make sense for them to destroy
all records in order to maintain
a sense of divinity and inspiration.
Right? They're trying to create awe
and fear and inspiration.
So, they would not want
for people to, like, know
how to build the pyramids.
They would think this has to be a
gift from God, from the Pharaoh.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay. But that's a great question.
Thanks. Okay.
Any more questions before I move on?
Okay. That's a great question.
Where was the mummy of the Pharaoh?
Okay. So, in this theory,
you have to understand what
matters is not the pyramid.
What matters is the body, the Pharaoh.
Right? Because it's the Pharaoh's
body that's sacred in the vine.
So, if it's sacred in the vine,
then you need a priesthood,
a cult of the Pharaoh to secure
and take care of the body. Okay?
Does that make sense? So, in other words,
there had to be a team
taking care of the
Pharaoh's body, the mummy.
And that ensure, first
and foremost, its safety.
Okay? So,
the Great Pyramid was part of a
complex called the Giza complex.
So, there are actually two other pyramids.
And then around the pyramids
are these tombs of people
who worked for the Pharaoh
but who were not the Pharaoh.
is the vine. Okay? And you can make the
argument what they're trying to do is create a constellation.
Right? Because when you look at the sky,
stars don't travel by themselves, they travel in constellations.
So, it makes sense for the son and
the grandson to be buried alongside curfew
but as lesser deities,
as lesser pyramids to show the
Egyptian people the harmony,
balance, and order of the system.
Okay? And
what's great is
it ensures loyalty
of people working for the
Pharaoh because you're loyal,
you're granted a tomb
around the Pharaoh which
guarantees your ascension
into the eternal afterlife.
So, you can be eternally with
the Pharaoh.
Okay? So, this is a system
of morality basically.
Right? So, this is fine
because there's lots of protections
for the Pharaoh, right?
He's surrounded by many different
systems. But, when
the system was breaking down, it was clear
that Egypt was breaking into civil war,
then the cult of the Pharaoh had
a responsibility to take the body
and place it somewhere
that no one could find it.
Right? Because again, what matters
in this system is not the pyramid,
what matters is the body.
The body is what gives the
pyramids energy and power.
So, they have to protect
that body at all costs.
So, the reason why we can't find the body
is they made sure we cannot find the body.
Right? Because the body is the mechanism,
the portal by which the Pharaoh
will resurrect himself.
If we have that, then
we control the Pharaoh.
We control God. Okay?
Does that make sense? So,
they must have a secret cave
or places where they put these bodies and
the purpose is to ensure
they can never be found.
Okay, so great question.
Thank you. Any more questions
before I finish the class?
Okay. So,
what's inside the pyramid? So,
first of all, the pyramids have been
around for about 45 hundred years.
And, tomb raiding was
a huge problem in the
early what's actually in the pyramids
we are not, we can't be sure about.
Right? Because of time,
because of tomb raiding.
Okay? We,
we didn't find that much
inside the pyramid.
Okay? There were no
pictures, artwork. There were very few
hieroglyphics inside the Great Pyramid.
There were hieroglyphics and paintings
which I think gives even more
credence to my theory that
this was meant to be a temple of worship.
Okay? And,
this is also why people believe it's
a tomb because there's so few artwork.
If you, if it were a temple instead, you would
imagine it, there would be a lot of artwork.
Okay? Okay.
Any more questions before I
finish the class? Are
you guys clear so far?
All right. So, I want to finish
the class with a different question
which is,
why is it like my interpretation is
so radically different from the
mainstream academic interpretation?
Okay? And, I want to propose the way
that our minds work today are
radically different from the way
that the minds of people
like the Egyptians worked.
Okay? For three reasons. Today,
the Egyptian people had a
pre -literate mind.
They also had a pre -science mind.
Also, pre -capitalistic.
Okay? So, let me explain.
Pre -literate is very simple.
It just means they didn't read and write.
They just spoke. And,
we are taught to read and write.
literate mind is more
powerful than the oral mind.
But, that's not true. Okay?
If you think about it, the oral mind
works through imagination.
The oral mind is capable
of tremendous memory.
Because back then, in order to do anything,
you have to memorize a lot of information.
Now, we can just
go online. Right?
So, their minds, even though they were
pre -literate, they were much more
imaginative than we are today.
And, their memories were stronger.
That's why they were able
to build a great pyramid.
Because everyone was able
to memorize the model and
figure out his or her
place inside the structure.
They were also able to imagine
in their heads the great pyramid.
Remember, Homer and Virgil.
The way that children learned
to visualize was by memorizing them.
And you can do that.
There are people today who memorize
the Koran and who memorize the Torah.
It takes some time, but
you're able to do that.
So, back then, they were
able to build the pyramid
because they were able to visualize
the pyramid in their minds.
And you can do that with
a pre -literate mind.
Okay? Second is the idea of pre -science.
So, in today's world,
we, science is our god.
Okay? So, in school, you're taught the
scientific method, which is basically
you collect information, then you
synthesize it, then you write your thesis.
Okay? It's a step -by
-step logical process.
But, if you're, if you're
a pre -scientific mind,
then where do you get your ideas from?
You get your ideas through divine
inspiration, through God, right?
So, you can make the
argument, like back then,
they were capable of these grand ideas
that we're not capable of today because
we're locked in by the
discipline of science.
The other problem with science
is it's very materialistic,
meaning we're focused on the here and now.
We're focused on what we can see as opposed
to what we feel or what we believe.
Right? So, when
we look at the pyramid, we're always about what
was built instead of like what were they feeling
when they were building this.
And that's a huge difference.
And the third difference
is pre -capitalistic.
Today, we do things to make money.
We come to school because
we want to get a job
because we want to make money
and we want to buy things.
Okay? It's a very utilitarian mindset.
But, for most of human history, most
civilizations were not capitalistic.
They were religious They
were focused on community.
They were focused on what they could contribute
to the betterment of the people around them.
They were concerned about
their relationship with God.
They were concerned about how
to create peace in the world.
They were asking big questions
like what is good and what is evil?
What is justice? What is fairness?
What is justice? And so,
they were much more focused on
building the world and the pyramid
as a way to build community and peace
and eternity on earth.
Okay? So, in other words,
what's interesting is even
though we are much more
technologically advanced,
we're much wealthier than the Egyptians,
we don't have the imagination,
we don't have the will to build
something like the Great Pyramid again.
Okay? And
that's why I think even today the
Great Pyramid captures imagination
and it's a great representation of so many
people around the world because it's really beyond our own imagination.
It really shows the limitations
of our own imagination.
All right? Okay.
That's it. Any questions?
Okay. Yeah.
Let's all be intuitive
in free science here.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. So, this begins the Bronze Age.
Okay? This is part of the Bronze Age.
Egypt is the greatest
civilization of the Bronze Age.
Next class we'll look at Mesopotamia
and the Innis Valley civilization.
Okay? So, there are three
great Bronze Age civilizations.
Egypt, Mesopotamia and
the Innis Valley. Okay?