Okay, let's start class.
So let's review where we are.
We are discussing or exploring why
the United States would
want to invade Iran.
And so far we have two good reasons.
The first good reason is
called the Israel lobby.
There are in the Israel lobby
millions of Christian Zionists
who believe that a
conflict in Middle East,
especially between Israel and Iran,
will bring Jesus back to earth.
They want their God,
Jesus, to return to earth
and they believe that
a war in the Middle East
will force him to return.
That's the first reason.
Second reason is the idea of an empire.
America is an empire and
as an empire it has a lot of privileges.
For example, it can just print as much
money as it wants, right? US dollars.
Right now America is 34
trillion dollars in debt
and the debt is growing by a
trillion dollars every two months.
America can do this as
long as it is an empire,
as long as people fear America.
But, as we discussed last class,
with Putin's invasion of Ukraine,
people are now starting to
rebel against the empire
and therefore
America must demonstrate it still
is the military hegemon of the world and
therefore it can do this by
invading Iran. Today we look at the third
and final force driving
conflict in Middle East and it's really
the conflict between Saudi Arabia,
and Iran.
Most people think that
Iran's major enemy in the
Middle East is Israel.
In fact, Iran's major
enemy is Saudi Arabia.
These two are bitter rivals.
And to understand why, we
have to look at their history.
So the year is 1979.
At the start of 1979,
Saudi Arabia and Iran
are very good friends.
So let's look at a map of the Middle East.
Iran is here.
It's next to Iraq.
Saudi Arabia is down here.
Then this is Egypt.
You have Yemen here,
Oman. This is the Strait of Hormuz.
And this is the Suez Canal.
The Red Sea, basically.
And in 1979,
Saudi Arabia and Iran
were very good friends.
They had a lot of similarities.
They were both monarchies.
They were ruled by a king.
They were secular.
They relied on American
power to defend itself.
And they were both oil exporters.
Both very prosperous oil exporters.
But then in 1979,
a political earthquake
radically changed the
landscape of the Middle East.
In 1979, there was a bottom -up
revolution called the Islamic Revolution.
Before 1979, there was a general
consensus agreement in the Middle East
that religion and
politics would be separated.
But in 1979,
the people in Iran demanded three things.
First, they demanded that
the king,
they would not be ruled by a king.
That's the first demand.
Second is that the United States
would not be ruled by a king.
The U.S. should not interfere
in domestic politics.
Remember that before the king,
the Shah, was supported
by the American military.
And the third demand is that
as a Muslim people, as people
who believe in the Islamic religion,
the government should be
focused on Islamic law.
Okay? So,
in the referendum,
98% of the people of
Iran voted to install an Islamic
republic to replace their monarchy.
And this was completely unexpected.
And this caused an earthquake
throughout the Middle East.
In November of 1979,
600 religious extremists
tried to besiege Mecca.
Mecca is the holiest city
in the Islamic religion
because it's the birthplace
of the prophet Muhammad.
600 extremists tried to take the city over
and demand three things.
That the Saudi Arabian
monarchy should abdicate.
The United States should remove
itself from the Islamic world.
The United States should stop the Islamic
State from the eternal affairs of Saudi Arabia.
And Saudi Arabia should be
governed by Islamic law. Now,
this revolt was crushed by the military.
But from that day on, Iran
and Saudi Arabia became bitter enemies.
Because they were both trying to install
their vision of Islam on the Middle East.
Middle East. So
this rivalry between Iran
and Saudi Arabia took three forms.
The first form is religious.
So even though they're both Muslim
countries, Islamic countries,
they have different
versions of the religion.
So Saudi Arabia is Sunni
and Iran is Shiite.
Now you may ask what the difference
between these two different
branches of the religion are
and the answer is no one actually knows.
It's a very complicated issue.
The major difference is this.
In 610, the Prophet Muhammad,
in Medina, in the city of Medina,
he had a vision to found a
new religion called Islam.
And he spread this religion
throughout the Middle East,
throughout the Arab world, forever
transforming the Middle East.
When he died, there's a
problem of succession.
Who would succeed the Prophet
as the leader of the religion?
The Shiite people believe that
only people of
Muhammad's bloodline can be
the leaders of the religion.
The Sunni disagreed and said that
anyone who proved himself competent
and faithful to religion
could be the leader.
And so for hundreds of
years, these two groups,
the Sunni and the Shia, fought
a war over the succession.
And this led to a bitter rivalry
that's lasted to this day.
Now the majority of people in the world,
about 8%, are Sunni.
The majority of Muslims
in the world are Sunni.
10% are Shia.
So why this is important is
that Saudi Arabia is a Sunni country
and
Iran is a Shia country.
And at the time of the revolution,
Iran dedicated itself, committed itself,
to spreading the Shia
revolution throughout the world.
Now Saudi Arabia considers itself
the leader of the Islamic world
because it is home to both Mecca
and Medina, which
are the two holiest cities
in the entire Islamic religion.
As you may know, there's
a requirement that
as a Muslim,
you must take a Hajj, a pilgrimage,
to Mecca and Medina once in your lifetime.
And because Saudi Arabia
controls Mecca and
Medina, that's really the source of Saudi
Arabia's authority over the Islamic world.
Iran says, Iran argues
that because Saudi Arabia
is ruled by a king,
that's anti -Muslim.
And because United States is
defended by the US military,
that's also anti -Muslim.
Saudi Arabia is a heresy. So
Iran is dedicated itself
to subverting Saudi Arabia's authority.
So this is all makes sense so far.
Now Saudi Arabia is Sunni
and it practices the most
extreme form of Sunni
religion called Wahhabism.
In 1744 the Wahhabi's,
which again are the most
extreme Islamic group,
made an alliance with the Al
-Saad family of Saudi Arabia.
The agreement was this.
That the Wahhabi's could,
the Wahhabi's would become the
national religion of Saudi Arabia
and the Wahhabis would swear allegiance
to the Al -Assad family.
But in the 1930s,
oil was discovered in Saudi Arabia.
In fact,
Saudi Arabia proved to have the
most valuable oil
resources in all the world.
At that time, as the
world was modernizing,
oil was becoming more and more important.
That made Saudi Arabia extremely wealthy.
And as it became more and more wealthy,
it tried to become more Western,
more secular, more
progressive, more modern,
which brought it into
conflict with the Wahhabis.
Now, Wahhabism accounts for 20 to
40 percent of all the population.
The people in Saudi Arabia.
So it is a very significant group.
More important,
Wahhabi people tend to
be extremely fanatical.
So for example, in 1979, the people who
laid siege to Mecca were Wahhabis.
And Wahhabis were also responsible for
terrorist attacks against tourists,
against foreigners in Saudi Arabia.
So Saudi Arabia has always had
this problem with the Wahhabis.
And a way that
Saudi Arabia has tried to resolve
the conflict is to export
the religion of Wahhabism
throughout the world.
So for example, Osama bin Laden was a
Saudi citizen responsible for
spreading Wahhabism in Afghanistan.
And that's what started al -Qaeda.
So, what happened? Saudi Arabia
is trying to export Wahhabism.
Iran is trying to export
the Shiite religion.
And so they come into
conflict with each other.
So the first source of
tension between Iran
and Saudi Arabia is over religion.
Second is economical.
And what that means is that
both countries are oil exporters.
In fact, Saudi Arabia is
completely oil -exporting.
Saudi Arabia is completely
reliant on oil for its economy.
40% of Saudi
Arabia's economy GDP is
based on oil exports.
Saudi Arabia is number one
oil exporter in the world.
75% of government revenues
comes from its oil exports.
In other words, Saudi Arabia does not
actually collect taxes from its citizens.
It just sells oil. Okay?
Okay? Iran also sells oil.
It's the number four oil
exporter in the world.
But it's less reliant on oil because
it has a diversified economy, meaning
that it has very strong human capital.
It has a very well -educated population
that does all sorts of
different activities.
Okay? Science, art, education.
So Saudi Arabia, for the longest time,
has been trying to control this.
It's trying to control the price of
oil in order to maximize profits.
For example, it wants to cut back production
in order to increase the price of oil,
which will increase profits. But
Iran often doesn't cooperate because
Iran is trying to sell as much oil
as possible in order to boost its economy.
Okay? So there's economic conflict
between these two countries.
And the third and
final conflict is geopolitical.
Okay? And geopolitical means that
both countries are trying to exert
as much influence as possible
over the Middle East.
Now, Iran is trying to exert
influence over the Middle East
because after the revolution in 1979,
many countries,
including Saudi Arabia and the United
States, encouraged Iraq to invade Iran.
And this invasion, called
the Iraq -Iran War,
lasted eight years and
it cost the lives of millions of Iranians.
And from then on,
Iran has adopted a policy
of aggressive intervention in the
Middle East in order to distract
the United States and Israel.
Okay? So for example, in Israel,
there are two groups opposing Israel.
Hamas. And Pesbala.
And they're both financed and
supported politically by Iran.
And the point of doing
this is to distract Israel.
Okay? Now,
Saudi Arabia is trying to exert
influence over the Middle East
because as the number
one oil exporter, it needs
to control shipping lanes.
Okay? It needs to control
this area and this area.
The Strait of Hormuz and the Middle East.
And the other two are the Suez Canal. And
40% of all the world's oil passes through these two straits
and they go mainly to East Asia.
China, South Korea, and Japan mainly.
Okay? So because
of these geopolitical tensions,
Iran and
Saudi Arabia have fought three proxy wars.
Okay? They fought three shadow wars.
The first is in Iraq.
The second is in Syria.
The third is in Syria.
And now in Iraq, as you know, in 2003,
America invaded Iraq and
destroyed the country.
And after they destroyed the
country, there's a power vacuum.
And so basically, Iran came in
and tried to take over the country.
And it could do so because
two -thirds of the population were Shiite.
And therefore, they
had affinity with Iran.
Okay? Okay. And the third were Sunni.
So what happened was that
to counter the Iranian influence in Iraq,
Saudi Arabia started to finance the
one -third of the Sunnis
against the Shiite.
So there was a very violent civil war
fought in Iraq after the invasion.
Okay? Many people also believe that
Saudi Arabia is responsible for
the financing of the Islamic state.
Okay? Or ISIS.
Okay? And
ISIS really hates the Shiite religion.
Okay? But over time,
because Iran has been
so much more effective in projecting
its power than Saudi Arabia,
basically Iran now controls much of Iraq.
Okay? So in this first war,
Iran defeated Saudi Arabia.
Then they fought another war in Syria.
Syria's leader, Assad.
Assad faced a rebellion.
And Saudi Arabia, America,
Israel support the rebels against Assad.
And Iran came in to support
Assad as well as Russia.
And over time, Assad was
able to crush the rebellion.
Okay? So in the second proxy war,
Iran won as well.
Now, there's another proxy war in Yemen.
Okay? And it started in 2016.
So the wars in Iraq
and Syria, they were
important to Saudi Arabia,
but they didn't really
threaten Saudi Arabia.
But this war in Yemen did
So for the longest time,
Saudi Arabia supported the
Yemen political leadership.
And then they were able to win. And then
there was a rebellion by the Houthis.
The Houthis.
The Houthis. And
the Houthis were Shia villagers
who lived in the mountains.
And they were trying to
overthrow the government.
And Saudi Arabia was afraid that
the Houthis would become
friends with Iran.
So Saudi Arabia launched a
massive invasion of Yemen.
It was 150,000 people.
That was a lot of weapons.
That was a lot of weapons. That
was a lot of weapons.
That was a lot of weapons.
use is what we call shock and awe.
Shock and awe is basically
we have so many bombs,
we have so many airplanes,
we have so many soldiers that we can
in about a week's time destroy you.
So go in, go fast, be
decisive, destroy your enemy.
Unfortunately, for Saudi
Arabia this did not work.
The reason why is first of all
the Houthis were in the mountains
and so your bombs didn't really stop them.
In fact, all your bombs did
was make them really angry
because of your bombs you
were killing civilians.
So you're basically uniting the
entire population against you.
That's the first problem.
Second problem is
that the Houthis are in the mountains
but Saudi Arabia is not.
Saudi Arabia has oil
fields and guess what guys?
It's really, really easy
to blow up oil fields.
So that's what the Houthis are doing.
They were sending these cheap drones.
They might cost a thousand
dollars, ten thousand dollars and
they would blow up oil fields and ports.
Saudi Arabia has another problem.
Saudi Arabia has no fresh water.
It's in the desert.
It is a desert. No water.
No water guys. No rivers. So
it relies entirely on desalination plants.
Okay and this is extremely
impressive technology right?
It takes salt water, seawater
and turn it to fresh water.
It's very impressive but
it's on the coast and guess what guys?
The coast. So Iran can
blow up these plants
and the Houthis can blow
up these plants as well.
Okay? So
Saudi Arabia basically lost this war
because
the Houthis could inflict massive
economic damage on Saudi Arabia.
So from this war, Saudi
Arabia learned three things.
The first thing it learned is that
if it wants to defeat their enemies,
the Houthis, the Syrians, and the Iraqis,
they also need to be able to defeat Iran.
That's the first thing they learned.
Secondly, they learned is that
their economy is extremely
vulnerable to attack.
At any point, Iran, with its missiles
and drones, could destroy the
entire Saudi Arabian economy.
It can easily blow up all the oil
fields and the desalination plants.
So the third thing that
Saudi Arabia learned from all
this is we really need America.
We need America to fight Iran for us.
In the long term,
that's the only way we're
going to survive as a nation.
We need to defeat Iran.
And we can't do it by ourselves.
We need America to do it for us.
Unfortunately for Saudi Arabia,
in 2001,
9 -11 happened.
Right? Right? Right?
Right? Right? Right? Right?
Right? Right?
Right? America invaded Iraq,
Saudi Arabia tried to exert as much
influence as possible in Washington,
D.C. to stop the war because
they knew that if America invaded Iraq,
it would make Iran more powerful.
Now as you know, Saudi Arabia
could not stop the war.
In 2008,
Barack Obama came into office
and Barack Obama's
understanding of the world was
that the Middle East is a complete mess
and it's hopeless.
I don't really want to
deal with the Middle East.
Plus China is rising.
The main threat to
American power is China.
China in the future will be East Asia.
He proposed something
called the Asia Pivot, which
is to transfer American military resources
from the Middle East to East Asia
to counter the threat of China.
To do that,
you needed to reduce
tensions in the Middle East.
In 2015,
he made a deal with Iran
called the Iran Nuclear Deal.
The deal was basically...
Okay. Obama said to Iran,
listen, I know you're trying
to develop nuclear weapons. So
what we're going to do is if you
promise to not develop nuclear weapons,
we will lift economic sanctions on you
so that you can prosper.
And Iran said yes.
And this really scared Saudi Arabia.
Because if America
leaves the Middle East...
And brokers of peace with Iran,
then Saudi Arabia would
be extremely vulnerable.
Okay? So
Saudi Arabia became very, very desperate.
Its very existence was threatened.
Also, the economic outlook
for Saudi Arabia was not
that great.
Remember, the entire
economy depended on oil.
But guess what, guys?
Oil is a finite resource.
Eventually, you're
going to run out of oil.
Okay? Now, if you're optimistic,
you'll be like, well, Saudi Arabia would run out of
oil in about seven years' time or 80 years' time.
Okay? But there are also
some people who believe that
Saudi Arabia will run out of
oil in about 10 years' time.
And if Saudi Arabia has no oil,
then its entire economy collapses.
Okay? Then you also have a global crisis.
You also have a problem
with global warming, right?
Climate change.
You also have a problem with the
entire global economy is slowing down.
Therefore, the demand
for oil is decreasing.
So the economic outlook for Saudi
Arabia, it's extremely grim.
Okay? And
that's why in 2017,
Saudi Arabia appointed a new leader.
He's called Mohammed bin Salman.
Okay? The crown prince. Whoever calls MBS.
And MBS promised to be a new leader.
He was young.
He was progressive.
He wanted women to drive.
He wanted young people to
go to the movie theater.
Okay? And
he proposed a new vision
for Saudi Arabia called Vision for Women.
He's one of the many leaders
in Saudi Arabia. 2030.
But MBS's most important achievement is
that he became friends
with the new president, Donald Trump.
So in 2016,
Donald Trump became President
of the United States
and MBS decided that
this is an opportunity for Saudi
Arabia to reset relations with America.
So Trump,
his first trip outside
the United States was to Saudi Arabia.
That was the first achievement.
Second achievement is that
MBS became best friends with
Trump's son -in -law Jared Kushner.
Jared Kushner was Trump's
Middle East advisor
and his job was to bring
peace to the Middle East,
mainly between Israel
and the Arab countries.
To that extent, Kushner did a great job
because MBS helped him.
His major achievement is something
called the Abraham Accords.
The Abraham Accords is just to establish
peace between the Arab and the Muslim world.
So MBS was looking very good.
But then in 2018,
he did something
that scared the world.
MBS was a visionary.
He had a plan for where
to take Saudi Arabia.
He wanted to modernize Saudi Arabia.
But he was also young.
He was a tyrant.
He did not like people who
criticized him.
So there's a journalist
named Jamal Khashoggi
who worked for the Washington Post and
who was a permanent resident
of the United States.
He was a Saudi national.
And MBS had him killed.
And this caused an international uproar.
The CIA, the US government,
conducted an investigation and
they determined that MBS was the
one who ordered the assassination.
Trump protected MBS.
And then the most important thing that
Trump did was in January 2020,
Trump ordered the assassination of
a man named Qasem Soleimani,
who is considered a terrorist.
He was considered to be the second most
powerful man in Iran after the Ayatollah,
the supreme religious
leader of the country.
It is Qasem Soleimani who
was responsible for Iran's policies
in the Iraq war, the Syria
war, and in the Yemen war.
So from the perspective of Saudi Arabia,
Qasem Soleimani is
public enemy number one.
He is the greatest threat.
He is the greatest threat to Saudi Arabia.
Now, before,
America had many opportunities
to assassinate Qasem Soleimani.
George W. Bush had the opportunity.
Barack Obama had the opportunity.
And both believed that
doing so would cause
basically World War III.
Because if you kill the
number two leader of Iran,
Iran would have no choice
but to go to war with you.
And that's why they both refrained
from killing Qasem Soleimani.
In fact, when
Trump made the decision
to assassinate Soleimani,
the entire military was stunned.
They couldn't believe this was happening.
So how does this happen?
So for some time, there was
some conflict between U.S.
soldiers and Shia militiamen in Iraq.
And the Pentagon thought it had to act.
So in these situations, they
had to go to the president
and present options to the
president of how best to respond.
And usually, the Pentagon
will design the choices
so that the president does what
the Pentagon thinks is best.
So an example is that
if I'm in the military, and
I go to Trump, I give you three choices.
The first choice is A,
one, let's do nothing.
Two is what you should do.
And three is let's blow up the world.
So when I present these
three options to you,
you as a president, being wise and
strategic, will obviously
always pick option two,
right? What you should do, what the
military suggests you should do, okay?
Unfortunately, in this instance,
Trump chose option three.
Let's blow up the world, guys. And so
they assassinated Qasem Soleimani, okay?
So in other words,
it is very likely that
if Trump stayed a second term,
the United States would
have gone to war with Iran,
given how things were progressing,
okay?
MBS was so happy about all this
that he once bragged privately to a friend
that, oh, Jared Kushner,
Trump's son -in -law,
the man responsible for
all Middle East policies?
Well, he's in the middle of a war. He's
in my pocket, meaning I own him, okay?
And the evidence that
suggests this is that
after Trump left office,
after Jared Kushner left office,
Jared Kushner set up
a private equity fund.
And MBS and
the Saudi government invested
$2 billion into the fund,
okay?
Does that make sense? So
we don't know how,
we don't know this for sure, but
it seems like Trump
is doing exactly what the Saudis want,
which is to inflame tensions with Iran,
okay?
And this suggests that
if in November Trump wins a second term,
then he's going to be
in a very bad position.
And so, in that case,
it's very possible that
Trump will declare war on Iran.
Or at the very least,
continue to escalate tensions with Iran,
okay? Which
will very likely lead to World War III.
So in that respect, the
election in November.
Whether or not Trump
comes back into office
is one of the most
consequential elections.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
Okay, any questions? Anything you want
me to clarify before we end class?
Okay. So
what we will do next class
is figure out if Trump
will win in November.
And I will make the argument to you that
it is almost very certain,
very likely that he will win in November.
Okay? So we will examine why next class.