Okay, well this is it.
The end of the journey, the final class.
So we've done a lot this year, right?
Last semester we did the
great books, the Iliad,
the Odyssey, the Bible,
Republic, Divine Comedy.
This semester we did how
screwed up the world is, right?
The world is hopeless.
We're all going to die.
And in this final class,
I want this class to be about hope.
And I want to show you the future.
And the argument I want to leave you with,
the thing that I want
you to remember is that,
remember Dante in Divine Comedy said that
the future, the future is the future.
And the future is the future. And the
future is the future. And the future is the future. And the future is the future. And the future is the future. And the future is not what happens to you.
It's not something that you wait for.
The future is what you imagine
and fight for.
The future is what you make happen.
There is a God, but
God gave us the ability to imagine
and the capacity to love.
And it's these two
things that will guide us
and enable us to build a better world.
Okay? So that's the message
I want to give to you today.
The future is what we imagine.
Not what we have to put up with.
So if we don't like the future, if we
don't like the way we live our lives,
then we can change that
with our imagination.
And today I want to show you how.
So just to summarize what
we did this semester.
Together we analyzed the world.
But what are some of the other two
things you can learn about the future.
But what are some of the other two things
you can learn about the future. But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future.
But what are some of the other two
things you can learn about the future.
But what are some of the other two things
you can learn about the future. But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future.
But what are some of the other two
things you can learn about the future.
millions and billions of people.
And because of climate change,
our world will eventually
collapse at some point, okay?
So this is an extremely hopeless,
extremely bleak and dark
picture of the world.
But remember, where there is
darkness, there can also be light.
So in this final class, I want to show you
some hope and some light, okay?
So this is what we call psychohistory.
And psychohistory is the idea
that the future can be predicted.
And if it can be predicted,
then it can be controlled
and harnessed for the
betterment of humanity, okay?
So where does this idea
come from, psychohistory?
In the 1950s,
there was an American science
fiction writer named Isaac Asimov.
And he's probably
the most famous science
fiction writer, okay?
If you happen to read science
fiction, he's really famous.
And he wrote a series called Foundation.
And I think there's a TV series
now based on Foundation books.
It's terrible, but you
can have a look at it.
And in the Foundation books, he
introduces the idea of psychohistory.
And so this book is set in the future,
like a million years from now,
where there is a galactic empire.
So humanity has colonized
the entire Milky Way.
There are billions of planets.
And there's an empire that
brings peace to this Milky Way.
But with all empires, it has to collapse.
And this will lead to 30,000 years of war,
violence, barbarity. But
the foundation proposes a new
science called psychohistory.
Which is to mathematically map out
human behavior over the
course of a million years.
But if you do that, what you discover is
that there are certain
patterns to human society.
But the way you discover is that there are
certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain Okay?
And if that's the case, then
you can predict the future.
If you can do that, then
you can manipulate the course of
events to make a better future.
Okay? So this is what
he called psychohistory.
And it's a science fiction concept.
And a lot of people have been
trying to make it into reality.
Okay? So there's this
very prominent historian.
His name is Peter Turkin.
And he's one of the founders of
something called Clio Dynamics.
Okay? And
Clio is the goddess of history.
Dynamics just means movement.
Okay? So
basically Clio Dynamics
is trying to figure
out the mathematical movement
of the mathematical history.
He's trying to create history
as a mathematical model.
And when he did that, there's
certain interesting trends
and patterns that he discovered.
Okay? And one idea that
he discovered is something called the
overproduction of
the elites.
Okay? Overproduction of the elite.
And this concept explains why.
So this concept explains why societies
collapse. Now, traditionally,
we've understood the collapse
of societies as having to
do with maybe like too much debt or too much
inequality or maybe climate change or war.
Right? What Peter Turkin points out, and
it's a really interesting idea,
is the reason why
societies collapse in the
end is you have too many elites.
All right? So let me explain the concept.
Okay. So.
So.! Society has many elites.
Right? You have people like Jack Ma.
Right? You have people
like Zhou Xun, Zhao Wei.
Right? Movie stars. You have
famous military generals.
Okay? So
over time, elites become
more and more numerous.
Right? The number of wealthy people go up.
The number of famous people go up.
The number of uneducated people go up.
The number of entrepreneurs go up. Okay?
The problem, though,
is they all want power.
Right? Now, wealth and
fame are all infinite resources.
Right? But
power will always be a finite resource.
In fact, it's what we
call a zero -sum game.
So, for example, in this classroom,
there can only be one teacher.
Right? If we're all teachers,
there's no teacher.
So in society, there can only
be a few powerful people.
If everyone has the power,
no one has any power.
Okay? So what happens over time is that
all these people who
believe they should have
power struggle for power.
And because there are too many of them,
this internal struggle of the elites
ultimately leads to social collapse.
Okay? So the most famous
example is in China,
in imperial China, where
you have the Keju system.
Right? People taking the imperial
examinations to become an official.
Problem is, you have too many candidates,
not enough positions.
Right? And guess who ultimately
gets upset with society
and leads revolutions?
It's the Keju candidates.
Who do not become officials.
And so they become angry.
And they lead revolutions
to overthrow society.
Right? So
the most classic example of the
failed Keju candidate is Hong Xiuquan.
Do you guys know who he is?
The leader of the Taiping rebellion.
Right? Why did he become a Christian?
Why did he lead the rebellion?
Because he failed the Keju.
Okay? So that's the idea of the
overproduction of the elite.
And he discovered this principle using
mathematically modeling of history.
He just compared different societies and
tried to figure out why they collapsed.
Okay? And what he discovered
is, well, it's because
of the internal struggle among
the different elite groups.
Okay? And that's why the Roman
Empire collapsed as well.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay.
What I'm proposing to you is that
we can actually go a step further
than what Peter Turchin is doing.
Because we have something
called now called AI.
Okay? Artificial intelligence. And
we can harness the power of AI
to create real psychohistory,
which is the ability to
not just analyze the past,
but to predict the future.
Okay? All right.
So let's first figure out what AI is.
Okay? So first I want us to understand
what artificial intelligence is.
Because most of you think you
know, but you don't actually know.
Okay? So what is AI?
All right. The AI, the technical term,
is supervised
machine learning.
Okay? That's the technical term.
AI is the popular term, but
supervised machine
learning is the technical
and correct term.
Have you guys heard of this term?
Supervised machine learning.
Yes or no? Have any of you
taken computer science?
Yes. Okay.
This is called supervised
machine learning.
Okay. So what is this?
Okay. So in computer programming,
you're taught to write
the algorithm, right?
And then the input. You put in
information, it gives you the output.
Okay? And this is traditionally
how computers work.
You write the algorithm,
the computer program,
you put in information, and
then there's an output, right?
For example, the algorithm could
be like, you know, A plus B.
Okay? So you put in two numbers.
Two, two, you get a four.
Okay? That's how computers work.
Right? Now, supervised machine learning is
that I will turn the
output into the input.
Okay? And the reason why I want to do that
is that as a human being,
I myself may not be able to
write the best algorithm.
Okay? So
I want the computer to
refine the algorithm for me,
to optimize it using the output.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So let's talk about a
very specific example.
All right? So
let's look at facial
recognition technology.
All right? You go to the
airport, and you scan,
and they know who you are.
Right? You go to a supermarket,
you scan your face, and you pay.
Right? And you're like,
wait, how does that work?
Okay. So
how this works is that there's a database,
okay, about 1 billion people,
like everyone in China.
And now what I need to do is figure out
how to differentiate the faces of
everyone in China in this database.
Okay? Does that make
sense? So what I do is,
for the face, I want to figure out how to
differentiate the faces of everyone in China.
So I go to the database, I create a
mathematical model based on topology.
Okay? Does that make sense? Topology.
So I turn everyone's face
into a mathematical model.
Okay? Which looks like
something like this.
Okay? And you're like, I
don't know what this is.
Okay. You don't need to know what this is.
This is like super complicated. Okay?
But all you need to know
is that within this model,
there are different equations.
Okay? So for example,
this model is trying to analyze
the distance between your eyes.
Okay? And how big your nose is.
All right? Does that
make sense? All right?
And so once I create
this mathematical model,
I am now able to differentiate everyone in
China. Does that make sense? Okay?
In fact, this mathematical is so
precise that I can only look at your eyes.
And I know who you are. Okay? Because
what I'm trying to do is match what your
model with the model in the database.
All right? But
what's important to remember is
that if you're not in this database,
you can't be recognized.
Okay? Do you understand? All right.
Now, what I will show you is
how this model is created.
So what happens is this. All right?
What I do is I teach the computer
how to create this database.
So I have input. I have output. And then
what I do is I create a
working thesis or a working theory of
what this model should look like. Okay?
Does that make sense? All right?
So it could be like this. All right?
And then what I do is I create a working
thesis. So what I do is I put faces.
Okay? And the output should
match what's in the database.
And if the model returns something that's
different, I tell them this is wrong.
And what the computer then does is
refine this model until it becomes this.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So what all AI is is infinite iteration.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
All right. So
the problem with AI is I need
to be able to solve three things.
And if I can solve three things,
then I can create an AI.
Okay? The first thing is that
I need
clear metrics.
Okay? Or clear outputs.
Okay? Does that make
sense? I need outputs that
I can define as a mathematical model.
Okay? So, for example,
if I'm an airline,
I'm going to use AI to maximize the
amount of money I make on a flight.
Right? Okay? That's my output.
How much money can I make out of a flight?
I want to have the
maximum amount of profit.
Okay? That's the first
thing I need to solve.
Second thing I need to solve then is to
make sure that I have the right metrics.
But the way I figured this out is, let's
try and figure out what are the standards.
But let's try and figure
out what are the standards.
But let's try and figure out what are the
standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards.
standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards.
But let's try and figure
out what are the standards.
data sets of different animals.
Okay, does that make sense?
I need to label my data.
But I can't tell,
I can't make an AI that's like, this
is the best ice cream in the world.
And the reason why is, I can't find data
on the best ice cream, you understand?
Because ice cream, the best
ice cream is subjective.
So I cannot turn that into a data set.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay,
the third thing I need to
do is create a
working algorithm structure.
You understand, okay?
Computers can only refine and optimize
the algorithm structure. It
cannot create it by itself.
Okay? So if I'm able
to do all three things,
then I'm able to do all three things.
I can use AI to optimize
what I wanted to optimize.
Okay? All right, any questions so far?
Before I move on? Okay?
So what this means is that
there are certain problems
that I can solve using AI, and
there are certain problems I
cannot solve using AI, okay?
So what are easy problems?
What are some of the problems that AI can
solve, right? Well, for example, facial recognition technology,
okay? Also, translation software, right?
I can create an optimal
translation software.
Also, recommendation engines, right?
So if you watch a movie on Netflix,
it recommends another movie, right?
Okay? Now let me ask you this question.
Can I ever solve,
self -driving cars? Can I
ever solve self -driving cars?
Self -driving cars. Can
cars drive by themselves?
Yes or no? Yes.
Why yes, Sally?
Because they're on.
I mean, they're driving.
Okay, the answer is no.
Why is the answer no?
Okay, the answer no is,
whatever I do, okay, I cannot solve
something called the edge case.
The edge case is, if
the car is on the road,
what could happen that would
screw up my AI system?
You guys know? Why can't
self -driving cars be solved?
Why can't we have self
-driving cars on the road?
What's an edge case?
Or this thing that I can never solve?
What is it? Excuse me?
Yeah, and what is not planned?
Hm? They can plan for traffic.
What can they not plan for?
And this is why we'll never
have someone driving cars.
They can plan for accidents.
What can they not plan for?
Yeah? Easily plan for traffic rules.
What can they not plan for? Okay, guys.
The edge case with self
-driving cars is if I,
as a human being, intentionally
want to crash into that car.
Do you understand? Does
that make sense to you guys?
Every other situation I can plan for.
But in a situation where
I'm the human being,
and I don't like self -driving
cars because I'm a taxi driver,
and it's stealing my job, right?
It's stealing my livelihood, and
I want to crash into that car.
There's no way for that
AI to avoid the accident.
Does that make sense? Okay?
Listen. Listen.
AI is a scam, okay?
It does not exist. What exists?
What exists is supervised
machine learning, okay?
What is supervised machine learning?
What I just told you, okay?
That's it. That's the
extent of our technology.
It does not have self -awareness.
It can only do what the
algorithm tells it to do.
And there's no way you can
design an algorithm that
plans for and prevents a human being
who intentionally wants to crash into you.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
Okay? So AI, in other words,
is actually a limited tool, okay?
So you think about actual
applications of AI, it's very limited.
You also look at self -driving cars.
Now, there are cars that
have self -driving features,
but they are not 100% self -driving.
Okay? Does that make sense?
In fact, they tell you,
don't rely on the autopilot, okay?
It's there to help you,
but don't sleep in the car.
Okay? Right? Because
they don't have an AI system
in place to prevent people
from crashing into them.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So now that we know what AI is,
let's talk about how we can use AI
to predict the future.
Okay? Okay?
All right. All right.
So basically, what you
need to do is three things,
right? You need to be
clear about the output,
you need to have clean data,
and you need to have a working algorithm.
Okay? Does that make sense?
And so that's what I've
been doing this semester.
Okay? So for example,
remember my predictions.
Okay? Okay?
Okay? if you go to a
legal lobby, Saudi Arabia
and the American Empire,
basically the need to
protect the petrodollar,
will force America to go to war with Iran.
Okay? These are the push factors.
The problem is that
there are no force to
counteract this, okay?
So for example, the military.
The military will be for this because
they have shock and awe, and they are
very confident they can win this war.
Okay? Iran itself wants this war
because it wants revenge
against America. Okay?
And then the President of the United
States, will be Donald Trump,
he wants this war in order
to cement his position
as President. Okay? And so,
because of this, we can predict that
there'll be a war in Iran.
Does that make sense? Okay.
Now, given this prediction,
what we can then do is
use mathematical modeling
and statistics to turn
this into an AI model.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay? Now we have the AI model.
Now that we have the AI model,
what we need to do now is to refine it.
And the way we refined it
is by going back in history
and looking at every
single war that started.
Does that make sense? And so,
you take this model and you
look at the different wars.
Okay? So for example, the 415 BCE war.
The invasion of Sicily by Athens.
You look at 1941,
Operation Barbarossa. Okay?
You have basically hundreds
of wars that you can look at.
And then you take this
model and then you test it
using each of these wars.
And what will happen is that
the model will begin to refine itself.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So it becomes more and more refined.
Okay? But then
that's one model for what causes war.
I've also said that
Trump will become president.
Right? Well
then, that's another
model that you can use.
And once you start putting
all these models together,
what eventually happens is,
what happens over time is
you develop cycle history.
Okay? Does this make sense, guys?
All right? So now the question then is,
okay, how would this AI model work?
Or what are the ideas behind this model?
Okay? So
we talk about game theory analysis a lot.
All right? And the idea
of game theory analysis is
that, okay, guys, there's
really no good and evil.
Okay? There are different
players in a game.
And they're all self -interested.
They all want to win this game.
So they're going to
develop strategies that
optimize their ability to win this game.
Okay? So you can use game theory analysis.
But then you can also use, you know,
you can also develop new ideas
that
would help you better
understand how the world works.
So let's talk about some ideas
that have come up in this course.
All right? So
one thing I want to talk about is
this week's European elections.
Have you guys seen the news?
The elections to the European Parliament.
Right? And
the results are pretty shocking.
Because it signals a
clear shift to the right.
So, for example,
Marylepain's party in France
picked up a lot of votes.
The AFD, the Alternative for Germany,
the Alternative for Germany, which
is considered a right -wing organization,
almost neo -Nazi, has picked
up a lot of votes as well.
The results were so dramatic
that Emmanuel Macron,
the president of France,
has called for an early election.
And it's possible in three months' time,
Marylepain's party will
run and govern France.
Okay? So
how do we explain this shift to the right?
And I want to explain three reasons.
Okay? The first reason
is anti -immigration.
Okay? So for the past 10,
20 years, there have been a lot of
immigrants to Europe from Libya,
from Syria, from Iraq,
Afghanistan, Sudan, Somalia.
Okay? These are mainly non -immigrants.
They are Muslim people who
threaten the Christian
social fabric of Europe.
And now Europeans are rebelling
or revolting against that.
Second thing that they
don't like about Europe
so far is the idea of federalism.
Okay? Or they can say bureaucratism.
But this idea that a foreign power,
Brussels, mandates rules
that they must follow.
So they think it's very anti -democratic.
Okay? And the third thing
that
they're rebelling against is
the idea of pan -Europeanism.
What the people of Europe are saying is,
there's no European identity, guys.
There's a German identity, there's
a French identity, Italian,
Spanish, Portuguese, but
there's no European identity.
They're rebelling against
the entire project of the EU.
In fact, I would bet that
in about five years' time, the entire EU
would be dead. Okay?
Okay? Why are they opposed to
pan -Europeanism?
Because, ultimately, they believe
that it's about destroying local identity.
It's about destroying local community.
It's about destroying my
relationship with my neighbors
and my friends and my relatives.
Okay? And my family. Does that make sense?
Okay? It's imposing a
foreign identity on me. And
proponents of
the European Union would argue
that, no, this is just a secular,
liberal idea.
Okay? The entire idea of the EU is
that for hundreds of
years, thousands of years,
Europe has been at war.
Why has Europe been at war?
Tribalism, right? Religion.
So the entire project of
the EU is to get rid of
this the factors that lead to war.
Local identity, nationalism,
religion. Right?
And what the European voters
are saying to the EU is,
um, sorry,
we don't want secular liberalism because
we want to be human. Okay?
What we strive for is not a abstract,
liberal idea.
We strive for structure,
meaning, and purpose in our lives.
Okay? What we really strive
for is the capacity to love,
create, and learn.
Okay? And grow.
Does that make sense? That's what we
are fundamentally as human beings.
And when you ask me
to obey an abstract foreign entity
that is very far from me,
then you are limiting or
destroying the structure,
meaning, and purpose in my life.
Okay? And so, that's what's going on,
not just in Europe, but
throughout the world.
You think about Brexit, right?
You think about the election
of Donald Trump, right?
All these things have to
do with this fundamental
human urge to have structure, meaning,
and purpose in our lives.
Okay? To have agency. Okay?
Does that make sense, guys? All right.
Any questions so far? Yeah?
Eric? Okay.
So, Eric asked, okay,
what is the source of all this?
And what Dante and Homer
would say is
the human heart, okay? The human heart.
This is just who we are.
And if we cannot fulfill our human heart,
we will rebel.
We will destroy.
We will want to kill.
Okay? And so, in other words,
one idea in this AI model is
that there is a fundamental
underlying structure to human society.
Okay? If society conforms
to the structure of the human heart,
this society will prosper.
For example, Athens,
right? The ancient Greeks.
That society prospered.
The word we used was eudaimonia, right?
Okay? But if society
represses the human heart, then
ultimately the society will
have to collapse at some point.
Okay? So,
that's another principle that we can
use when developing this AI model.
The last idea that
we can use in developing this AI
model is the idea of synchronicity.
Okay? Synchronicity. And
the idea of synchronicity
is, as a society,
how willing are people
how, how willing are people
in following the rules?
It doesn't make sense. So, when you use the
subway, do people actually follow traffic rules?
When you use the subway, do people actually
give up their seats for the elderly,
for children, for pregnant women?
Okay? When you go to the park, do
people actually pick up garbage
and throw it in the garbage bin?
Okay? Synchronicity tells us that there's
cohesion and trust in society,
that society is resilient,
okay? And that
society is resilient because society can
grow, okay, or learn from its mistakes.
Okay? So, societies that are, that
have high synchronicity will do better in the
long term than societies with low synchronicity.
And so, societies with high
synchronicity would include Japan
and Germany, right?
And societies with low
synchronicity would include
India and Brazil and China,
okay? Does that make sense?
All right? So, when
you go to the park, and
you're totally
totally totally totally totally
totally totally totally
totally If you insert a human
body into a human body,
then why would it be a human body?
Excuse me? Why would it be a human body?
Okay, that's a great question. So
one thing that
was not supposed to happen
is the idea of mass society.
Mass society. You can say that
mass society is a complete
deviation from
human history. We're not
supposed to have mass society.
And mass society is completely an
accident, a historical accident.
But when you have mass
society, what happens is
that you need an elite.
Okay? You need an elite.
But guess what, guys? The elite,
the people in charge, they're not better
than you and me. Okay? You understand?
We in this classroom could swap
for the leadership of the world, right?
And guys, nothing would change.
You understand? Right?
So you have mass society, and therefore you
have to have an artifact of mass society.
And you have to have an elite. You have to
have an elite. You have to have an elite. Because you need people in control.
And because they're in control,
they need to now maintain
the illusion of their power.
Okay? They need to create fictions.
For example, maybe, well,
I went to Yale or Harvard, and
therefore I should be at the top.
Or maybe I have a higher IQ than you do.
Or maybe, you know, my dad or my great
-great -great -great -grandfather was king.
Okay? They had to create these fictions.
Now, what happens over time is that
these fictions fall apart because
they're not that competent.
Okay? And the most recent example is you
look at the global management of the economy,
and you look at the global
management of, like, COVID.
Okay? You look at the
global management of war.
Okay? They're pretty incompetent.
And so people sort of wake
up and like, wait a minute.
These guys don't really
know what they're doing.
Okay? And now, so
now the elite is now
forced to suppress us.
Okay? That's a lie. They have to
use force to make us obedient.
Okay? And that's what's happening today.
And so this repression
can go on for a long time,
but to control us, they must
repress the human heart.
Okay? Because
it's in the human heart
to want to question,
to be curious,
to grow.
Okay? And if you think, like,
the people in charge don't
know what they're doing, then
you're sort of compelled
to challenge them.
And so what they have to do
is suppress the human heart.
And they do that by trying to get
you to focus on buying new things.
But then you try and learn new things.
But then you try and learn new things. But
then you try and learn new things. But then you try and learn new things.
But then you try and learn new things.
But then you try and learn new things. But
then you try and learn new things. But then
you try and learn new things.
But then you try and learn new things.
But then you try and
learn new things.
model okay you understand it
has the human heart has to
become like a model like facial
recognition model okay does that make sense
okay so Sally's question is isn't it true
that we're all individual and unique
and isn't it true that
over time we change okay and
that's that's great point but what Homer
and Dante would say that
no no no no at the
fundamental level okay we all
have the same desires we're motivated
by the same needs okay
there's no one in this world
that does not want structure meaning and
purpose now the way you want to
achieve this may be different okay
but that's your underlying motivation and
there's no person in this world that
does not seek to have to achieve
these three things like love create
and grow as people okay that's
when you achieve full happiness
as a person when you feel
that you're married to someone
you love you have children
when you're doing a job
that is creative and
when you're constantly
learning every day and
growing every day okay
when you achieve that
these three things what
do we call this when
you've achieved all
three things what do we
call this eudaimonia
right this is eudaimonia
this is what the Greeks meant by a happy
and self -fulfilled life
it doesn't make sense okay
so there may be
differences in needs
and motivation but
the fundamental at the fundamental
level we're all human beings
and we're all driven by the same
fundamental needs okay does
that make sense okay okay
so Sally
asked the question like
how do you construct this
AI okay and so you're totally totally
totally totally totally totally totally
So for this AI to be valid,
let me explain how we
would actually implement.
So first of all,
you need at least 50 to 100
years to actually create this AI.
And the reason why is that
for this AI to be valid, you
constantly need to be testing it.
So what I've been doing in this
class is basically doing a self -AI,
where I have an analytical
model and I have a prediction.
But guess what guys,
we won't know if my predictions
are fully correct until 50 years from now.
Is that correct? Therefore,
I can't validate my analysis
until 50 years from now.
Does that make sense? And you
need to be constantly doing this
where you have to be constantly
making these predictions
and seeing if they're correct or not.
If they're not correct, what
you have to do is go and
change these predictions
and analysis.
Does that make sense? Then
what you have to do is
you basically have to,
and this is actually what's the most time
consuming, you have to rewrite history.
Do you understand? Because
most of the history is
actually not correct.
So what you have to do is you
have to take this AI model and
look back at history and say,
according to this AI model, what actually
happened in the Peloponnesian War?
What actually happened in World War I? What
actually happened during the Tang Dynasty? So
you basically have to challenge
the entire discipline of history
and reconstruct a new history that
you think is more factually
correct based on this AI.
So you have to be doing
these two things at once.
Making these predictions and
seeing if you're correct, but
also going back throughout history
and seeing how history
can be revamped or changed
so that it's more accurate.
Does that make sense? That's a project,
but then there's the technology.
Because you actually need mathematicians
and computer programmers and historians
to collaborate together to build this AI.
So I can tell you how I
would analyze the issue,
but then a mathematician has to turn this
into a mathematical equation or a model.
Because computers only
recognize data and numbers.
They don't recognize ideas.
I can't talk to a computer.
I have to give a computer a number
or an equation or a model
for it to calculate on.
Does that make sense?
So it's not an easy project.
But the argument is that
if this project actually works,
it would change the fate
of humanity forever.
Because if there's one thing
that you notice in this class,
it's that we tend to
repeat the same mistakes.
The question is, why do we do that?
It's because, the history that
we have is complete bullshit.
It just is. It's not true.
It can't be true. Okay?
There's things that we believe, which
if you just think about it, can't be true.
Okay? And we did that like last semester
when we talked about the rise of Christianity, right? You're telling me that
this illiterate guy named Jesus was able
to spread Christianity all by himself,
after he died? I don't believe that.
Okay? I think a much
easier explanation is that
it became co -opted by the Roman
Empire in order to control the Empire.
Right? But if you would
talk to a historian,
they would say, you're just wrong.
Okay? So, not only are you
trying to predict the future,
but you're trying to also correct the past,
which is, I think, an even more difficult job.
Right? Any more questions?
Yeah, Eric?.
Excuse me? Oh, so, Eric
asked a great question.
Will this cycle history
model encounter edge cases?
And the answer is, that's
the best question, okay?
That's a great question.
And the answer is,
yes. What are edge cases?
Do you guys know? What are
edge cases in this model?
. Who,
what would be edge cases here in history?
Okay, it's called great man theory, okay?
Great man theory. And this is a problem.
Meaning, like, okay, we believe,
we argue that
these underlying historical
forces control humanity,
right? But now and then, you have
this great man coming out of nowhere,
and he changes the course of
human history forever, okay?
The example is, before we had Homer,
right? Then we had Dante.
Then we had Plato,
Jesus, Julius Caesar,
Octavius, Poutin today, okay?
We can't account for these
people, because by definition,
they're beyond, you know, beyond history.
They can step outside of
history and control history.
That's what great men are. So how
does your model account for that?
Okay? And the answer is, you cannot.
So, in foundation,
okay, the solution, okay, but
there is a solution to this.
The solution is to create
another organization.
Okay, remember that, technical
history is an AI model.
It's basically a computer. But
as Eric points out, you
will always have edge cases.
You'll always have someone
appear out of nowhere.
And for whatever reason,
he's able to manipulate events to control
and direct history in his favor, okay?
So what you do to solve this problem
is you create another organization,
okay? And in, I think, Asimov's foundation,
it's called the Second Foundation.
Okay? And the idea of
the Second Foundation is
that there is a computer,
there is the AI, okay?
But behind the AI are
a team of specialists
who observe the AI, who observe history,
and who correct the AI
for edge cases, okay?
Does that make sense? So if
Putin appears and is like,
okay, well, clearly, I'm not
accounting for Putin, well,
then I change the equations in
the AI to account for Putin, okay?
So this team of experts,
the Second Foundation,
will correct the AI, right?
Now, what's interesting about
the Second Foundation is
that these people are telepaths.
Okay? Telepaths.
Meaning that they can read your mind.
Not only can they read your mind,
but they can troll your mind, okay?
So... And
that's another reason why I think we're really
interested in something about psychohistory.
Like, okay, there's a promise that
we can predict the future,
but there's also a promise
that within our minds,
there are some special abilities that
we might have the potential for, but
we never ever fully attempted to achieve.
Okay? Does that make sense?
And is it possible in the future
that telepaths will arrive I think yes.
And the answer is that you
can make the argument that
these edge cases that Eric refers
to, these great men of history,
they're actually telepaths.
Okay? Does that make sense?
They're actually telepaths.
So someone like Putin, why is
Putin able to do what he does?
And you can make the argument, like,
he has almost some telepathic abilities,
okay? He can read other people's minds.
He can troll other people's minds.
How else can you explain that someone
who does not come
from a special background, right?
He's not of the Russian elite.
But he's able to amass so much power
all by himself in only a few decades
so that today, he's basically
the emperor of Russia.
And all of Russia heeds his command.
Russia just moves the way
that he wants it to move.
Okay? So you can make the argument that
Putin is almost a telepath.
And is it possible
that in the future we'll
have more telepaths?
And we can, over time,
harness the power of these telepaths
to create the second foundation
and to control psychohistory?
Possibly, right? Okay?
Because, like, how else would
we explain great men, okay?
You look at someone like
Homer and Dante, right?
The only explanation that you
can have for Homer and Dante is
they were... They had
God -given gifts, okay?
Or maybe God was speaking to them.
Or maybe they were just speaking for God.
Right? That's the only explanation
that you can have for Homer
and Dante because they so
clearly stepped out of
history and directed history.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay?
But thanks for the question, Eric.
Okay? So edge cases are great men
who appear now and then, and you
cannot ever predict these people.
Okay? Any more questions?
Okay. This...
Yeah? Yes? Yes, Celine?
..
Oh, that's a great question, okay?
Um, okay. How do you model
love, learn, and create, okay?
And the answer is that
there has to be a certain amount of
autonomy or agency
in the lives of people.
Does that make sense? What
we call freedom and liberty.
Because if you have freedom and liberty,
then you're able to do what you want.
And what you want to do is love,
um, create, and...
and grow, okay? Does that make sense?
So you need to model, um, agency
and freedom into the structure, okay?
The second thing is, um,
social interaction. Okay?
In other words, the more we're
able to interact with each other,
the more we're willing to love,
create, and grow.
Because these powers
come from others, right?
You can't love yourself. You
have to love someone else.
You can't create by yourself.
You have to create in a group, okay?
And you can't learn by yourself.
You have to learn from others. Okay?
So you also have to model in, um, as
much group interaction as possible.
Okay? And the last thing is
you also have to model in
the idea of compassion.
Okay? So the idea here is that, um,
if I all put you on an island together,
okay, and you must survive,
well, you will become
compassionate with each other,
because that's the only
way to survive, right?
But, if I put you guys into a bank,
and I say to you that
if you make a million dollars, and
I give you two million dollars,
whoever makes the most money, I will
give a Ferrari to, guess what, guys?
You will all hate each other.
You will all want to
kill each other, okay?
You understand? So
this model also has to
factor in compassion.
How compassionate is this society?
Okay? Because if you have compassion,
then people are willing to work together.
If people are willing to work together,
then people will have the greater capacity to love, create, and grow.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Actually, guys, we have
all these theories.
It's just like no one's turned
this into a mathematical model,
okay, for society. Any more questions?
Yeah? .
Yeah, so
Eric asked a question,
is it possible to
completely understand human
behavior and motivation?
And there are two different ways
of looking at the issue, okay?
The first way is to use a
social science approach,
okay? So you look at
economics, psychology,
anthropology, sociology, right?
What are they trying to do?
They're trying to figure
out mathematically
what drives us, okay?
You understand?
But there's another approach.
It's called the literature approach,
which is that we can't actually quantify
or explain human behavior, okay?
But there are truths that can
be expressed in literature.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So think about the very first
book we read, The Iliad.
Right? Where
Achilles has killed Hector
and Prime wants the body back.
So Prime sneaks into Achilles'
tent and kisses his hand,
right? That moment.
You can never mathematically express it.
You can only write about it.
But think about how much truth and power
is in that one scene.
Okay? Does that make sense, Eric?
Okay? So again, I think someone like Homer
and Dante,
their mission is to express to us,
in the most beautiful way,
the human truths, okay?
Like what drives us.
And Dante is very explicit.
He says that what drives us is love
and the willingness to imagine, okay?
That's who we are. If we
love, we'll be more human.
If we imagine, we'll be more human, okay?
And that's really the
argument I make as well.
All right? And that
has to be the underlying truth
of whatever AI model you create, okay?
All right? Any more questions? Yeah?
Okay. Okay.
So, Celine asked a great question.
Okay, well, if it says that
we want to love, create, and grow, then
why do we end up destroying ourselves?
And the answer is that love
and hate are one force.
You understand? If I can't love
you, I'm going to hate you.
You understand, okay? Guess what, guys?
Creation and destruction are two different
things. Destruction is one force as well.
If I can't create, then I want to destroy
because my need for creation
can't be satisfied.
Does that make sense? So, a society
that nurtures our willingness to love
and create and grow, like the Greeks,
will flourish, okay?
But eventually, you reach a point where
the elite have amassed power.
They've centralized and
consolidated power, and so
they want to turn everyone
else into basically a slave.
When you're a slave, you can't love.
You can't create. You can't learn.
You can't grow. Therefore, you
rebel, and you destroy the society.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
But, again, the fundamental human
need are these three things,
but within each of these
things is another force.
And if love can't express itself,
then hate will express itself.
Does that make sense? Okay?
All right. Any more questions?
Yeah?.
... .
. So, Sally asked a great
question, which is, like, who
would control this AI?
And how can we ensure that
this AI is not exploited by the
elite in order to justify their
corruption and cruelty, okay?
And the answer has to be
really the second foundation, okay?
Basically, a group of scholars,
academics, experts, who
dedicate themselves to this AI, okay?
And this AI, the other thing is that
it has to be open and transparent.
That's why it's so hard to build, right?
It has to be open and transparent.
Okay? If it's open and transparent, then
everyone has to agree that this AI
is going to be used for good, okay?
Meaning that what this AI does is
you can ask it different questions,
and it will give you different scenarios.
And we can all agree on
which scenario we want,
and therefore we can agree
on what action to take, okay?
So this AI has to be part
of a democratic system
where everyone is involved.
Otherwise, as Sally points out,
it can only be abused,
okay? It can only be
used to oppress others,
okay?
But the point of this AI is that
it gives us a platform
as humans to agree on certain actions
that we must stick together, okay?
Does that make sense? So for
example, we can all agree
that climate change is bad.
We can all agree that war is bad, right?
But this AI will actually give
us solutions to these problems
because this AI can map
out the future for us.
And AI will say, well, listen,
if the United States
intervenes in Ukraine,
then this will happen, right?
The United States attacks
Iran, then this will happen.
And that becomes a very
powerful argument for correct
and proper behavior, okay?
Does that make sense? All right.
But again, guys,
this is just conjecture, okay?
And I've already said this.
It's going to take at least 50
to 100 years to build this AI,
and you will be up against
tremendous opposition,
right? Historians aren't
going to like this.
The elite aren't going
to like this, right?
But at the same time, we have
to remember, like, guess what?
Homer, I'm pretty sure if Homer
were living in a centralized society,
the elite would be opposed to him, okay?
Because he was making fun
of very famous Greeks,
like Achilles and Menelaus
and Agamemnon, right?
He was making fun of these
guys. Well, guess what?
When Homer's writing,
society had collapsed, right?
When Dante was writing,
society had collapsed.
So if it is true, if my
predictions are correct
and society is approaching collapse,
then there should be a
lot of space and leeway
and flexibility to create this AI, okay?
Okay. Any more questions?
Yeah?.
That's a great question.
So won't different people, different
nations want different outcomes?
And the answer is yeah. Like,
if you are alive today,
if you're America, you want
America to be a hegemon.
If you're Putin, you want
Russia to be the hegemon.
If you're China, you want
China to be the hegemon, right?
You want different outcomes. So
my argument is that
the structure of society
today is not sustainable.
Everything's going to collapse. And
we are going to transition from a
population of about 8 billion people
to a population of 1 billion people.
And when you have 1 billion people and,
like, there's no place to grow crops,
and pollution is everywhere,
and war is everywhere, guess what happens?
Humans are united in their goals,
which is basically how do we
create a better civilization,
okay? Does that make sense?
When all of a sudden it's collapsed, everyone's
like, how do we recreate civilization?
That's the goal. But in a more
progressive, more democratic,
and more prosperous way.
Okay? That's what I'm betting on.
But I don't know, okay? And again,
if everyone's fighting over the AI,
this AI cannot be created, okay?
Because different people will want this
AI to be biased in a different way.
This AI can only work if
it steps outside of history
and steps outside of
human interests, okay?
If it's speaking for all of humanity rather
than one nation or one group of people.
Okay? Any more questions?
Is this clear to you guys?
Alright. So, um...
Alright. So, this is the very end,
and I'll spend, like, five
more minutes to talk about
this year, okay?
So, um...
This is the very first time
I've taught both courses, okay?
In the first semester,
we read the great books.
And... Um...
I was blown away
by how much you guys
enjoyed the great books. And
how much you benefit from
reading the great books,
okay? And quite honestly, I don't
think anyone has tried this before.
Um... I know there are great
books courses in university,
but not at the pace
that we had,
and certainly not at the level
of difficulty that we had, okay?
So you guys should be proud of yourself,
because the great books courses was very hard.
And, um... You enjoyed it.
Um... Even today, most of you
really like the Iliad, right?
You guys still remember the Iliad
and think very highly of it, okay?
Um... So, so...
So that's very impressive, so thank you.
This semester is also a new course, where
we looked at geopolitics.
And, um... I'm...
I'm also very impressed
by how much you've grown as well
in this course. Um...
The way you guys think,
it's much more logical.
Much more analytical.
You guys are asking great questions, okay?
So, um...
Thank you again, because...
You don't have to work hard in this
course, but you chose to work hard.
And this is gonna carry
you very far, um...
in life, okay?
So, um...
The course is...
Um... Has come to an end.
And I will share with you
um... Why I teach this course, okay?
Because... Some of you know,
I do have a very prestigious
education background,
as well as a career background,
okay? And...
I could have been,
what, a lawyer, I think?
A lawyer. A rich lawyer.
A professor, okay?
But instead, I'm teaching
high school in China.
Right? Why am I doing this?
It's because... Um...
I have three kids.
Okay? I have three young kids.
My eldest is six.
My youngest is only about eight months.
Okay? And as a father,
you have to believe in a better world.
But not only do you have to believe in
a better world, you have to imagine.
You have to fight for it.
Because... Um...
You have to leave behind a
legacy for your children.
Okay? So,
why I teach this course is to
bring you a message of hope.
Okay? Like, through your own imagination,
through your own hard work,
you can create a better world.
You don't have to sit back
and just let the world happen.
You don't have to wait for the future.
You can make it happen. And...
If you really...
work hard at it, you can make
the world a better place.
And I think, like, this year
has proven to me
that I can make the world a better place
if I work hard. Because I've
seen the growth in all of you.
Okay? So, I hope we can stay in touch.
I hope that...
Um... You will tell me
how you progress, because
I'm very confident that all of you
will do very well in university.
And in life. And maybe at some point,
we can share this dream of psychohistory.
You know? I know it
sounds very complicated.
It's very abstract. But
to make this work, you need a
lot of people working together.
Okay? And it's something that's
not going to happen tomorrow.
But it's something that we might
come back to later on in our lives.
Okay? So, that's it.
Thank you. And we'll stay in touch.
Okay? Subtitles by the Amara.org community