So
this week Vladimir Putin in
a speech said to his Russian people
that
all of Russia must now
prepare for total war.
Even if you are not fighting
on the front lines in Ukraine,
pretend you are.
And because of this speech,
there are many analysts
who believe that
Putin is preparing Russia for total war.
And total war means that
every aspect of your society is
geared towards winning a war.
And so we last had total
war in World War II, okay?
But not after that.
So why is Putin doing this?
Now, there are some
people who believe that
it's because Russia is not
doing so well in Ukraine.
They lack manpower and so
they need to mobilize their society
to fully win the war in Ukraine.
Okay? Another explanation is
that Putin knows
that
NATO is preparing to send
reinforcements to Ukraine.
Remember that because of
last summer's offensive,
Ukraine is desperately short of manpower.
Okay? The average age of their
soldiers right now is over 40.
They have men in their 60s who
are fighting in the front lines.
Emmanuel Macron of France
has publicly stated
that he is considering sending
French troops to Ukraine.
The British themselves are
thinking of conscription,
drafting all young men into the army.
The American politicians have said
that they're considering a new law that
would give citizenship to illegal
immigrants who join the army.
Okay? So it seems like NATO is only
going to escalate the war in Ukraine.
And so Russia is preparing for that.
One more explanation,
one more possibility is
that Putin wants to expand the war.
Okay? So he knows he's winning in Ukraine.
He's thinking about attacking Moldova
and possibly the Baltic states.
Okay? These are all possibilities. Today,
this morning, what I want to do
is argue another possibility,
which is that
Putin is mobilizing his society
because he sees war as a tool,
as a mechanism,
to radically reshape
the people in Russia.
Okay? So think of a metaphor.
Okay? You're fat and you're like, okay,
how do I get fit?
How do I get trim? Right? You
go to the gym and you work out.
And for Putin, that's what war is.
War is a workout for society.
When you enter war, you become a
much more disciplined, unified,
and prosperous society.
Okay? So that's what
I want to argue today.
Okay. So why does Putin think like this?
Well, let's look at the
current state of Russia.
Okay? Russia, in many aspects,
is a broken society. Corruption.
Russia is the most corrupt
society in all of Europe.
The rich people, steal,
and then they run off to Europe
or the United States or Dubai.
Okay? So corruption is a
huge problem in Russia.
And because of corruption,
the GDP of Russia is very low.
So South Korea, which has about a
third of the population of Russia,
has a higher GDP. Okay?
The state of Texas, this one state in the
United States, has a higher GDP than Russia.
So Russia, in many ways, in many
respects, is a very poor country.
Okay? Second problem is alcoholism.
One out of every six Russian males,
about 16, 17% of the population,
they're alcoholics.
Okay? It's a disease.
They have the disease of alcoholism.
One out of every three deaths in Russia is
because of drinking too much.
And because of alcoholism,
the rate of young men
dying is just increasing and increasing.
Okay? The third problem is fertility.
So right now, the fertility
rate in Russia is 1.5.
That is below the replacement level.
Right? Remember that the replacement
level for society is 2.1.
Russia is 1.5.
But probably you have a lot of
men dying because of alcoholism.
Okay? So since the year 2000,
the population in Russia
has been declining steadily.
And all this means is that
if current trends continue,
then Russia will cease
to exist as a society.
Okay? The nation will die.
So why is this happening?
Well, okay. The Western explanation is,
is that this is happening because
Russia is not democratic.
Right? If you have full democracy and
you unleash the human potential
of your people, then
Russia will prosper.
But Putin, Vladimir Putin,
has a different explanation.
Okay? His explanation is that
this is happening to Russia.
Okay? Corruption,
alcoholism, and low fertility
because Russians have been lied to,
deceived,
and manipulated by Western civilization.
Western civilization preaches
the gospel of liberal democracy,
of freedom, of human
rights, of consumerism.
And these are all lies.
They're hypocrisies that have
fooled the Russian people
and have corrupted the Russian soul
and destroyed Russian civilization.
And because Russians are
abandoning their soul,
their civilization, their nation,
this is why this is happening.
Okay? Does that make sense?
That is Putin's argument.
So why does Putin believe this?
Well, in the late 80s,
the Soviet Union had
basically lost the Cold War.
And they lost the Cold War because
their elite basically gave up.
They no longer believed in communism.
They didn't believe in self
-sacrifice for the nation.
They thought that Western values,
the Western lifestyle was much better.
Okay? So they gave up. In the late 80s,
there was an American historian.
He actually works for the
American State Department.
And his name is Francis Fukuyama.
And he wrote an extremely
influential essay called
The End of History.
End of History.
Okay? With a quotation mark.
And he argued that
the Soviet Union fell
and America became triumphant
because liberal democracy
is the best idea
to have ever been invented.
And to make his argument,
he uses the philosopher Frederick Hegel.
Okay? Now, Frederick Hegel had something
called the theory of the dialectic.
Dialectic. And
what Hegel argued is that history
is determined by a war of ideas.
The progress of history is
determined by the movement of ideas.
And how ideas work is
that they have a pattern
called the dialectic.
Okay? So there's a thesis.
A new idea comes into being.
But then we recognize that
this idea has problems.
It's too extreme. It's too problematic.
So we create an antithesis.
Okay? But
this antithesis itself
is also too extreme.
And this creates also problems. So then
what happens is the thesis
and antithesis come together
and create a more moderate,
more efficient idea.
Okay? Called the synthesis.
And this is how
history moves or progresses.
And so Fukuyama takes
this idea and says, okay,
well this explains what's happening today.
Where at first you have a
thesis called capitalism.
Okay? Capitalism.
And this creates the
industrial revolution.
Right? And because
capitalism was too extreme,
we move towards communism.
Okay? Communism was created
to counteract the extremes of capitalism.
But communism itself is too extreme.
So then we move towards the middle.
Which is the right idea.
Which is called liberal democracy.
Okay? So what is liberal democracy? Well,
at the core of liberal democracy
is the idea of consumerism.
And the idea of consumerism
is that we exist
to buy things.
And as long as we buy things,
there will be world peace.
Why? Because consumers have
the right to buy things.
And they have a need to buy. And therefore
nations have a need to produce.
And nations produce the best when
they are trading together as opposed
to warring against each other.
Okay? So this is the argument
that Francis Fukuyama makes
in the end of history.
I want to explain this argument further.
Okay? What's he really saying?
Okay. So throughout human history,
all societies have
struggled with one problem.
Which is how do we optimize
the workforce? How do we get each and
every person to work as hard
as possible for our society?
And if everyone did that,
then our society would be
strong, united, and prosperous.
Right? Okay? So that's a
fundamental problem of politics.
How do we optimize
workforce participation?
And traditionally, or historically,
there have been three answers.
The first is war.
The second is religion.
And the third is civilization.
Okay? Now,
as you can understand,
these three things work because they give
structure, meaning,
and purpose to our lives.
Okay? And we have structure,
meaning, and purpose,
we are much more motivated to work hard.
But as you can also see, there
are actually lots of problems
with all three.
Right? War is you kill people.
That's bad. Religion is superstitious.
Okay? But civilization itself is also
problematic. Because the larger
extreme of civilization is
racism. Okay? Which
is to say that we Russians
are better than everyone else.
We Chinese are better than everyone else.
Therefore, we can do whatever we want.
Okay? And this naturally
leads to imperialism. Right?
We have a duty to go conquer other people,
to civilize them.
Right? Something called
the white man's burden.
And this leads to fascism.
Okay? Okay?
War and conquest are the ultimate good.
So, historically, war,
religion, and civilization
have given people structure,
meaning, and purpose,
but they create a lot of problems.
They create suffering, and war,
and pain. Okay?
So, but over time,
what has happened is that
all of them, over time, have
become much more abstract.
And the reason why they've become more abstract
is in order to increase the population,
in order to create mass society.
Okay? So, let me give
you an example of this.
The earliest religions
in humanity have been polytheistic.
Okay? And the gods themselves
were very much like humans.
Think of the Greeks. Okay? Zeus,
Athena, Hera.
Okay? It was a polytheistic society, and
they were very much like humans.
But over time,
this polytheism became monotheistic,
and it became abstract.
Okay? The idea of God was
so much removed from us.
And the benefit of that is that
you can have more people
believing in one God.
And it motivates you to work harder.
Okay? It's just an abstract concept.
And because of abstraction,
we develop new ideas.
For example, money.
Okay? So,
rather than have war, religion,
and civilization as the structure
and center of our society,
one would make money
from the structure of your society. Okay?
This is what we call capitalism.
And capitalism, of course, led
to the industrial revolution.
Industrialism. Okay?
Capitalism meant that
societies were becoming
wealthier and wealthier,
more industrialized.
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright.
But there's a problem
with capitalism. Right?
What's the problem with making capital or
money at the very heart of your society?
Exactly. Okay? So,
the first major problem with
capitalism is it's all -consuming.
So, as Jack says,
all capitalism cares
about is the expansion and
growth of capital, regardless
of its effect on society.
Okay? Profit for the
sake of growing profit.
It's an all -consuming idea, which
can ultimately lead to the
destruction of the planet.
Okay? That's the first problem.
What's another problem with capitalism?
Or the idea of having money as the
heart and center of your society?
Anyone? Okay. So,
what this means is that
money likes to consolidate itself.
Okay? Consolidating. Okay? Meaning that
if, so the example is, let's just say
that each of us had a million dollars.
Right? What's the fastest
way for us to grow our money?
If we put it together, right?
And then we go invest it.
Okay? So, in other
words, if you just like,
let capitalism do whatever
it wants to infinity,
what happens is that you exactly
have one person with all the money.
Okay? Does that make sense? Because that's the
fastest way to grow money, by consolidating it.
Okay? So that's problematic.
What else is wrong with
capitalism or money? Okay.
So another problem is
the idea of alienating.
Or dehumanizing.
Okay? What does this mean?
Capital alienates and dehumanizes.
What does that mean?
Exactly. Okay. You are, you
as a person cease to be human.
Right? To be human is to be a complex,
multifaceted individual
who likes to create and love.
But in capitalism, you're
only your production value,
you're only the amount of
money in your bank account.
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright?
So, for all these reasons,
capitalism is really bad.
There are actually more
reasons. Okay? So, Karl Marx,
in his Communist Manifesto, points
out all these problems of capitalism
and he proposes a solution.
Which is, okay, rather than
make money at the heart
and center of your industrial society,
make the worker the heart
and center of your society.
Okay? So he makes this argument.
But what's very revolutionary or prescient
about his argument is
this is a natural cycle.
Okay? This is part of the Hegel cycle
where capitalism comes along and
capitalism will be the natural evolution
of capitalism. Okay?
Why? Okay.
Okay. So let's do the thought experiment.
Okay? Let's do this thought experiment
where your parents have died
and now you're working in a
factory in order to survive.
How do you feel about this?
Your parents have died.
There's no one to support you.
So, at age 16, 17, 18, you
have to go off to a factory.
To make money for yourself.
So how do you feel about this?
Are you happy about this?
How, how do you feel?
Depressing and? And lonely and?
Yeah, exactly. You're bitter.
And you're depressed.
Okay? You're alienated.
So then what do you do?
Then what do you do?
What can you do now? You're bitter.
You're angry. You're depressed.
You're lonely. So what do you do?
Okay. You start to
think about why this is the case.
Right? You start to have
a political consciousness.
What Marx calls political
consciousness. From this
alienation of the worker,
workers will start to develop
a political consciousness.
Right? They're like,
why is this happening?
Why has the government abandoned me?
Why has society abandoned me?
What can I do about this?
Okay? So then what happens?
That's exactly right. You want change.
Right? And how do you enact change?
Yes. Okay. You spread your
ideas and you organize.
Right? And when you organize,
what do you realize?
Yeah. What you recognize
when you start to organize is
the capitalist needs you to do the work.
Right? The capitalist owns the capital and
the factories, but you're the one
who's actually doing the real work.
So without you,
the factories can't run. So
as long as you stay united,
you can enact whatever
political demands you want.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
So for Marx, this is just a
natural evolution of capitalism.
Capitalism leads to the
alienation of the working class,
which will lead to their political consciousness,
which will lead to their solidarity,
which will lead to a
political revolution, and
so you can make the worker
as the heart and center
of your society.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
Alright? Now,
what's amazing about Marx
is that today we say he's wrong.
Right? Communism happened
in the Soviet Union,
it happened in China, but it didn't
happen in Europe and in the United States.
Where Marx said it would
happen first, because
Germany was more industrialized
than Russia or China.
Okay? Does that make
sense? That's what we say.
If you think about it deeply, okay,
Marx was right. After World War II,
every society, every industrial
society, to some extent,
adopted the ideals of communism.
Does that make sense? Okay?
We call this socialism, not communism, but
basically it adhere to the thinking
of Marx, which is to make
the worker the heart
and center of your society.
And why did they do
that after World War II?
Exactly, okay? Because
workers create value.
Money doesn't create any value.
Money just creates more money.
Okay, it's speculative. But
the workers create value.
And therefore, you have to
treat your workers properly.
So, in America and in Europe,
workers became the heart
and center of your society.
And the workers through unions
could demand political reforms.
And so, all of society was geared towards
making the lives of the middle class,
the working class, better, okay?
That's why you had excellent healthcare,
great public schools.
Cheap universities. Okay?
So, the 50s and 60s and
70s was basically the peak
of society for the working class.
But in the 80s,
we started to change this.
Why? Why would we want
to change the system?
It's a great system, right? Marx is right.
Having the worker as the heart
and center of your society.
As the central organizing unit of society
makes a lot more sense than
having money as the heart
and center, okay? But starting in the
80s, we start to go back to money.
Why? Excuse me?
Who wants more? Yes, exactly.
So, what happened in the 80s is something
called the revolt of the elite.
Okay? In other words,
the problem with having a society based on
the worker is it becomes too egalitarian,
too equal, right?
But if you're like the elite,
you don't want equality,
you want difference.
You want to have the same values.
You want to have power
and money in your hands.
Does that make sense? So, the revolt
of the elite happened in the 80s.
And this is what we call in the
United States the Reagan Revolution,
okay? The Reagan Revolution.
The beginning of neoliberalism,
free market capitalism.
And in Britain it was
called Thatcherism, okay?
Margaret Thatcher. The
Thatcher Revolution.
And so, now you need to transition
away from the worker to
something else, okay?
Another ideology that
allows the elite to amass power, okay?
So, just to show you how
radical this revolution was,
in the 1970s, okay?
In the 1970s, if you were a CEO,
the head of a company, okay?
You were making on average
one million US dollars a year.
That's pretty good, right?
That's really good money.
And that one million dollars
was more than
20 times the worker.
Okay? And that's
pretty reasonable. Today,
the average CEO in the United States
makes 20 million dollars a year.
And that
is 200 to 300 times more than the
average worker in the company.
Does that make sense? So,
in the 80s inequality started
to explode.
Right? And so, they're transitioning
from the worker to a new
organizing unit called the consumer.
Okay? So, they needed to destroy
the working class, the middle class.
And the way they did it was by introducing
a new concept called the consumer, okay?
So, in the 50s, 60s, and 70s, the
government promised you a good job.
If you were a member of a
society if you were a citizen,
I promise you a good job
that you would have for
the rest of your life.
Okay? So, in the 80s,
the government said I promise you that
you have low prices and a
wide selection of goods.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Alright? So, this sounds
like a subtle shift,
going from the worker to the consumer.
Okay? But what this meant was a revolution
in society. A revolution in politics.
So, remember that an
example of the worker,
the worker has to have political consciousness
in order to protect his or her rights,
in order to organize and unify
and push for favorable political reforms.
Okay? That's what the worker must do.
Okay? But now let's think about
the mentality of the consumer.
And to do this, let's do another
thought experiment. And the
thought experiment is this.
Everyone in the school, about 500 people,
I decide to give everyone
1 million US dollars.
Okay? So, everyone in the school
has exactly 1 million US dollars
to spend. What happens now?
Think about this. What happens now?
Use your imagination. What happens?
What's the first thing you do? What's the first
thing you do? I've given you a million dollars.
What do you do with it? Well,
the first thing you do
is buy something, right?
What do you want to buy? A 1
million dollars is a lot of money.
What do you want to buy, Nav?
You buy a house. You buy a house, right?
That's great. That's a great purchase.
Then what do you do? Then what do you do?
Then buy a house.
Then buy furniture.
Okay. First thing is Nav buys a house.
Then what does he do? Buy furniture.
Buy furniture. Then what does he do?
There's something that he
must do that's very important.
What does he buy the house?
What does he want to do?
He wants to take pictures
and post on social media.
Right? So everyone sees
it on social media.
Then you see this.
Nav has this huge house in Beijing
with lots of fancy furniture.
What do you do now? You
also want to buy a house.
But what kind of house?
A bigger house, right?
And then what do you do?
You also post pictures.
You also post pictures, okay?
Then how do other people feel?
You think this is funny, okay?
But this happens all the time. So
very quickly what happens in the school?
And you all spend your money
and you all go into debt.
Right? Because you're in
competition with each other.
That's not the biggest thing. And one
million dollars is a lot of money but
it's not enough to buy everything, right?
So you go into debt. You borrow more money
to buy more things. And then what happens?
And then what happens? How do
you guys feel about each other?
Do you guys have lunch together?
Do you guys have dinner together?
Do you guys like to
share homework together?
Do you guys like to share homework
together? You guys hate each other, right?
At the end of the day what will happen is you
all go into debt and you all hate each other.
Right? So that's consumerism.
This is what consumerism is.
Consumerism creates a competition
in society in society for prestige,
okay? To see who can post the
nicest social media pictures.
This leads to the individualization
or the optimization
of you, okay?
In other words, you are now
unable to act together.
You don't want to organize.
You don't want to act in solidarity. Okay?
And ultimately this means that
you develop economic logic.
Okay? And what is economic logic?
It's to see the world
only through the lens of capital.
Okay? Does it make sense?
So when you see someone
and you're like, okay well,
do I want to date this person?
You don't ask, oh is this
person a nice person?
You ask yourself, how much
money does this person have?
Okay? You understand? You use
economic logic in order to
understand the world and to reason
and analyze the world, okay?
Now let me ask you this question.
Today is this how China works?
Is this how the world works?
The answer is yes, okay?
Are you like this?
Yes, you are like this, okay?
You've been brainwashed into thinking
that this is the only way to behave
and to think. You're in school.
Why are you in school? So
you can get a good job.
Why? To make money.
So you can buy things,
okay? You understand?
That's how you all think. But there are
different ways to think about school, right?
You're like, I'm in school to learn, to
open my mind, to have an imagination,
to think critically
about the world, right?
Now it's a way we thought about school
when the workers were dominant.
But now that consumers are dominant,
all we think about is
how do I get a good job?
How do I buy a bigger house?
Because I want to post it on social media,
okay? So if you think about this,
what this really is
is the perfection
of slavery. Does it make sense?
What does this phrase mean?
The perfection of slavery?
Yeah, you become a slave
of the money, but what?
Why is this perfect? Yes,
okay? You understand? If
you're a slave, you rebel,
right? But if you don't
know you're a slave and
you like this, you choose this,
then you will never rebel, okay?
So the consumerism
is the perfection
of slavery, okay?
And you can't do that. You can't do
that. That's why Francis Fukuyama thinks
that consumerism is the end of
history. Because it is a system
that achieves what the elites want
and the masses are unwilling
and unable to protest and rebel.
Okay, does that make sense?
It's a perfect system.
Okay? So
but there are certain civilizations
that rebel against slavery
intrinsically. It is in their
nature to rebel against slavery.
And one of these civilizations
is the Russian civilization.
Okay? So when you impose slavery
on Russians, they become corrupt,
they become alcoholics, and
they refuse to have babies.
That is why Russia is
failing as a society.
Because slavery is being imposed
on Russians by the Westerners,
and the Russians refuse to be slaves.
But because this system,
consumerism, is so perfect,
Russian people lack an understanding
of how to rebel against the system,
and that's why Russia is falling apart.
Okay? That is a Putin argument.
Does that make sense? Okay?
In other words, consumerism
has corrupted the Russian soul.
And Russian have chosen to
be corrupted by consumerism.
Okay? So does it make sense?
So what Vladimir Putin
must do is free his people.
Even though they may enjoy prison.
Okay? Even though Russians
may enjoy slavery,
Putin is still going to free his people.
And he's going to do it by
creating a new concept to combat
consumerism. Okay? So
we've gone from the
worker to the consumer,
and Putin is going to introduce
a new concept called the warrior.
The consumer is a person,
an individual, who acts alone and
does so to preserve
his or her life. Okay?
The consumer is a coward.
The consumer lacks imagination.
The consumer is alienated.
The warrior is different.
The warrior is an individual who sees
that through his actions,
he or she can shape the
direction of history.
I can make my own reality
through my courage
and through my imagination.
And by acting with others.
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright.
So, let's do another thought experiment
to understand the warrior concept.
Let's just say that, okay, in this school
I give everyone a million dollars and now you hate each other.
Okay? Then what happens
is I put you on a plane
and I take you all to an island.
Okay? And you're on this island and
unfortunately on this
island there are millions
and millions of flesh -eating monkeys.
They want to eat you.
Okay? But you hate each other.
You don't want to work
together. What happens now?
What happens now? Yeah,
that's right. If you don't do anything,
everyone gets eaten by a monkey, right?
But what are you going to do? How?
You will fight the monkeys by
how will you fight the monkeys?
Okay. What's going to happen is
that everyone is going to put aside
the differences and work
together to fight the monkeys.
Okay? And how will you feel
in this process? Are you going
to be happy or depressed?
You're going to be happy. Why? Exactly.
You're all working towards the same goal.
Okay? Structure, meaning, and purpose.
Okay? That's what war does.
War gives you structure, meaning, and
purpose so you feel happy about yourself.
Okay? Now let's say that during this war,
um, like Celine dies.
Okay? Now what happens?
What does death do now?
Yeah. Yes.
And? So Celine dies.
She goes to martyr. You all
celebrate her, remember her.
You give her a great funeral.
And then what do you do?
You fight harder. Do you understand?
Because death gives you purpose.
Her death makes your life much
more valuable to you and to others.
Okay? Not only do you celebrate her life,
but you celebrate her, your own life.
Okay? Alright.
Now let's just say that
the monkeys are coming.
Okay? And there's a bridge.
There's a bridge. And
Jack is standing on this bridge.
And there are ten of
you on the other side.
Okay? So Jack has a choice.
He can either cut the
bridge and kill himself
and save the others, or he can run, run,
and possibly all get killed.
Right? By the monkeys. What does Jack do?
For sure he will do this.
What will he do? He's
going to sacrifice himself.
He's going to sacrifice himself. Okay? Do you
understand? We've seen this in war over and over.
Okay? That's what war does to people.
It makes you, it gives you
structure, meaning, and purpose.
And it makes you a stronger,
more disciplined person.
Okay? Does that make sense? Right?
So that's the thought
experiment. So, in theory
then, when
Putin launched this military operation,
it's called a special military operation
in Ukraine back in February 2022,
then we should see improvements
in Russian society.
Okay? Does that make sense? So,
what's happened in Russia since this war?
Are people happier? Do you
think people are happier?
Do you think people are happier now? Okay,
I think they are. Do you
think people are more unified?
I think they are. Okay?
So one example of this is
the Russian economy
is surviving U.S.
sanctions. In fact, it's
getting stronger and stronger.
Why? Because people are fully
participating in the economy now.
Okay? So, an example of
this is that every month
Russia is producing 150,000
ammunition cells. Okay?
For the war. Every month,
Russia is producing more
ammunition shells for the war.
Okay? 150,000. Can you guys guess how much
the United States produces every month?
In comparison? Guess. Guess the number.
Jimmy? 100,000?
2,000. Okay? You understand?
So Russia is steering
towards a war economy.
Factories are producing
more and more weapons.
But that means more and more people are
employed. Which means that
they're drinking less.
Okay? When you have structure and meaning
and purpose in your society,
all this goes down.
Corruption goes down.
Alcoholism goes down.
Oh, sorry. Fertility goes up.
All right? Does that make sense?
So, last year,
Putin made this statement.
Okay? He was asked, okay,
you have a lot of Russians
dying on the battlefield.
And he said, well, when
they die on the battlefield,
we honor them.
They sacrifice themselves
for their country.
They will always be remembered as heroes.
Their families will always love them.
But if we just let them do what they want,
all they're gonna do is
drink themselves to death.
Okay? You understand?
So Putin is saying is
that what war is, ultimately,
it is a mechanism for society
to rejuvenate itself.
Okay? What war is,
it's opportunity for society
to cut away the fat.
To make it more lean.
So for Putin, this war is not really
about conquering Ukraine
or defending against NATO.
It's really about saving
Russian civilization.
It's really about saving the Russian soul.
Okay? If you don't fight this war,
and you let these trends continue,
then Russia will eventually
cease to exist as a nation.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So what's gonna happen is that over time,
a new concept will arise
to challenge consumerism
and liberal democracy. And we
will call this concept Putinism.
And the idea of Putinism
is really continuous war.
That as a society,
you should be constantly fighting
wars in all order to discipline,
unify your nation.
Okay? And make your people stronger
and more prosperous.
That is Putinism.
Okay? And I think this will
be his defining legacy.
And Putinism is a direct
response to liberal democracy.
So we will shift as a society from one
that is based on the consumer to
one that is based on the warrior.
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
Any questions?
Oh, so Selina asked a question.
How is capitalism different
from liberal democracy?
That's a great question. So capitalism
is only concerned about capital.
So you can be a fascist
country and be capitalistic.
So capitalism, many people
say, leads to fascism.
So Nazis were extremely capitalistic.
They see communism, the Soviet
Union, as a direct threat
to its existence. Okay?
The idea of a liberal democracy is
the participation of everyone in
the generation of capital.
Does that make sense? So in other words,
this is one of the ironies
of the 20th century is that
capitalism and democracy
are opposing forces. And
the idea of liberal
democracy is to put the
two together in a synthesis
as to explain away
or ignore the contradictions.
Okay? But capitalism and
democracy are contradictions.
Does that make sense?
Okay, any more questions?
Okay, so Jack makes a great point, which
is like wars that have been fought before
have destroyed societies.
Okay? So think of Athens and Sparta.
And think of World War II and World War I.
Okay? Societies become
exhausted and destroyed. So
the idea of continuous war is
you fight small -scale wars
so as to manage the!
!
the size of the conflict.
Okay? And it's important to do that.
Why? Why don't you want
a large -scale war?
No, no, no, no. You, what might
happen in a large -scale war?
That's right, okay. The problem is you
have nuclear weapons in place now.
Okay? So it is not
it's not smart to fight
a large -scale war.
When you fight a large -scale
war you can't really control
the escalation. And eventually,
say the United States
and Russia fight a ground war in
Europe, eventually they'll be so
angry at each other, they might
have to use nuclear weapons.
Okay? That's why
one of the major tenets of Putinism
is you pick small contained conflicts.
So Ukraine is a small contained conflict.
Okay? An invasion of France or an invasion
of Britain would lead to nuclear war.
Does that make sense? Okay?
And that's why the United
States would also pick Iran.
Because Iran would be a
small contained conflict.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So this is the Putinism.
Okay? War is a mechanism
to transform your society.
Whereas before, we understood war
as a mechanism to conquer others.
Okay? As imperialism or the
spreading of civilization.
Now, the idea of Putinism is no, guys.
We don't care about the other people.
We care about ourselves.
We're using war as
basically a mechanism to
discipline our bodies.
Just like the gym. Okay?
Does that make sense? Okay?
The thing about global leaders,
world leaders is they're all
insane but they're not stupid.
You understand? There's a difference.
They're happy to kill millions of people.
They're not happy to blow up the world.
Okay? But
Jack's other point is that
Russia's not a very wealthy country.
Right? Eventually, you're
going to exhaust yourself.
And that's why we think war
is usually a pyramid scheme.
Okay? And what that means is
so the example is Nazi Germany.
When they were fighting these wars,
it was costing their economy a lot of money
so they were forced to fight even more wars.
Okay? That's what eventually led
to Germany's invasion of Russia
because they needed the
resources and the manpower.
Okay? And that's the same
thing that will happen here
where, okay, Putin is spending a lot
of money to fight this war in Ukraine.
Okay? But after he finishes
this war in Ukraine,
he needs to go conquer more
territory for their resources.
Okay? So in the long term,
this could lead to disaster.
Okay? This could lead
to a large scale war.
But in the short term,
it does work. Okay?
Does that make sense?
Okay. Any more questions?
Okay. So,
Selena asked a great question, which is like
eventually people are going to get exhausted.
Okay? And
what Putin
believes is that
the Russians are a warrior culture.
Okay? Russians enjoy war.
Russians are good at war.
So, Russians won't be exhausted by war.
They'll be galvanized
and energized by war.
That's a theory. Okay? And he's right.
Okay? There are warrior cultures
out there around the world
that do enjoy fighting.
Okay? So you think of the German people.
Right? The Germans have
been fighting wars for
a thousand years and have
been really good at it.
Okay? You think of Japanese.
Okay? Japan is also a warrior
culture that enjoys fighting wars.
Okay? China is not a warrior culture.
It's very hard for the
Chinese to fight wars.
And Chinese, okay, I hate to say this,
but China would probably lose most wars.
Okay? It's not a warrior culture.
So, for Chinese civilization,
war would be exhausting. But
for Russian civilization,
war can be energizing and
illuminating. Okay? Does that make
sense? It depends on your civilization.
Okay? Any more questions? Okay.
So, um,
what's going to happen?
And the answer is that
um, culture works right now.
Okay? Because war culture
beats consumer culture easily.
So you see the war in Ukraine where
Russians are destroying the
Ukrainians and the Europeans are
like ah, I'm too busy watching TV.
I'm too busy buying things.
I'm too busy vacationing. Okay? So
consumers don't want to go to war.
Okay? But eventually Russia
is going to reach a point
where it directly threatens
Germany and France and Britain.
And then they will
start to transition into a war culture.
Okay? So, Putinism will
become the dominant ideology
for the next 50 years.
Okay? But Putinism can
spread to other countries.
Okay? So Japan can adopt Putinism.
Germany can adopt it.
Britain can adopt it. Okay?
And so the world we call, so when
this happens, we call this world
multipolar. So
the word we use is multipolar.
Okay? Or multipolarity. Meaning that like there are
different centers of power throughout the world.
Right now there's only the United States.
It's a global hegemon. But
over the next 10, 20 years we
expect a multipolar world where
each region has different hegemons.
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright.
Any more questions?.
..
Okay. So, what happens
to the United States?
So next week we'll
discuss the United States.
Okay? But what I will show you is that
if the United States
fights this war in Iran,
what it has to do is retreat
back to its borders.
Okay? And has to become isolationist.
But I'll explain that to you, I'll
explain that to you next week.
Okay? Any more questions?
Sorry, sorry. Go ahead.
..
....
... Okay, so that's a
great question, okay?
So we just said that consumer
culture is the perfection of slavery,
but is warrior culture slavery?
And you can make the argument
that it's actually anti -slavery.
Why? Why?
What can the warrior do
that the consumer cannot do?
What's the problem with having
a warrior culture, really?
See what I mean? What can warriors
do that the consumers would never do?
Guys, warriors can rebel, right?
Warriors can mutiny. The army can
be like, you guys are terrible.
We're going to rebel against you, okay?
You understand? Does
that make sense to you?
Consumers don't do that. Consumers are
like, okay, we're going to do this.
Hmm, I'm going to rebel.
I'm going to stop buying things.
No one's going to do that, okay?
You will never be like, I'm going to stop
buying things because I think it's bad for the environment.
You won't do that. Whereas
warriors are like, you know what?
I don't like this leader. Let's
march to Moscow and get rid of him.
They can do that. And they
do that all the time.
That's why warrior
culture is so destructive.
That's why warrior culture was so
dominant before and then we got rid of it.
Because for political leaders,
warrior culture is a direct threat.
Does that make sense? Okay.
So, but in this question,
this reveals a contradiction
in Putinism, okay?
What is the ultimate
problem in Putin turning
his entire country into a war society?
What's the problem with that? And
it's a huge problem for Russia.
And this is why ultimately Russia will
not triumph in a multipolar world.
In fact, it will probably...
Does it? Does it?
It will probably fall apart. Why?
For a warrior culture to
triumph, what does it need?
Warriors fight best when what?
When there's a king,
guys. When there's a king.
That's why we have kings. Right?
So what's the problem with Putin's Russia?
Russia is a country of kings.
What's going to happen to Russia?
Guys, eventually Putin's going to die.
Do you understand?
Eventually he's going to die.
And then what's going to happen? The
country's going to fall apart because
there's a warrior culture and you have
these different generals fighting each other for total control.
There's going to be civil war, okay?
Putin right now is a strategic genius.
He's the king. Everyone admires him.
So he unites everyone. He
can direct officers to war.
He can direct the entire society into total war.
When he dies, this society's going to fall apart.
Okay? That's why Putin's legacy
will not be a strong Russia.
It will be Putinism. Okay?
The idea of continuous war. Russia
may not survive without Putin.
Okay? And
quite honestly, when you have a great leader
like Putin, it's impossible to replace him.
All right? No one would have
his genius and authority.
Right? Nothing like that.
Nothing like that. Nothing like that.
Nothing like that. Nothing
like that. Nothing like that.
Nothing like that.
Nothing like that. Nothing like that. Nothing
like that. Nothing like that. Nothing like that.
Nothing like that. Nothing
like that. Nothing like that.
Nothing like that.
Nothing like that. Nothing like that.
Most people don't like to go to war, okay?
Most people are scared by war.
But ultimately, society is determined
by those who are willing to
act on their beliefs, okay?
So when we looked at America,
look, they issue a lobby,
they're only a small faction,
small fraction of the American
population, like less than 1%, okay?
But because they're willing to act, and
they're organized, and they're determined,
they're willing to act their way. Does that
make sense? Same thing in Russia, where
at most, okay, I would
say at most, you have 10%
who are like, oh, Putinism is a great
idea, let's go conquer the world.
At most you have 10%.
Most people are like,
we want peace, we want to live our lives.
I have children, I want
my children to be safe.
I don't want to send my
children to war, okay?
But again, history is determined by those
who are determined to
act and act in unison.
Okay, so it's usually the most
extreme individuals who get their way.
Does that make sense? Okay, but
thanks for the question, okay?
Any more questions?.
Okay, so Putin believes that
Russia is first and foremost
a great civilization,
okay? But as a great civilization,
it also has to fight
wars to protect itself,
you understand? So Putin's like,
you know what, if America left us alone,
we would not fight wars, okay?
It's only because America
insists on encircling us,
insists on trying to destroy
our culture, our civilization,
that we must fight a war.
Okay, does that make sense?
All right, and so what
people say is, listen,
the war in Ukraine, it's ultimately caused
by NATO encroachment into Russia,
right? So NATO,
after Soviet Union fell,
expanded five times.
Guys, NATO was set up
as a defensive alliance
against the Soviet Union. Well, if you don't
have a Soviet Union, you don't need NATO anymore.
So why is NATO expanding?
In fact, NATO was gonna
expand into Ukraine.
So Putin is like, we
are fighting this war,
ultimately, to defend our civilization.
That's what matters, the
defense of our civilization.
And if it requires us into going,
if it requires us to go to war, then
we will do so, okay?
And this is this process that
will create Putinism, okay?
Or continuous war. Does that make sense?
Okay, any more questions? Yeah?
Yeah?. Okay, so even though
only 10% agree with Putinism,
I actually don't know
the real number, okay?
But I think it's only a
minority. What happens is that,
in war, people become much more unified,
okay? So the example is
Ukraine, where actually,
about 50% of the people in
Ukraine were Russian speakers.
Okay? And there was a
large group of people,
at least a third, who were
sympathetic towards Russia.
But the moment that Putin invaded,
they all united under Zelensky, okay?
So that's what war does.
War unifies people.
So again, back to the island example.
You guys may hate each other
when you land on the island.
But hey, if there's a million flesh
-eating monkeys that wanna kill you,
you guys are going to become a family.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay.
Any more questions? Is
this clear to you guys?
Okay. You look at,
so you wanna ask a question. question.
Are you confused by something,
Celine? Excuse me?
Okay, so again Russia
is a warrior culture.
It enjoys war, it's good
at fighting wars, okay?
But China is not a warrior culture.
And the reason why is that
throughout most of Chinese history,
China was the dominant
power, the hegemon, okay?
Also, China is surrounded
by natural defenses, right?
So to the east you have the sea,
to the south and to the
west you have mountains,
to the north you have
the Great Wall, okay?
So China doesn't feel threatened by anyone and
therefore it doesn't have a warrior culture.
Does that make sense? But
Russia is a huge country that's
been invaded multiple times
and all these invasions
were traumatic for Russia,
okay? So you look at the German
invasion of the Soviet Union in 1941,
that killed 20 million people.
Millions of Russians died in that war and
people still celebrate that war, okay?
So China is not a warrior culture,
okay?
Does that make sense?
Okay, any more questions?
Okay, so
what we will do next
week is we'll talk about
Putin's strategic genius,
okay? And what I will show you, and
this will be interesting, is that the way
that Russians see the world is radically
different from the way we see the world,
okay? So
we'll discuss Putin's
strategy moving forward next class, okay?
Does that make sense? Alright, good.