So we are doing Octavius
and the birth of the Roman Empire today.
So let's review where we are.
The year is 44 BCE and
Julius Caesar has just been assassinated.
And the three main conspirators,
there are 60 senators,
but the three main conspirators
are Marcus Brutus, who
is considered the leader
of the conspiracy,
Cassius, and
Decimus Brutus.
And after they assassinated Caesar,
obviously Rome is in turmoil.
And Mark Anthony, who
is currently the council or
the head of state in Rome,
he reaches an agreement
with these conspirators.
The agreement is this. Mark Anthony, who
is a staunch ally of Julius Caesar,
he will not seek retribution.
And in return,
the conspirators will declare
that Caesar was not a tyrant.
He did not want to become king. So
a peace settlement was
reached to avoid a civil war.
Um... The problem is
that Mark Anthony was
working behind the scenes
to work up the Roman people
against conspirators.
And eventually, public sentiment was
so much against the conspirators,
they had to flee to the provinces.
Okay? And then,
Mark Anthony read the will of Caesar.
Okay? Caesar's will. Remember
that there's private property in Rome.
And so when a man dies, he has a will.
And then this will stipulates how this
private property will be distributed.
Okay? And
there are three really
surprising things about the will.
The first thing is that
Caesar right now is the
wealthiest man in Rome.
And he stipulates that upon his death,
every Roman citizen will get
three months of a soldier's wage.
That's a lot of money. Okay?
That's extreme generosity.
He also stipulates
that a lot of his private property
will be turned into public parks
for the benefit of the Roman people.
So this will demonstrates
Caesar's love of his people.
Okay? The second thing is
actually more surprising.
Mark Anthony believed that
he would be named the
heir to Caesar's legacy
and wealth in the will.
But in fact,
Caesar names this complete
stranger to be his heir.
His name is Octavius.
And Caesar named Octavius
to be his adopted son.
And so Octavius' name is
actually Gaius Octavius.
And upon his adoption,
he is now named
Gaius Julius Caesar Octavius.
This is like much too complicated.
So historians use the shorthand Octavian.
Okay? So we will now name
this person Octavian.
And this is the historical shorthand,
even though this is not his real name.
So that's the second big surprise.
In the will. And the third
big surprise is this.
Caesar names secondary heirs.
These are individuals who
will inherit Caesar's property
and legacy if Octavian were to die.
Mark Anthony is a secondary heir, but
so is Decimus Brutus.
One of the men who
conspired to kill Caesar.
Okay? So this will of Caesar's,
it is shocking. And
it shows to the Roman people
that Caesar really loved them
and that Caesar loved everyone,
including the people who
conspired to kill him. Okay?
Mark Anthony is very
upset about this will.
So that when Octavian, and Octavian
right now, he's only 18 years old.
Okay? He's only 18 years old.
And he returns to claim his legacy.
Mark Anthony is so upset that he
refuses to meet with Octavian.
And he refuses to give Caesar's property
and wealth to Octavian.
Remember, the first
stipulation of the will is
that every Roman citizen will
be given three months of wages.
Okay? And Octavian,
what he does is to honor Caesar's will,
he borrows money. Okay?
This is a lot of money in order to ensure
that every citizen got three months of wages.
So in this situation,
okay, and this is only a few
months after Caesar's death,
this is now a volatile
Game of Thrones situation.
Game of Thrones. Mark Anthony
considers himself the legitimate heir.
Of Caesar and refuses
to acknowledge Octavian.
Octavian has returned and demands
to be acknowledged as the heir.
Okay? So that's one conflict.
The other conflict is you have these
three conspirators, Decimus Brutus,
Marcus Brutus, and Cassius.
And they're not in Rome, but they're
in the provinces with huge armies.
Okay? So Decimus Brutus, he is in Gaul.
Marcus Brutus and
Cassius are in the Roman East,
which includes Anatolia and Syria.
Okay? Extremely wealthy provinces
where they have many loyal soldiers.
And they understand that eventually
there's a conflict coming,
so they raise a huge army,
about 100,000 soldiers,
to prepare for the eventual conflict.
And this is like the largest army
ever assembled in Roman history.
You also have, you have
a name, named Lepidus,
who is a very competent administrator.
And he has his own army.
And he actually wanted to avenge Caesar,
but Mark Anthony stopped him.
Okay? So Lepidus is also
part of the equation.
In the center is a name, named Cicero.
Cicero is considered one of the
greatest orators in Roman history.
It was very common, it's very common
as part of the liberal arts education,
to study the speeches of Cicero.
Okay? And Cicero is the
last remaining optimist.
And the optimists are the
ones who are conservatives,
and who believe in the
primacy of the Senate.
So Cicero is right now
in charge of the Senate.
And everyone in this Game of
Thrones has a different motivation.
Right? So Cicero,
his main motivation is to maintain
the supremacy of the Senate.
So he wants a balance of power.
So what he will do, is he will play
everyone off against each other,
in order to maintain the supremacy of
the Senate, and therefore his authority.
Okay? That's Cicero. Octavian
wants to be the heir of Caesar,
but so does Mark Anthony. And
Lepidus also wants to be a heir as well.
And then on the other side, are
Decimus Brutus, Marcus Brutus,
and Cassius, who are fighting
for their own legacy.
Okay? So this is the situation in 44,
B.C.E.
And it's a Game of Thrones situation,
and you would expect
the one who would most likely
lose this Game of Thrones
would be Octavian, right?
He's 18 years old, he's got no army,
and he has no allies in Rome.
What happens over the next 15 years is,
one by one, Octavian
destroys all his enemies.
What happens first is that
Mark Anthony goes to war
with Decimus Brutus.
Decimus Brutus is in charge of Gaul, and
Mark Anthony wants the
armies of Decimus Brutus.
So Mark Anthony marches
against Decimus Brutus,
and then Cicero, to maintain
the balance of power,
he authorizes Octavian to raise his
own army to challenge Mark Anthony.
Okay? So now they're
at war with each other.
Eventually, Mark Anthony loses, and then
he steals basically Lepidus' army to
march against Decimus Brutus again.
And at this point, what
happens is very strange.
The three of them, Lepidus,
Octavian, and Mark Anthony,
they sit down together, and
they agree to share power and
form their own dictatorship.
This is what we call the Second War.
The Second Triumvirate. Okay?
The Second Triumvirate is brutal.
The first thing they decide to
do is kill all their enemies,
anyone who could challenge them,
including Cicero, who
was previously the patron of Octavian.
So they kill about a
third of the Senate, and
replace the Senate with their allies.
Then, Mark Anthony and
Octavian marched against
Marcus Brutus and Cassius.
Okay? Decimus Brutus has been destroyed.
They now march against
Marcus Brutus and Cassius.
And then in 42 BCE,
they fight the Battle of
Philippi in Macedonia.
Okay? Philippi is a city
named after King Philip.
And in this battle,
Mark Anthony and Octavian triumph.
In the largest battle
in history at that time.
Okay? And after this battle,
where Marcus Brutus
and Cassius are killed,
Octavian, Mark Anthony, and
Lippidus agree to share the world.
So Octavian would get Rome,
Lippidus would get Northern Africa, and
Mark Anthony would get Egypt and
the Near East, Anatolia, Syria.
So Mark Anthony basically
gets the lion's share.
Of the Roman world.
Okay? And they agree to share it.
Then what happens is Lippidus comes
into conflict with Mark Anthony.
Well, sorry. Lippidus comes
into conflict with Octavian.
And Octavian gives a speech
to Lippidus' soldiers
who all defect over to Octavian.
Then Octavian comes into
conflict with Mark Anthony.
And in 31 BCE,
at the Battle of, um, um,
um, what's that battle called again?
31... Actium, sorry.
Actium in Greece. It's a huge battle
where Anthony's forces are aligned
with Cleopatra's forces against,
um, Octavian.
In this battle, what happens is
basically Mark Anthony and Cleopatra,
they run away from the battle.
Where, and then they return to Alexandria
and then Octavian goes
and hunts them down.
And they both commit suicide
before they're captured.
And then this ends in 27 BCE
when Octavian returns to the Senate,
the Roman Senate, in triumph.
And they declare him Augustus Caesar.
Okay? Augustus Caesar.
His name has now changed
to Augustus Caesar.
And he's considered the
first emperor of Rome.
Okay? So this is the brief history.
Now I want to ask the question,
how did Octavian, again, who in 44 BCE,
he's only 18 years old,
he has no army, and
has very few allies in Rome, how was
he able to triumph over everyone?
Okay? All right, and there
are different explanations.
Um, the first you can say is just,
well, he got lucky. Okay?
Um, yeah, I know he, he was
lucky, and that is a possibility.
But, um, um,
you don't become emperor
by becoming lucky.
Okay? So that's, that doesn't suffice.
Second is, you can say he was brilliant.
Julius Caesar was brilliant.
Right? Um, King Philip
of Macedon was brilliant.
These are all brilliant people. Very few
people say Octavian was a brilliant person.
He didn't have the
charisma of Julius Caesar.
His oration was good, but
no one near as good as,
say, Mark Anthony's, or, or other Romans.
Okay? And he, and it was, it's generally
agreed upon that he was a terrible,
terrible military leader and strategist.
He won, he lost a lot of wars, sorry, he
lost a lot of battles during this conflict.
Okay? So he was not a
great military leader.
So he was not brilliant. I mean,
he was brilliant in his own way.
He was brilliant politically. Um, but he
was not brilliant in the traditional sense.
Okay? The third explanation is,
well, he's just ruthless.
He will do anything for power.
And again, this is true.
There is some truth to this.
But guess what? In the Roman world,
everyone was ruthless.
Right? Mark Anthony was
especially ruthless.
Mark Anthony killed his own wife.
Okay? So that doesn't explain it.
Fourth is, um, the legions, the army.
They remembered Caesar, Julius Caesar.
And now that Octavian is considered
the son of Julius Caesar,
the legions swore loyalty to him.
And that is true. Okay?
But they also swore
loyalty to Mark Anthony.
And you can, you can argue Mark Anthony had a
stronger claim to Caesar's legacy than Octavian.
So that by itself doesn't
explain it either.
Next explanation is Marcus Agrippa.
And Marcus Agrippa is considered,
um, Octavian's partner.
And he was considered a great general.
And it was actually Marcus Agrippa who
was responsible for all
of Octavian's major,
uh, military victories, especially the Battle of
Actium, which, which basically ended the Civil War.
And this again is true.
Marcus Agrippa is a
brilliant military leader.
But so were Cassius,
Decimus. Okay?
There were other brilliant
military leaders.
The other issue is that,
in this ruthless world of Roman politics,
how could Octavian trust Marcus Agrippa?
And why didn't Marcus Agrippa
stay loyal to Octavian?
Okay? Okay.
So these are five explanations.
And there's also some truth to that.
Okay? But I want to offer you
today another explanation.
And the explanation is this.
The death of a Roman emperor,
the death of Caesar,
allowed Octavian to become emperor.
Okay? And here's my argument.
Remember last class, we said that Caesar,
his greatness was in his
myth -making genius.
He created a myth of himself
that he was a man of destiny
who would save the Republic.
But his myth was counter to other myths
that were more dominant in Rome.
Especially the myth of Lucius Brutus.
Right? Lucius Brutus. The man who
created the Republic and killed the king.
And so Caesar had this great myth,
but it was against other dominant myths.
When Caesar was killed,
it made his myth the
dominant myth of Rome.
In fact, it turned his myth into reality.
And it was this new reality
that propelled Octavian into power.
Okay? So
another simple way of saying this is
that it was the love of the Roman people
that propelled Octavian into power.
And we see this in history
all the time, right?
So for example, in Canada,
Doug is from Canada, so am I,
there's a man named Justin Trudeau.
The most incompetent person,
politician you will ever meet.
Okay? But he's prime minister.
And he's been prime minister
for like 10 years, right?
Why? Because his father is Pierre Trudeau,
who is considered one of the most popular
prime ministers in
Canadian history, right?
So it was basically people transferring
their love of Pierre
Trudeau onto their son.
Okay? So that's one example.
The other example, of course,
in America is George W.
Bush, right? Whose father was George H.
W. Bush, who was considered,
you know, a very good president.
Okay? So is it, yeah, Doug?
Just to add in a little bit,
I'm not only naming stuff, but
what's interesting for me here
is you see it almost as a
new origin story, right?
You know, like, you're going
to break together and then
you're just going to make this that's
people that take it around, right?
Yeah, that's, I mean,
this is not an example,
but you could do this in
Russia, like, the revolution.
That's right. And Lenin becomes,
like, the great figure that...
That's right....brought from
his legacy, everybody's.
Yeah....here in China, you know,
still that picture of power and...
That's right....there.
So if you think about it,
politics, political change,
it's really about a mix, right?
If you want to create political change, you have to
change those under, you have to change the myths.
And new governments will create new myths.
Okay? Great.
All right, so that's a basic thesis, okay?
So let me explain it some more, okay?
So let's go back to the death of Julius
Caesar, the assassination of Julius Caesar.
And there were three major assassins,
as I said, Decimus Brutus,
Marcus Brutus, who was considered
the leader, and Cassius.
And they were just the leaders of a huge
conspiracy that involved 60 senators.
That's about 7% of the Roman Senate.
That's a lot of people, man.
Right? 7% of the Roman Senate.
And each of these individuals had
different reason for wanting Caesar dead.
Okay? So Decimus Brutus was considered
Julius Caesar's most competent general.
Okay? And he wanted to
be acknowledged as such.
So you could say that Decimus
Brutus, he was driven by jealousy,
or maybe thought and ambition.
Okay? He wanted to prove that he
was better than Julius Caesar.
So that's Decimus Brutus.
Cassius is a different story.
Cassius fought for Pompey the Great.
And because Cassius was
such a great general,
Julius Caesar showed mercy to him
and forgave him and
made him a general, his own general, okay?
So this is Caesar,
demonstrating his benevolence
and clemency and mercy.
The problem is that in the Roman world,
mercy is not considered a good thing.
Okay? So by showing mercy on Cassius,
Cassius could have interpreted this as
Caesar showing contempt for him.
Caesar didn't really see him as a threat.
Okay? And so Cassius might
have been motivated by
a sense like a desire to win.
A desire for vengeance, right?
Marcus Brutus is the
most interesting person here.
And actually, you know, Shakespeare wrote a
play about Marcus Brutus called Julius Caesar,
okay? But it was really
about Marcus Brutus.
It was trying to explain the
psychology and motivations
of why Marcus Brutus
would want Caesar dead.
Okay? Marcus Brutus did
fight for Pompey the Great.
But he's also the son of Julius
Caesar's favorite mistress,
favorite lover. And so
Julius Caesar made a point
of telling his soldiers,
do not kill this guy in battle.
If you see him, capture
him and send him to me.
And so Marcus Brutus was captured
and Julius Caesar adopted
him basically as a son.
And he basically fast -tracked
Marcus Brutus' career.
And so Marcus Brutus had every
reason to thank Julius Caesar,
right? But instead, Marcus
Brutus becomes the major,
the main conspirator. And
in the play by Shakespeare,
Julius Caesar, the argument that
Shakespeare makes is
Marcus Brutus is driven
by his own sense of virtue.
Okay? Basically vanity.
He believes, or he's told, that
he's named after Lucius Brutus,
the founder of the Republic, and
therefore he has a responsibility to save the
Republic from wannabe tyrants like Caesar.
And that's what drives him.
What Shakespeare doesn't mention though
is what Romans believe is
that Marcus Brutus is the son, the
biological son of Julius Caesar.
Okay? So maybe there was
that interpersonal dynamic
where Marcus Brutus despised Caesar,
okay? All right,
so it's a very complicated situation.
But what unites everyone is
that, is the feeling that
Rome was changing too fast.
Okay? So remember, Julius Caesar,
he did what he did in order to save
the Republic, to restore the Republic.
And so when he had obtained power,
he was making changes that were necessary,
but which changed the
Roman sense of themselves.
Okay? So one example is, he brought
in senators from the provinces.
And these were aristocrats
who spoke perfect Latin,
but because he was from the provinces,
and they were foreigners,
the Roman people were very upset by this.
Okay? That's the first
thing. Second thing is,
Caesar ended corruption in the provinces.
And that goes against the
interests of the nobility, because
one way for you to become rich, as a noble person,
is to go to the provinces and steal a lot of money.
Okay? So Caesar was doing
a lot of things that
were good for the empire
and for the Republic in
the long term, but which
hurt the interests of the senators
and nobility in the short term.
This is what caused the conflict. Okay?
And because Caesar was
so fast, and so effective in his reforms,
it not only sort of
disturbed the nobility,
but also disturbed the people as well,
because Romans were very conservative.
They were not used to all these
changes happening so fast. And so
this is what compelled the
conspirators to act against Caesar.
Okay? But this raises a
very interesting question.
Caesar is a genius.
He's brilliant. How could he not steal?
How could he not see this coming? Right?
How could he not imagine the possibility
that people were conspiring against him?
And the answer, okay, and this is
hard for us to understand today,
but it was unimaginable
that they would conspire to
kill Caesar in the Senate.
Okay? So
there are lots of taboos in Rome.
One major taboo is the
idea of the promerium.
Okay? The promerium just
means the boundary of Rome.
And the idea here is that Rome,
the city of Rome, the physical
geographic space of Rome,
it is sacred and divine.
It is protected by the gods.
And therefore, you are not allowed
to bring weapons into Rome.
Okay? If you're a soldier, you
must come in as a private citizen.
You must come in as a soldier. You are
not allowed to come in as a soldier.
You are not allowed to
commit acts of violence
within the promerium.
Otherwise, the gods will spite you.
The gods will take vengeance against you.
Okay? So that's the first taboo.
Second taboo is this. The Senate
is considered the most sacred
and divine space in the entire,
in all of Rome.
And so no one's allowed to bring weapons.
No one's allowed to commit
violence in the Senate.
Okay? Also,
the Senate's laws are
basically the laws of the gods.
The Senate declared the body of
Julius Caesar to be sacrosanct.
Okay? Meaning divine and sacred.
You are not allowed to touch
the body of Julius Caesar.
Okay? The third thing is
that everyone in the Senate was
personally appointed by Julius Caesar.
So everyone owed their good fortune
to the generosity of Julius Caesar.
Okay? Do you understand? It was just
unimaginable for Julius Caesar to think
that his friends could be
conspiring against him.
Okay? Okay.
Does that make sense so far, guys?
Okay, it was beyond the
imagination of Julius Caesar.
But if this is true, then
something else is true,
which is that Julius Caesar
did not want to become king.
Because being king was the
ultimate taboo in Rome.
Does that make sense? Julius
Caesar could not imagine
that Buddhists would kill him because
he, like all Romans,
believed in these taboos.
And the ultimate taboo was Rome
could never, should never be king.
So he himself did not want to become king.
He was behaving very arrogantly.
He was behaving like a king.
But he did not, but he would
not become king himself.
Because it would go
against the Roman Republic.
It would defy all the taboos
of the Roman Republic.
Okay? And also, before Caesar,
there was also another
dictator named Sulla.
Okay? And this example of
Sulla is, he's a man who
comes to the Roman Empire, kills all
his enemies, and then he retires.
Okay? He could become king,
but he chose to not become king
because to become king would
mean the death of the Republic.
And that's not taboo.
That's a rubicon he refused to cross.
Okay? So we can imagine that Caesar
saw himself as a better Sulla.
Okay? As a more merciful Sulla.
He would not kill his enemies. He
would show generosity to his enemies.
And he would restore the
Republic to its greatness.
He would make the necessary reforms.
And then he would retire and
lead the Republic as it was.
Okay? Okay.
Does that make sense? All right. So,
it was unimaginable for Caesar to think
that he would be killed. And
also, what's interesting is,
what do you think
happened to these three individuals
after they killed Caesar?
Right? They killed Caesar because
they feared Caesar would become king.
But, after they killed Caesar,
what they recognized is
they could only kill Caesar
because Caesar did not
want to become king.
Right? Otherwise, Caesar would
surround himself with party guards.
Otherwise, Caesar would not make
himself available to his enemies.
So, upon the death of
Caesar, all his enemies,
Decimus, Marcus, and Caesar, all
of them, all of them, and Cassius,
realized they were in the wrong.
But not only that, but
the very attitude of the
people of Rome changed.
Right? While Caesar was alive,
the Roman people were very
skeptical towards Caesar
because they feared that
he would become king.
Right? They loved Caesar, but they were
afraid that Caesar was too ambitious.
Right? But, upon the death of Caesar,
the Roman people felt
tremendous guilt for doubting
Caesar. Does that make sense?
Right? Because it was their doubt that
allowed the conspirators to kill Caesar.
If all they did was believe in Caesar,
if they believed in Caesar's myth that
he was here as a man of destiny
to restore the Republic,
and that's all he cared about,
he didn't want to become king,
then Caesar would still be alive.
Right? And to compound the guilt,
Caesar showered the people
with generosity upon his death.
Okay? So,
you can see how the death of
Caesar creates this new reality
where people now recognize Caesar
did not want to become king.
All he wanted to do was save the Republic.
And people are now,
they're sort of paralyzed
by their guilt.
All right? So, the
evidence for this is this.
While Decimus Brutus was
being attacked by Mark Anthony
and the later Bartholomew,
Cassius told Marcus Brutus,
hey, maybe we should
come to this guy's aid.
He's our ally. If he falls, they're
going to come after us next.
And Marcus Brutus did nothing.
He refused to act.
All right? And the reason
why is he could not act.
All right? He killed Julius Caesar
because Julius Caesar was too ambitious.
But if Marcus Brutus were to
move his army against Rome,
then Marcus Brutus is the ambitious one.
He's the one who wants to become king.
Right? Therefore,
Marcus Brutus and
Cassius could only wait for their deaths.
Because they feared the case.
They believed that Caesar
wanted to become king.
But the king wasn't true.
It couldn't be true. And therefore,
they committed wrong against
Rome by killing Caesar.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So this explains his enemies.
How about Mark Anthony? Okay.
So, Mark Anthony had a different problem.
Mark Anthony loved Caesar so much, he
wanted to continue Caesar's legacy.
And Mark Anthony sort of
felt betrayed by Caesar.
When Caesar named Octavian to be
the heir and not Mark Anthony.
Okay? And so, what does
Mark Anthony want to do now?
Well, he wants to prove
that Caesar's wrong.
Mark Anthony wants to prove that
he is the rightful heir of Caesar.
And to prove so, he will
continue his legacy.
Okay? So, Mark Anthony
started to do things
that
were against his own personal self -interest and
which ultimately led to his self -destruction.
The first thing that he did was
he marched against the Parthians.
The Parthians are Rome's last great enemy.
Okay? Rome destroyed Carthage.
Rome destroyed the Greeks. But
the Parthians still had an
empire to the east of Rome.
And Romans,
Roman generals failed to conquer Rome.
And Rome decided to make
inroads against Parthia.
And in fact, Julius Caesar,
he wanted to basically end
his life by invading Parthia.
Okay? So, Julius Caesar's plan before
his death was to attack Parthia,
conquer it, then sweep back
to Europe and conquer Germany.
Okay? Basically conquer the whole world to
prove he's better than Alexander the Great.
So, Mark Anthony decides that
this is how he will prove he
is Caesar's rightful heir.
By finishing Caesar's
legacy against the Parthians. Okay?
The problem is Romans are not
good at war against the Parthians
and the Persians. Okay? Because
the Romans are infantry focused
and the Parthians and
the Persians are cavalry
focused. Right? They have horses. So,
Mark Anthony goes over to Parthia
and he gets his ass kicked.
All right? He gets his ass kicked.
He's not Julius Caesar. He's
not the heir to Julius Caesar.
And he falls into a major depression.
He basically becomes a drunk.
Okay? That's his first major mistake.
Second major mistake he makes is
he falls in love with Cleopatra.
Cleopatra is the queen of Egypt, but
much more importantly, she is
the mistress of Julius Caesar.
In fact, rumors were that
upon his retirement, Julius Caesar
would bring back the queen of Egypt,
bring Cleopatra to Rome, and they
would live happily ever after.
Okay? That's the rumor.
So, Mark Anthony goes over to Egypt
and he becomes the lover to Cleopatra.
Okay? Because he's trying
to be Julius Caesar now.
And this is a problem
because to marry Cleopatra,
he has to divorce his wife, who
happens to be the sister of Octavian.
Okay? So, this causes a personal
rift between Octavian and Cleopatra.
And the third thing
that he does, which is
what causes his demise,
is he names in his will, okay?
He names in his will that
his children of Cleopatra will become
the heirs to the Roman East.
All the property, all that land that
Mark Anthony controls will
be given to his children,
will become his property. And so, he's the
only one who can give that land to Cleopatra. They're foreign citizens.
And also, Mark Anthony does
not have the authority to give
that land out to his children.
Only the Senate has the
authority. Okay? So,
Octavian uses the will as a
pretext to attack Mark Anthony.
And he's heavily supported
by the Roman people.
Okay? So, Mark Anthony, because
he's trying so hard to escape
the shadow of Julius Caesar,
because he's trying so hard to
prove he is the king of Egypt.
He's the legitimate heir to Julius Caesar.
He basically self -destructs.
He didn't have to do
any of this, but he did.
And by doing all this, it
guarantees his destruction.
Okay? So, Mark Anthony
basically self -destructs.
Let's look at Lepidus.
Okay? Lepidus, he is an extremely
effective administrator,
but he is not as charismatic
and as blunt as Julius Caesar.
And Lepidus basically shied away.
Okay? He didn't have the confidence to
challenge Octavian for the ultimate power.
And seeing this lack of
confidence and this insecurity,
his soldiers basically
went off to join Octavian.
Okay? And a lot of soldiers did that.
A lot of soldiers that were fighting for the
enemy's side would just jump ship because
Octavian is the heir of Julius Caesar.
Okay? He is the new Julius Caesar.
And they all worship
Julius Caesar. All right?
Now, let's look at the other
side. Let's look at Octavian.
Why did Octavian succeed so much?
Again, he became partners with Marcus Agrippa,
who was a much better general than him.
But Octavian, again,
he was not a blunt man.
He was not charismatic. He
was not a great general.
But he believed himself to
be the heir to Julius Caesar.
For whatever reason, Julius
Caesar believed in him.
And therefore, he had
a responsibility to...
To finish the legacy of his father,
which is to restore the Roman Republic.
And that meant he had to do whatever
sacrifice was necessary in order to do so.
Okay? So,
the difference between Octavian and
the others was he acted.
He wasn't very successful,
but he was willing to act,
whereas Marcus Brutus
was not willing to act.
And when you act, sometimes
you will succeed. Okay? And
only a few successes will allow
you to become the emperor of Rome.
He was driven by the fact
that he believed himself to
be the heir of Julius Caesar.
He was a son of Julius Caesar.
Julius Caesar believed in him.
Therefore, he had his responsibility
to restore the Republic.
And that's why he trusted Marcus Agrippa.
Okay? And that's why
Marcus Agrippa trusted him.
They were all fighting for
the legacy of Julius Caesar.
And that's why ultimately the Roman people
allowed Octavian to amass so much power.
Right? So, remember,
the Roman people have
been taught to fear kings.
But, over time, Octavian
was in power for 40 years.
Okay? Augustus Caesar was
in power for 40 years.
Over time, he became even
more powerful than a king.
This is what he did. He
amassed all powers to himself.
After he conquered Egypt,
he made Egypt into his
own personal property.
Okay? This was his private estate.
He used all the money from Egypt.
And again, remember, Egypt is right
now, and for the longest time,
the wealthiest country in
the world at this time.
Okay? They have so much wealth.
He used his money in order
to have his own army.
Before, the Roman army
was loyal to the Senate.
Now, because it was Octavian himself
who personally paid every
soldier in the army, which
is now a professional army,
they're now loyal to the emperor.
Okay? He took Gaul, which was,
you know, which was land that
Julius Caesar basically
depopulated with genocide,
and he gave the land to his veterans.
Okay? So, basically, he
made Gaul his own land.
And he made the entire army
loyal to him personally.
So, he now has the power of God.
The Roman people allowed him to
do that because they believed
that, like, Octavian,
sorry, like Julius Caesar,
Octavian was driven by
his sense of mission,
his desire to save and
restore the Roman Republic.
But ultimately, because
they believed him too much,
Augustus Caesar would
destroy the Republic and
concentrate all power in his hands.
Okay? Does that make sense?
All right. Any questions? Yeah?
Why did Julius Caesar name Octavian?
Okay, that's a great question. Okay.
So, why did Julius Caesar name Octavian
as the hero and not Mark Antony?
Okay. So,
Octavian is the great nephew
of King Charles the Great.
And he was the great
nephew of Julius Caesar.
So, Octavian was Julius
Caesar's sister's grandson.
And so, Octavian basically
grew up with Julius Caesar.
Like, they knew each other very well.
But as Echo says,
Mark Antony is the man
who is most loyal to Caesar.
Okay? The most trusted
lieutenant of Caesar.
Why didn't Caesar trust him?
And the answer is, Caesar, as a
genius, he doesn't care about loyalty.
He cares about talent.
He cares about ability.
And Mark Antony was a notorious hothead.
He had a violent temper. He was a drunk.
Okay? I mean, he just had, like,
terrible, terrible personal qualities.
So, an example of this is, while
Caesar was a genius,
he was off campaigning against Pompey.
He put Mark Antony in charge of Rome.
And all Mark Antony did
was piss everyone off.
He got into fights with the
Senate. He was so bad that
Caesar had no choice but to
replace him with Lepidus.
Okay? So, Mark Antony
was a notorious hothead.
He was emotionally unstable.
He was emotionally volatile.
And so, Caesar didn't really trust him.
Even though Mark Antony would
give his life for Caesar.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So, Octavian was considered much more
competent, much more level -headed.
And Caesar was correct in his assessment.
Because Octavian was a brilliant
political manipulator.
Okay? Being an emperor is very hard.
He was emperor for 40 years.
So, he had to balance all these
different political factions within Rome.
Okay? So, great question, Eko.
Okay, any more questions? Or comments?
About this argument?
Is all clear?
Audience Member 7
Audience Member 8 Audience
Member 9
Audience Member 10 Audience Member 11
Audience Member 12
Yeah. That's right.
That's right. Yeah, I mean it was
very hard to kill Caesar, okay?
So they were in the Senate. There
were six conspirators, okay?
They all brought knives. They were, they hit
the knives, the daggers in the toga, okay?
They were all supposed to
like lunge Caesar together.
So but when you...
But only five senators,
only five senators actually
physically attacked Caesar.
Everyone else just stood paralyzed
because as you said, it was taboo.
It was the ultimate taboo to
commit violence in the Senate.
So they were all paralyzed by this fear even
though they had this intense hatred of Caesar,
okay? They had for months imagined how
they would go about killing Caesar.
They had this plan meticulously.
But when it came to actually
acting it out, they couldn't do it.
Only five actually managed
to take out their dagger
and stab Caesar.
In fact, the first person who
attacked Caesar stood behind Caesar
while Caesar was talking to the Senate
and he was shaking, okay?
And he only managed to like
pinprick Caesar in the back, okay?
This is where we get the
idea of backstabbing from.
So and Caesar didn't really notice.
He was like, hey, what are you doing, man?
Okay? Caesar wasn't really hurt by this.
Even Caesar, even though he was
being attacked, could not imagine
that anyone would be so bold
enough to break all these taboos
and attack him, okay?
So I mean,
it was an incredible act that
forever changed Roman history, all right?
It was just unimaginable that anyone
could attack anyone in the Senate,
like physically, okay?
Especially the dictator,
Julius Caesar. He was like,
hey, what are you doing? And
yet you
got to fight against the
great pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie
pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie
pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie
pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie
pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie pie They're generals,
they're used to killing people.
So it wasn't fear of death,
it was just fear of breaking this
ultimate taboo of this Roman Senate.
Okay, so thanks for that, Doug.
Any more questions before I finish?
Okay, so,
Octavian Augustus Caesar
was considered the first
and the greatest emperor
of the Roman Empire.
And like Julius Caesar, he did
not consider himself the emperor,
he considered himself like first citizen,
okay, or the first man in the Senate.
And his responsibility was to
ensure the eternal prosperity
and stability of the Roman Republic.
And so, towards his old age,
he had to consider the public, sorry, he had to
consider the public as a problem of succession,
right? He was a great emperor, but
the second emperor had
to be great as well.
And so, his solution was this.
His solution would be, he would adopt
the most competent relative
that he had to be emperor.
And he would create this new system
where emperors would be adopted, okay?
So the best man in Rome would always
be adopted into the imperial throne.
And Augustus Caesar had the perfect man.
His name was Germanicus. Germanicus
was very much like Julius Caesar.
Brilliant speaker,
loved by his soldiers. The problem
was that he was too young, okay?
Germanicus was too young,
so he needed a transition.
And so, he appointed
his stepson, Tiberius,
who was pretty old at this point,
okay, to be the transition.
Tiberius was not charismatic,
he was not very popular,
but he was competent, he was
a competent administrator.
He'd be emperor for like five to 10 years,
and then when Germanicus came of age,
then Germanicus would inherit the throne.
And he'd be a good emperor,
and as a good emperor,
you would then be able
to find someone else
who had good talent, and you would
appoint him the next emperor.
If you had this system, this
system could go on forever.
Okay? And so, this is a good system.
The problem was Tiberius, okay?
Tiberius didn't like the idea that
he could not appoint his successor,
okay? So, what did he do?
Well, he killed Germanicus.
But not only did he kill Germanicus,
he killed basically all
of Germanicus's family,
okay? And not only did he kill Germanicus,
did he kill Germanicus's family,
but he killed, well, he
killed a lot of people, okay?
And then he adopted
someone named Caligula,
who was Germanicus's youngest son,
to be the emperor.
And Caligula was a
notoriously bad emperor,
okay? So, this system
broke down very quickly.
Even though Augustus Caesar,
his intention was to continue
the legacy of Julius Caesar
and create an eternal prosperity
for the Roman Republic,
okay? And by the time you got to Tiberius,
the system collapsed. And
you could make the argument that
Tiberius marked the death
of the Roman Empire,
okay? The Roman Empire would continue
for another, like, 300 years, but
it was basically dead, okay?
Meaning that it was wracked
by all these internal revolts,
internal tensions. And so, the Roman Empire
was dead. And it was only because of its size
and inertia that it was able
to continue for so long, okay?
So, next class,
we'll finish Rome by discussing
the Roman legacy, okay?
What is Rome's contribution
to Western civilization?
And this will mainly have to do
with the legacy of Augustus Caesar,
right? Any questions?
Okay, all right, great.
So, we will continue, we'll
finish with Rome next class,
and then we'll start Egypt, okay?
And Egypt will be a lot of fun.