Okay, so today we start
Greek civilization.
And it is incredible what
Greek civilization is.
It is the greatest, most creative,
most significant civilization
ever in human history.
The Greeks really created
Western civilization.
And not only were the Greeks
the greatest civilization,
there's really not been a
second great civilization.
So let's think about how
incredible the Greeks were.
If you look at literature,
the Greeks basically created
literature with Homer.
Homer wrote two books called the Iliad
and the Odyssey.
And he wrote these books
about 3,000 years ago.
Now last year I taught the
great books to the students.
And we read many books.
And by far their favorite
book was the Iliad.
Okay, so think about this, how a Greek writer
writing 3,000 years ago for a Greek audience,
his book still resonates, still impresses,
and still impresses
students in China today.
Okay, so that's Homer.
Then you have Plato, philosophy, Plato.
And even today, you have Plato. Just, even
today, there are many who considered Plato
the greatest philosopher, who ever lived,
there are many people
who read, The Republic,
by Plato, and they, and
they, say, it, transforms,
their, lives, okay, it, makes, them, think,
very, differently, about, the, world,
then, you, have, in,
history, a, man, named,,,,
If, you, are, a, military,
leader, today, you, read,,,
read Thucydides, okay?
There are still many
generals today in America,
in Russia, in Europe, who
believe reading Thucydides
will help them win wars.
Okay, so not only the
Greeks create civilization,
but their works, their books,
are still widely read today,
and considered amazing,
okay? So now the question I have is,
how did this happen?
How were the Greeks able to create
humanity's greatest civilization?
In really about 200 years, okay?
They really were not
dominant for a long time.
They really created all these works
in about 200 years altogether.
So how is this possible?
Okay, so let's go back
to the Greek history.
Let's go back to the last class. We talked
about the Bronze Age collapse, right?
And we talked about
how, in about 1200 BCE,
Greece was united in a place
called Mycenaean Greece,
okay? So basically the Mycenaeans controlled
Greece, and Greece was the monarchy.
And it was no different from
any other place in the world.
At this point, 1200 BCE, the
world was basically the same.
Okay? And then the society collapsed,
and the world was the same.
because of the Bronze Age collapse.
And three things happened, okay?
First of all, centralization.
The idea that you had a unified society,
it went away, okay? So Greece
became chaotic and decentralized.
That's the first thing that
happened. Same thing that
happened is Greece became illiterate.
So the Greeks lost the
ability to read and write.
We call this the Dark Ages.
So from about 1000 to about 600 BCE,
but for 400 years, the Greeks basically
lost the ability to read and write.
We call this the Dark Ages because
we don't have any books or
writing from that period.
It's completely dark to us, okay?
So the second thing that happened,
the Greeks became illiterate.
The third thing that happened
is the Greeks became poor.
Okay, so before the Greeks traded with
the world, it was very prosperous,
and then, because of
the Bronze Age collapse,
it started to become more isolated, and
it became a lot poorer, okay, so
these are the three major consequences
of the Bronze Age collapse in
Greece, it became decentralized,
it became illiterate, it became poor, and
the amazing thing is,
it's because of these three things
that Greece became the most
creative civilization,
civilization in the world
Okay, so remember this it is because
of the destruction of old Greece It's
because Greece became chaotic
illiterate and poor that Greece
eventually became The most civilized
the greatest civilization in the world.
Okay, so let me explain how this happened
Okay, so there are three major reasons
Why Greek civilization became dominant?
The first reason is the polis
the polis It's hard
for us to translate it.
We usually translate it as city -state.
Okay, a City state
And this is where we get the
word politics, but really
What it means is community
Community And
the idea of the polis is a
community of people who discuss
politics together
How how to best run the town?
Okay, and because
of this chaos there were thousands
of policies around Greece
Of about a thousand people each.
Okay, so it's a very small community and
This became the main political
structure of Greek society.
Okay, so the polis is one factor
second factor that happened is the
alphabet So
after the Greeks became illiterate
they had to relearn literacy Okay,
they had to relearn how to
read and write in the process.
They adopted a new writing
system called the alphabet
Okay, which forever transformed a society
The last thing is Homer
Homer was a poet who
introduced to the Greek a new
way of imagining the world Okay
So, these are the three major factors that
led to the rise of Greek civilization,
and if you look at each factor
Okay, so the polis, was a political
revolution revolution
revolution revolution revolution
revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution with each other. And
Homer was really an
intellectual revolution.
It forever transformed how Greeks saw and
imagined the world around them.
Okay? So
let's go over each
of these revolutions one by one.
Okay? So, the polis.
There were three things about the polis
that allowed for innovation
and creativity in Greece.
Okay? The first thing about
the polis was competition.
Okay? These polises were all spread out
and they were all competing
against each other for resources.
They were constantly at war
with each other and that
allowed for massive innovation.
Okay? And again, remember, there's
no centralized authority now.
Okay? So, there's no centralized authority
now. There's no centralized authority now. That's the first thing.
Second thing is diversity.
So, if you look at a map of Greece,
Greece has very diverse geography.
Okay? It has farmland, it has mountains,
it has plains, it has coastal land.
Okay? And depending on where
you were geographically in Greece,
you develop a different equation.
Okay? So, you have a map of Greece, you
have a map of Greece, you have a map of Greece, you have a map of Greece, you have the economy and culture and society
based on the geography. Okay?
Does that make sense? And
so, you add on diversity.
And the last factor was
the idea of democracy.
Okay? So, Greek civilization
introduced the idea of democracy or
the modern sense of democracy to us.
And the reason why is, at this
time, Greece was very poor.
Okay? If you're very poor Or you
need everyone to participate
and work hard,
especially in battles
against other polices.
So the rule was, you
could be rich or poor,
but if you fought for us,
you had the right to speak.
You could be the leader of this polis,
and you had the right to speak, but you
could be the poorest person in this polis,
and you still had the
right to speak because
everyone had a responsibility
to defend the polis.
So this introduced the idea of democracy.
And what this meant was that
everyone basically had to
participate politically.
So you could be a farmer, but you still
had to think about the political life,
and you still had a responsibility
to speak up in front of your peers.
And this is where we get
the idea of polis from.
And this was a major driver
of innovation in Greece.
So does this make sense, guys, the polis?
Any questions so far? We might move on.
So one of the major
innovations of the polis
was the introduction of the
alphabet into Greek society.
So let me explain the
development of writing systems
over time to you.
And this is going to be a bit complicated,
so make sure you're following along.
If I'm saying something unclear to you, make
sure you interrupt and ask me questions.
So writing was first developed in Europe,
in Western society, in
Egypt and in Samaria.
And they did so to support the development
of the alphabet in the Middle Ages.
to solve an economic problem. So
these societies were very
wealthy, and they needed people,
farmers, to help them build roads and
build irrigation networks
and build temples.
To do so, I need to pay these workers.
So writing system became a contract.
So basically, the writing system,
at first, was a pictogram, a pictograph,
that served the function of a contract.
So for example, if I do this,
okay, two people, okay?
So what this is saying
is, if you work for me,
I promise to give two
people two bushels of wheat,
okay? And so when you
have this, you can then
give it to me, and I have
to give you the wheat.
Does that make sense? So it first started
out, I have to give you the wheat.
So it started out as pictograms.
And what they recognized is, hey,
we can just have this as symbols.
So maybe just two faces and then two Vs.
And this could represent the same thing.
Because everyone understood what it meant.
So you went to symbolism.
That's the next step.
But then what they recognized is,
hey, these symbols can
also represent ideas.
Okay, so here's an example.
All right, so you have maybe a sun
and a moon, right?
Okay, sun and moon. They
can represent the sun
and the moon, but if you
put them together, okay,
sun and the moon, you
get the concept of day,
right?
So now you have a concept,
an idea, day, okay?
We call this an ideogram.
And guess what, guys? Chinese
is an ideogramic term.
It's a language. Does that make sense?
Okay, and then as they
continued developing writing,
they recognized that, you know what?
It would be a lot easier for
us to communicate if these
ideograms represented syllables
and sounds instead.
Okay? So rather than representing ideas,
let's get them to represent sounds.
So for example, this is sun, right?
And this is moon. Well,
now if we do this,
it becomes moon, sun, right?
Which is the English word for
monsoon, which means storm.
Okay? So
now this tells us to read it as monsoon.
Okay? And then
the final recognition is, guess what?
We can actually just have
the sound represent a consonant,
okay? The simplest sound.
And this would be an
M, this would be an S.
So if I write something like
this, it now becomes SM,
or sum. Okay?
And we call this the alphabet.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So this is the development of writing.
And the reason why we do this is,
with each innovation,
with each development,
we're allowed more flexibility in our
language to communicate our ideas.
Does that make sense, guys?
Okay? So now with the alphabet,
something remarkable has happened.
Before these different stages
of writing required a professional class
of people to manage the writing system.
Okay? We call these scribes, right?
Scribes. The reason why is that
writing is not speaking.
Speaking is one language, but
writing is a different language.
This is true for Chinese, right?
Well, it was true back then as well.
So to learn to read and write,
you had to have professional
scribes to do so,
because it was such a complicated task.
Okay? Does that make sense?
All right? But
now with the alphabet,
writing can become speaking.
And this marked an incredible revolution
in human thought, in
the capacity to think.
Okay? So let me explain why.
Before the invention of writing,
we lived in an oral culture.
Okay? An oral culture
means we don't write,
we just speak to each other. All right?
Now we live in a writing
culture, a literary culture,
where we don't actually speak to each
other, we mainly just write to each other.
Okay? So mainly through email or texting.
Okay? Now, there are certain advantages
to both cultures.
With oral culture, the
first major advantage is
it's very emotional.
Okay? When I'm speaking to you,
I'm trying to get you excited.
I'm trying to get you to pay attention. So I'm
trying to think about how to rouse your emotions.
So oral culture, it's
very emotional focus.
That's the first major advantage.
Second major advantage
is it's very innovative
and open. And what this means is
I can create words when I speak.
Right? I can say, Okay?
That means nothing.
Okay? But I can create it and when we're
speaking, you can figure out what I mean.
So when I'm speaking, I can
create all these different words.
So there's room for innovation
and imagination in oral culture.
Does that make sense? Okay?
The third thing is
the thing about oral culture is it forces
everyone to have a really strong memory.
The reason why is when I speak,
I have to remember my speech.
Right? And then you have to remember my
speech in order to respond to my speech.
And these speeches go on
for like hours and hours.
So back then, during oral culture,
everyone had a photographic memory.
Okay? Does that make sense? So back then,
they were a lot smarter than we are today.
And it's the same as, remember,
during the hunter -gatherer stage, right?
When we're out in the
field, guess what, guys?
They were a lot stronger, faster,
and healthier than we are today.
Because today, all we do is sit around.
Right? Does that make sense? So back
then, they were a lot smarter than us.
So these are the three major
advantages of oral culture.
It's a very emotional
language. It's very innovative.
And it forces you to have
a really strong memory.
Okay? But
there's also a lot of advantages to writing
culture as well that oral culture doesn't have.
So for example, the first major advantage is
rather than emotional, it has to be logical.
Right? It has to make sense by itself.
I can't trick you with rhetoric.
All right? I have to use reason and
logic to persuade you because
you can read it at your own time.
Okay? So that's the first major advantage.
Second major advantage
is it's very disciplined.
Okay? Meaning, okay,
I can't make up words.
I have to use words we agree on.
Okay? The third major advantage is
even though it decreases my memory,
it stores up brain space for me to
think deeply about the argument,
for me to reflect on your argument
and find logical problems
in your argument. Okay?
Does that make sense?
All right? So we are basically,
before they were in oral culture,
and that has its advantages.
Now we are in a literary culture
and we've lost the oral culture.
But when the Greeks
discovered the alphabet,
what happened was they combined
the advantages of both cultures.
Okay? They were, most of the
time, they were speaking,
they were living in oral culture, but
they also had the opportunity
to write down their thoughts.
Which allowed them the advantages
of the literary culture.
To have a more disciplined,
focused, logical mind.
Okay? Does that make sense? And
this marked an incredible revolution in
the capacity for human beings to think.
Okay? Any questions so far? Okay?
This is a very complicated concept. I
want to make sure you're following along.
Okay? Any questions
about what I just said?
Before I move on? All right.
Now, let's move on to Homer.
Okay? Homer. So,
we discussed the polis and how
it is a new political structure
which allows for freedom and democracy.
We discussed the alphabet, which
marks a revolution in
our capacity to think.
Okay? Now it comes along, Homer.
And Homer is, is a man who is a poet.
And back then, there were many poets
who went around and told stories
about the world. Okay?
Legends, mythologies.
And the very best poets
are usually hired by kings.
Okay? Rich people. Because kings
need poets to solve three problems.
Okay? Kings usually hire
poets to solve three problems.
The first problem is
legitimate authority.
Okay? What this means is,
you have to answer the question
if you're king, why are you king?
Now, we know that most kings get power
by killing a lot of people.
Okay? That's how they become king.
By fighting wars and by winning wars.
So, when they become king, they
need to clean up their image.
Okay? They need to
legitimize their authority.
So, what they tell people is usually what?
Why am I king? Why?
Because I, I,
I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
I, I, I,
I, I,
I, Because there's a poet who
sings a beautiful song about me.
And this song can only come
from divine inspiration,
right?
The poet is a
vessel for divine messages,
right? Does that make sense?
This poem, this song is
so beautiful, it must be divine.
And if this divine song is saying,
I am born of a god,
the gods want me to become king,
then I must be divine myself.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So it's the first major function
of poets in the society,
to legitimize authority.
Second function is to
create a cultural identity.
So, you know, in China you have
books like San Guanyin, okay?
Romans of Three Kingdoms.
You have the Bible. All
these literary works,
the function is to create a common
culture, a cultural identity,
okay? It tells us what
it means to be Chinese.
Does that make sense? Because
then you unify the people
who then obey the king,
who unifies them, right?
That's the second function. The third function
is the idea of cultural differentiation.
To know who you are, you must
also know who you are not.
We're Chinese, so therefore
we are not Japanese.
We're not Korean. We're not American.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So most literary works
that we have
were sponsored by leaders, kings,
to solve these three problems, okay?
So in the future we will read the Iliad,
which is what the Romans had.
We'll read the Bible, okay?
In China you have like the
Romans of the Three Kingdoms.
And all these literary works were
designed to serve the powers
that exist at that time, okay?
Does that make sense?
The problem with Homer is
when he was around, and
we don't know actually
when he was alive, maybe
about 800 to 600 BC,
okay? Around then. We
don't actually know, okay?
But there was no king.
There was no one to pay him.
Therefore he could only make his living
by appealing to the
people around him, okay?
He had to appeal to ordinary people.
And so the question then
is, if you're a poet,
how do you get ordinary people,
who are poor, to pay you money?
Why would they want to pay you
to sing songs for them, okay?
Well, there are three reasons.
The first is just entertainment.
Today we listen to songs, we go to movies.
Well, back then, their entertainment,
their source of entertainment
was to pay people like Homer
to sing songs to them, okay?
That was what they thought was fun to do.
That was their source of entertainment.
Second reason is education.
So remember that back
then Greece was poor.
They didn't have schools. But
because of the Polish system,
they had to speak in front of their peers.
So how did you learn to speak well?
Well, you do so by imitating people
who do speak well, who
are usually poets, right?
So when you listen to Homer speak and
give speeches, you can imitate him and
copy what he does to make your own
speech in front of the people around you.
In front of your peers, okay?
So second reason is educational.
Basically, Homer was a
teacher as well as a poet,
okay?
And the third reason, and
what made Homer special,
is what we call edification. Edification.
Edification means to be a better you,
to be a higher you, okay?
And edification, the way that
Homer accomplished edification
is by changing the way
that you saw the world around you,
the way you felt about the world,
the way you imagined the world, okay?
So let me explain how he did so.
But first of all, before I continue, are
there any questions about this so far?
Anything you are not clear about?
Anything I've said that you are not
clear about or you're confused by?
Before I continue. Okay,
so Homer was a poet who told stories.
And the most popular story at that time
was something called the Trojan War.
So the main story of the
Trojan War is this, okay?
So there was a Greek
goddess named Nemesis.
And Nemesis likes to create problems.
She's always thinking of ways to get
the gods to fight against each other.
So one day she creates this apple.
It's a golden apple. And
the golden apple says,
to the most beautiful
goddess in the world, okay?
It doesn't say who, it just says, to
the most beautiful goddess in the world.
And then she just puts it on Mount
Olympus for the gods to find.
Three goddesses find this apple,
and they fight over it, okay?
The first goddess is Hera, who
is the queen god, okay?
Second goddess is Athena,
who is the goddess of wisdom.
And the third goddess is Aphrodite,
who is the goddess of love.
They're fighting over
this apple all the time.
And they're creating a huge ruckus.
And so the king god, Zeus,
gets tired of all their fighting, and
he finds a human stupid
enough to be the judge, okay?
So this human, his name is Paris,
his job is to pick who is
the most beautiful goddess
in the universe, okay? Is it going to
be Hera, Athena, or Aphrodite, okay?
And again, he's stupid enough to want
to piss off two goddesses, right?
So when he's making his decision,
all the goddesses try to bribe Paris.
Paris says to Paris, Paris,
if you pick me, I will
give you your own kingdom.
I will make you king of the world.
Paris is like, oh, that's pretty good.
Athena says to Paris,
I will make you the
wisest man in the world.
I will give you all the
knowledge of the world.
And Paris is like, oh, that's pretty good.
And then Aphrodite says, hey,
I will give you the most beautiful
woman in the world to marry.
And then Paris is like, I want that, okay?
And so, Paris, but
the problem is, the most beautiful
woman in the world is Helen,
queen of Sparta.
She's a Greek who's
married to a Greek king.
Paris steals Helen,
takes her back to Troy,
and then the Greeks get angry,
and they raise this huge army.
And for 10 years, they attack Troy,
which is a walled city, okay?
And the war ends when a Greek
general named Odysseus,
he comes up with this plan.
He has this idea called
the wooden horse, okay?
So the Greeks pretend they give up.
They're going to go home
because they're homesick.
And as a present to the Trojans,
they leave behind a wooden horse. The
Trojans take the wooden horse into the city.
At night, the Greeks jump
out of the wooden horse,
open the gates, and the
Trojans are slaughtered, okay?
And this is the story of the Trojan War.
And the Greeks love this story,
because it's really the
Greeks being heroes, right?
The Greeks have this great victory.
People love to win battles. What's
amazing about Homer's story,
okay? It's called the Iliad, and
we'll read this next semester.
But there are three things that
Homer does in the Iliad
that's really never
been done before, okay?
And so, with the Iliad, we have
the invention of literature.
The first thing,
that Homer does is,
rather than telling the
story from the Greek side,
he tells the story from both
the Greek and Trojan side.
In fact, when you read the
Iliad, you'll discover that
the Trojans are actually more heroic,
more courageous, and more
brave than the Greeks.
Okay? That's pretty amazing.
And by switching perspectives,
a new idea comes into being
that never really existed before.
And we call this idea empathy. Okay?
Empathy. The ability to see the world
from the perspective of other people.
And before, in human civilization,
this didn't really exist before, okay?
But Homer creates this for the Iliad.
The second thing that
is new and
unique to the Iliad is human psychology.
So, for the first time,
Homer discusses what motivates
the characters in the Iliad,
okay? Why are you fighting this war?
And so, the story is
between two individuals,
Achilles and King Priam.
Okay? So, Achilles is the greatest warrior
of the Greeks.
Priam is the king of the Trojans.
And they hate each other, okay?
Because they're enemies.
Achilles is trying to kill Priam.
Priam is trying to defend
his family and his home.
So, the Iliad starts like this.
Achilles, at the beginning,
gets in a fight with Agamemnon, who
is the king of the Greeks, okay?
They get in a fight. And
they curse each other.
And Achilles says,
You're a dog, Agamemnon.
I'm never going to fight for you again.
And Agamemnon, the king,
says, I don't need you, man.
So, Achilles refuses to fight, okay?
The problem is, Achilles
is the greatest warrior
of the Greeks. And the Trojans,
led by Hector, who is a son of Priam,
he sees an opportunity because
Achilles refuses to fight.
And Hector leads the
Trojan army out of Troy.
And they're destroying the Greeks.
And the Trojans are about
to crush the Greek army.
So, the Greek generals say to Agamemnon,
Could you please beg Achilles
to return to the battlefield?
And they go and they talk to Achilles.
And Achilles basically says, Screw off.
I'm not helping you
guys, okay? His friend,
Patroclus, okay?
Patroclus is basically
like his younger brother.
He feels sorry for the Greeks,
so he pretends to be Achilles
and goes off to battle against Hector.
Hector kills Patroclus and
this angers Achilles, okay?
Achilles is so angry that he jumps
into the battle and he kills Hector.
Once he kills Hector, he does
something very odd, okay?
Usually, when you kill
someone's body, you return
that body to your enemy for a ransom.
Because the belief back then is,
only if you bury your dead can
the dead find peace in
the afterworld, okay?
But Achilles is so angry at Hector that
he's torturing Hector's body, which
is torturing Priam.
But even after Achilles does this,
he can't sleep and
he feels tremendous sadness, even though
he's avenged the death of Patroclus.
And the reason why is, in
his heart, Achilles knows
he was the one responsible
for killing Patroclus, right?
Because if he didn't get into the
stupid fight with Agamemnon, and
if he did not refuse the Greeks when they
requested help, then Patroclus wouldn't have died.
So it's because Achilles
was so stubborn and so proud
that his friend Patroclus died.
So he feels tremendous guilt
for what happened.
And his guilt turns into an
intense hatred for Hector.
That's why he's torturing Hector's body.
Then what happens is Priam, King Priam,
who can't sleep either because
his son is being tortured, okay?
His son is dead, but his soul is
still being tortured by Achilles.
He sneaks into Achilles' tent, okay?
And he's right behind Achilles while
Achilles is talking to his generals.
And at this point, remember,
Achilles doesn't see him.
He's standing behind Achilles. He can
take his knife and stab Achilles' head.
He can stab Achilles' neck, right?
And that's what most people would do.
But Priam doesn't do that.
Priam instead kneels down and
kisses the hand of Achilles,
which forces Achilles
to be in awe of this king
who has knelt down before him.
And he admires Priam's courage
and love for his son so much
that he feels tremendous shame and
remorse for what he's done to Hector.
And he returns Hector's body
to Priam as compensation.
And that's how the Iliad ends, okay?
The main message of the Iliad is it's
not war that creates civilization.
It is love that creates civilization.
It is Priam's love for Hector
that gives him the courage
to defeat Achilles,
in battle.
And in this defeat, Achilles
becomes a better person
because he's able to forgive himself and
he's able to do what is right and just
and return Hector to his father, okay?
That's the Iliad. As you can imagine,
this is extremely complicated psychology.
And it forces you to think deeply
about who we are as humans, okay?
Okay? Okay?
Does that make sense?
And the third thing that
is shocking about the Iliad
is the use of metaphors.
So what are metaphors?
Metaphors are connections between
things that were unseen, okay?
So for example, if I
say, the sky is a snail.
You're like, oh, I didn't know that.
I didn't know that. Okay? Do you
understand? That's what a metaphor is.
A metaphor is connecting two things
that before were not connected.
If you think about it, what
this is is a new thought.
And there are lots of
metaphors in the Iliad, okay?
So essentially,
metaphors teach you how to think, okay?
They are the tools for thought.
So these are the three distinct
characteristics of the Iliad
that make it unique in the world, okay?
It's switching perspectives
all the time, which
creates empathy, right?
It talks about human psychology all
the time, which creates imagination.
And it uses metaphors, which
enables you to think much more
deeply about the world, okay?
If you put these three things together,
what this is, ultimately, is
a theory of human, okay?
It's a theory of what it
means to be a human being.
Before, we thought human
beings fought over land.
They fought over a
woman, like Helen, okay?
They struggled for power.
What Homer is saying is, what
it means to be human is someone
who has empathy, imagination,
and the willingness to think.
Okay? Only if you're willing to see,
feel, and think, are you human?
This is a new theory of human
that becomes the basis
for Greek civilization. And
that's why the Greeks believed
the founder of the civilization
was not a general, he was not a king,
it was a poet named Homer.
Okay? And it's because of the Iliad
that they all read and memorized
and they could recite, okay?
Because, again, this is an oral culture where
you're trained to have a very strong memory.
And because they memorized the Iliad,
it further transformed them as humans,
okay? This is a new theory
of what it means to be human.
And this becomes the basis
for Greek civilization,
which then becomes the basis
for Western civilization.
And it's because of these
three reasons, the polis,
the alphabet, and Homer, that
we have Western civilization
as we know it today.
Okay? Any questions so far?
Any questions so far, guys?
All right. Now I'm going to spend
some time and discuss, okay,
why is Greek civilization different
from Chinese civilization?
Okay? And this will help
you better understand
Western civilization. So
the first question is,
why is it that Greeks developed alphabet,
okay, the alphabet, and the Chinese
did not develop the alphabet?
Okay? And the answer is this.
The answer is,
Greece was not an isolated culture.
Okay? So the people who actually
developed the alphabet were the Egyptians.
Okay? Egyptians. And the reason why is,
Egypt was constantly in
contact and communication
with many different societies and cultures,
including the Sumerians and the Greeks.
And they could adopt new practices
to advance their language.
Okay? So it was the Greeks, it
was the Egyptians who developed
the alphabet. The
Phoenicians were traders.
And the Phoenicians connected the
Egyptian culture to everyone else.
Okay? So it was the
Phoenicians who brought
the alphabet to the Greeks, who, because
they became illiterate, were
looking for a new language system.
Okay? Does that make sense? That's why,
that's how the Greeks got the alphabet.
Again, the question is, why
didn't China develop the alphabet?
And the answer is this. China,
for most of its history, was
isolated from the rest of the world.
But not only was China isolated, but
it was stable for most of its history,
because for most of Chinese history,
China was run by a class of
people called scholar officials.
Right? Confucian scholars.
What was their power?
What was their secret power? It
was the ability to read and write.
That's what differentiated
them from everyone else, right?
That's what made them
indispensable to the emperor.
That's why they were so powerful.
And so when you have a
monopoly over literacy,
you don't want to give it up.
You want to increase it.
And the way they did so
is by creating a new language
called classical Chinese.
Literally Chinese. Okay?
Does that make sense?
That's why there was this
divergence between Greece
and China at this time.
Because China, literacy
was monopolized by an elite
who benefited from this
monopoly. And therefore,
they made this monopoly
much more effective
by introducing a new language
called classical Chinese.
That only they could master.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
Excuse me?
Because the scholar officials,
they were in charge of bureaucracy, right?
If you're running a bureaucracy, you
need the ability to read and write.
You need the ability to basically
transport information from
one place to the next, right?
That's through reading and
writing, through literacy.
Does that make sense? So only
they could become bureaucrats.
Okay? So, does that make sense?
Okay. Any more questions?
Okay. Second question is,
why is it that Greeks had Homer
and the Chinese, we Chinese,
we never had Homer?
Okay? And again, the problem
are the scholar officials.
If you look at Confucian thought,
there's a hierarchy in
Confucian thought, right?
At the very top are scholar officials.
They're the most virtuous, they're the most well
-educated, they're the most cultivated, okay?
They're the best people.
Next to the, below the scholar
officials are the farmers
and the artisans, right?
Because they produce wealth for society.
Below them are the merchants, right?
And then at the very bottom are who?
The artists, right?
The poets. Now guess what, guys?
In Greece, this was the complete opposite.
They placed Homer
at the very top of the society.
Everyone wanted to be a
poet, like Homer, okay?
So when Plato was writing the Republic,
he was trying to become Homer.
He was trying to become a
teacher of civilization,
an inspirer of civilization,
okay? A bigot of civilization.
That's what Plato wanted.
But guess what? Thucydides, when
he wrote the Peloponnesian War,
he was trying to do the same thing.
He was trying to inspire civilization.
He was trying to inspire new ideas.
Because they all wanted to become Homer.
Okay? Because they all knew Homer
was the father of civilization.
And they wanted to continue his legacy.
And that's what made the Greeks
unique in human history.
Because only the society put poets first
and foremost at the top.
And no other society did so, okay?
In China, it was the complete opposite.
Because if you're a scholar official,
what you're most afraid of is
independent thinking, okay?
So censorship. Censorship.
Censorship was their main role, okay?
Controlling how people
thought through censorship.
And that's why China never really
produced a Homer or a great thinker.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
And so, this is going to be strange,
but it's only because
Greece got destroyed at
the end of the Bronze Age.
It became decentralized. It lived in poor.
That they could then become
a great civilization.
It was only through destruction
that they could have the polis,
the alphabet, and Homer.
Okay? And that's the main
message of human history.
It's through destruction
that we have innovation.
And it's only through this process that
human beings are able to
rejuvenate their society.
Okay? Does that make sense? Any questions?
Was this clear to you guys?
Okay. So we'll continue
in the Greeks, okay?