Okay, so good morning. We are
continuing the Hebrew Bible today.
Last class, we talked
about King David of Israel
and how he created the Bible,
the project of the Bible,
in order to create
legitimacy and authority.
Okay, and we are continuing
along this theme today. So,
let's go over the chronology of the Bible.
Okay, so
in the beginning, there was God.
In the Bible, his name is Yahweh.
And he created the world.
And then he created Adam and
Eve in the Garden of Eden.
And people who
take the Bible literally
believe this, was about 4000 BC.
As we know, Adam and Eve,
because they disobeyed God,
they were banished from
the Garden of Eden.
And they had two sons, Cain and Abel.
And then their family started
to populate the earth.
But then humans started to misbehave.
We went to war. We were greedy.
And so God decided to destroy the world.
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats was
about 2000 BC Abraham was born in
the city of Ur in Mesopotamia and
he was beloved by God
because he was a righteous
and decent man and
God made a covenant with him covenant
and a covenant is a
contract it's a promise
and the contract is this if you
Abraham swear allegiance to me
Yahweh I will make you
and your descendants founders
of a great nation called Israel
that will stretch from the Nile to
the Euphrates that's a promised land
and
return as a mark of this covenant Abraham
and his ancestors will engage in circumcision
they're basically the foreskin of the covenant
and they're going to be the first to be
circumcised by God so of their penis will be certainly surgically removed at birth okay so
that's a covenant Abraham
had a son named Isaac
and Isaac had a son named Jacob
okay um Jacob is the
younger son of Isaac
so Esau should have inherit the birthright
and the blessing from his father Isaac but
Jacob played a trick on Esau and
stole Jacob played a trick on Jacob
and stole Thats
Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Jacob
will be renamed by God as Israel. So
Jacob really is the founder
of the nation of Israel.
Jacob's youngest son is named Joseph,
and he is beloved by Jacob
so much that his brothers
became jealous of him
and sold him into slavery in Egypt.
Joseph was also beloved by God, and
he had a special gift
of reading dreams, and
he became a special advisor to the
Pharaoh, and he became very wealthy.
Meanwhile, back in the land of Israel,
Jacob and his sons, their family,
are facing this massive famine.
So Joseph comes and rescues them, and
the entire nation of Israel
moves down to Egypt.
Okay? Where they become
very wealthy and prosperous.
And because they have
many children, eventually,
after a couple of decades,
they become a threat to the establishment.
So the new Pharaoh, who
has no memory of the
contributions of Joseph,
enslaved the Israelites,
and he wants them to die.
So he basically forbids them to have sons,
and he basically...
tries to sanction the Israelites
as much as possible. Eventually,
a man named Moses is born
into the Israelites in Egypt.
And because he's a boy,
he has to be killed.
So his mother puts him in a basket,
and then this basket drifts down the Nile
and into the hands of
the Egyptian princess.
So Moses grows up to
become an Egyptian prince.
But eventually, he dies. And eventually,
God informs him of who he really is.
And he's the prophet who
will deliver the Israelites
back into the Promised Land.
The Pharaoh refuses to
let the Israelites go.
There's a major contest, duel,
between Moses and the Pharaoh.
And then God sends down like ten plagues.
Okay? Ten plagues. To force the
Pharaoh to release the Israelites.
Moses is taking the Israelites
into the Promised Land.
And then Pharaoh has
a change of heart, and
he wants to destroy the Israelites
before they can escape.
So the Pharaoh chases them.
Moses causes the sea to part.
They cross the valley.
And when Pharaoh and his army
are about to enter the sea,
the sea closes in on them and drowns them.
Okay? And then when...
When Moses and the Israelites
are in the desert,
Moses ascends the mountain
to receive the law of God.
And this is what we call
the Ten Commandments.
But while Moses is away,
the Israelites create an
idol to celebrate Yahweh.
And Yahweh hates this, because Yahweh
does not want to be represented on earth.
So... Yahweh sends them to
a long exile in the desert.
And he tells Moses,
You will deliver the people
from Egypt, and that
is your mission, but you will
not enter the Promised Land.
You can see the Promised Land, but
you will not enter the Promised Land.
So the mission goes to Joshua,
who is Moses' disciple.
And Joshua and
the Israelites start a massive military
campaign into the land of Canaan,
which is the Promised Land.
And over the span of years,
they basically massacre the people,
and they create the nation of Israel.
And then we enter the
period called the Judges.
And these are 12 individuals who
become the tribal leaders of Israel.
And Israel at this time is at
war with all their neighbors,
the Moabites, the Edomites, the
Philistines, the Canaanites.
And this period lasts for a long time.
Until the Israelites pick a
king named Saul to lead them.
King Saul. And then as we know
from King Saul will come David,
who will use up the throne from Saul
and be the great king of Israel
that we remember today. And
David is considered
the real founder of the
State of Israel as well
as the Jewish faith.
So that's the chronology of the Bible.
Now, because the Bible is written
almost like a historical document,
for most of human history,
people believe this to be literally true.
Okay? But in the past
400 years, 300 years,
there are many archaeologists
who have tried to prove
the events in the Bible.
For example, Noah's Ark.
If there really was a flood, well,
there would be a geological record.
There would be a ship. Okay?
There would be a memory of this.
But there was never, but
we have never been able to find any
concrete evidence to support North Arctic.
Okay? How about the Garden of Eden?
Well, if the Garden of
Eden really existed,
well, we could also find it.
And we've never been able
to find it. All right?
How about Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob?
Again, no evidence.
No evidence that any of these
individuals ever existed.
How about Moses?
Well, we would think if
Moses really did exist,
there would be some records of
him in the Egyptian history.
Right? I mean,
10 plagues is a travesty and a
disaster on the Egyptian people.
No record of that. The parting of the sea.
No record of that. The judges.
Joshua. Nothing.
Okay? It is only until we get to David
when we begin to see
historical records and
prove that David actually existed.
But before that, nothing in the Bible
has proven to be historical.
Okay? And so this is very confusing.
So what I will show you today is if you
see the Bible as a historical record,
you will only get confused.
If you see this as a chronology,
this makes no sense. If you
see this as a work of fiction,
like a lot of people do, this
doesn't make much sense either.
Okay? Because when you read the Bible,
these events aren't actually
interconnected with each other.
David has no memory of Moses, for example.
That's weird. Moses has
no memory of Abraham.
Okay? So these stories
are not interconnected.
So if this is not a historical record,
if this is not a work of pure fiction,
what is this thing? Okay?
What I will show you today is
this is not a chronology.
This is a cosmology. Cosmology. Okay?
Remember, last class, we talked about why
things are written down
in the ancient past. And as I said,
King Sponsor wrote, he wrote writing
projects for three major reasons.
The first reason is to create
legitimacy and authority.
The second reason is to
create a national identity,
cohesion among the people.
The third reason is the
idea of differentiation.
To tell people who they are not.
We're Israelites, we're not Egyptians.
We're not Canaanites. We're not Thracians.
We're not Philistines. Okay? So
these are the three major reasons
why kings sponsor writing projects.
And for the Israelites and David,
these three imperatives
are particularly salient.
Okay? They're really necessary.
All right? So let me explain
why that's the case.
So legitimacy.
Remember, David usurped
the throne from Saul.
Saul came from a noble family and
he was elected by the chieftains
to be their king.
And then David launched a rebellion
and eventually usurped the throne.
So David has a major legitimacy problem.
So how he solves the problem,
as we discussed last class,
is the Bible presents him as a poet king.
Okay? This is a very important concept.
Poet king. There have been warrior kings,
right? Kings who go to war
and they win legitimacy
by defeating all their enemies.
There have been priest kings,
kings who are head of a major religion.
But David is the first poet king.
Okay? He writes poetry.
He sings songs. He's a sensitive soul.
That's what explains his
affair with Bathsheba.
And that tells us he could never
have possibly been ambitious
and wanted to kill Saul.
Okay? He's the first poet king.
So why is he king of Israel?
Because guess what, guys?
God is the poet god.
Okay? Poet god.
Yahweh is the poet god.
So this is a radical conception
of divinity in the ancient world.
Gods previously have
been priests or warriors.
And this is the first time
in human history where God,
Yahweh, has been presented as a poet god.
When you read the Bible, it's very
interesting how he creates the world.
He speaks and things are created.
Okay? He says, let there be light.
Let there be heaven and earth.
He speaks. And when he speaks,
a new world is created.
And then he looks at this world
and says, and this is good.
Okay? So he's like a writer who
speaks words and then
edits his words in order to create
something much more beautiful.
He's a poet. And as a
poet, he's very sensitive.
Okay? Which means he creates Adam and Eve
because he's lonely.
He wants friendship.
Okay? So
in other words,
the Bible is fundamentally a story
of friendship of two poets
who are alone in the world
and who found friendship
and comfort in each other.
Okay? And the way the Bible accomplishes
is through the idea of covenant.
So in the Bible, there are
four covenants, promises.
So the first covenant is
between Noah and Yahweh.
It's what we call the Noah -had
covenant, the Noah -had covenant.
And the idea of this is this.
After Yahweh destroys the world, he feels
tremendous remorse for what he's done.
He promises Noah, as long
as humans are not too evil,
I will not destroy the world.
Okay? If humans stay good, I
will not destroy the world.
The second covenant is between Abraham
and Yahweh. It's called
the Abrahamic covenant.
And in this covenant,
Yahweh says to Abraham,
if you and your ancestors,
sorry, if you and your
descendants stay true to me,
I will create a great nation out of you.
I will give you the nation of Israel.
The third covenant is
between Moses and Yahweh.
It's called the Mosaic covenant.
And the idea is,
if the Israelites
follow the Ten Commandments, and
worship Yahweh, only Yahweh,
then Yahweh will protect them as a nation.
Yahweh will show them favor.
Okay? So those are the three covenants.
But, when we get to David,
called the Davidic covenant,
something interesting happens.
All three priests are what we call
conditional covenants.
If you do this, then I will do this.
But when we get to David,
it's unconditional.
Ah Yahweh will promise that you,
David, and your descendants
will forever rule Israel.
The house of David will
forever rule Israel.
Okay? It's an unconditional covenant that
shows his everlasting
friendship with David.
In other words, the covenant
marks the end of biblical history.
Yahweh, this great God,
poet God, who searched the
universe for friendship,
has now found his great friend in David.
And so his search has ended, and
biblical history has ended. Okay?
This is a radical new
idea in human history.
How a king and a God can be poets.
And how the world, how reality
can be constructed through words.
Okay? And that's why in the Bible,
there's a very famous phrase called,
in the beginning, there was the word.
And that's why Jewish people are
so literary.
Okay? Because that's
part of their tradition.
If you look at some of
the most famous writers,
some of the most famous
thinkers in the world,
they're mainly Jewish. And
again, a lot of it is because
the Jewish faith is the first faith
to focus on literary creation.
Okay? So that's the idea of legitimacy.
Cohesion. There's a lot of cohesion.
Okay? The second purpose
is great cohesion.
And as we discussed,
after the Bronze Age collapsed,
the land of Canaan was in complete chaos.
You had all these different
groups within Canaan.
You had the nomads from the desert.
Okay? The Bedouins. You had
the hill people of Canaan.
You have refugees from
the cities of Canaan who
have been, and these
cities have been destroyed.
You have Egyptian priests.
You have foreign mercenaries.
And now you have sea
peoples, these Greeks and
these other peoples who are coming into
Canaan because they've lost their lands
back at home. Okay?
So you've got this very different
group of people together.
They're in competition with other
groups, like the Philistines.
So now they need to create
a national identity
out of all this, right?
And that's what the Bible is doing, guys.
Okay? Remember,
there's a concept we learned that's very
important in class called syncretization.
Right? Syncretization.
It means when you bring
different religions together
and create a new religion.
So, for example, let's just
say my god is Zeus, and
your god is Hera.
And I conquer you,
and I make you part of my people.
Okay? So what we do in this instance
is we marry our gods to each other.
So now Zeus is married to Hera, and they
have children like Aphrodite and Athena.
Okay? And this is a way to soothe
the process of conquest.
Because even though I've conquered
you, I still have to live with you.
Okay? So
we have to blend in our
different cultures.
This is also true for the idea
of genealogy, family history.
Every tribe has a patriarch.
Okay? And the reason we have a
patriarch is to tell the people,
we've been in this land
for the longest time.
And that's why we have legitimacy and control
over this land, because we were here first.
Okay? Now, when
tribes get together, they
intermarry, they form alliances,
what they do that's very common is
their ancestors merge together.
And they become sons and
fathers of each other.
So as though it's like one family history.
Okay? You take these different
family histories, and
you merge them into one line, the
same process of syncretization.
Okay? So if you look at this
instance, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob,
it's basically three
major tribes of Israel
coming together to form
one family history.
In this instance, the
most powerful family is
that of Jacob.
Because Jacob, Israel,
gives his name to the
new nation of Israel.
The second most important
person or tribe is Abraham,
because he's the
progenitor of this family.
Okay? And third will be Isaac.
And in fact, in the Bible, Isaac
receives the least amount of attention.
Okay? But
the syncretization process
also helps us explain Moses.
Because we've been looking
for a hundred years,
and we have not found any
evidence that Moses ever existed.
Or anyone like Moses existed in Egypt.
Okay? So what's Moses doing?
Well, what Moses is doing is explaining
why there are Egyptian priests
in the nation of Israel.
Right? And why are priests important?
Because if you're David,
and you're now king,
you want to create legitimacy,
and you want to create authority.
And the best way you create authority
is by centralizing your power.
Back then, the best and
easiest way to centralize power is
by centralizing religious ritual.
Does that make sense?
So what he did was this.
He created, he made his
new capital Jerusalem,
and he built something called the Temple of
Jerusalem, which became the house of Yahweh.
This is where Yahweh lived.
So if you wanted to worship
Yahweh, and you had to,
because he was your God,
you had to come all the way to
Jerusalem to offer a sacrifice.
And who controlled the sacrifice process?
Priests. Okay?
And why did the priests,
and why did the priests,
Egyptian priests, why are they
controlling the sacrifice process?
Because they're the ones, Moses, who
led the people of Israel out of Egypt.
They're the ones who delivered
the Israelites into freedom.
Moses is an Egyptian name.
It means son of. Okay?
So it's a very common Egyptian name.
So for example, Ramesses means son of Ra.
Okay? So Ramesses is a very
famous Egyptian pharaoh.
Ramesses means son of Ra, the sun god.
So both Moses and his brother Aaron,
these are Egyptian names
for Egyptian priests.
Okay? So
David was heavily reliant on these
Egyptian priests in order
to centralize authority.
Also, the idea of circumcision,
it is an ancient Egyptian practice
that priests specialized in.
Right? So
if the new law is to
be a member of Israel,
to be an Israelite, means
you have to get circumcised,
you have to circumcise your children,
you're going to go to the Egyptian
priests to circumcise your children
because they're good at that
and they know how to do that.
Does that make sense? So
by making circumcision the major mark of
what it means to be an
Israelite, it gives authority
and power to these Egyptian priests.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay? The judges.
What we believe is the judges
are these local heroes
that bring in all the other
tribes of Israel together.
Okay? So in other words, if you are a
member of this new nation of Israel,
you have an opportunity to be a deity or an
ancestor within the cosmology of the Bible.
Okay? And
this explains why the history of Israel is
so convoluted, contradictory,
and complex. Because
they're trying to create
a national identity
where everyone, all tribes,
all, everyone is able to contribute
effectively to the creation
of Israel. Okay?
Any questions before I continue?
Is this clear to you
guys? What's going on?
Any other questions? All right.
Now the last question is differentiation.
And this is the most important, okay?
Because remember, you
have Egyptian priests
in Israel. How do we know they're
loyal to Israel and not to Egypt?
Because the Egyptian priests
went to war with a pharaoh.
Which means they were going to war with a pharaoh.
We have Canaanites within the state of Israel.
How do we know they're loyal?
Because they went to war
with the Canaanites.
Okay? So in the Bible,
what's interesting to you with the Bible
is the Israelites in their history went to war with everyone.
Okay? The Egyptians, the Philistines,
the Canaanites went to war with everyone.
Why? Because they had members
from every single geography
and location in that area.
And so they needed to
differentiate themselves.
The best way you differentiate
yourself is by going to war with them.
Does that make sense? Also,
guys, when I use the word nation,
I have to warn you.
This is not the modern sense.
Nation, it's a loose political affiliation
that is fluid. Today, the nation state,
you're Chinese, you're
stuck being Chinese.
But back then,
if you're an Israelite, guess what?
You could walk across a
street and become a Moabite.
Okay? So
the idea of identity back then
was extremely loose and fluid.
So when we use the term
Moabite or Canaanite,
basically we're talking
about a geographical location
that has some political force.
But it's not a fixed identity.
Okay? The very idea of ethnicity, race,
group identity, back then was extremely
fluid, was basically nonexistent.
Okay? So Israel, the very idea of
Israel, it's a literary creation.
The idea of Israelite, it
is a political creation.
All right? Does that make sense, guys?
Any questions so far before I move on?
Okay? Are you clear?
Okay. All right. All right.
So this explains why the Bible
is structured the way it is.
Okay? But then the question then is, and
this is a very important question, is, okay,
you know what? This was standard
cultural practice back then.
Everyone did this to create identity.
So why is it we have
the Bible today and not,
say, other texts from
Egypt or Mesopotamia?
Why is it that the Bible was able
to conquer the world, basically?
Right? Because you have
two billion Christians,
you have a billion Muslims.
The Bible was able to conquer the world
and capture the imagination of humanity.
And here I want to explain
why the Bible is so powerful.
It was how it was written
that made it so powerful.
Okay? So last class we talked
about the Apology of David,
about the Apology of David
and about the Bathsheba story,
about the Abner story. And
we believe the person who
wrote those stories are what
we call the court historian.
We have absolutely no idea who he is.
He's basically the official
historian of the court of David.
Okay? And every court will
have an official historian.
And those stories are good,
but they're not literary.
Okay? They're just propaganda and spin.
But the person who
wrote the Bible, especially Genesis,
was a unique literary genius
of the statue of Homer
and Plato and Dante.
Okay? The person who wrote the
Bible, who first wrote the Bible,
was an incredible literary genius.
And we call her the Yahwist.
Okay? Why do we call her the Yahwist?
It's just convention because
she uses Yahweh as the name of God.
And other writers don't actually use
Yahweh as the name of God. Okay?
So by convention, we call her the Yahwist.
Another question then is, who is she?
And we're fairly certain
she's a, well, it's a she.
Okay? And as I will show you,
we're fairly certain it's a she
because she focuses not on war,
not on conflict, but
on domestic tragedy and affairs,
childbirth, marriage, love.
And this is unique in human history.
Okay? So we're fairly
confident it's a she.
There are many who believe
she is of the court of David.
And the reason why is,
first of all, what she writes is very
favorable to the court of David.
Also, back then, as you can imagine,
only aristocratic women had the
privilege of reading and writing.
Okay? She clearly had access
to the mythology of Egypt,
Mesopotamia, Anatolia.
She has access to a great education.
So we believe she's a princess.
I will further make the argument
that she must be either the daughter
or the granddaughter of King David.
Okay? I would make this argument
that she has to be the daughter or
the granddaughter of King David.
And the reason why is, what she wrote,
and I'll show you what she
wrote, what she wrote was so
controversial and so unique
and so imaginative that the priesthood
could not possibly accept what she did.
If she was just a priest or if she
was just an aristocratic of low birth,
there was no way
her writings would become
part of the Bible. Okay?
So she must have been
someone of high authority.
And there is actually
a precedent for this.
So, for example, we know
that in about 2000 BCE,
this is, you know,
at least a thousand years before
the Yahwehs began to write,
the Sargon of Akkad, who
is the first great empire builder, okay,
the first emperor, basically.
And this is someone that back then,
during the time of King David,
everyone knew and worshipped.
Okay? King David knew about him
and he knew about his practices.
When Sargon of Akkad
conquered Mesopotamia,
he appointed his daughter
named En -h -du
-an -na to be like the high
priestess of the religion.
But what's interesting
about her is, she's a poet.
And she's the first name
author in human history.
Okay? This is 2000 BCE.
She wrote a lot of poetry.
So there is a history, a precedent,
for these kings to appoint their daughters
to be the official poet of their nation.
Okay? So that's who I
think the Yahwehs is.
But honestly, we'll never
know and it's not important.
Okay? We just have to
know she was an author.
An exceptional literary genius who
made the Bible what it is today.
Alright? So let's go over some of her
literary contributions very shortly.
And again, because the Bible has
been redacted for about 2,000 years,
3,000 years, we've lost a lot
of her original writings.
Okay? So
I will analyze a couple of stories
that we know for sure she wrote.
The first is called Adam and Eve. And the
second is called The Story of Jacob and Rachel.
Okay? Alright. So
you think you know the story of Adam and
Eve, but I guarantee you it's wrong.
Okay? I guarantee you, even if you know
the story of Adam and Eve, it's wrong.
Alright. So let's go over the official or the
mainstream understanding of the story of Adam
and Eve. God told Adam
and Eve, listen, this is the
Garden of Eden, it's paradise,
you can do whatever you want.
You live in heaven, life is easy,
apples fall from the sky,
okay, you can pick
tomatoes and carrots from the ground,
life is easy, it's paradise for you.
But there's one rule and only
one rule in the Garden of Eden.
And the rule is, do not eat
from the tree of knowledge of good
and evil because it's poisonous.
And of course, Adam and
Eve had to disobey God.
And God became so angry that he banished
Adam and Eve from the Garden of Eden.
And now see, our act of disobedience,
the first act of disobedience, our
first sin, the original sin that
has doomed us forever until
the redemption of Jesus,
right? That's a story we all know.
The story is completely and utterly wrong.
That's not what it says in the Bible.
Okay? So, I'll explain first
what the Bible says and then I'll explain
how we can interpret the story.
Okay. So,
God says to Adam and Eve,
don't eat that fruit, okay? And
then Adam and Eve are curious.
Why can't you eat that fruit?
And then Eve meets a serpent
on the ground, and the serpent talks.
And Eve basically says,
we can't eat that fruit.
And the serpent says, why?
Eve says, it's poisonous.
The serpent says, no, it's not poisonous.
You're being lied to. The reason why
Yahweh does not want you to eat
from the fruit is once you eat it,
you'll become like God.
Your eyes will open.
You'll have the knowledge of the fruit
and the knowledge of good and evil.
And then Eve gets angry
because she feels manipulated.
And she convinces Adam
to eat the fruit as well.
So they eat the fruit. And
their eyes are open now.
They have knowledge of good
and evil. Yahweh visits them
in the garden, and he discovers
they're hiding from him.
And Yahweh commands them to come out,
and he sees right away
they're embarrassed about their nakedness.
They're embarrassed about
being confronted by Yahweh.
So Yahweh knows they've eaten the fruit.
Adam says to Yahweh, it's Eve's fault.
Eve says to Yahweh, it's
the serpent's fault.
And Yahweh decides to punish all three.
He says to the serpent, from now on,
you will slither on the ground,
and you'll be hunted by man.
Eve, from now on, you and
all the people of your descendants
will suffer the pains of childbirth.
Childbirth will be an
extremely painful process.
And then he says to Adam, from now on,
you must sweat to grow
food, to feed yourself.
From now on, life will be hardship.
It will be a, it will be
toil and pain and suffering.
Okay? And then he does this, okay?
This is very interesting.
And this is where the Bible
demonstrates its genius, okay?
And the Lord God made
garments of skins for the man
and his wife and clothed them.
Then the Lord said, see,
the man has become like one of us,
knowing good and evil.
And now he might reach out his hand and
take also the tree of
life and live forever.
Okay? This is where the Bible is genius.
And the Bible is telling us
why God is banishing Adam and
Eve from the Garden of Eden.
It's telling us. It's because there's
another tree God didn't mention to them.
It's called the tree of life. And
it allows you to live forever.
So why is this a problem? Well, there
are two things that differentiate God
from us, humans.
The first thing is God has
knowledge of good and evil.
Second thing is God lives forever.
That's it. That's the only difference.
That's the only difference. So if
Adam and Eve now know good and evil,
if they eat from the tree of
life, they can live forever.
So God's afraid will become like God.
Therefore, to protect the tree of life,
he has to banish us from the Garden.
Okay? Yeah?
Excuse me? Yes?
What is good and evil?
Exactly. Okay. What is good and evil?
Okay. So this is what, so this
is a really complicated idea.
Okay? But good and evil does not
mean you know God and you know Satan.
That's not what it means. It means you know
what's good for you and what's bad for you.
So for example, if I knew good and evil,
I hit this table.
Okay? I feel pain, right?
And I'm like, what pain?
What is that? Is that good or is that bad?
I don't know. So I do it again.
Okay? And I do it again.
I cannot learn from my mistakes
because I cannot differentiate
what's good for me and what's bad for me.
But now I know good and evil,
I'm like, oh, I hit this thing.
I feel pain. Therefore, it's evil.
Therefore, I shouldn't do it again.
Therefore, I should avoid this table.
So knowing good and evil
means you have the capacity
to learn and
to grow through a process
of self -reflection.
Once you have judgment, once you're able
to differentiate what's good for you
and what's bad for you, you
can always grow as a person.
Does that make sense? And
if you can do this forever,
that you have life and live forever,
it means you become God because
your knowledge is now infinite.
Okay? Does that make sense?
That's what knowledge of good and evil is.
The ability to differentiate
for yourself what is good for
you and what is bad for you.
To engage in a process of reflection
and self -growth. Okay?
So God's afraid that
if we continue to grow, we will
become as powerful as God himself.
Is there any question? Any more questions?
Before I continue? The key line is this.
The Lord God made garments of skins for
the men and his wife and clothed them.
This is right after He
punishes Adam and Eve.
This is right after He scolds them.
Right? This is God giving,
pitying them and giving them
a present this is very strange this is
paradoxical why would god do this okay
there are different ways to interpret this
but i think this is god showing remorse
and regret
okay this is a radical
idea but this is god
saying to adam and eve i'm sorry
for this this is god showing remorse
and regret why is god
showing remorse and regret
you show remorse when you've got you
just when you just think wrong right but
what did god do wrong
why why is god in the wrong here it's a
radical idea wait can you figure it out
okay god lied to adam and eve
god said to Adam and Eve
do not eat from this tree
because it's poisonous right
so imagine this imagine
you're my two daughters okay
and you're like six or seven years old
and you see me at night drinking
whiskey or beer I'm really happy
because I'm drinking whiskey
and beer so you two are curious
and you say to me dad what is this and
I say it's um poison and
then you're like why are you drinking
poison dad like well because because
I'm older than you are when
you're as old as I am you can drink
this poison okay you two are now curious
right you're curious why
is dad drinking poison
so
your uncle comes to the
house one day you ask
your uncle hey it's alcohol poisonous your
uncle's like of course it's not poisonous what are you talking about
and so of course what you
two do is you break into the
alcohol cabinet right and
you drink whiskey and you're very you
come very happy you throw up I come home
and I shout at you you guys are
terrible I told you not to drink
that go to your room and
you're suspended for a month
okay you go to a room you cry
and then I come knocking and say hey dad
you're not drinking this you're not drinking this okay you go to a room you cry and then I come knocking and
say hey dad you're not you guys
want to go out to McDonald's
and have a hamburger together you guys
want to go out to McDonald's and have a hamburger together you understand the story
because I know I'm the
wrong I should have said to
you alcohol is poisonous
okay I'm your bad parent
so
what we mock about the story
is it's basically a
domestic comedy you understand this
is what happens among families
all the time this is a power of
this is a power of family
the story of Adam and
Eve it's a domestic comedy
it's something we can
all relate to something we can all
understand what's also really powerful
about the story is
God is
fallible God is has made
a terrible mistake what's
important is this God understands he's made
a mistake that's why he's showing remorse
and he's showing remorse and he's showing
remorse and he's showing remorse he's showing remorse and he's showing remorse
he's turning
hell he's turning hell
he's turning hell he's
turning hell he's turning
hell he's turning hell he's
turning hell he's turning hell he's
turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's
turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's turning hell he's
turning hell he's turning hell
he's turning hell he's turning hell
he's turning hell animals is
our capacity to make mistakes
and to learn from them because
we ate from the knowledge of from
the tree of knowledge of good and
evil okay you see how radical
all this is these are radical
new ideas in human history
God is
fallible what's important is to understand
and admit your mistakes and
grow from them okay okay
the story continues because now Adam
and Eve are banished from the Garden of
Eden they have two sons named Cain and
Abel Abel is
a shepherd okay and
Cain is a farmer okay but
they both love God they
both want the respect
and attention of God
so
they present they think they
give presence to
God Abel is a shepherd
so he offers mutton okay to God
and then Cain is a farmer
so he offers I don't know like
wheat or vegetables to God God tastes both
and then
God's like this mutton no it's
tasty awesome thank you Abel
and then he eats Cain's offering
and Cain's very anxious he's very excited
and Cain's like and
Abel's like oh sorry sorry and then
God Yahweh is like this
food sucks man all right
and this is what it says in the Bible and
the Lord had regard for Abel and
his offering but
for Cain his offering he had
no regard he hated Cain's
present he loved Abel's present so
Cain was very angry and
his countenance fell the
Lord said to Cain why
are you angry if you do well
will you not be accepted okay
so
again it's a domestic comedy
you're my girls you're
my you're my daughters you go to school
and you work very hard on
presenting a present to me right
and I say to one of you oh this
is an awesome present thank you
and I say to the other you suck man
okay I'm a bad parent God is
being a terrible parent okay
if you do well will
you not be accepted you suck man the
problem isn't me the problem
is you you just suck okay
and
of course what happens
next is Cain kills Abel
but then
what happens next is interesting he is
Thats Thats about this he banishes Cain
and then
Cain says to God hey you banish
me people will know I committed wrong
and therefore I will be
killed by other people then
Yahweh says to Cain okay I'll
put a mark on you the mark of Cain
and if anyone touches you
then I will punish that
person I will protect you
with the mark of Cain and
this is again God showing remorse
and regret for what he's done because
God knows in his heart he's not wrong here
but
what allowed God to
understand he committed wrong is
because Cain argued with
him okay Cain
argued back so
this is a radical conception of
faith in the in the Hebrew Bible
faith love of
God requires you to argue with God
because it's only for the
price of argument that
God who's fallible will learn
and grow so when
you argue you fight back you're
helping the other person grow
you've gained respect from God he Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats and
divinity okay any more questions
before I move on okay
so again the Yahweh's is a literary genius
and there are two things
that make her stand out that
I make that make her unique in
the history of literature the
first is her economy economy just means
using as few words as
possible to express as much
as possible okay you can
see the story of Adam
and Eve the story of Cain and Abel it's
very economical she's using very few words
but within these words are a universe
of ideas almost infinite
meaning you're gonna
interpret these stories anyway
you want okay
the second idea
is irony irony just
means she's funny
okay if you tell your kids don't eat
that apple don't eat that fruit because
it's poisonous guess what your
kids are gonna eat that fruit okay
and then you look like an idiot
because it's not poisonous
so
it's ironic she's
making fun of Yahweh she's making fun
of the highest authority in the
Israelite faith and
again that's why if she
were not the daughter
of David or granddaughter David there's no way
this story would have gone into the Bible okay
but it's a great story that
has infinite literary power does
that make sense the last story I
will mention is a story of Rachel
and Jacob it's a very
interesting story okay so
what happens is this Jacob
runs away from his brother Esau
because Jacob stole Esau's birthright
and blessing and
Jacob ends up with a relative named Laban
and Laban has two daughters Leah
and Rachel Leah is the eldest
Rachel is the younger one
and
Jacob falls in love with Rachel
right away and he says to Laban
I will work for you for
free for seven years and
then I will want your daughter Rachel's
hand in return for my work
Laban says well you're a relative and
it's better for me to give her
to you than to complete stranger
so yeah okay seven years pass
and there's a wedding between Rachel
and Jacob
that night
Jacob has sex with a woman he wakes up
and sees it's not Rachel its Leah he slept
with Leah he is now married to Leah
then Jacob says to Laban you've tricked me
and then
Laban says it is the
custom of our people to
marry the firstborn first
we have to marry Leah
off first before we can
marry off Rachel if you
continue to work for me for seven
years I will give you Rachel as well
and Jake agrees okay
there's a very short story
and there's a lot of economy
and irony in the story but
again within the short story
there is a universe of ideas
and emotions you're able
to think very clearly
and closely about the
story we will discover
that
a Rachel
and Leah hate each other how do we know
that because
Leah stole Jacob from
Rachel we can imagine
that when
Laban announced that Rachel would
marry Jacob Leah was very jealous
and
for seven years every night
at dinner Leah would cry
and scream at her father you
know how could you
embarrass me like this I'm
your firstborn do I mean nothing to
you we can imagine the family drama
and the comedy right Laban's like you know
what if after seven years Jacob marries
Rachel they're gonna run off together right
and for the rest of my life I'm
be stuck with Leah screaming at me
and hitting me in the head for
the rest of my life right
so he's like I need to figure out
how to get out of this deal right
so that's why he tricks
Jacob we can also figure out
that Rachel and
Jacob love each other their love
is the greatest love in the world
because first of all Jacob's
willing to put up this
crap for another seven
years in order to be
of Rachel right second of all Rachel's
willing to wait for Jacob she
could at any time just run off
and be with someone else but
she's willing to endure
she's willing to suffer
so
we can imagine the
entire family dynamic in history
based on just a few sentences in the Bible
that's a that's a power of the
hours okay the part the Yahweh's
she's really writing about what it means
to be human what it means to have a family
and that's why the Bible
endures to this day
these there are these
powerful stories in the Bible
that tell us that
reveal to us what it
means to be human what it
means to love what it means to
forgive what it means our family
and that's
why the Bible has inspired
people for thousands of years
because in these stories you are part of
the writing process it's co
-creation okay your meaning co
-creation your meaning your
understanding interpretation
is what gives life to
these words there are
that many words but your understanding these
words is what makes these words powerful to you
and
again these stories are unique in history and
they're not just stories they're stories that
are in human history the story of Adam and Eve
is everyone knows the story of Adam and Eve
okay it's just a powerful story you
can also argue the power of Adam
and Eve is because
it makes us nostalgic for the Ice Age
right around the Ice Age we
were in egalitarian society
where everyone was equal
and
the Garden of Edom is the
Garden of Eden
and the Garden of the! ! Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats so
in the Bible there are
people called prophets prophets
and
how prophets work is they visit
heaven or they visit by an angel
and there's one scene where
the angel or God takes a parchment and
puts it into the mouth of the Prophet
so
the prophets is speaking every word
that's a direct word of God does
that make sense like it's almost like
he's just a mailman
I'm God I put a parchment in your
mouth you come back to earth
and you basically announce
the Word of God okay
so there are people who
believe God wrote every word okay
but this is only my note of Christians
you most Christians believe
that whoever wrote the
Bible was inspired by God
that
these are prophets were inspired by
God to write down the truths of God
but
if you actually try to read the Bible
by yourself it's impossible okay
because it's been redacted so
many times as I explained to you last class there
are at least four different sources in the Bible
that have been spliced together randomly
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats Thats
but you won't actually have
to read them together does
that make sense so
what i'm offering you today is
not a scriptural interpretation
of the bible i'm offering you a uh what
we call a literary interpretation of the
bible okay
uh any more questions
any more questions are
you guys clear about this
okay so um we'll continue
this the bible next class
and next class we will look at
the religion of zoroastrianism
because when the persian
empire conquers the world
zoroastrianism their religion
will start to merge with the bible
which creates new rations of
zoroastrianism which is the new rations of zoroastrianism which is the new rations of ideas that will eventually become the basis of Christianity.