Okay, good morning. We are
doing Mesopotamia today.
This is the Bronze Age.
We did Egypt last class.
We are doing Mesopotamia today. In the next
class, we will finish with the Indus Valley.
So, before I begin,
I want to make three general
points about the study of history
and how civilizations develop.
The first point is this.
Every culture has a mythology.
And the mythology is the
collective worldview of the people
that lets them understand
the reality around them.
So another idea that
we can say is mythology
is a shared reality.
And every civilization has mythology.
So, for example,
today our mythology would be science
and history, right?
We think they are true and objective,
but they're actually mythologies.
They're a shared reality. And
every civilization would
have its own mythology.
And that's what makes the culture unique.
Okay? So that's the first point. So
what we will do today to better
understand Mesopotamia is to compare
and contrast its mythology
with that of the Egyptians.
Okay? Second point is
there's an idea called the dialectic. And
this was an idea proposed by the German philosopher
named Frederick Hegel in the 19th century.
He believes that
history is driven by opposing ideas.
So whenever you have one
mythology or one idea,
there always must arise
another opposing idea
that challenges it.
And that's what drives history.
And history is always moving
towards a synthesis of ideas.
Okay? So the example would
be there's capitalism,
and the opposing idea would be communism.
And the synthesis of the
idea would be socialism.
Okay? And what's really
important to understand
is that ideas can be living things
that change over time.
The third idea I want to introduce is the
idea of diversity and differentiation.
And the idea here is
we humans have some
fundamental natures about us.
So for example, we're all
religious in some aspect.
Another fundamental
instinct about us, we
strive to be different.
And that's why diversity
is the iron law of society.
Okay? So the example is in a family,
all the siblings will be different.
In a classroom, the
students will be different.
And you could be a certain
way in a classroom,
and then you go to another classroom
and you figure out the students
there are similar to you,
so you will change as a person to
differentiate yourself from other people.
Okay? So that's also another
principle of history.
Societies strive to be
different from each other.
They strive for diversity
and differentiation.
We cannot make generalizations
about societies.
The only thing that we can say is
societies or cultures
fall into a spectrum.
Okay? And
they're usually defined by
the elite or generalizations.
So this is another way of saying today I'm
going to make very broad
generalizations about these societies
and generalizations. And
they're useful for our purposes,
but I want you to be aware that
these are simplifications,
these are generalizations.
Okay? Alright.
So let's start.
Okay. So
Mesopotamia is a very different culture
and civilization than Egypt
because of its geography.
Okay? So if you look at
the geography of Egypt,
it has natural boundaries.
So for example, to the
west is the Sahara Desert.
To the north is the Mediterranean Sea.
To the east is the Red Sea.
Okay? And then to the
south are the Cataracts.
So it makes it hard to travel up the Nile
from the south.
So there are really only two
access points into Egypt,
which can be easily defended.
The south and also from the Levant,
which is basically Israel, Syria, Jordan.
And because of its natural boundaries,
Egypt doesn't really feel
threatened by external enemies,
right? Also, it has the Nile River,
which is the foundation
of its civilization.
Remember last class we talked about
how the Nile was very generous.
It flooded predictably every season,
and so it made agriculture very productive
in Egypt, which
allowed them to sustain
a very large population,
which then
can be used to create
monuments like the pyramid.
So for most of its
history, Egypt was stable
and prosperous.
Mesopotamia is completely different.
So first of all,
Mesopotamia, which
is in what we call Iraq today,
it has no natural boundaries.
Mesopotamia is Greek for
the land between two rivers.
These two rivers are the Euphrates
and the Tigris.
To the
west of Mesopotamia would be Arabia,
and the Levant, okay?
To the north would be Anatolia.
To the east are the Zagos Mountains.
The thing about Anatolia is it
itself is a very prosperous place.
So it will become eventually
home to certain empires,
like the Hittites, who
will always threaten Mesopotamia, okay?
So Anatolia is a threat to Mesopotamia.
The people of Arabia and
the Zagos Mountains are nomads.
And as we know, nomads are
a very aggressive people.
And so they will constantly
launch raids against Mesopotamia,
which threatens its safety.
Okay? So,
Mesopotamia throughout its history
has always been at war with its neighbors.
The other thing about Mesopotamia is,
even though it's fertile, it's part of
something called a fertile crescent,
okay, which extends from
Mesopotamia into the Levant, okay?
It's called a fertile crescent.
The Euphrates and the Tigris
don't really cooperate.
They're very chaotic. They
change course all the time.
And so, the only way to tame the Euphrates
and the Tigris is through irrigation.
Okay? Because if you farm
too close to the bed,
the river bank, you're
going to get flooded.
Okay? So they have to develop irrigation in
order to tame the Euphrates and the Tigris.
Okay. So, the geography,
all these two cultures are very different,
and therefore the history
is very different.
For most of its history,
Egypt was unified as an empire.
It was very stable. But
Mesopotamia was always in flux, okay?
So the first great civilization
of Mesopotamia were the Sumerians.
They were eventually
conquered by the Akkadians.
And then you have the
Assyrians and the Babylonians.
And these four civilizations
are what we call Mesopotamia,
okay? Okay? Okay, any questions so
far before I go into the
brief history of Mesopotamia?
Okay, yeah, that's a good question, okay.
But what is the relationship
between these four relationships?
The Sumerians, the Akkadians,
the Babylonians, and the Assyrians.
Okay, so the very first
civilization were the Sumerians.
And then they were eventually
united by the Akkadians.
Okay, so Sumeria was not really an empire,
it was a culture and a civilization that
was divided into city -states, like the Greeks
before the conquest of the Macedonians.
And the Akkadians under Sargon of Akkad,
or Sargon the Great,
united the city -states,
and gave us the idea of
Sumerian civilization.
After the Akkadian Empire fell,
North Mesopotamia became
the Assyrian Empire,
South Mesopotamia became
the Babylonian Empire.
They all saw themselves as heirs
to the Sumerian civilization.
So even though they're
different civilizations,
they share a common mythology,
okay, which I will discuss
later in the class.
Okay, does that make
sense? Great, okay, so
I'm gonna talk very briefly
about how Mesopotamia developed,
okay? So, remember
that in the beginning,
agriculture first appeared in two places,
Anatolia and the Levant, okay?
Then there was something called the
8.2 kilo year event.
And we can see this as
dramatic climate change.
That radically changed the geography
and the climate of this world,
okay?
And because of the
cooling and temperature,
the people in the Levant, and the people
in Anatolia were forced to spread out.
So they went to Europe,
they went to Egypt,
they went to Mesopotamia.
And when they did that,
they spread agriculture.
And remember, the
agriculture, the mythology,
is the mother goddess, which meant that
they were mainly peaceful,
egalitarian people, okay,
who were very artistic.
So this is a very peaceful, stable world.
But then, you have the
5.9 kilo year event,
year event. This is about 6,000 years ago,
4,000 BCE.
And again, you saw a radical change
in temperature, which
again forced migration
and
forced these
civilizations to change.
One of the major
changes in Mesopotamia
is the founding of
a place called Uruk.
Uruk is interesting because
it is considered the
first city of the world.
And so this is the beginning
of what we call civilization,
the modern idea of civilization.
And that's about 40,000 people. And
this is what we consider the beginning
of the Sumerian civilization.
And the Sumerian civilization is
considered the cradle of civilization.
It is the beginning of the
foundations of modern civilization.
They gave us irrigation technology.
They gave us mathematics.
They gave us astronomy. They gave
us writing, cuneiform writing.
They gave us the legal system.
They gave us
hierarchy and religion. So
there was an explosion of innovation
with the founding of Uruk.
Now Uruk eventually
would become a huge city,
which compelled the people to migrate
and found cities that are similar to Uruk.
They're basically colonies. And they're
scattered throughout Mesopotamia.
These are city -states that
at first were part of
the Uruk civilization.
But eventually they became prosperous
and wealthy themselves.
And so they broke away from Uruk.
And this led to tension and
conflict and maybe sometimes
even outright warfare.
But please remember, during this time,
the idea of the Uruk, the Uruk
civilization, was massive warfare that
we would see during the
Greek and Roman periods.
It's still pretty
absent. There's conflict.
It's short -term.
And they have conflicts
in order to resolve
like territorial disputes
or trade disputes.
But they're not trying
to wipe each other out.
One of the great mysteries is
where the Sumerians come from.
We have this problem because when
we discovered cuneiform, and we
translated the Sumerian language,
we discovered the spoken language is
very different from
the surrounding regions
who spoke something
called a Semitic language.
So the languages spoken in the area
are part of a Semitic language group.
But Sumerian is not part of that group.
There's not enough similarities.
Also, there is no other language
like Sumerian in the world.
Okay? It's what is called
a language isolate.
It is unique.
And so this has puzzled scholars
for decades. And quite honestly,
no one knows why this is the case.
Okay? No one knows. There
are different theories.
One theory is the Sumerian
people are people
who came from Anatolia and settled in the Middle
East. And they were not the only ones who
settled in the dataset due
to due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due people who
believe the Sumerians are people
who came from the Indus Valley.
Okay, we'll talk about the
Indus Valley next class,
but all you need to know
is the Indus Valley,
it is a very advanced civilization,
it's very large, five million
people, and it covers three
major areas, Afghanistan,
Pakistan, and northwest India.
It is larger than Egypt
and Mesopotamia combined.
Okay, so people believe that
the Indus Valley sent
a colony to Mesopotamia,
which found it in Yorick,
and it makes sense because
it's actually pretty easy to get
from Indus Valley to Yorick
because of the Arabian Sea.
Okay, so
these are the different theories,
but then there's another theory,
okay, which I think makes the
most sense, which is this.
Sumerian is a Creole language.
It was invented by a
melting pot of cultures and languages,
and it's very similar to
the Mandarin we speak today,
right, where Mandarin didn't exist,
but because you had so
many different cultures
coming to the palace,
they had to create their own language
in order to communicate with each other.
And we call that language today Mandarin.
Okay, does that make sense?
Okay, so why do I think
this idea makes the most sense?
And again, just to be
absolutely clear, no one knows,
and we'll probably never know the answer, but
I believe that Sumerian is a Creole language.
This theory makes the most
sense because of this.
Why was Yorick able to
develop into the first city?
What makes it special? The answer is this.
It is at the center of the world.
Okay, so let me explain.
From Yorick, you're able
to access the Indus Valley.
You're able to access the Arabian Desert.
You're able to go north to Anatolia
and the Zagreus Mountains, okay.
And these civilizations we
know traded with each other
due to due due due due due due
due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
That explains why Europe
was able to prosper
so fast, because it's
the center of the world.
To get anywhere, you have
to go for your Earth, okay?
But if that's the case, if it's
a trading center of the world,
it makes sense for it to
be also a multicultural
and
multilingual community of people, right?
Because these traders from Arabia,
Anatolia, the Zagos Mountains, also
let's not forget about the Yemeni,
okay, who are up here in the steppes.
They also trade with these people.
People from the Innis Valley, it makes sense for
them to come together in a training community
and develop their own language and their
own culture, which eventually spreads.
Also, because this is a melting pot,
it's really an immigrant culture,
they're able to bring the most advanced
ideas from all around the world
and combine them together, which
creates new inventions like writing,
like legal system, like mathematics,
like astronomy, okay?
And that's why Samaria became
the cradle of civilization,
because of the meeting place
of the world's cultures
and ideas.
And because of the very
instability of the environment,
okay, meaning they have to
tame the Tigris and Euphrates,
and because they were always
threatened by outside enemies,
they had to develop a new culture,
a new mythology based on struggle, right?
The Egyptians can afford to
be passive and fatalistic.
Let the gods decide.
But because this is an immigrant community,
they have to focus on struggle and attack. Yeah,
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah
yeah with Mesopotamian
mythology to show how the geographic
and cultural difference
translates into the mythology,
the shared reality of the people, okay?
So let's look at Egypt first.
All right, so again, Egypt, it's
a very ancient civilization,
and their mythology is extremely complex.
They have different versions
of the same stories, okay?
But I'm gonna give you the generalization,
which will be useful
for our purposes, okay?
So let's look at Egypt. So, and
then we'll look at Mesopotamia.
Okay, Egypt. Egypt believed
the first god was Ra,
okay? There are other gods
who they believed to be the first
god, like Atum and Amon, okay?
But let's just say the first
god is Ra, who is a sun god.
He comes to our world, and
he creates life, okay?
He basically gives life
to everything, okay?
Including humans.
And as such, we worship him.
But eventually, we start
to become misguided,
and we start to worship. And we start
to worship another god, a false god.
Ra becomes angry and kills many of us.
But after he kills many of
us, he has tremendous regret,
and he decides his time is up.
He should give his throne
to someone else, okay?
And this other god becomes Osiris.
Osiris is a great god, because
he gives people civilization,
which includes cities,
which includes the pyramids,
which includes writing, okay?
So it's Osiris who gives us civilization.
Now here's a brother named Set.
And Set is very jealous of the fact
that Osiris is worshiped by the people.
So he plots to usurp
the throne from Osiris.
So what he does is this. He builds
a sarcophagus, a tomb, okay?
He presents to Osiris and says,
Osiris, my great king,
this sarcophagus is the most beautiful
and comfortable sarcophagus in the world.
You will love lying in here.
And Osiris is like,
oh, that's interesting.
Let me try. So
Osiris gets into the sarcophagus,
and Set closes it forever, okay?
Then he kills Osiris
and dismembers his body.
Osiris has a wife, Isis, and when
he hears about the death of her husband,
she looks for his body
and assembles it together.
But she can't find the head. And then
Osiris becomes the god
of the underworld, okay?
After Osiris is reassembled,
he impregnates Isis.
They have a son named Horus.
Horus eventually grows up,
and he's angered by the fact
that his uncle, Set,
has usurped the throne.
He's going to usurp his throne, okay?
So the two are going to battle.
And the gods, who judge all, tell them
they have to challenge
each other to a duel, okay?
So they have a series of duels.
One duel is they both
turn into hippopotamus,
and they try to stay in the river
for the longest time possible.
Horus sees this as an opportunity
to kill, you know, Set.
He tells his mother, Isis,
while Set is distracted,
while he's a hippopotamus,
take a spear and kill him.
And Isis agrees. But when
she tries to kill Set,
she is paralyzed with fear, and she fails.
Horus, in anger, strikes,
beheads her mother.
He doesn't kill her,
but she loses her head.
That's how angry he is, okay?
So Isis and Horus
continue their challenge.
Eventually, Set decides to poison Horus.
But before he can do so,
Horus first poisons him.
Okay? Then Horus becomes king, and
he gives Egypt the
institution of kingship.
So every pharaoh is a
direct descendant of Horus,
or another reincarnation of Horus, okay?
That is the Egyptian situation.
Egyptian myth of creation.
Now, the Mesopotamians, okay,
they have a different myth of
creation called the Enuma Elesh,
from up high.
Okay? The Enuma Elesh.
And this is the story of the Enuma Elesh.
There are two gods.
The first god is Tiamat,
who is basically salt water, okay?
Then you have Apsu, who is fresh water.
The two great gods get together,
and they give birth to other gods, okay?
They're children. These gods then
give birth to other gods, okay?
Eventually, Apsu gets
annoyed with his children
because children are
loud, and he can't sleep.
So he resolves to kill
all his children and...
bring peace to the world.
Tiamat finds out about
Apsu's diabolical plan,
and he warns, she warns her children.
The gods get together, and they kill Apsu.
Tiamat is enraged by the
death of her consort,
and she resolves to raise a great army
and destroy her children, okay?
The gods get together, and
they elect Marduk,
who is the son of the god.
So he's basically a third
-generation god, okay?
They elect Marduk to lead
them in battle against Tiamat,
okay? So you have these two massive
armies converging against each other,
and then Tiamat turns
into a huge water serpent
and challenges Marduk to a duel.
They fight, okay?
Marduk unleashes whirlwinds,
into the mouth of Tiamat,
and that sort of like, dizzies her,
and then Marduk strikes her down.
After he kills her,
she uses her body to create the world.
She uses half of her body
to create the sky, and
she uses another half of the body
to create the continents, okay?
He creates the moons,
and he creates the stars.
He creates the entire universe,
basically, from the body of Tiamat.
After that,
the gods all decide to rest in peace,
but they need people to take care of them.
They need people to watch the land,
to farm and till the land.
So they create humans
as their slaves, okay?
Humans. Humans.
And that's how the Enem -Elish ends,
okay? Each city has...
Each city has its own god, and the
humans in that city must revere
and take care of that god to be
their slave for all of eternity,
okay? All right,
so as you can see right away,
there are massive differences between
Egyptian mythology and
Mesopotamian mythology,
okay?
The first major difference
is the gods are benevolent,
right? The gods give us everything.
We just sit back, and the
gods will give us light.
They will give us civilization.
They will give us kingship.
They will give us the pyramids. So
all we have to do is respect
and revere and worship the gods.
We humans don't need to participate
in the order of things.
But, in the Enem -Elish,
we find out that gods
are extremely violent,
and they demand our servitude.
They are our masters, okay? So
we must constantly work
to please the gods.
That's one major difference. Second
major difference is, as you can see,
from the Egyptian mythology,
the main virtues of the
gods are, due due due
due due due due due due
due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due
And this is no different
from China, right?
Because remember in China, we have
something called Shunzi Bingfa,
the art of war by Shunzi.
That is a manual on
palace intrigue, right?
How to trick other people.
It's not a manual on how to go to war.
Okay? But
here, the value
that
is most prominent in Mesopotamia
is bravery or strength.
Okay, not cleverness.
There's no trickery going on.
It's just pure power, pure bravery.
Okay? And
the third major difference is in Egypt,
they believe the gods.
Are helping each other.
Okay, they build on top
of each other's legacy.
That's what progress is.
That's what improvement is.
But in Mesopotamia, they believe in
something called creative destruction.
Which is to say, in order
to create something new,
you must destroy the old.
Okay? Tiamat represents the old.
Therefore, she must be destroyed.
And from the old, you can.
Okay? Build a new civilization.
But you must first destroy the old.
And conflict is a source of creativity.
Okay, does that make sense?
And again, they have these
two different mythologies,
because they're reflecting the shared
reality of the different geographies
and history. Okay?
So, they're both in the same
place. Any questions so far?
Before I continue?
Are you clear? Okay, great.
Great. Okay. All right.
Let's continue. All right.
Okay. So, both Egypt
and both Mesopotamia,
they are in a struggle to prove
their mythologies are the best.
Okay? The reason why is, remember that
this is a time when
all these civilizations are
trading with each other.
But also what's important
to understand is,
there's a lot of migration going on.
And people have a choice.
If you're not happy here, you
can always move somewhere else.
Okay? There isn't any idea of
like nation or culture or race.
People have autonomy.
Okay? So, you need to
constantly prove that
your civilization is the
best to attract people,
which provides the labor
to drive your civilization.
Right? So,
the Egyptians created
something called the pyramids.
The pyramids. To show
the people around them,
we are favored by the gods.
Because they're the ones who are
favored. Because it's only the gods who
could inspire us to build the pyramids.
Okay? So now,
the people in Mesopotamia have a problem.
Because how do you compete
against the pyramids?
Right? I mean, at first they tried.
They created things called the ziggurats.
The ziggurats, which are
temples to house the gods.
Okay? But then, they did something
that was completely different.
And which made them immortal.
Just as the pyramids
made Egyptians immortal.
They created something
called the Epic of Gilgamesh.
And today,
we celebrate the Epic of Gilgamesh as
the first work of world literature.
Okay? So,
let me first explain the plot
of the Epic of Gilgamesh.
And show you how it works.
How it reflects Mesopotamian
culture and values.
And then explain the meaning of it.
So, the Epic of Gilgamesh.
So, there was a king of Uruk.
Okay? The first city.
Uruk. And he's the king of the first city.
And he's a demigod.
Okay? He's huge.
He's a giant. And he's very brave.
The first city. The problem is, even
though he's built this great city, Uruk.
High walls. Prosperous land.
Advanced civilization. He
gets bored very quickly.
And he starts to bully
the people around him.
So, he sees young men.
He challenges them to a fight.
And he beats them up. Okay? He's a bully.
He also rapes all the young women in Uruk.
And this drives their parents
to pray to the gods for relief.
So, the gods decide to create
an equal to Gilgamesh.
And his name is Enkidu. Enkidu.
And Enkidu is made of clay.
The two fight.
And even though Gilgamesh
defeats Enkidu in battle.
He's defeated. Gilgamesh is happy
because he thinks he's
found a good friend.
Someone who is equal. Who he
can share adventures with.
So, the two become great friends.
The best of friends. They go
on these adventures together.
And these adventures are
tremendous challenges.
For example, they
challenge gods to battle.
And at first they're afraid.
But through their friendship
and through their bravery.
They're able to triumph in the end.
There's a god named Ishtar.
And she falls in love with
Gilgamesh because he's so heroic.
But Gilgamesh rebuffs Ishtar.
Because Gilgamesh basically knows
that Ishtar wants to turn
him into her sex slave.
He doesn't want that.
He wants his freedom.
He wants to prove he's a great hero.
Ishtar feels rejected.
Feels ashamed. So, she says.
She sends someone called the
Bull of Heaven to destroy Uruk.
Gilgamesh and Enkidu
fight the Bull of Heaven.
And they kill this great bull.
The gods now are really pissed
off at Gilgamesh and Enkidu.
And they decide that Enkidu must die.
So, they inflict a disease on Enkidu.
Which kills him. At this point,
Gilgamesh is heartbroken.
He's lost his best friend.
At the same time, he knows
death is waiting for him.
He has all these accomplishments.
He's a great king. He's
built this great city.
But eventually he must die.
And he does not want
to die. He fears death.
So, he hears about this immortal man.
This man who has lived forever.
And who will live forever. And
he decides to seek him out.
On his journey. He has
to overcome many hurdles.
And along the journey. Along the
journey, everyone implores him.
Gilgamesh, give up this vain project.
Immortality is for the gods.
We are humans. We must die.
That's what makes us
different from the gods.
Enjoy your life.
Drink. Be merry.
But Gilgamesh refuses to turn back.
And he insists.
On continuing on his journey.
Eventually, he finds this immortal man.
Who explains to him.
He was made immortal.
Because he survived the great flood.
The gods created humans.
But the humans became too loud.
For the gods. So the gods
resolved to kill them.
But this man.
This one man was favored.
By one god. So he was
told about this plot.
And he built a boat.
And put a lot of animals in the boat.
In order to escape.
And this is the basis of the
story of the north's flood.
In the bible. Okay.
After the flood receded.
This man came down.
And built an altar. To worship the gods.
The gods felt regret for what they did.
So to compensate.
They promised. Never to do this again.
To never destroy humanity again.
And also. They grant this man immortality.
Okay. So.
But this is just a one off.
The gods would never do this again.
And so the man tells Gilgamesh.
The search for immortality.
It's pointless. Just go home.
But Gilgamesh refuses to give up.
So the man challenges Gilgamesh.
To not sleep for seven days.
Seven nights and six days.
Sorry. Six days and seven.
Six nights and seven days.
Okay. Gilgamesh tries.
But he can't do it. So it's all futile.
And then he goes home. But
the moment he goes home.
He has an epiphany. He sees
the great walls of Urich.
He sees the people happy in Urich.
And he realizes. This
is what immortality is.
Immortality is. Not living forever.
Immortality is.
To be remembered.
By the people who love you.
So the irony of all this is.
He goes on this search for immortality.
He fails. But because
he goes on this search.
Because he goes on this quest.
He becomes immortal. Because his story.
His struggle. His struggle. Is remembered
and celebrated by the people
in the Epic of Gilgamesh.
Okay. So this is a reflection
of the values of Mesopotamia.
The point is in the achievement.
The point is not in the victory.
The point is in the exploration.
The point is in the struggle.
And that's why the Mesopotamians
were so innovative.
But that's also why they went to
war with each other all the time.
And this is the beginning
of the idea of literature,
where
memories can be shaped in such a way
that becomes so beautiful that
it becomes implanted in the
minds of others for centuries,
centuries, centuries, centuries,
centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries,
centuries,
centuries, centuries,
centuries, centuries, centuries,
centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries,
centuries, centuries,
centuries, centuries, Egypt.
But the Epic of Gilgamesh is also a
testament to the tremendous creativity of
that civilization. And if you think about
it, the Epic of Gilgamesh was written
because it is in a dialectic
with the pyramids, right?
The Epic of Gilgamesh is
also saying to the pyramids,
immortality it is an illusion.
Eventually these pyramids will collapse.
For the Pharaoh to seek
immortality is an illusion.
What matters is for the Pharaoh to look
after the well -being of his people here
and now because that's why he will
be loved and remembered for eternity.
He will die if
his people die. But
if your people live on
because of your contributions,
then you'll remember forever.
You'll become immortal. Right?
And that's the story of Gilgamesh.
Any questions?
Is this all pretty clear?
Okay. Alright. So
I will make a final point
about these stories,
okay? Within these stories,
we can see the evolution of the world.
Of societies over time.
Okay? So let's go back to
the story of the Enuma Elesh.
So, remember, Tiamat and
Apsu create the world.
That's the first story.
Then, the gods are created, okay?
And then they inhabit the
world, that second story.
And then, Tiamat and Marduk go to war.
And then, from the victory of this war,
before Marduk creates the universe.
So basically we're seeing three different
mythologies embedded within this mythology,
which gives us the idea of
social change and evolution,
Mesopenia, at this time.
The first story is Tiamat.
Who is Tiamat? She's the mother goddess.
She's the one who gives life.
So this shows Mesopenia as
an agricultural society.
Then you have the emergence of the gods,
which the urban people would celebrate.
And then finally you have the
battle between Tiamat and Marduk.
And this shows the battle between
the old society with the new society,
okay? The urban and the agricultural.
The agricultural, it is egalitarian,
it is peaceful.
The urban is patriarchal, right?
So why, how do we explain,
or how do you justify the transition
from an equal society to a patriarchy?
The answer is this. The answer is
embedded in the mythology, right?
Tiamat represents chaos.
Marduk represents order.
So even though we are letting go of
the old, we're destroying the old,
it's to create a more peaceful,
peaceful and orderly world.
So remember, Tiamat is the water serpent.
And for the longest time,
we believe the water
serpent to represent life
and divinity.
Why? Because if you think about it,
the water serpent looks like the river.
And the river is the basis
of all civilization, right?
So, and this is true
for most civilizations.
In China, what do we
call the water serpent?
What do we call the
water serpent in China?
Long, right?
The problem is the river floods.
And if you flood too much,
you destroy civilization.
So it's chaotic, okay?
And that's why it's important
to have a patriarchy
or an urban elite,
because they can help us,
command us, to create irrigation,
to build walls, which
will tame the river and the water serpent.
Okay, does that make sense?
So within this mythology,
we are seeing the evolution
of society from an egalitarian
one to a patriarchy,
okay? Yeah,
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
Right, because remember,
the story starts with the king
going on all these adventures.
Okay, the story ends
with the king coming back
and recognizing what matters is
the well -being of his people.
And for that, you need a bureaucracy
to manage everyday affairs.
Okay? And so this represents,
you can interpret this as
representing the beginning
of a bureaucratic elite,
which will help the king
order the world in a way
that brings more stability
and prosperity to the people.
Okay? But first, the king
must recognize his own hubris.
He must become humble.
So the great fear of the Mesopotamians
is their king will become like a pharaoh
who will channel all resources
to build this monument,
which will create
inequality, corruption, and
waste in society, which
will lead to massive suffering
during times of drought.
Okay? Okay.
Okay, any questions?
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
that would change over time.
The thing about Sumeria is
because it's trading and because
there are different city -states,
this becomes a hotbed of innovation
because if one city -state creates
a really good irrigation system,
another city -state could
just copy it really easily.
Does that make sense?
Any more questions?
Okay. Okay, so next class,
we'll discuss the Indus
Valley civilization,
okay? And the Indus Valley civilization,
if we just use the analysis we did today,
where basically geography is destiny,
you would think the Indus Valley civilization
is very much like the Egyptian civilization
where you have a monarchy, you
have centralized authority,
where they build these
great monuments, okay?
The irony is when
you look at the Indus Valley civilization,
and it's a huge, huge civilization,
they have very advanced technology.
They have these big cities
that are very well designed.
They have plumbing, they have sanitation.
They even have air conditioning.
They have these towers.
That sort of like trap hot air.
People live for a very long time.
I think over half of the
population will live past 55,
which is incredible, which
is an incredible achievement.
But what is startling
about the civilization,
the Indus Valley civilization is,
it's peaceful and it's egalitarian.
So it's a complete
mystery as to why they're
so different from the other civilizations.
So, the reason why they're so different is
because they're so different from Egypt and Mesopotamia, okay, because again, Egypt, it's a centralized empire.
Mesopotamia is always at war.
So, next class,
we will look at the Indus
Valley civilization
and try to resolve the paradox
as to why it is advanced,
prosperous, but at the same
time, peaceful and egalitarian.