Okay, so
we are starting an
overview of Greek history.
Remember the story so far.
We talked about the Bronze Age and
where Mycenaean Greece was trading
and fighting with the rest of the world.
And then the Bronze Age
collapse happened and
Mycenaean Greece came to an end.
And because of its destruction,
this allowed for massive
innovation throughout Greece.
So we saw the introduction of
the polis, the city -state.
We saw the beginning of
the use of the alphabet.
And so literacy rates increased
radically throughout Greece.
And we saw Homer who gave us the Iliad
and the Odyssey.
So today,
I'm just going to go over the
overview of Greek history,
mainly focusing on the polis.
So one thing to understand
about the polis is
that geography is destiny.
Geography is destiny.
And this basically means that
your geography will determine the culture,
the economy, and
the political structure of your society.
And we see that with the Greek polis.
The Greek geography is very diverse.
There are mountains, there are rivers,
there are plains, and
there are coastlines.
And depending on where
you are geographically in Greece,
you will have a different type of polis.
And so the two classic
examples are Sparta and Athens.
Sparta and Athens are the two most
dominant polis in about the year 500 BC.
So let's first talk about Sparta.
So Sparta is located on the Pelonese.
This is Sparta.
And the land around Sparta
is basically plains,
which makes it ideal for agriculture.
Okay? So for most of its history,
Sparta was an agricultural nation.
And because
it is ideal for agriculture,
it needs people to work the land.
And through its conquest,
Sparta developed a slave system.
Okay? And these people are called helots.
And helots are just slaves in Sparta
that work the land. They are farmers.
And these are people who have
been conquered by Sparta.
And because there are so many helots,
okay, the ratio is about 10 to 1.
So for every one helot, sorry, for
every one Spartan, there's 10 helots.
Sparta had to become a military
society in order to control the helots.
So it created an education system in
order to train its
citizens to be soldiers.
So the system worked like this.
About age 7, you left your family
and you were put into
a boarding school where
you were watched over by kids
who were older than you.
Okay? Maybe 11 or 12.
And obviously, you put
young kids with older kids,
the older kids will beat the
crap out of these young kids
who are about 7 or 8. And
this instills the idea of emotional
discipline into the system.
And this is what happened to the children.
Now, when these children became teenagers,
they were paired with a mentor
who was maybe 25 to about 30, okay?
An older adult. And they became lovers.
The Spartans did not
consider this homosexuality.
We would consider it homosexuality.
But they themselves did not
consider this homosexuality.
Okay? They just considered this as a
way to build emotional cohesion,
love among its soldiers.
And about age 18 or 19,
the students would graduate and
they would go on to marry
and have their own families.
But the Spartan soldiers were
all required to eat together.
Okay? So the soldiers, even though they had
families, they were still required to eat together.
They were required to train
together and to eat together.
Spartans had no private property.
Everything, including the
helots, belonged to everyone.
Okay? So it's basically like
communism or proto -communism.
They had no money system.
They had no wealth. Everything
belonged to everyone.
And it was a brutal state.
The Spartans were notorious
for being brutal people.
So an example is the helots.
So they had a campaign of terror to
maintain control over the helots.
So young soldiers would often be
required to patrol at night.
Okay? They would maybe lie in the fields.
Because now and then, some
helots would break curfew.
They would, at midnight, try
to sneak out and have some fun.
And if you, as a Spartan young man,
saw a Spartan, you would say,
I saw a helot be out at night.
Well, they would kill you.
They would take out a knife and
stab you in the neck. Okay? And
this was meant to instill terror
in the helots to prevent
them from rebelling.
Okay? But the problem
is, because there were so
many helots, and the
Spartans were so brutal,
rebellions and revolutions
would break out often.
Okay? So this created a society
which focused on the helots.
And this focused on maintaining
control in the Pelonese.
So the Spartans were not at all
interested in foreign policy.
Okay? They had absolutely no
interest in the world outside Sparta.
The Spartans, as a culture,
was very conservative.
Okay? They liked the way that...
They liked the way...
They wanted things to stay the way...
They are. So it was a
very conformist culture.
Now and then you had
some kings or individuals
who tried to change society.
The Spartans would kill those people.
Okay? You were not allowed
to question authority.
You were not allowed to
promote change in Sparta.
The Spartans were also isolationists.
Okay? Their entire society was
a society of isolationists.
Their entire policy was, if you leave
us alone, we'll leave you alone.
Okay? And so that
was the society of Sparta.
When you think about it, in many ways,
it's very much like China
throughout its history.
Okay? So the analogy is China,
which China has always been,
throughout its history,
very conservative and very isolationist.
China is just not interested in
the outside world. Why? Because
it's focused on maintaining
control over its peasantry.
Okay? There's too much internal chaos.
China just is not interested
in the outside world.
So China, for its history, has both
been conservative, does not like change.
Okay? And very isolationist.
It's not concerned
about the outside world.
Does that make sense,
guys? Any questions so
far about Sparta before
I move on to Athens?
Okay. So Athens was a completely
opposite society to Sparta.
And the reason why, again, is geography.
This is Sparta. Sorry, this is Athens.
And Athens is in Attica.
And it's by the coast.
And Athens, the countryside is very hilly.
So it's bad for growing crops.
But Athens has two major advantages.
The first major advantage is
it has a very good harbor.
Okay? And also,
it's hilly.
But the hilly terrain is actually
good for growing olive trees.
Okay? Olives. It's also
very good at pottery.
So because of this, Athens,
for most of its history, focused on trade.
Right? It was a trading nation.
And because they are traders and merchants,
they are also very good at trading.
So they have a very different
culture to the Spartans.
Okay? So the first thing is
they're very expansionist.
Okay? They're aggressive. And
the idea here is the Athens will
go and seek out new markets.
They also plant new
colonies throughout the Aegean.
To the west is the Aegean Sea.
To the south is the Mediterranean.
Okay? And they will plant
colonies throughout this area.
And they have to encourage
their citizens to go out
and explore the world in
order to find new markets,
in order to bring goods and
ideas back to Athens.
Okay? Because
Athens was expansionist,
its cultural system,
its cultural beliefs was very different.
From the Spartans.
Okay? So whereas the Spartans
were very conservative,
the Athenians had a policy,
had a belief in the idea of eudaimonia.
Eudaimonia. So
eudaimonia is a Greek word
and it means human flourishing.
Flourishing. And
the idea here is to be
the best that you can be.
All right? So the example of eudaimonia,
the most famous example
of eudaimonia is this.
In Homer's Iliad, the main
character is Achilles.
And Achilles is the best warrior
of the Greeks against Troy.
And Achilles says this in the book.
He says, before I came
to Troy, I saw a prophet.
I saw a fortune teller
and he told me my fortune.
He said I could choose
to not come to Troy.
And live to be a, live a very long,
healthy life.
But I'd be a nobody.
If I came to Troy, I would die
young, but I would die as a hero.
I would be remembered by everyone.
Everyone would sing of
my glory and my triumph.
So that was my choice. I could live for
a very long time and just be a nobody.
Or I could be a hero and die young.
And he said, well for
me, that's not a choice.
Okay? For me,
to be alive means to achieve eudaimonia.
I have to be the best that I can be.
And therefore, my only
option is to come to Troy
and die a hero.
Okay? And that's the mentality in Athens.
It is much better to die young as a hero
than to live a long time as a nobody.
Whereas in Spartans, we're
the complete opposite.
Okay? It's just better to be a nobody and
get along with everyone
than it is to die as a hero.
Okay? So very opposite societies.
But, and what this did,
this idea of eudaimonia,
it made Athens into a
very competitive society.
Okay? Because if everyone's
trying to achieve eudaimonia,
then you're going to have
a lot of competition.
Okay? Because they're
going to be one hero.
Everyone cannot be a hero.
They're going to be one hero.
So again, the example is Homer's Iliad.
And when Achilles got into
a fight with Agamemnon,
Achilles basically says, I don't like you.
You're a dog. I'm not
going to fight for you.
And Agamemnon says, I don't need you.
What Achilles did was,
he went to his mother,
who was a goddess, and
Achilles said to Thetis, his mother,
could you please get the
gods to help the Trojans
so that
Agamemnon would have to come beg
for my help against the Trojans.
Okay? He was basically committing treason.
And in the Greek world,
you're allowed to do that
because the most important
thing is eudaimonia.
To achieve eudaimonia.
Okay? Does that make sense?
It's a very weird world, but
in Athens, it's extremely
competitive where
everyone's trying to backstab each
other in order to become the hero.
And because of this, because
there's so much competition,
Athens created a new
system called ostracize.
Okay? So the idea here is, because
the Athenians were so
at each other's throat,
if someone was breaking the rules,
or if someone was being too competitive
in the pursuit of eudaimonia,
the Athenian people could
choose to ostracize this person.
And what this meant
was, you'd be banished,
okay, banished or exiled
from Athens for ten years.
And this was considered
even worse than death.
Okay, this punishment
was worse than death.
The reason why is, in the Polish system,
the only people that
mattered were citizens.
Okay? And
the Greek world was very chauvinistic,
or closed, which meant
that you could not be,
you could not earn the
right to be a citizen.
You had to be born to become a citizen.
You understand? You had to
be born into citizenship.
You could not become a citizen
for your own hard work
and for your merit. Okay,
does that make sense?
So in other words, if you were banished
from your Polish, you became a nobody.
You were basically dead to everyone.
Because only citizens had
rights in the Greek world.
If you were a slave, or you were a
foreigner, you had absolutely no rights.
You could not own land, you
could not even speak in public.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
Um, so,
Athens was a democracy.
Where everyone had the
right to speak and to vote.
Okay? But really, when we talk
about democracy in this world,
we're not saying that everyone could become
president, or everyone could become a leader.
Really, political power can
only be held by people of,
um, nobility.
Okay? So democracy usually
was a battle between
different factions of the nobility.
Usually between the upper nobility,
and the lower nobility.
Okay? And this is a lesson
that's true throughout history.
Okay? So remember,
usually we think history,
societies, um, the conflict is
between the haves and the have -nots.
Right? The poor and the rich.
All right? Haves
versus have -nots.
Whatever you do, what I would teach you in
this class, one important thing I would teach you in this class is, this is not true.
Okay? When you look at history,
the conflicts in society are
usually between the have a lot
and have somewhat more.
Does that make sense? Okay?
It's usually between the have a lot
versus the have some
but I want more.
Okay? And throughout history, we
call these people different names.
So, um,
in this society, these are
basically the low nobility.
Okay? These are the
nobility who have money
but they want more.
Okay? And, um,
in the French Revolution,
we'll call them the petite bourgeoisie.
And today, we call them the middle class.
Okay? Does that make sense?
The poor people do not rebel.
They might riot, but they do not revolt.
It's usually the middle
class, or the low nobility,
or the petite bourgeoisie that revolt.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So, Athens is a democracy and
it's usually a conflict between the
upper nobility and the lower nobility.
Um, Sparta is an oligarchy.
Okay? Which is, basically,
means ruled by the few.
And they hate democracy. So, so,
these systems, these
cultures, Sparta and Athens,
are diametrically opposed to each other.
They hate each other. Uh, they're
always in conflict with each other.
Okay? Does that make sense? Any
questions so far about Sparta and Athens?
Are you guys clear about this?
These two different cultures?
All right. So, this is
about the year 500 BCE.
Um, around this time, the
Greeks are colonizing,
uh, the Mediterranean and the Aegean.
Okay? And this territory
belongs to Persia.
The Persian Empire is
considered one of the greatest empires
ever in human history. We will do the
Persian Empire, uh, later this semester.
Okay? But I want to focus
on the Greeks for now.
All you need to know is,
the Persian Empire spread
throughout most of the world,
including Egypt, uh, Mesopotamia,
um, and what we call Iran today.
Okay? It was a huge, huge empire
that was extremely enlightened
for its age.
Okay? It was really considered,
uh, the best empire at that time.
Uh, um, and there were Greeks who lived
in, uh, Anatolia or what
they call Asia Minor back
then. The thing about
the Persian Empire is,
if you were a subject city, you could do
whatever you want, but you have to pay taxes.
And these people did
not like to pay taxes.
So, they revolted.
And, and this is the
reason why they revolted.
they went to Sparta and
to Athens and sought help.
Okay? They basically said,
look, we're all Greeks, uh,
we're being oppressed by the
Persians, could you please help us?
What did the Spartans say?
What was the Spartan response?
No. Because we don't care, okay?
Your problem, not my problem.
Well, and what did the Athenians say?
Yeah, sure. Let's achieve eudaimonia, man.
Let's be Achilles. Let's go over
and help them and maybe make a
lot of money for ourselves, okay?
So, because the Persian
Empire was so powerful,
they destroyed the rebellion, okay?
And, in 490 BCE,
uh, the Persians decided to attack
Greece to teach the Athenians a lesson.
And this was called
the Battle of Marathon.
And in the Battle of Marathon, um, we
actually don't know that much about it,
The sourcing is very limited.
But, what they say, okay, is,
in the Battle of Marathon,
there are about 10,000 Athenians
versus 25,000 Persians.
That's a huge advantage
for the Persians, right?
Well, the Athenians
destroyed the Persians,
okay? The Athenians lost about 192 men.
The Persians lost about 5,000.
It was a slaughter. And a lot of the
reason why is in the Battle of Marathon, the Persians used military tactics.
So, the Persian Empire
is huge.
Okay? Lots of flat land.
And in this geography,
the, your main advantage is
cavalry, right? Horse archers.
That's what the Persians were known for.
Men on horses who would run
around and shoot arrows at you.
Okay? The geography of
Greece was different.
It was hilly. So,
you didn't really use cavalry.
It was more mainly infantry
fighting against each other.
What the Greeks did over hundreds of years
was develop a new military
tactic called hoplites.
So hoplite comes from the word hoplin.
Hoplin is Greek for shield.
So these are men with
large shields and spears.
The way they fought was
using the phalanx formation.
The innovation of the phalanx
was it was basically a wall.
So men would stand together and
behind each other so
that they made a wall.
And because they had these shields
and spears, it was a moving wall.
And the Persians didn't have armor.
So when men of armor went to
battle with men without armor,
usually armor wins. So the Greeks,
the Athenians, destroyed the
Persians at the Battle of Marathon.
That made the Persians even more angry.
So in about 480 BCE,
Persia organized a massive
invasion force against Greece.
And this massive invasion force, again.
The numbers,
the data, we can't confirm it.
But we think it's about
half a million people.
Half a million soldiers.
That's huge. Okay?
But not only that, you
had a huge navy. And
basically Persia called on every nation
of its empire to fight against Greece.
Which included Egypt.
Which included the Phoenicians.
Which also included Greeks.
Which also included Greeks. And they
lived in the territory of Persia.
And these Greeks are
called the Ionian Greeks.
So it was a massive invasion force.
And Sparta and
Athens became allies to
resist the Persian invasion.
But there were also
some Greek policies that
sided with the Persians, including Thebes.
Okay? The Macedonians to the north
was also a big part of the invasion.
And also siding with the Persians.
So the invasion came north
from Macedonia down here.
And you may have heard of
the Battle of Thermopylae.
The Thermopylae. This was made
famous by a movie called 300.
I'm not sure if you've
seen the movie 300. Okay?
But basically it was
about 300 Spartans and
about 5,000 other Greeks who
tried to make a stand
against the Persian invasion.
And they got destroyed. Okay?
So the Spartans, so the Persians came in
and the Greeks decided,
okay, you know what?
Their numbers are so
much bigger than ours.
Let's retreat. Okay? Back to Sparta.
And here at Corinth,
they decided to build a wall
to stop the Persian invasion.
The problem though is Athens is here.
Okay? So the Persians came in
and burned down Athens. Now.
What's important to understand is
the Greeks have the concept of polis.
It's not a place.
It's a community. Okay?
A polis is wherever the
Greeks choose to be.
So what happened that's
very interesting is even
though the Athens came to destroy,
sorry, even though Persia
came to destroy Athens,
the Athenians just got into their ships.
Okay? They just boarded their ships
because Athens is a naval power
and they just sailed away.
Okay? Do you understand? So
Athens was not destroyed.
The city of Athens was
destroyed, but not the community,
the polis of Athens.
And so, but now the Greeks
are in a lot of trouble.
Okay? Because
what the Persians can
now do is
basically take their ships
and sail around and attack
Sparta from behind.
And this is a huge problem for Sparta.
Because what happens? Why?
What is Sparta's ultimate weakness?
Why is it so easy to
defeat Sparta in a war?
What's the problem? Do you guys remember?
What are the Spartans really afraid of?
The helots, right? Okay?
The helots. Remember, there's
10 helots for every one Spartan.
And the helots hate the Spartans
because the Spartans are terrorizing,
have terrorized them for centuries.
So all that Persia has to do now, okay?
Very easy, is take their ships,
land on Sparta, and build forts,
defenses, and the helots
would run into them.
Then the king, King Xerxes of Persia says,
I, the benevolent king of Persia,
declare the helots to be free people now.
Now you have a revolution, okay?
The helots are now armed by the Persians.
And guess what? The Persians are going to,
the helots are going to kill the Spartans.
Okay? Game over, okay? You understand?
The war is over.
That's all the Persians have to do.
Take their ships, sail around
to the coast of Sparta,
build forts and defenses so
that the helots can run to them,
give the helots weapons, and then
let the helots run loose against
the Spartans, and the war is over.
Greece is forever destroyed.
Okay? You understand? Very simple, right?
The Persians did not do that.
Okay? The Persian king,
King Xerxes, had a war council.
And there were a lot of generals
who said to King Xerxes,
King, we've won the war.
Okay? We're all over Greece. We
have half a million men in Greece.
There's nothing the
Greeks can do about this.
Okay? So, the Persians were
feeling very confident.
And the Greeks,
the Greek navy was on an
island called Salamis.
Okay? Salamis. And
everyone was freaking out.
Okay? And what the Spartans
wanted to do was say,
let's take our navy and defend
the coastline of Sparta.
Because we know the Persians are
going to invade Sparta at some point.
They're going to land
their ships on Sparta.
Let's take our navy and
defend Sparta.
There was one Athenian general, okay?
His name is Phemistocles.
Phemistocles. And he said, okay.
You know what? That's great for you guys.
Okay? But remember, our city,
Athens, has been destroyed.
We need to take on the Persians head on.
We can't wait. And the Spartans are like,
yeah, that's fine.
But the outnumber is three to one.
They have three more ships. They have
three ships for every one ship we have.
There's no way we can beat
them in a naval battle.
And Phemistocles says, we
either fight the Persians now
and achieve eudaimonia or we,
Athens, we'll be like, okay.
Screw you, Spartans. We're
going to go take our ship and
sail off west to Sicily or Africa.
Who cares? Okay? But
we're going to go away.
And we're going to leave the
Persians to kill you guys.
Okay? So Spartans say, no, we don't have a
choice but to listen to Athenians and fight.
Then what Phemistocles did was
he sent a spy to King Xerxes.
And King Xerxes was having this
war council about what to do.
And most of his generals were
like, James, you're going to die.
My great king, we've won the war.
Let's just take our ships and
attack Sparta and the war is over.
Okay? Then a spy sent by
Phemistocles says to King Xerxes,
oh, great king,
the entire Greek navy is stuck in Salamis.
But they want to run away.
Now's your chance to attack them and
destroy the Greek navy once and for all.
Okay? And at this point,
King Xerxes says, no.
I made the decision to
send his entire navy,
okay, to destroy the
Greek navy at Salamis.
And his generals were
like, don't do that, man.
That's a risk you don't have to take.
Why do that? Why take the Greeks on?
Why fight the Greeks head on
when we can just starve them out?
And King Xerxes said, no,
I came to defeat the Greeks.
Okay? I'm the great king.
I want to defeat them at Salamis.
And build a monument to celebrate
my great victory over the Greeks.
My father, King Darius,
set an army in 490 B.C.
And the Athenians killed or
destroyed his army at Marathon.
I'm going to prove I'm a greater king than
my father by defeating
the Greeks at Salamis.
Okay? I don't want this war
of attrition, this slow war.
I want one great battle so that
history will remember me forever.
Okay? So he sends his entire force,
about a thousand ships, to Salamis.
And Salamis, it's a strait, okay?
It's very narrow. So the ships have to
line up and attack the Greeks one by one.
Okay? And at Salamis,
in a headlong battle, okay,
the Greek ships were heavier and the Greek
ships were manned by hoplites with armor.
And in this battle of Salamis,
the Greeks destroyed the Persian
navy. Okay? Do you understand?
The Persian army had won the war.
And at Salamis, they lost the war.
Okay? Now the problem is, now
that the Persian navy has been destroyed,
supply lines are in trouble.
Okay? Do you understand?
Because Greece is very poor.
Greece is a very poor nation.
You cannot resupply yourself in Greece.
How do you feed half a million people?
Well, you need to bring
in supplies from Persia.
But now your navy has been destroyed.
So now King Xerxes freaks
out and he goes home.
He's like, you know what?
I burned down Athens.
That's good enough for me.
Okay? And he leaves his cousin,
General Mardonis, to fight the Greeks.
Okay? And at this point,
Mardonis could have chosen
to not fight the Greeks.
Right? Because Athens has been destroyed.
And Sparta is still there.
It's still under threat. So
all Mardonis had to do
was, he was in Thebes.
Okay? He was in Thebes. All he
had to do was stay in Thebes
and wait out the war. Okay?
This is what we call a war of attrition,
where you wait out the other enemy
because the other enemy has
basically less resources than you.
Okay? Does that make sense? Again,
really easy for the Persians to win.
But Mardonis chose to fight the Greeks
at the Battle of the Thracians.
The Battle of Palatia.
And here, it was about equal forces,
100,000 Greeks versus 100,000 Persians.
And the Greeks destroyed the Persians.
The Persians lost five times
more men than the Greeks.
Okay? And
General Mardonis was
killed in this battle.
So this war that the Persians
should have won very easily,
the Persians lost.
And were completely destroyed.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay, any questions so far
about the Persian invasion?
Okay. And because of this war,
Greece now became extremely wealthy.
The reason why is Persia is
forced to retreat from Asia Minor
and the Greeks were able to
capture a lot of treasure.
Okay? Now,
after this, Persia switches strategies.
Okay? Persia never again invades Greece because
they think this is stupid to invade Greece.
Okay? But the Greeks don't know this.
The Greeks think, okay, the Persians
will come back at any point.
Okay? So the Athenians say,
let's take the battle to Persia.
And what do the Spartans say?
The Spartans say, no. We're
going to go home and that's it.
Okay? So to battle against the Persians,
the Athenians create something
called the Delian League.
The Delian League is a defensive
alliance between Athens
and these colonies and
islands in the Aegean.
And the idea is if the Persians come back,
we will master forces and
fight the Persians at sea.
The problem is that
only Athens had a navy.
Everyone else didn't really have
a navy. So everyone else is like,
we don't have a navy, but
we'll contribute money.
Okay? And they agreed that
this money, this treasury,
could only be used against
Persia if Persia invades.
Okay? So they put all this
money on a place called Delos.
Okay? An island called Delos.
That's why it's called the Delian League.
All right? Does that make
sense? So basically,
Athens would put up a navy and
everyone else would go back to Persia.
And this money,
this treasury of the Delian League can
only be used in a war against
Persia. Okay?
Does that make sense? Okay.
So while this is happening,
Athens is the rising power in this world.
And in 461 BCE,
a new political leader called
Pericles comes into power.
And as you should know from your research,
Pericles is considered the
father of Athenian democracy.
He's the one who spreads
democracy throughout Athens. And
historians today worship Pericles.
Okay? Pericles is considered one of the
greatest leaders ever in Western history.
Okay? I'll talk more about Pericles
and democracy in a minute.
But I want to show you
that Pericles was first and
foremost a politician who
was concerned about
amassing and keeping power.
Does that make sense? So he did a
lot of wonderful things for Athens.
But I want to show you these things that
he did, even though they seem great,
they really were about him
amassing power for himself.
Okay? So, Pericles was a great politician.
The first thing he did was he
spread democracy to everyone.
Okay? He basically gave every
citizen the right to vote.
And you're like, okay, that's great.
Direct democracy. Athens
creates democracy.
This is great. Right? But
the reason why he did
that was to change the
balance of power in Athens.
So he basically represented the lower
nobility versus the upper nobility.
Right? Usually, the upper nobility has
more power because it is the most powerful.
It has more money. Okay?
It has more prestige. So
the way for the lower nobility to defeat
the upper nobility is by
allying itself with the people.
Okay? Does
that make sense? And you do that
by giving people the right to vote.
And so by doing this,
Pericles basically made
himself king of Athens.
Does that make sense? In fact, he stayed
in power from the beginning until the end of the 20th century.
From 461 to 429.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
And to please the people even more,
he basically made corruption official.
What he did that
was very important was he
basically took the money from Delos
and brought it to Athens.
Basically, Pericles said to the
Delian League, you know what?
This money in Delos, it's a lot of money.
I'm afraid that the Persians will come
and steal it, so let's take it to Athens.
Okay? When he brought it to Athens,
the next thing he did
was he spent all of it.
Okay? He built a lot of
really impressive buildings,
including something called the Parthenon.
The Parthenon is this
great temple to Athena,
which is a patron goddess of Athens.
They made the Athenian statue out of gold.
Okay? They spent billions and
billions of dollars on this temple.
The reason why is when you do
that, right, you give people jobs.
And you give people who support you money.
Okay? So this is basically
official corruption.
Now, there are people in
the upper nobility who
thought what Pericles was
doing was terrible for Athens.
And basically, in meetings, they
wanted to ostracize Pericles.
Right? They accused
Pericles of corruption,
of basically bribing the city of Athens.
And they said, you are
corrupting our morals.
Okay? You are hurting our democracy.
Therefore, we want to ostracize you.
And there was this vote against Pericles.
And what happens? Do you guys know?
The people voted to exile
Pericles' opponents.
Okay? Those who criticized
Pericles were now exiled.
They were exiled from Athens.
Therefore, Pericles no longer
has any political opponents.
And Pericles can do whatever he wants.
And so, the two big innovations
of Pericles is democracy.
Okay? Right?
Let's give people the right to vote.
And let's give people more money. Okay?
But also, empire.
The reason why is after Pericles
basically stole the money,
the money was stolen. So, the people who
were exiled from the Delian League, the allies were obviously angry.
You stole our money. So,
we are out of this league.
And Pericles said, well,
if you leave our league,
we're going to come and invade you. So,
Athens started this expansionist campaign
in order to maintain its empire.
So, the Delian League basically
became the Athenian Empire.
And now, Athens got basically 20%
of its revenue from the Athenians.
So, it's allies. Okay?
Does that make sense? So,
that's what Pericles was doing.
He was promoting democracy in order
to make sure people voted for him.
He was promoting empire in order to
maintain the easy money flow into Athens.
Empire is important because remember,
Athens has a culture of eudaimonia.
So, empire makes the rich extremely rich.
Extremely wealthy. You understand?
Empire makes everyone rich, but
it makes the wealthy even more so.
And so, the lower nobility, okay,
the lower nobility became very jealous.
And so, the way to resolve this issue is the lower
nobility could choose to invade other places.
Okay? And if they win, they could
make a lot of money for themselves.
So, one place they chose
to invade was Egypt.
But that failed. Okay?
So, throughout this time,
you had a lot of Athenian expeditions throughout
the world in looking to conquer new territory.
And sometimes they succeeded, but
a lot of times they failed as well.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So, as Athens is expanding and
becoming much wealthier,
other Greek colonies,
other Greek policies start
to get angry at Athens.
Okay? And Athens is
basically the big bully.
They were afraid of Persia before.
But Persia didn't really
bother the Greeks.
Whereas, Athens was a big bully.
They wanted to control all of Greece.
Okay? They basically
were a mafia organization
that was forcing these islands
and the Aegean Sea to
pay tribute to Athens.
And they were trying to take more
territory from other Greek policies.
So, in 431,
the Greek policies united around Sparta
and started something called
the Peloponnesian War.
Okay? And historically,
what most historians will tell
you is this war was started
because Sparta was afraid of
an emerging Athens.
Okay? Sparta was the hegemon.
Sparta was the most dominant
power in Greece at that time.
And now that Athens was ruined.
And now that Athens was rising,
Sparta felt threatened
by Athens and therefore
declared war on Athens.
That's not true. Okay?
That's not the reason.
The reason why is because
Athens was an empire
and it was going around
and bullying everyone.
And so, you didn't have
a choice in the matter.
You got to fight Athens now or
wait for Athens to invade you.
Okay? So, it was because
Athens was an imperial power.
And so, other nations had to, other Greek
powers had no choice but to stand against
Athens. Okay? And Athens was
an imperial power because
of its theory of eudaimonia.
Okay? So, the great irony here,
and you will see this pattern
repeat itself throughout history,
is the thing, the culture that
allows a nation to rise,
okay, and this is eudaimonia,
will also cause it to decline.
Does it make sense? Okay?
Because it's because of the
Peloponnesian War, which
lasts from about 431
BC to 404 BCE,
27 years, that Athens loses its empire.
Okay? So, the culture, eudaimonia,
that causes Athens to rise will
ultimately lead to its decline as well.
All right? So, are you guys clear so far?
Okay. So, please let me know
if this is clear to you,
if you have any questions
before I continue.
Okay. So, even
though Sparta and Athens are
now at war with each other,
this war, again,
should have been pretty
easily won by Athens.
Why? What can Athens do to destroy Sparta?
Okay. Do you guys know?
What can Athens do,
really easy, to destroy Sparta?
Hellas, right? The Athenians have ships.
They can choose to do what the
Persians should have done, but
they didn't do, which is
to basically take its navy,
land its navy on the coast, and
support the Hellas in the rebellion.
Okay? If that would have happened, Sparta
would have been destroyed very quickly.
The Athenians didn't do that. All right?
Do you understand? The
Athenians didn't do that.
Now, Sparta, to counter
this threat against Athens,
what should it have done to
counter this threat from Athens?
Exactly. Thank you. Okay? Its only option
in this scenario is to free the Hellas
and save the Hellas before they
fight for us against Athenians.
We will give you your liberty.
Okay? And the Hellas
would have been, yeah,
let's go fight for the Spartans.
Okay? So, Sparta would have
increased its army ten times,
and it could have destroyed Athens.
Sparta didn't do this either.
Okay? Do you understand?
So, from a military strategy perspective,
the way the Peloponnesian
War didn't make any sense.
The only way to understand
what happened is to understand
that the very basis of conflict in
society is between the upper nobility
and the lower nobility.
Okay? Do you understand?
The upper nobility is only interested
in maintaining the status quo.
They're very conservative.
They don't like wars because
you could lose wars, and also
because if you win wars,
you have people who are
now richer than you are.
Okay? So, the upper nobility is very
conservative in both Athens and Sparta.
The lower nobility can only become
upper nobility through war or revolution.
Okay? So, they're always
looking to upset the status quo.
So, even though this war
is going on, internally,
there's still conflict between the
upper nobility and the lower nobility.
Okay? And that's why, if you
look at the Peloponnesian War,
a lot of the military strategy
doesn't make any sense because
Sparta isn't really trying
to win a war against Athens.
Sparta is trying to maintain peace.
So, the upper nobility is losing
the status quo in Sparta.
Okay? Athens is not really trying
to win a war against Sparta.
Athens is trying to maintain
the status quo within Athens.
Alright? An example is Pericles.
The war starts in 431 B.C.
and a lot of people are saying,
Pericles, hey, let's go invade Sparta.
And what Pericles says
instead is, oh no no no.
The Spartans are the greatest
warriors in the world.
We have no chance against Sparta.
So, what we'll do is.
is we have these walls, okay?
We have these walls, we'll
hide behind our walls
and let our navy protect
us in the sea, okay?
That was the defensive
strategy of Pericles.
And so what the Spartans could
do was they could come to Attica
and destroy all the farmland.
And the Athenians could only watch
as the Spartans destroy the farmland.
This was a disaster for the Athenians
because if you think about it, over time,
the Spartans could starve
out the Athenians, right?
The other problem is you have too many
people in one place, what happens?
You have too many people living
in a city, what happens usually?
Disease, right? Disease.
So because of the overpopulation,
in Athens, they had the plague,
which killed one third of
the Athenian population.
Okay, do you understand? One
third of the Athenian population.
If the Athenians went
to war against Sparta
and they lost,
they would have at most lost
about 10% of their population.
But because they chose not to fight and
hide behind the walls, not only
did they lose their farmland,
but they lost a third of their population.
Including Pericles, who
died because of the plague.
Pericles died as well
as his two sons, okay?
Doesn't make sense, right?
So again, this strategy makes no sense.
If you think from a military perspective,
it only makes sense if you understand
there's an internal conflict in Athens between
the upper nobility and the lower nobility, okay?
Pericles represents the upper nobility,
he wants to maintain the status quo.
There's a war going on, and he
wants to maintain the status quo.
But he doesn't really want
to fight this war, okay?
He just wants to wait it out because he
does not want to change the status quo.
Okay, does that make sense? So,
after Pericles dies,
the lower nobility become ascendant, okay?
And because of this war,
they propose an aggressive
strategy against the Spartans.
Basically, it's like, let's
go attack the Spartans.
And cause a revolution in Sparta, okay?
And this was proposed by Cleon,
who after Pericles died,
became basically the de
facto leader of Athens.
And he was considered a demagogue, okay?
If you look at the history, everyone
says bad things about this guy, okay?
But really, what he is,
he's lower nobility who's trying
to achieve eudaimonia, okay?
And he's basically like,
from Mexico, please.
Okay? Alright?
And he's a great military
strategist as well.
So, Cleon proposes this aggressive
strategy against Sparta,
and guess what happens? Athens
is now destroying Sparta.
Okay? Now, Sparta is
under a lot of pressure.
It's losing the war. So,
now what Sparta does is,
it picks a new general, Brasidas.
And says to Brasidas, listen, we're
losing the war, what can we do?
So, Brasidas goes north,
and he starts winning his
victories against Athens.
And his policy is this, listen,
we need to change our social structure
in order to win against Athens.
So, what he does is he tells the helots, if you
fight for me, I'm going to give you your freedom.
And so, a lot of helots fight for
Brasidas, and Brasidas wins a lot of wars.
And this is what happens. And how
do the Spartans feel about this?
Brasidas, who's a Spartan, is
now winning wars against Athens.
And so, how do the
Spartans feel about this?
Are they happy about this? No,
they're really unhappy about this, okay?
Because it's changing
their social structure.
You understand? They don't want this crap.
They want the helots to be slaves.
They don't want the helots
to be free citizens.
They want free citizens who
help them win wars, okay?
So, what ultimately
happens is, even though
Cleon and Brasidas have
both proposed strategies
that allow Athens and
Sparta to win the war,
ultimately, what happens is Cleon
and Brasidas get into a battle with each
other, and they both die in this battle.
That's extremely convenient, guys, okay?
That's really, really convenient.
So, I'd be very surprised if they
actually did both die in battle.
My guess is what happened is they were both
assassinated during the battle against each other.
Does that make sense? Because ultimately,
both were the bigger threats to
the social structure of Sparta
and Athens than losing the war itself.
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
Any questions so far?
Okay. Does that make sense?
Okay. Okay.
So, now,
so this war keeps on going,
and then what happens is
the Persia gets involved
and gives Sparta a navy.
Basically, Persia gives
Sparta a blank check.
And because Sparta is so
conservative and insular,
it doesn't really know how to, you know,
have a navy, okay? It doesn't
know how to fight with a navy.
In fact, Sparta is militarily, like,
in terms of strategy, it's
actually very weak, okay?
If it's, like, Spartan soldiers
by themselves are very strong,
but in terms of, like,
overall military strategy,
Sparta, because it's so conservative
and insular, it's very weak,
again, it's very weak
compared with Athens.
But Persia has a lot of money, and
Persia is bankrolling Sparta, okay?
And eventually, Persia
says to Sparta, hey, guys.
Why don't you try a new strategy?
The strategy is this. If a general
is winning against the Athenians,
promote the guy, okay?
And you're like, okay, well,
that makes total sense.
The Spartans didn't do that, okay?
The Spartans were not concerned
about winning the war.
They were concerned about
maintaining their social order.
Do you understand? There's a
social hierarchy in Sparta.
That's what's important,
not winning the war.
And then there was a Spartan commander,
Lysander. And
he was really the only Spartan who
knew how to win naval battles.
The problem with Lysander
was he was a half -citizen,
which meant
that his father was a Spartan
but not the mother. Do you understand?
Only if both your parents are citizens
are you allowed to be a citizen.
So Lysander was really
looked down upon in Sparta.
But he could win naval battles.
So he wasn't promoted.
The Persians said to the Spartans,
listen, this is stupid, okay?
Lysander is a great commander.
You have to promote him.
The Spartans didn't really
have a choice in the matter.
And so Lysander, after he was promoted,
single -handedly won
the war against Athens.
He laid siege to Athens in 404 BCE.
And then Athens had no choice
but to surrender because
they were out of food, okay?
Does that make sense? Now,
for 27 years,
Sparta and Athens were
at war with each other.
They were killing each other. Now
Athens had finally been defeated.
So what do you think should happen now?
What should happen to Athens now?
Okay, the answer is nothing
happened to Athens, okay?
Usually if you lose a war, in this world,
what happens is they come and kill
all the men and enslave all the women.
And that's what the Persians wanted, okay?
That's what the other Greek
cities wanted to happen to Athens.
The Spartans didn't do anything to Athens.
They left Athens alone, okay?
And there are many different
explanations for this.
One explanation is Sparta wanted to maintain
a balance of power in the Greek world,
okay? They destroyed Athens, then Persia
could come back and destroy Sparta, okay?
But another explanation
is, well, guess what, guys?
The upper nobility of Sparta and
the upper nobility of Athens,
they're good friends
with each other, okay?
Do you understand? Rich people
tend to marry each other.
They tend to be good friends
with each other, okay?
So Athens and
Sparta weren't really enemies,
do you understand? They had
to fight this war because
of the internal pressures
from the lower nobility.
Because this war was killing off so much
lower nobility, it maintained the status quo.
Does that make sense? All right?
You guys understand so far? Any questions?
All right. So I'm going to
conclude with evidence for you.
I'm going to give you some
evidence for this theory, okay?
So what I just said, like,
war is really about killing
off internal dissent,
not really about beating the other enemy.
That's very controversial, okay? So I will
give you some evidence for this theory,
and it's called rat utopia.
So in the 1960s and 70s,
there was an American
researcher, American scientist.
His name is James U.
He was engaged in wartime
engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged
engaged engaged
engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged Well he couldn't really experiment on humans,
so he decided to experiment
on rats instead.
So he built this universe,
basically this big house,
and food was plentiful for rats.
The food, the water
was plentiful for rats.
So rats could just play all day.
Now I'm not sure if you know
anything about rats, but
the thing about animals, and
this is a very important idea,
is that animals live in
a heavily ritualized
and rules -based world.
It doesn't make sense, guys. We think
of animals as chaotic, no, no, no.
If you actually study their
society, ants, monkeys, rats,
they live in an extremely rule -based,
heavily ritualized world, okay?
So let me give you an example of this.
So rats, when they mate with each
other, what happens is this.
A female rat is interested
in having sex, okay?
So she's going out, and
then a male rat spots this.
He sees the female rat in heat.
So what he does is he gets
on a mound, okay, where
she can see him, and he
starts to dance, okay?
He starts to dance. And
the female rat becomes interested, and
he sees, she's interested, so
he comes down, and they start
chasing each other, okay?
They're having fun together. And
then what she does is she runs home
and hides herself in her burrow.
The male rat just stands outside
and waits for her to come out.
After some time, she comes out, and they run
together again, and then she runs back again.
They do this many, many
times until finally
she lets him catch him,
and then they have sex.
Okay? And then after they have sex, they have
children, and they start a family together, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay,
that's how rats usually behave.
When they often like to play with each other,
and they fight, but it's very playful, okay?
So there's lots of rules,
there's lots of rituals
in this rat society, but
that's out in nature.
In the world of James B.
Calhoun, he creates a rat utopia, okay?
Where everyone has enough to eat.
And at some point, the
society breaks down, okay?
These rituals, these rules all break down.
What happens is male rats,
when they start fighting each
other, they become very violent.
They're no longer playing, they're actually trying
to kill each other, and some actually die, okay?
And this mating ritual, it breaks down.
So the male rats don't
even try to dance, okay?
They're not dancing. They just see a female, and
they, you know, they're like, they rape her, okay?
And it's like gang rape. It's not one
male, it's like lots of males raping her.
These gangs of rats, they
try to break into boroughs,
homes, and try to rape the wife, okay?
The mother. And at first,
the husband is fighting off
these other rats, right?
But eventually what
happens is he gets tired,
and he just runs away, okay?
He just abandons the family. Now the female rat is
responsible for fighting off now the other rats.
But she becomes so traumatized, she starts to
beat everyone up, including her own children.
So she kicks her children
out of the house.
It is a complete social breakdown.
And after a few more months of this crap,
the entire colony of rats dies.
The entire society collapses.
Does that make sense? Alright?
So this is what we call rat utopia.
It's been done many times. And each
time they do this, this happens.
At some point, this society will collapse.
Okay? And this makes no sense to us.
Everyone has enough food to eat.
Everyone should be happy, okay?
Why does society collapse?
Okay, so there are different
explanations for this.
James B. Calhoun, his argument is,
if there's too much food,
there's overpopulation.
There's overpopulation,
then that creates conflict.
And the conflict causes the
rules to collapse, okay?
The problem, though, with this theory,
is the colony never became
overpopulated, okay?
There was space for everyone.
But at some point, everyone
started to fight each other.
Alright? So this is my theory.
And this goes back to
the Peloponnesian War.
It has to do with the idea of status.
So in a world of abundance,
in a world of wealth,
who benefits the most?
It's the elderly.
Older. Older people, okay?
Old people can live a
lot longer in a society
that is wealthy and abundant, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay?
But then what happens is the
status becomes locked in,
which prevents younger
rats, younger people,
from ascending into power and status.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So the idea is,
the metaphor is, these
rats are online, okay?
I'm waiting for, to climb
the mountain, okay?
This is the mountain top. You're waiting
and waiting to climb the mountain.
And everyone's moving along.
It's slow, but you're
still moving along, okay?
And eventually you will
reach the mountain top,
which is where you want to be. But
let's just say for whatever reason,
the line stops moving, okay?
And that's not a good thing. Everyone's stuck
in place. Well then you get very anxious.
You get very stressed out.
You get very agitated. You're
like, when is it my turn?
And it's never gonna come because
the people at the top won't leave,
okay? So what do you do?
Well you start kicking the
people behind you, right?
You start fighting with each other.
You understand? That's
what we call rat utopia.
In a world of abundance, in
a world of extreme wealth,
old people do not die.
If they do not die,
it is impossible for young people
to ascend into power and status.
And so they have all these energies.
And because they cannot
reach their potential,
they become violent and
start attacking each other,
okay? So that's rat utopia.
That's what rats do. But if you
look at the Peloponnesian War
and what happened between Athens and
Sparta, it's really no different,
okay? It's really no different.
They were killing each
other for no reason.
Extreme violence, which
led to nothing, okay?
431 BCE,
the political world was
no different from 404 BCE.
The only difference is a lot
of young people died, okay?
In wars against each other.
So that's my argument to you.
If societies become too wealthy,
you have a problem of rat utopia,
okay?
If rat utopia, societies will then
engage in wars
that will lead eventually to its collapse.
And that's what happened to Athens.
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
All right, any questions about this?
Does it make sense? Does
it make sense to you guys?
All right? Any questions? Yeah.
Okay, so the question is,
in the rat utopia,
why do the mothers want to
start attacking the kids, okay?
Okay, so this is actually
a complicated question.
The answer is this. Humans
are different from rats, okay?
So humans have the ability to reason and
to adapt to new circumstances, okay?
Does that make sense? Rats don't.
There are these rules in place, okay?
And if these rules are broken, then
the rats don't know how to adapt.
So if you're a rat mother,
you have a husband, okay?
Your understanding is the husband
will protect you from strangers,
okay? Okay?
Okay? Your understanding is if
someone is violent towards you,
you have to be violent
against that person, okay?
So in a situation where
the husband leaves,
the husband runs away or is dead,
the mother does not understand
this new order anymore.
So the mother becomes, the
word we use is traumatized.
You're traumatized, you
can no longer reason, okay?
You're so focused on protecting yourself,
you attack everything and everyone, including your own children.
Does that make sense? Yeah, this is an
experiment because obviously this would not happen in real life, okay?
There's no way the rats
get free food in real life.
So they have this experiment where the
experimenters gave the rats free food every day.
And this is what happened..
No, no. So the experiment is.
The rats were left by themselves,
okay? The rats could do
whatever they wanted.
The only thing the experimenters
did was feed them every day.
Okay? If you do that, if there's
abundance and there's wealth,
then you have complete social collapse.
Okay?.
Okay, okay, all right. So, okay, all
you need to understand is this, okay?
. So the entire society collapses.
Okay? How it collapses can be
different from family to family.
So the entire society collapses.
Everyone dies at the end.
Okay? Do you understand?
Okay. Any more questions?
Any more questions?
So I know this is a very important question.
I know this is a lot to take in, okay?
This is very confusing
and this is very hard,
but it's okay, just ask
any questions or points
where you want me to clarify.
Okay, so next class we
will do Greek theater,
and then after that we'll do Greek
philosophy, which includes Plato,
Socrates, and Aristotle, okay?