Okay, so let's begin class.
And today we are discussing whether
or not Trump will win in November.
And I'm making the prediction
that he will win in November
and that
he will pick Nikki Haley
as his vice president.
Okay, so let me make
you the argument today.
Okay, so let's first discuss
why Biden won in 2020
and why it's possible
that he may lose this year.
Okay, so in 2020,
it was a very special
year in American politics
because it was a larger,
it was the largest turnout in
American history since about 1900.
Okay, so 74 million
people voted for Trump.
For Biden, 81 million
people voted for him.
And two out of every three
American adults came out to vote.
Okay, so it was the largest
turnout in American history.
It doesn't, it sounds like a
very lopsided victory for Biden,
81 million versus 74 million.
But because America has an
electoral college system,
which is not director -elected,
it's not a democratic democracy, actually,
the margin of victory
was only 65,000 votes.
Meaning that if 65,000 people in key
battleground states flipped their votes,
then Trump would have won.
Okay, so the margin of
victory was very, very close,
as is usually the case in highly
contested American elections.
So let's understand the coalition that
brought Biden into the White House.
Okay, so
the first major component of
this coalition are black people.
91% of all blacks voted for Biden.
Only 8% voted for Trump.
That's a huge majority for Biden.
So why did so many black
people vote for Biden in 2020?
Well, first of all, it's because
Biden was Obama's vice
president for eight years.
And so a lot of older black people
had a certain loyalty to him.
Okay, they felt that we
owe this man because
he served loyally to our man,
Barack Obama, for eight years.
And so now we must bring
him into the White House.
But this year, the debt
is paid off, right?
So they won't feel so loyal to Biden.
Okay. Also in 2020,
there's something called
a George Floyd protest.
So what happened was that
in May 2020,
a black man in Minneapolis, George Floyd,
he was strangled to death
by a white police officer.
It was captured on video and
it caused a national uproar.
In fact, there were riots
and protests throughout the country.
And Trump came out and did this.
He did not acknowledge the pain that
black people felt because of this death.
And so black people felt
antipathy towards Trump. Okay.
So these are the two major reasons why
black people voted for Biden in 2020.
But this year,
Trump's not in office, right?
Biden's in office. So black
people are asking the question,
what has Biden done for
us these past four years?
And unfortunately, the
answer is not that much.
And in fact, you can
make the argument that
Biden has really hurt the standard
of living of black people.
Why? Because inflation has gone up.
Okay. When inflation goes up,
it usually hurts poor people the most.
Okay. The standard of
living goes way down.
Also, illegal immigration
has gone up. Okay.
So in 2020, when Trump left office,
there were about 10 million
illegal immigrants in America.
Now there are 20 million
And it seems like Biden's doing
nothing to stop this trend.
And of course, when illegal
immigrants come to the country,
they usually take the jobs of poor people.
Okay. They bring wages down.
And that again hurts black people.
And then third is Ukraine.
So while the standard of
living for black people
and other poor people in
America are going down,
America is sending tens of billions
of dollars to Ukraine to fight a war
that has nothing to do with America.
So many Americans see this
as just bad leadership.
Okay. So that's black people.
And recent polls show that
actually Biden's lead with black
people is not a bad thing.
Not as much as it was in 2020.
Okay. So this lead is going down.
Young people. Okay.
Well, young people tend to vote
Democratic in all elections.
And they were extremely
galvanized to vote in 2020
because they saw Trump as
this very hateful racist
that they must remove from office.
Right. And they were driven to believe
this because of the George Floyd protests.
Unfortunately, this year,
young people may not feel
compelled to vote for Biden.
In fact, a lot of young people are
choosing to sit out this election.
Why? You guys know?
Gaza. Okay.
So as you know, right now,
throughout America on college campuses,
young people are
protesting the war in Gaza.
So these young people are
not going to vote for Trump.
Okay. But
they probably will not vote for Biden as
a protest against American
policy via the Israel.
Okay. Now let's look at
the college educated.
Okay. So 70% of people with
college degrees voted for Biden.
These are what we call the coastal elite.
Right. The coastal
professional managerial elite.
And they usually
overwhelmingly vote Democratic.
And this year, they
will still say the same.
But they will be less enthusiastic
because of what they perceive
to be poor global leadership.
Okay. Biden under Biden's
watch, Ukraine blew up.
But so did Gaza.
And many are starting to
feel that it's because
Biden comes across as too old,
too weak, and too feeble
to stand against Putin.
Okay. So college educated people
will still vote for Biden.
So overwhelmingly vote Democratic.
That is the core Democratic base.
But they'll be less
enthusiastic about Biden.
And they'll vote primarily against Trump.
Okay. Woman. Okay.
So 54% of women voted for Biden.
44% voted for Trump.
Okay. And again, because
Trump is seen as this hateful figure.
We expect that
woman will still consistently
vote Democratic this year.
Okay. And also because of abortion issues.
Right. So women are very
passionate about abortion.
And they will come out and
vote for Biden to ensure
that abortion rights are protected.
Last, let's look at suburban voters.
Okay. So the suburbs.
The suburbs are between the cities,
the urban areas, and the rural areas.
Okay. Cities, urban areas, overwhelmingly
support the Democratic Party.
Rural areas overwhelmingly
support the Republican Party.
So the suburbs are where
the battleground is.
And so if you look at 19,
sorry, 2016,
when Trump defeated Hillary Clinton,
only 45% of
the suburbs voted for Clinton.
Which allowed Trump to
defeat her in the election.
Okay. Now, what's
interesting is that in 2020,
this flipped and
54% of suburban voters voted for Biden.
That's a flip of 2 million voters.
Okay. So in elections,
usually it's a suburban vote that
determines the election
because there's swing voters.
Okay. So
for Trump to win this year,
he needs to win the suburban vote.
He won that in 2016.
He lost that in 2020. Okay.
So let's examine very
quickly why the
suburbs went Biden in 2020.
Okay. And there are three major reasons.
The first is the media narrative. So
what's happening throughout
Trump's presidency
is basically the entire
mainstream media got together
and criticized Trump.
Okay. So the first major criticism
of Trump, if you remember,
is he was a Russian asset.
Okay. He was a paid Putin puppet.
And of course, that was
just a complete lie.
What we call Russiagate. Okay.
But then they start to say that
Trump was a divisive figure.
Okay. And
this idea caught
the imagination of the suburbs.
Okay. Because if you live in the
suburbs, you tend to be middle class.
You tend to be pretty
wealthy and well educated.
So you like the status quo. You
want a leader who's conservative
and who's a unifier.
And throughout the Trump
presidency, we saw that.
We saw the polarization of politics.
The left and the right hate each
other and they fought all the time.
And what really showed this
was the George Floyd protests.
So you had protesters
rioting in the streets.
And Trump was like, let's send in
the military to crush the protesters.
And so people in the suburbs
were very worried about this.
They thought that a leader, the
president, should be a uniter.
Right. And Biden came
across as extremely steady,
as very establishment, as someone who
could unite both the Republican
Party and the Democratic Party.
Okay. That was his perception in 2020.
So that's the first major reason
why the suburbs went Biden.
Second was the pandemic.
So as you know, COVID
hit the United States.
And the suburbs were extremely
freaked out about this
because they tend to have
children who go to school.
They tend to be older.
And they thought that
Trump's handling of the
pandemic was very incompetent.
Okay. He was an outsider,
a political outsider. But that meant he
could not get things done in Washington.
Okay. So that's the second
problem with Trump.
And the third reason why
the suburbs went Biden is Kamala Harris.
Okay. And this is key.
Biden picked Kamala Harris to
be his vice president.
To be his running mate.
And Kamala Harris, let me tell
you a little about Kamala Harris.
Her father is Jamaican.
Her mother is Indian. And
she has a younger sister.
But she was young.
Her dad left the family.
So her mom raised the
two girls by herself.
And Kamala Harris is an
extremely accomplished person.
She went to Stanford.
Then she became Attorney
General of California.
Then became a U.S.
Senator. Okay. And
there are three reasons why
the suburbs love Kamala Harris.
Okay. First of all,
like us.
Okay. Meaning like she
comes across as someone who
speaks and
thinks like people in the suburbs.
Okay. Well educated, articulate,
smart, conservative.
Okay. Second is she's seen
as very establishment.
Meaning that she's not liberal.
In fact, when she was Attorney
General of California,
she was extremely tough on crime.
She was trying to send as many
people to jail as possible.
And sometimes, quite honestly,
some of these people were innocent.
Okay. And she still sent them to jail.
She was very controversial
as Attorney General.
But guess what, guys?
People in the suburbs like tough on crime.
Okay. They want safety.
They want security. They have kids.
Okay. And
the third reason why they
like Kamala Harris is
because of the redemption story.
So, in 2019,
there's a Democratic
primary. Okay. This is when
the Democrats try to
get a nomination for the general election.
Okay. And there was a lot of people who
are vying for the nomination,
including Joe Biden and Kamala Harris.
In June 2019,
there was the first Democratic debate.
Okay. And at this point, Kamala Harris and
Joe Biden were considered very heavy
favorites to win the nomination.
And in that first debate,
Kamala Harris and Joe Biden
got into a very serious fight.
And they had a very nasty
argument on television.
Okay. So, what happened is that
Kamala Harris turned to Joe Biden.
And Joe Biden is kind of shell -shocked.
Okay. He's kind of old.
And Kamala Harris is
directing her words at him.
And he doesn't really want to see her.
Okay. He doesn't really
want to confront her.
And what Kamala Harris
says to Joe Biden is,
Joe, you've been in Washington,
D.C., for 50 years.
And some of your policies I don't support.
For example, you do not support
the integration of black
and white students together.
Well, you know what, Joe?
I'm a black student.
I was a black little girl, grew
up in the 70s in California.
And I got an opportunity
to succeed in America
because of integration, because
I could go to white school.
And you opposed my opportunity to succeed.
Okay. So, basically, she was calling.
She was calling Biden a racist.
And at that point, everyone thought that,
okay, well, if Biden gets a nomination,
there's no way he's going
to pick her to be the VP.
Okay. And then
he picks her to be the VP.
And so what do people think about Biden?
What do people think of Biden?
What impression do people
get because of this?
Anyone? Or there's no
other impression or other
sort of impression or
other sort of impression.
Or there's no other impression or other
sort of impression or other sort of impression or other sort of impression or
other sort of impression or other sort of
impression or impression or other sort of impression or other sort of impression
or other sort of impression
or empathy
okay he understands that voters want from
that Harris okay and
guess what guys these three things
doesn't hold grudges listens team player
and empathy this is anti -trump
right this is the anti -trump
and
because of this narrative
woman especially woman in the suburbs
went for Biden okay previously
that gone for Trump now
they went for Biden because
as it turns out woman want
compassionate empathetic leadership that
is decisive and bold
but is also
tolerant okay and that
this is also why even
though Hillary Clinton
what like ran in 2016 and
she was a woman the suburbs
didn't vote for her
because she was she didn't
come across as someone who
was a woman and she was a woman and she
was a woman and she was a woman and she was compassionate and forgiving and
tolerant okay does that make sense and
this is why Biden was
able to win in 2020
so
this year what can Trump do
to win the suburbs what can you do
yeah he
can copy this exact same thing okay and
it turns out he can do
this okay why because
on the Republican side
there's someone not called
Nikki Kelly Nikki Kelly
I'm sorry Nikki Haley
and
Nikki Haley is very similar
to Kamala Harris okay
Nikki Haley her parents
are Indian immigrants okay
so she's Indian she's of
South Asian this descent
and her father is a Muslim
and she's a Muslim and
she's a Muslim now there's a Muslim
there's a Muslim there's a Muslim
there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's
a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim
a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's a Muslim there's
a Muslim there's a Muslim
there's a Muslim
and even though
she lost to Trump there
was a group of people
who loved her guess who
just loved her who
voted for her in droves guess guess
what what demographic group anyone
sub -urban
woman okay you understand college
educated suburban woman okay
so in other words if Trump
brings her on to the ticket
then
it's very likely he can
swing the suburbs back to him
and win the election but
there's a problem the problem is that
Nikki Haley and
Trump got into a very nasty
fight during the primary okay
so Nikki Haley said listen
I served under Trump
and I think he's going to win the
election he's a divisive figure and
right now in our country we we need a
unifier that's why I'm running for president
because I want to unite this country whereas
Trump can only divide this country okay
and then Trump being Trump responds
and says Nikki Haley is a
birdbrain she's stupid okay
so
you think you see this you think like
there's no way Trump will pick her because
Nikki Haley's not loyal to Trump right
and Trump will pick her because she's a!
И ему ему ему ему И
ему ему ему И ему ему
ему И ему ему ему И ему ему
ему И ему ему ему И ему ему ему
И ему ему ему И ему ему ему
И ему ему ему И ему ему ему И
ему ему ему И ему ему ему И ему ему ему
И ему ему ему И ему ему ему И ему ему И
ему ему И ему ему И ему ему И
ему ему И ему
ему И ему ему
But let me ask you this
question. If in August,
during the Republican convention,
he does pick Nikki Haley,
how would people feel about him?
How would the media report this?
Nikki Haley is an enemy of Trump.
Trump called her a bird brain.
Trump said, I will never pick Nikki Haley.
And then in August, three months from now,
he says, you know what, I was wrong.
I think Nikki Haley is the
best person to be my VP.
That's why she'll be my
running mate in November.
How would people feel about him?
What would the suburbs think about Trump?
How would you feel if you saw this?
Or you saw this now, or you saw
this now, or you saw this now,
or you saw this now.
Or you saw this now.
Or you saw this now. Or you saw this now.
Or you saw this now. Or you saw this now. Or you saw this now.
Or you saw this now.
is he's divisive but much more than that
he's immature he's incapable
of growth okay but hey
if in august he picks
nikki haley to be his vp
then the media will be
like he is a changed man
he's learned his lessons
he's willing to let go
of grudges he's willing to
listen he now has empathy
therefore
he should be president
okay do you understand
but then
what happens is the suburbs
switch over to trump
and then he wins so
if he picks nikki haley in august
he will win okay i'm not completely sure
that he will pick nikki haley i think that
this is his best strategic move okay but
trump is not really predictable all right
and who he picks as vice president will
give us a good clue as to how he will govern
when he when he becomes
president okay does that
make sense all right now the question then
is okay who
is nikki haley and
what will she do as vice president okay
now what's important to
understand about nikki haley is
that when she left office when
she left washington dc political office in
2018 she had nothing in
her bank account okay
she had no money in her bank account now
she has 10 million dollars
in her bank account
and she lives in a five
million dollar mansion
so where
did she get this money okay she got her
she got this money mainly for
an organization called united against
a nuclear
iran okay and
this organization's primary purpose is
to create conflict between
the united states and
iran okay they they go
against any companies or individuals who
support iran united states who
does business with iran okay they
are a very anti
-iranian organization one of
their main donors his
name is sheldon alderson
and
sheldon alderson is an extremely
pro -israel business person
okay he owns a lot of casinos okay
so mgm sands uh he's he's a billionaire
and what's interesting about sandal
uh sandal alderson he's dead okay but
he was the main patron of a
man named sheldon alderson
he's the main political patron and
financial donor to benjamin netanyahu okay
he is the main political patron
and financial donor to benjamin netanyahu
so sheldon alderson
supports both netanyahu
and supports this organization
called united against a nuclear iran
and united against a nuclear
iran hired um nikki haley
and paid a lot of money okay that's
the first thing second thing is
that in iran there's a lot of people who
support iran and in 2019 she got a job
with boeing boeing is a weapons
manufacturer they make airplanes
but they mainly make
bombs and missiles okay so
they love war she sat on the board of
boeing an extremely prestigious job
and she was paid three hundred thousand
u.s dollars just to sit on the board
and do nothing okay she has
also given speeches at an organization
called christianism there's a
series of
uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh
uh uh uh uh Kingdom of
Heaven and therefore
they want as much conflict in
the Middle East as possible.
So all this is telling us is
that if Nikki Haley
becomes vice president,
her main responsibility
will be to agitate for war against Iran.
She will be the one in
the White House pushing for war in Iran,
escalating tensions in Iran.
So Nikki Haley.
What's also interesting is
in January 2019
basically the primary is over.
Trump has won everything.
But in January 2019.
even after Trump won,
Haley was able to raise
more money than Trump.
So Haley got about 12
million dollars from donors,
Trump gets 11 million dollars.
Okay? And
the only explanation for
this is these donors knew
that Haley would not become president,
she could not be Trump, but
they're trying to position her to be
his vice president by
making her stay in the race
and giving her as much
publicity as possible.
In fact, even though she
dropped out of the race,
she's still getting about 25%
to 33% of all Republican votes, okay? So
she comes across as an extremely
popular establishment figure.
So this is the the Haley Haley Haley Haley
Haley Haley
Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley
Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley
Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley
Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley
Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley
Haley Haley Haley Haley Haley
Haley Haley
Haley or Trump has slight advantage,
okay? Trump can basically seal the victory
if he picks Nikki Haley
to be his vice president,
because Nikki Haley will
turn the suburbs to him
very strongly, and it's the suburbs that
basically decide US elections.
And as vice president,
what she will be doing is
advocating for war against Iran,
which means that she's on the payroll
of anti -Iranian forces
in the United States.
Okay? So, any questions?
Anything you're not clear about right now?
What if she holds a grudge against Trump?
Okay, so Jack asked a
great question, okay?
He's like, what if Haley holds
a grudge and says no, right?
And quite honestly, she
has been asked in the past,
are you willing to serve
as Trump's vice president?
And she's like, no,
because he's a divider.
He's divisive, and we need
to move on from Trump, okay?
All right. Do you guys remember in class,
when we studied Trump, very
closely, his personality?
We looked at his days in the WWE, okay?
And there was a scene where Vince McMahon,
the owner of WWE, a
billionaire, challenges Trump
to a fight, right?
Well, guess what, guys?
Politics is the same thing.
It's all theater, okay?
Politics is theater. What Nikki Haley
and Donald Trump are doing is
pretending to be bitter enemies,
so that their reconciliation will be
so dramatic. You understand?
So, Nikki Haley served under
Trump in the first administration,
okay? So, from 2016 to 2018,
she was used to being a fighter. She was
used to being an ambassador for Trump.
And everyone says that the
two got along really well.
In fact,
Trump was considering
having her be his VP,
running mate, in 2020.
He was thinking of dropping Mike Pence
and putting her on the ticket, okay?
So, the two of them together
actually have a great rapport.
The two respect each other.
They get along very well, okay?
So, that's the first thing.
Second thing is that,
the thing to know about very
successful politicians is they are first
and foremost opportunists.
They have no ideas.
They have no principles.
All they care about is
political power, right?
So, why would Nikki Haley
agree to be Vice President?
Why? Because
there's one step away from the presidency.
presidency, do you understand? If anything
happens to Trump, she's president.
And in four years time, she can run as
the Republican nominee for the presidency.
Does that make sense? So that's the thing
you need to know about politicians.
All they care about is political power.
They will do anything to
achieve political power.
They will sell their own mother
to achieve political power.
But it's the same thing for rich people.
Rich people love money.
They will do anything to get money.
Sell their own mother, fine.
Also, celebrities, famous people, right?
All they care about is fame.
So, do you understand, Jack?
Any more questions?
Is this clear to you guys?
Is there anything you're not clear about?
I'll explain further.
Is there anything that
Biden could do before the election
to have an advantage over Trump?
Okay, so Jack asked a
great question, okay?
Well, listen. Like,
I can figure this out just
by reading the news, right?
Biden has an amazing team
of extremely well -paid,
professional, experienced
strategists working with him.
They know this. They
can see what's going on.
So, what can Biden do to
counter Trump's strategy
or the polls, okay?
And the answer is this.
If you look at 2020,
everyone thought
that Biden could not get
the nomination, okay?
Why? Because he lacks charisma.
Nobody really likes him, okay?
So, when Biden goes to school, he's
not going to get the nomination.
He's going to speak. There's
no one there to listen to him.
He's boring, and he has
no ideas, and he's old.
I mean, Biden ran for president two
times before, and he lost both times.
And the reason why is
he's not charismatic, and
he has no ideas, okay?
But Biden's like, nope, I'm going to stay
in the race because I believe I can win.
And you ask him, Biden,
what is your strategy?
What is your reasoning going forward?
I don't know. I'm going to win, okay?
So, if we were discussing this in 2020,
in May and June,
I would be like, Biden
has no chance, okay?
Because Trump's going to go out there and
give speeches to 100,000 people, and
they're going to love him, and they're
going to go and vote for him, okay?
Biden gives a speech,
everyone falls asleep.
And under the debate stage,
Trump will destroy Biden, okay?
So, I was sure that
in May, April 2020,
Biden had no chance.
But then what happened? Hey, the
George Floyd protest happened.
So all these young people
who didn't really like Biden,
they were now galvanized
to go vote for him.
All these black people,
all these suburban voters,
they wanted Biden to win because they
thought Trump was divisive, okay?
And then what happened?
The pandemic happened.
So, Trump couldn't go out to debate.
Trump couldn't go out to campaign anymore.
You understand? Biden could
just sit in his basement
and do nothing, right?
Do you understand? So,
unfortunately, Biden learned
the wrong lessons from 2020.
The lesson that he learned
in 2020 is that, hey,
if I just sit in my basement
all day and make no mistakes,
my surrogates, the Democratic Congress,
they're going to be like, oh, I'm going to be the president of the Democratic Party.
Hillary Clinton, Bill
Clinton, Barack Obama,
they'll go out and give speeches for me.
They'll fire up the base.
And I'll win because
I'm not Trump, okay?
That is the entire Biden strategy.
I'm not Trump.
Okay? The problem with this idea is,
okay, in 2020,
the American people, the American
people, people had four years of Trump,
and they know he sucks, okay?
The problem now is the American
people have seen four years of Biden,
and Biden sucks as well, okay?
And so, it's a question
like, who sucks more,
Biden or Trump, okay?
So, in other words, people are
not going to come out to vote
because they think both suck,
and which means that the
party with equality, right?
The only coalition with a base that feels
more strongly about the issues is going to come out to vote, okay?
And what we know is that
the Republican coalition
of rural voters,
conservatives, Christians,
white voters,
they feel much more passionately about Trump
than the Democratic coalition feels about Biden.
Okay? Does that make
sense? So, unfortunately,
the answer is that Biden
is only going to vote.
Biden has no strategy going forward because he
didn't have a strategy going forward in 2020.
And he won in 2020, so why
can't the same thing happen in,
same thing happen this year, right?
And unfortunately, because
Biden's so old, he's 81,
he doesn't have the energy
to change the way he is.
You understand? It's much
easier for him to sit around
and pray the way that
I'm not Trump will deliver another
election than it is for him to go out
and change who he is. He
can't change who he is.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay, but that's a great
question, all right?
Any more questions before?
Okay. Okay, so again,
I am not sure
who will win this year, okay?
I think it's Trump. I'm not sure that
Nikki Haley will be his vice president.
I'm just making a guess. So the
question then is why are we doing this?
And the answer is this. We try to think.
We have to build an analytical model,
right, of how the world works.
And the only way we know if this model
works or not is by making predictions
and testing it against reality.
Okay? So you know what?
It's possible that in August,
Trump will pick someone else okay?
Possibly someone named JD Vance okay?
The only thing you need to know about JD
Vance is he's very loyal to Trump okay?
It's possible he picks JD Vance okay?
I think he'll pick Nikki
Haley. I often actually...
I often think that there's a very good
chance he picks JD Vance as well okay?
But I'll make the bet
that he picks Nikki Haley.
So it's possible in August
he does not pick Nikki Haley,
he picks J.D. Vance or
someone else instead.
It's also possible that
in November Trump loses.
Well that's fine because if I'm wrong,
then what I do is I go
back to this analysis
and I make changes to this analysis
so that it's much more
reflective and accurate.
Does that make sense?
And that's how we try to think
critically about the world.
By building analytical models that
we can then test against reality
and then based on what happens in reality,
we can go and refine our analytical model.
Any questions? Okay, so
next week we discuss the war in Iran,
okay? Because if you look at this,
again if Nikki Haley
becomes the vice president,
it is very likely she will
agitate for war against Iran.
And Trump will go along, okay?
And if that's the case, then
we need to understand how America will
fight the war and how Iran will respond.
And that's what we will do
next week, okay? Thank you.