Okay, so in this first lecture,
I want to ask a question.
The question is,
why did humanity transition
from hunter -gatherer
society to agriculture?
Okay? And in the traditional
paradigm, a paradigm.
Paradigm is a very
sophisticated English word, and
all it means is story or
model or understanding.
Okay? So in a traditional story paradigm,
we transitioned because
we're first hunter -gatherers
and we lived in groups
of about 20 to 50 people
and we roamed the land looking for food.
It was uncertain.
It was unstable. And then
suddenly there was a Revolution.
we discover farming and
farming provided a stable source of food
that we could control okay the word
we use is domestication okay
domestication just means
that we bring it under our control
and because
of farming we can now create
more food than we need the word
we use for this is surplus
and because
there's a surplus people now
could do things besides farming
so for example we could have leaders
which
creates the idea of politics
right we could also have priests
which
introduces the idea of religion
we can have creative people right
which then gives us arts and
slowly over time these
villages grew into cities
and because
there was a lot of people in our
surplus we could now have literature
reading and writing so
we can now store knowledge and then
pass it from generation to generation
and across cultures okay
we're gonna have science
and technology and
slowly over the course of this
process we create modernity,
okay? Which is the world
that we live in today.
So the pivotal step
towards modernity was this
transition into agriculture.
And this is traditionally what
we believed about the world.
Unfortunately, there's no
evidence for this, okay?
And in fact, the more evidence we collect,
the more we realize this is not true.
In fact,
what we now know is it was
actually pretty stupid to transition
from hunter -gatherer into farming, okay?
For a variety of reasons.
The first reason is that when
you're a hunter -gatherer, it's
actually a pretty easy life.
Okay? Because there's
food everywhere, okay?
When you're a farmer, it's a hard life
because you have to grow that food.
So maybe as a hunter -gatherer,
you're working maybe an hour a day,
but as a farmer, you were
working six, seven hours a day.
It was very hard to grow that food.
So in the book Sapiens,
the Israeli
historian named Yoel
Harari, he's very famous,
Sapiens is also a very famous book,
there's a very famous sentence, okay?
The sentence is like this, we did not
domesticate wheat.
Wheat domesticated us, okay?
So we thought that we made wheat, okay,
the food wheat, into our slave.
But in reality,
wheat made us its slave.
And the reasoning for this is this.
Okay? Out in nature, if you're
wheat and you want to survive,
you have to make yourself attractive
to other people and to animals, okay?
So you have to be tasty and
you have to be easy to find.
You have to do a lot of work.
But when you're on a
farm and you're wheat,
you can just lay back, do nothing,
and make humans do all the work.
Okay? So it was a bad deal for humans
and a very good deal for wheat, okay?
So that's the first problem. You actually do more
work on the farm than you do as a hunter -gatherer.
Which means that now you have
to have more children, right?
You need to have labor to
do all that work, which
creates a problem of overpopulation.
Which means that you are
using too much land and
then eventually the land
becomes dead, okay?
Or not arable anymore.
So it's the first problem. Second
problem is that we're able to
dig up the skeletons of hunter
-gatherers and farmers.
And what we see is that
hunter -gatherers are a
lot taller than farmers.
Why? Protein, right?
Food. As a hunter -gatherer,
you have access to meat.
You have access to fruits and
nuts and vegetables, okay?
Your diet is varied and very nutritious.
But as a farmer, you have
to have a lot of food.
You have to have a lot of food. You have
to have a lot of nature. You have to have nature. You have to have nature. And as a farmer, you're eating only what you grow,
which is mainly wheat and
some vegetables, okay?
So you're not getting that much nutrition.
And the third problem is that as a farmer,
you are much more likely to die early
than if you're a hunter -gatherer.
Why? Have you guys been to a farm?
What's the problem on a farm?
Exactly. Thank you. pigs, right?
Animals, they're everywhere.
Plus, where do you put the garbage?
Where do you go to the restroom, right?
So because people are together
in a very unclean place,
it's much more likely to
contract disease and then die.
Okay? So for these three reasons,
the transition from hunter -gatherer
to farming makes no sense.
And even today,
we are not able to explain
to you why this transition happened.
Okay? We don't know why we did this. So
the only thing we can do is construct
theories as to why this might have happened.
So even though we can't go in the past and
look at why we did this,
we can do some research
and collect evidence
and then create theories
as to why this happened.
Okay? So
there are four different disciplines
from which we can collect evidence.
The first discipline
is called archaeology.
Archaeology is just the study of the past.
So basically, you go and you dig stuff
up and you see what you can find. Okay?
Maybe you can dig up someone's house or you can
dig up someone's skeleton or someone's clothing.
Okay? And from that,
you're able to figure out what
happened in the past. And so
three pieces of evidence
from archaeology we
will look at today are
Gobekli Tepe, Jericho,
and Katahaljóek.
Okay? And these are places that
we've actually dug up and we know what
life is like in these three places.
So that's archaeology.
Second discipline we can
look at is anthropology.
And anthropology is the
study of other cultures.
So in other words, there are
places still on this planet
where people live a hunter
-gatherer lifestyle.
Maybe in the Amazon, maybe in Australia,
maybe in Africa. Okay? And
so we're able to go and
study these people to understand why,
how originally we thought
and why we might have
transitioned into farming.
Okay? So anthropology. The third field
that we can look at is
psychology or neuroscience.
Basically how the brain works.
How do we feel? What motivates us?
Why do we behave the way we behave?
Okay? So that's a third
field we can look at.
The last field we can
look at is primatology.
The study of primates.
Okay? Or monkeys. Because guess what guys?
We're monkeys. We're primates.
995 007 percent of our DNA are monkey DNA.
So we can look at certain groups of
monkeys to understand how they behave.
And there are three types of primates
that we look at very closely.
Okay? The first is gorillas.
We also look at chimpanzees.
And we look at binaural bowls.
Okay? Chimpanzees and binaural
bowls are very close to us.
Genetically they're the closest
to us of all the primates.
So, by looking at these
four different fields we're
able to collect evidence
to construct theories as
to why we transitioned from
hunter -gatherer into farming.
Okay? So now I will share some
of these theories with you. And
again what's really important to
understand is we don't know what happened.
We can only guess about what happened.
So the first theory is
the idea of coercion.
okay. And what this
basically means is that
there's an elite group of
people who didn't want to work
So they made everyone else work
Okay, so that's coercion
and the evidence for this is
that well guess what?
Gorillas do this right?
If you study gorillas, you will see that
they always have an alpha male
The male who's bigger
than everyone else and who
makes everyone do all
the work He just sits and
naps every day, but he gets all
the girls and he gets all the food
Okay, so gorillas That's the first theory.
The second theory is
War Okay,
and The idea here is that
if you are on a farm It's easier to
protect yourself in a time of war
and you're out in the force, right?
You can build walls around your farm
you can Defend yourself a lot easier.
You can see the enemy coming Okay, so
War the evidence for this
is that chimpanzees.
Okay again who are like us
They go to war a lot.
They're very violent. They're
always fighting each other
So the argument here is that
we human beings are just a violent
People who are always at war and
we Must be afraid of each other and
therefore when we have the chance we'll
settle down Build fortifications build walls
and fight each other.
Okay That's the second theory and
again the evidence for
this are chimpanzees.
The third theory is
respect for
elders Meaning
that as a hunter -gatherer
It's very hard on
Old people, right? so
at a certain point
you're gonna have to leave the old
people to just stay there and die and
Maybe we as human beings we are
biologically programmed to take
care of elders for whatever reason,
okay, and again, the evidence for this is
Anthropology where every culture
respects its elders, right?
So that's a third theory The last
theory is religion The
last theory is religion
Okay, meaning that
we settle down in order to
celebrate a religion to
practice a religion and
Just to be clear
There's evidence and arguments
for all four theories
and there are scholars who argued
for different theories Okay,
but the consensus what most people?
agree on today,
okay, most scholars not every
scholar, but most scholars is
Religion, okay, so
let me explain why we think the
answer has to be religion slowly.
All right, okay so
coercion While it is true
that with gorillas, there's an alpha male
Who controls everything?
the problem is That
if you look at gorilla's the
alpha male is huge Okay,
and males are a lot bigger than females
So
it's possible for one
gorilla to exert force
and pressure on the others.
Okay with human beings
That's harder, right? Because
let's just say a nine -foot giant
human being comes into this room
and It's like I'm now your brother
Boss you have to you have to go for me.
You have to give me all your woman.
Okay, what can we do as a class?
Beat the crap out of him.
Okay, you understand because
we have big brains and
these big brains allow us
to cooperate together Okay,
so this guy's around and
at first we're afraid of him So
we let him do whatever he wants,
but then he goes to bed and then and then we
have to class discuss Hey, what can we do?
Well, we can make weapons, right?
Or we can trap him?
Or we can trick him we
can give him poison food
Okay, so coercion
Among humans is Very very hard to
do the worst case scenario scenario.
We can't beat him up. What
we'll do is just run away
Okay, does that make sense? So
we don't think portion is an explanation
Because there's so many
ways for us to fight back
and to rebel against
bigger people, okay so
Quarantine doesn't really work war
Okay, so
We don't think war is a
good explanation either
So it is true that chimpanzees are
Naturally violent. Okay, they're
always being the crap out of each other
But guess what? bonobos
Who are actually closer to us
genetically than chimpanzees?
They're actually very peaceful.
They don't fight each other
Okay, so there's no evidence
that we human beings are
naturally violent
Also if it is war
then we should be able to find weapons
And we don't really find weapons,
okay in archaeology We don't really
find weapons of early human history
okay okay
okay okay okay okay okay
okay okay okay okay okay okay okay
okay okay okay
Now it's possible that in the
future we'll find evidence,
but I'm just saying that right now,
in archeology and anthropology,
we do not have any evidence, okay?
The last, then we look
at respect for elders.
And even though this is a valid theory,
there's an argument that back
then they didn't really
care about dying that much.
And the reason why is that
for most of human history,
we human beings have seen life,
history as a circle, right?
So for example, right now it's summer,
it's gonna turn into fall,
then winter, then spring,
then summer again, okay?
So the world, history,
moves in a cycle.
Well human life also moves in a cycle.
You're born, you're born, you die,
then you're reborn,
then you die again, then
you're reborn again, okay?
So back then, they really
didn't care if you died.
In fact, if you're an old
person, you're probably like,
you know what, I'd
rather be dead, and then,
so if I die, I'll either be reborn
or go into the spirit world, okay?
So they didn't really fear death, or they really
didn't see death like the way we saw death.
Yeah? What is the evidence for death?
Okay, that's a great question, okay?
So the evidence for this is what
we understand about their religion,
which we will discuss later
on and in next class, okay?
All right, the last,
so that leaves religion
as the most likely possibility.
And this, again, this is what
most scholars believe happen.
And so we're gonna look at three
different archeological sites.
The first is Copeca Tepe.
The second is Jericho. And
the third is Catahoyac, okay?
All right, so I'm gonna draw up a,
we'll first see a picture of Copeca Tepe.
And guys, these places
were only discovered
in the past few decades,
okay? So these are new places. We're
only starting to understand these places.
And so this place is in
Turkey, in central Turkey.
And this dates back to about 9500 BC.
So this is about over 11,000 years old.
And we don't even think this
is the oldest place, okay?
So if you did your research,
you will know that
this is basically a place
of religious worship.
You can see that they
constructed this place
so that there are these T -shaped holes.
These are the T -shaped pillars, okay?
And these things are huge, right?
This is a human being and this
is a T -shaped pillar, okay?
We think, again, this is all theory, okay?
This is all what we know.
We don't know that much because this
is all recent, okay? But we think that
these T -shapes represent human beings,
okay? And within these
T -shapes are animals.
And you can see that they align,
you know, they're not, you know,
they're not exactly the same.
This is where we think
that that makes sense.
This is where we think that that makes sense.
This is where we think
that that makes sense.
This is where we think that that makes sense.
This is where we think
that that makes sense.
is a place of religious worship.
Now what's interesting about Gobeitepe is
that the religious site is the oldest,
but we also find houses
that are built later on.
So what we think might
have happened here is that
hunter -gatherers will come to a place now
and then to practice religion because
ultimately as human beings,
and we discussed this last class,
we have a yearning or we have
a need to understand why.
And religion solves this problem for us.
Also, as hunter -gatherer,
you need to associate with other hunter
-gatherers in order to find mates,
to find husbands and wives to reproduce.
And so this sort of religious
center, it's a great time to come
and practice your religion, but
it's also a great time to feast and
to meet someone you can
marry and have children with.
So that
was the original function of the temple.
Now these places are often led by shamans.
And what makes them special is
that they are charismatic leaders.
Okay? Charismatic leaders.
Charismatic leaders are
people like Mao Zedong,
Barack Obama, Bill Clinton, okay?
They're people who for whatever reason,
people just love them
and want to follow them.
Okay? And so maybe what happened was
that these charismatic leaders,
they built this place and
they became like celebrities.
And people came from
all over to meet them,
to hear the religion,
and to meet other people.
And over time,
some people even chose to stay with them
and build houses to celebrate them.
Okay? And then when they died,
what happened was they still
worshiped them in their death.
And so this place became a temple.
Okay? Does that make sense? So
that's one theory about Kobayatepe.
There are other theories. Okay?
There are some people who will tell
you that space aliens came down
and built this place because
it's so sophisticated.
Okay? But, so there
are different theories.
But the one that scholars
most agree with today,
okay, is that it was a religious center.
Any questions before I move
on to, before I move on?
So this means that religions were honored?
Yes. Okay.
So that's a great question.
Okay? Where does religion come from?
And this is something that we will
look at very closely next class.
And the answer is this.
Okay. Even though
we all have the need for religion,
we don't all have the
ability to produce religion.
Okay? So who these
charismatic leaders are,
are people who
have visions or dreams of God.
Okay? Or the spirit world.
Okay? And then they present
their visions to other people.
And we have people like this
throughout human history.
Right? So think of Jesus.
Think of Mohammed.
Think of Buddha. Think of Confucius.
Right? These are people who
have these visions of
God or of spirituality
or of a new world and present to people.
And because they're charismatic, they're able
to attract followers and spread their religion.
And that's what probably
happened here as well.
Because as you can see from this picture,
it was very hard work
to build this temple.
Okay? This is 11,000 years ago.
They didn't have bulldozers.
They didn't have shovels.
Okay? This is all by hand.
So for them to want to dedicate
their lives to building this temple,
because it took a long time.
It took years and years
and hundreds of people.
Well, you needed something
called religious devotion.
Faith. Does that make sense?
Okay? And again, throughout
human history, we've seen this.
Right? So think of Christians.
Think of Buddhists.
Think of Muslims.
Religious faith. So
that's what built this.
Okay? So does that answer your question?
Yes. Okay. Any more
questions before I continue?
Yes?.
Okay. So that's a good question.
Why is a temple structured like this?
Okay? And the answer is that
there's cosmological significance
to the structure.
Meaning that on a certain
time of the year,
what will happen is that
the sun will hit this
place in a certain way.
So it's almost like a clock.
Does that make sense to you guys?
They designed this in a
way so they can tell time.
But their intention was not to tell time.
Their intention was to
connect with the outer world.
Right? Does that make sense to you guys?
So they were extremely sophisticated.
They knew a lot about
the way the stars worked.
Okay? So basically, for
them, this is science.
Okay? Today we say this is a religion.
But their science back then is no
different from our science today.
Okay? Does that answer your question?
Okay. And you had a question? .
Okay. So if you talk to any
religious people, they saw it.
Okay? They were there.
They talked to God. Right?
So we're like, well, you know,
that doesn't make any sense.
But they really believe it.
And that's why they're able
to convince their followers.
Okay? So in the future, we will
look at someone like Muhammad
who had religious visions in a cave.
And you're like, did
he really see an angel?
Well, he thought he really did.
Okay? And
in fact, in our research,
what we discovered is that people
who use something called the
psychedelics. Okay? Do you
know what psychedelics are?
Psychedelics are drugs. What drugs, and
what these drugs do is they
shift your neural system
so that you see the world
in a different way.
When you do that, you're able
to have different visions.
Okay? But we also know that
if you go hungry for a long time
or you meditate for a long time,
you're able to see different things.
So from their perspective,
they actually saw this thing.
Okay? Even though like we don't
think it actually happened.
Does that make sense? For them, it's true.
But maybe for us, it's not so true.
Okay? All right. Any more
questions before I go on?
All right. So
these are great questions.
And keep on asking them.
Okay? And these are hard questions that
we will go over the next few classes.
So let me show you another picture. Okay?
This is what is in the
pillars at Goblete Tepe.
Okay? Now,
what's really interesting
about these pictures,
okay, is that these are animals
in the motion of hunting.
So the fox, right?
The way the fox hunts is
the fox jumps up in the air
and then goes down. And attacks the prey.
So this is in the motion of attack.
Why would they do that?
What's the point of having
animals on these pillars?
Why would they do that?
Good. Okay. Yes. Okay.
So what's really
important to understand is
that back then, and again, I'll
explain to you what I mean.
I'll explain to you over
the next couple of weeks.
Back then,
we human beings did not see us
as separate from the other world.
Okay? Does that make
sense? Animals, trees,
humans, all equal.
So first of all, if you're
going to kill these animals,
you need to ask for their forgiveness.
Otherwise, their spirit,
their soul will haunt you.
Okay? They'll take revenge on you.
So if you kill these animals,
you're going to get a reward.
If you kill them, you must
ask for their forgiveness.
Okay? And the one way to do that
is by paying tribute to them.
Okay? That's number one. Number two is
that we can learn from these animals.
Right? They're the best
hunters in the world.
So before we go on a hunting trip,
we might have a ceremony
to channel their energy
and power and wisdom.
Does that make sense? Okay?
And the third thing is basically, you
know, you're going to have to be a hunter.
Basically, to appease them
or to become their friends.
Because we don't want to hunt foxes.
We want to hunt gazelle.
There's more meat than gazelle.
They're easier to capture.
But we want to be friends
with the gazelle.
We want to be friends with the lion.
Okay? We don't want to be enemies.
So, it's a sign of respect to the animals.
So that's basically their religion. And
coming together at the
religious festival was
about celebrating their
relationship with these animals
as well as channeling their power,
their energy and their wisdom so
that they could go hunt as well.
Does that make sense? So this is probably
one of the earlier religions that we have.
Is this clear to you guys so far?
All right. All right. Let's move on.
Okay. So now this is Jericho.
And Jericho is part of something
called the Natufian culture.
And the Natufian culture appeared about
13,000 years ago or even more actually,
maybe 15,000 years ago in
a place we call the Levant.
The Levant is basically the
Middle East, Israel and Syria.
And what was special about the
Natufian culture are three things.
First. First of all, they were sedentary.
Okay. Sedentary basically means that
they basically stayed in one place.
Okay. Remember, hunter
-gatherers, they roamed around.
They moved from place to place. But
they were hunter -gatherers
who were sanitary.
Okay. They were not farmers.
They were hunter -gatherers.
But they stayed in one place.
And the reason why we know,
there's a lot of evidence, but
one reason why we know is that
they basically hunted gazelles.
Gazelles are like deers, right? And
the thing about gazelles is their teeth
color is different according to the season.
So in the summer and in the winter,
because they eat different foods.
Okay. So the teeth color is different.
So we're able to dig up these gazelle bones,
look at the teeth and recognize that, oh,
they were hunting gazelle in
this area both in the summer
and the winter, which
meant they did not move.
Okay. So they were sedentary.
That's the first thing.
Second thing is that they
had domesticated crops.
And the reason why we know is we're
able to dig up seeds of crops.
Okay. Vegetables and wheat and
barley, which meant that
they had the capacity,
the technology to farm,
but they chose not to farm.
Does that make sense? Okay.
So basically, the way they developed
this technology is for gardening.
Right. They were hunting -gathering.
They were hunting -gathering most of the
time. But some of them, for fun, for pleasure, had their own garden.
And that's how they
developed the technology.
Okay. And the third thing
that
was very important is they had something
called the cult of the skull.
Okay. So
they probably worshipped animals,
but they also worshipped ancestors.
And the reason why we think so is
because they worshipped animals. Right.
Right. Right. Right.
Right. Right. Right. Right.
Right. Right.
Right. Right. Right.
Right. and it's called
the Tower of Jericho.
When we first discovered
this, we thought, oh,
this must be a evidence
that Jericho went to war, okay?
Because it had walls and
it had a tower, right?
The walls are to protect
you from your enemies.
The tower is to see your enemies coming.
But then they did more research
and realized that, oh, no,
no, no, this tower is
a religious monument.
It is the same as Gobletepe
where it is cosmological,
meaning that at the
longest day of the year,
the mountain over here will cast
a shadow over the tower.
The tower will cast a shadow
over the entire village,
covering it all up in darkness.
Okay? Does that make sense, you guys?
Why would they wanna do that?
What does that do for you?
To have the entire village
cover up in darkness?
Any guesses? Why would they do that?
Excuse me? What do you mean by that?
..!
. I know,
but if that were the case,
you'd just move, right?
So, okay, so what's
really important is that
this is like right after
the last ice age, okay?
So it's actually pretty cold.
Okay? They did this for
religious reasons, right?
Because when you cover your
village in darkness, you feel as
though you are in connection with the sky.
Does that make sense? So they
must have a religious belief.
They must have a religious belief in which part of
the worship is to cover the village in darkness.
..
.......
...
..
. This makes
sense. This
makes sense.
This makes sense.
Okay So they design a
tower in a certain way
So that it would cover
the village in darkness
and they could see that as
magic and that's evidence
that your religion is correct
Does that make sense?
Right these otherwise, how do you
know your religion is correct?
Only by performing magic.
Can you show that this charismatic leader?
Okay, who came up this idea?
It speaks to God Okay,
does that make sense?
Okay, so let's look at sort
of pictures of skulls.
Okay, because this was
actually very common back then
Okay, so basically this is a
skull they covered up with clay
and they carried around with them all over
the place and this Is true throughout the world at that time.
Okay, and just answer worship Okay
So this is another picture of the skull
Skull okay. Let me ask
you why they would do that
Their ancestors dead.
Why would they do that?
Why would they have to skull around?
Where's the ancestors now?
Where's the dead person?
The spirit ward right
someplace in another world
and therefore having a skull around
allows you to communicate with
that world and learn its secrets
You understand and
some of the secrets may be like
how to construct a tower in a way
That you're able to cast
a shadow over the village
Okay, so that's their method But then we
also have the idea of scientific discovery
Does that make sense to communicate with
the spirit world through for your ancestors?
Does that make sense? Okay, the
point I'm going to tell you is that
Their level of intelligence
or their understand the world.
It's just as sophisticated
as artists in the world.
Okay There's that we think
that when we go to science
class we're learning facts and
Knowledge but guess what?
Maybe a thousand years from now?
people will look at our science,
like the physics, and be like,
oh, that was a religion too.
Does that make sense? So,
in terms of intelligence,
they were just as creative and
as sophisticated as we are today,
but they just had a
different set of beliefs.
Alright, so the last place I want to look
at is Kanahoyak, okay? So Kanahoyak,
Kanahoyak is a huge place,
okay, in Turkey as well,
pretty far from Gopalantepe,
but about the same place.
And this dates back about 7500 BCE.
And as you can see, it's a huge village.
And we think that, at its height, okay,
maybe this was around for about 2,000 years, but
at its height of development, of civilization,
it had about 8,000 people.
That's a lot of people, guys, okay?
And the thing about Kanahoyak
that stands out is, first
of all, it's huge, okay?
Second of all,
they didn't have a place
of worship or government,
okay? Meaning that all
the houses were the same.
It was a very egalitarian society.
Everyone was the same. And
what's even more interesting is
that if you go to every house,
there's a site, the living room
is basically a temple unto itself.
It was a place of worship
and religion, okay?
Meaning that the first,
like, Kanahoyak is a place where
religion permeated, okay, the temple.
It was in every place.
They were, okay? So we think
that Kanahoyak is one of the
first religious communities.
Remember that before, religious
sites or places you went to,
maybe once in your lifetime
or maybe once a year, okay?
But it wasn't part of your everyday life.
Whereas in Kanahoyak,
religion was in your
life from birth to death,
okay? So, you know, it's a very, very, very,
very, very, okay, okay. Does that makes sense.
And the think about Kanahoyak that's
very interesting is at this point,
their religion is extremely sophisticated.
Meaning that they can explain
everything using their religion.
Okay. So their everyday life
and their religion was
completely aligned together.
So let me show you some evidence of this.
So this is a painting that
you will see in every house
or most houses in Kanahoye.
Okay? All right?
So you're like, what is going on here?
So again, there are different theories.
But let me explain to you what most scholars
believe to be the accurate theories.
Okay? So this is just a theory.
We have no evidence for this.
But this is what we believe. We believe
that the people at Kanahoye,
they worship a mother goddess.
Okay? Because a mother goddess
is what gives life to everything.
Right? Think of Mother Nature.
Think of a woman giving birth to a child.
Okay? So they worship a mother goddess.
And the mother goddess is
represented by the bird.
Because the bird flies all around the sky.
Right? So the sky belongs to the bird.
Now, what is the mother goddess? Now,
the bird can take different forms.
This is a vulture. Right?
So the mother goddess can also
take the form of a vulture.
So what's going on here?
Why is the vulture with headless people?
Okay? Because the way that
they combine ancestral
worship with their belief
in the mother goddess is
they believe that when
a person dies, what
they'll do is they'll die.
They'll put that person's
dead body out in the open.
It's a sky burial. Right?
You go to Tibet, they have sky burials.
The vultures will come
and eat all the flesh.
And that is the tribute or the
sacrifice made to the mother goddess.
Okay? So the mother goddess
basically cleans the body.
And then you take the bones and
you bury it back in your house.
And you take the skull and
you keep the skull in your living
room to worship your ancestors.
Does that make sense?
So in other words,
it is an extremely comprehensive
or complete religion,
understanding the world. Okay?
Is that clear to you guys?
What the religion is?
Any questions so far?
Again, by the way guys, a theory.
Okay? But right now,
the most useful theory
that we have about this place.
Any questions before I move on?
Okay. So.
So what's going on here? Okay?
Now, this again also is
in Kadahoyak, many houses.
So what's going on here? Okay.
So different scholars have
different interpretations of this.
Okay? Clearly, this is a hunt.
Right? This is a hunt.
And. And some people believe that
these human beings who
are, you know, part of
the Kadahoyak people,
they are mocking or taunting or
laughing at the animals as a way
to subdue them, to tame them.
Okay? To domesticate them.
That's one theory. But
another theory is that
what they're really doing is dancing
because
they are worshipping or paying tribute
to these animals they are about to kill.
Or they are trying. So,
let's go back to Kobayatepe.
Right? Where they're trying
to respect the animals.
Right? Dance with you.
We're friends. I'm sorry
I have to kill you.
But, hey, we're only taking your meat.
Your soul. Right?
Is still going to be reborn.
Or it's going to go to the spirit world.
Okay? So,
this is a way of paying tribute
or respecting the animals.
They're about to kill or about to hunt.
To maintain the harmony of nature
and their relationship with nature.
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
Again, what's really important is that
this is a pretty complete religion.
Right? That explains
everything to these people.
And that's why it's so
attractive to people.
Right? If you're a human being,
you like, you want to know why.
Well, Kadahoyak, the religion
there, explains everything.
It explains why. Okay?
Does that make sense so far?
Any more, any questions?
Okay. So, this is a picture
of the mother goddess.
Okay? Again, we have, we have
debate about what this is.
Some people believe that it's
just a fertility goddess.
Okay? But others believe
this is the mother goddess.
And you think about it.
If you are a place like Kadahoyak,
you're most concerned about giving birth.
Right? Because giving birth is
what rejuvenates your society.
So, it makes sense that your god,
the person you worship the most,
would be a mother goddess.
Okay? Okay?
This is clearly a bull.
And if you see pictures of Kadahoyak,
you realize that it's a mother goddess.
Okay? And you will see
that they have many,
many depictions or pictures
of bull in their house.
Okay? And what we believe,
again, this is a theory.
Okay? What we believe is that
if the mother goddess represents life,
okay, giving life, the bull
represents vitality energy.
And so, it's the bull that
gives the mother goddess
the energy to give birth.
Right? Does that make sense?
So, the bull represents the male.
The mother goddess represents the female.
But only if the male and the female
conjoin, they come together,
will you have life.
Okay? So, this is another picture.
Clearly, okay, they're not hunting.
Okay? Clearly, they are
worshiping the bull.
Does that make sense? They're
paying tribute to the bull.
Okay? So,
are we clear about this?
How religion was a fundamental
part of people's existence
when they chose to become sanitary.
Okay? Or they chose to
settle in one place.
So, let's go back to
the original question.
And I'll take questions.
The original question is,
why did people transition
into agriculture?
And the theory that most scholars
believe is because of religion.
It was because people had a religious need
that they came together to have
these religious festivals.
There were some charismatic
leaders who were
so brilliant that people chose
to settle down with them.
Okay? And so, they became sanitary.
They developed a religion
around the sanitary lifestyle,
which included ancestor worship.
But over time, because
you're in one place, you're going to deplete
the resources of the area around you,
right? Of the forest. Which means
that you must go to farming.
Okay? Does that make sense? So,
but then eventually, because
you have so much population
and you farm too much, you're
forced to move somewhere else.
And when you move somewhere else, you
actually bring your religion with you.
Okay? And that's how we
can explain the culture.
And that's how we can explain the transition
from hunter -gatherer to agriculture.
And there was no one spark or
one moment when this happened.
We think it took thousands
of years over time.
Because ultimately,
the hunter -gatherer lifestyle was
so much more attractive
to people, so much easier
and attractive to people
than the farming lifestyle.
Okay? But the benefit of the farming
lifestyle is that you had a religion.
And that's why people
chose ultimately to farm.
Okay? So that's it.
And next class, we'll continue this
discussion about early religion.
And how people developed
these religious visions.
Okay? So next class, we'll
look at ice cave paintings
that goes back 40,000 years.
Meaning that they practiced this sort of
religion or something like this religion 40 to 50,000 years ago.
And we know through ice cave paintings.
Okay. So
questions before we finish class.
Is this clear to you guys?
Okay? Anything you're confused about?
Any questions before we conclude?
Okay. Do you see it more clearly?
And again, this is all on
the internet, by the way.
So if you're interested, you can go
online and just read up more on Catahoyac.
Okay? These places are very famous.
We'll be discussing these
places throughout the semester.
Okay? Cabo Batepe, Jericho, and Catahoyac.
Excuse me?.
. We discussed all three.
Okay? But I'm introducing
you to these three places.
In future classes, we'll go
more in depth into these places.
Okay? Because Cabo Batepe
is a very interesting place.
Okay? And
we're only slowly
discovering all that's there.
Basically, we basically uncovered
about 5% of Cabo Batepe.
So over the next few
decades, we'll know more.
Okay? Any more questions?
Any more questions? Okay.
All right. So next class, we
will do Ice Cave paintings. .