Okay, so let's start class
and start to think about the question how
and why did the Iranian president,
Ibrahim Raisi, die.
So when
you do history or you
when you do analysis about current events,
you're always going to have, you're always
going to encounter three major problems.
The first major problem is
that there's very little information
that you can work with.
Truth is very limited.
That's the first problem.
Second problem is
that the information
that you have may not be true.
Okay, so there's also misinformation.
That's the second problem.
And the third problem is that
there's always going to
be an official narrative
that the media, the government publishes,
and it may not be true.
But it's the one that
people people accept.
Okay, so
the challenge for us
today is we know that
the Iranian president,
Ibrahim Raisi, died. He died in the war.
He died in the war. He died in the war. I think I'm going to have to use analysis,
okay, game theory analysis
to figure out how he died
and who might have killed him.
Does that make sense?
But the problem again is
we are working with very
limited information
that the Iranian government
chooses to disclose to the public.
Okay, so what do we know?
We know that as a fact that the Iranian government
has a very limited information on the matter.
That's why we know that on May 19th,
the Iranian president was
in Azerbaijan for a Dem opening ceremony.
And then he got into his helicopter
and he was flying back into the country.
And when he was flying back,
there was an accident that
caused the helicopter to crash,
killing all nine people in the area.
That's why we on board,
including the president,
the foreign minister, three crew members,
the governor of a province,
a local religious leader,
the bodyguard of the president, and
the head of the president's
security detail.
Okay, so all nine people died.
And we have reason to believe that
the most probable reason is an accident,
okay? That
this was an accident,
that it was bad weather,
there was a fog, the pilot couldn't really
see, and he crashed into the mountain.
Okay. And the evidence for this is that...
One, this happens a lot.
For example, in 2020,
the very famous basketball player,
Kobe Bryant, he died in a helicopter
crash along with his daughter, okay?
So this actually happens a lot.
The second piece of evidence is that
the helicopter they were
flying in is very old.
It was basically an American helicopter
that they started to use in the 70s.
And after the revolution, America
refused to cooperate with Iran,
so they could never actually
maintain the helicopter.
So maybe it was just a malfunction,
okay? So
these are two compelling reasons why
most people believe this is an accident.
And this is, again, probably the cause
that will go down in history, okay?
Okay. Okay.
So this is a very interesting theory. And it
requires us to explore other possibilities.
So there are two other possibilities.
Second possibility is foreign adversary,
which means that
either the United States or Israel,
or even possibly Azerbaijan, okay?
But a foreign adversary
was responsible for this.
The problem with this theory,
though, is one of opportunity...
And motive. Okay? So
what this means is it's very
hard as a foreign government
to plan an assassination
of an Iranian leader in Iraq, okay?
It's very hard. The
opportunity isn't there.
So maybe Israel, America want him dead.
Well, how could they pull it off?
It's very hard to do such a thing, okay?
Second possibility. The problem is motive.
What reason would Israel or the United
States have for killing the president?
Now, in the past, the United States
and Israel have killed Iranians before.
So, for example, in January 2020,
President Donald Trump ordered the
assassination of General
Soleimani in Baghdad,
okay? But there was a motive here.
And the motive is that
Soleimani is responsible
for Iranian foreign
policy in the Middle East and therefore
a direct threat to
American interests, okay?
And Israel in the past has
staged assassinations of Iranian
nuclear scientists in Iran.
But again, the motive is, well,
Israel is afraid that Iran
developed a nuclear weapon.
And therefore, the easiest way to stop
that is to kill the scientists, okay?
Israel, on April 1st of this year,
also staged an airstrike against
the Iranian embassy in Damascus,
killing two Iranian generals.
But again, the motive
is, what Israel said was
that these generals were working
with Hamas to threaten Israel.
So, the motive is very clear.
And the problem here is,
it's very unclear what the motive is
for killing the Iranian president,
okay? In fact, there's
a lot of risk in that.
But again, I am not discounting the
possibility it could be a foreign adversary.
And the third possibility is
an internal enemy,
okay? Meaning that there is a threat.
And there were certain individuals
or factions or groups in Iran
that wanted the president dead,
okay?
And so, with this internal enemy idea,
opportunity, this problem
doesn't exist because
obviously these enemies would
have resources to track down
and kill the president, okay?
So, an example of this is that,
remember that when the
president was flying home,
he had, there were three helicopters,
right? It was only his
helicopter that crashed.
The two other helicopters were fine.
Now, in theory, and like we don't know
who was in the other two helicopters,
but we can guess that they were
probably military escort, right?
They were there to protect the president.
But at the same time,
if they wanted to kill
the president, they could,
okay?
So, was it the military?
So, the opportunity was there.
But then the question then is, motive.
Why would they do that?
And the answer is that
the possibility, again, we are
looking at possibilities, right?
Everyone agrees that the military
is a threat. Another argument is
that the military is a threat. Another
argument is that the military is a threat.
Another argument is that the military is a threat.
Another argument is that the military is a
threat. Another argument is that the military is a threat. Another argument is that the military is a threat.
Another argument is that the military is a threat.
Another argument is that
the military is a threat.
and Reizi, who
many see as Khomeini's protégé,
will become the Ayatollah.
Now the Iranian political system,
it's kind of strange because
it's an Islamic Republic.
And what that means is that
the ultimate authority is God,
the Koran. And it's the Ayatollah
who represents the God
and Koran. So he's the ultimate authority.
He has ultimate veto power.
And the president is maybe
like the CEO of the country.
So the person with the real power
in the country is the Ayatollah.
And if Reizi becomes the Ayatollah,
then we can expect major policy shifts.
So then the question then is, well
who would benefit from Reizi's death
and stopping him from
becoming the next Ayatollah?
And what people say is,
and again guys, I'm working
with very limited information.
I don't know Iran that well.
I just read the news.
But what people say is that
there are two top contenders
to be the next Ayatollah.
The first contender, the
most likely, is Reizi.
The second contender is
actually Khomeini's son,
Mostaba Khomeini.
Okay? So
with him gone,
Mostaba Khomeini is most
likely to be the next Ayatollah.
Now this presents a
problem for Iran
because it's an Islamic Republic.
It's supposed to be under
the rule of God, right?
And one thing that
most Iranians oppose is the
idea of hereditary leadership,
okay? A father passing away.
Another argument for
a father passing away.
Another argument for a son
passing down ownership
ownership ownership ownership ownership
ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership
ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership
ownership ownership ownership ownership ownership
Alright, so Murshid Tuba Khomeini benefits,
but who would benefit from
having him as Ayatollah?
And the answer is actually very simple.
There's a group in Iran
called the Islamic
Revolutionary Guard
Corps,
or the IRGC.
We will call them the
Revolutionary Guards.
And what's interesting about them is
that they are separate from the army,
the military.
So where do these guys come from,
and why are they separate from the army?
Well, it goes back to 1979.
Remember in 1979, there was a party.
There was a popular uprising against
the Shah of Iran, the king of Iran.
And the government brought
back Ayatollah Khomeini
from exile to run the country.
And Khomeini, at that time,
was afraid of the army, because
the army had sworn allegiance to the king.
So to deal with this problem,
Khomeini established another armed
group called the Revolutionary Guards.
And what they do is actually
very different from the military.
The military has an obligation
to protect the nation. But
the Revolutionary Guard Corps has a
responsibility to protect the revolution,
the Islamic Republic.
Which means ultimately that
they are Khomeini's private army.
They only own the army.
They only obey him. And
the other thing about the revolution is
that not only were they trying to
bring the Islamic Republic to Iran,
but they were trying to export the
revolution across the Middle East.
Okay? So basically,
the Revolutionary Guard
Corps had two main functions.
The first main function is
to protect the Ayatollah,
and ensure the revolution
succeeds in Iran.
But the other function is to export
the revolution to the Middle East.
Okay? To spread Islamic
revolution to Syria, Iraq.
And that's why the Middle East was so
disturbed and so angered
by the revolution.
Alright? Now,
this was why the IRGC was so angry.
They were so dumbfounded. And because
so many countries considered
Iran to be a threat,
they encouraged Saddam Hussein
to invade the country in 1980.
Okay? And
this started something
called the Iran -Iraq War.
And it was not just the
Americans who support this war.
The Soviets also support
Saddam Hussein and
the Middle East countries, like Saudi
Arabia also supported Saddam Hussein.
It was a brutal war and
a lot of Iranians died.
But ultimately,
the Revolutionary Guard Corps was able
to protect the revolution
from foreign invaders.
And because of that, they became
the most dominant military group in Iran.
And so they almost had
unlimited access to funds,
not only to protect
the revolution in Iran,
but also to export it overseas.
Okay, so does this all
make sense to you guys?
But with so much power,
they eventually became corrupt.
Today, people believe that
they control about 10 to 50 percent of the
population 50% of the entire Iranian economy
and Because
you have such a monopoly
of power it meant that
over time The economy stagnated,
okay now Western sanctions American
sanctions played a major role Okay,
Iran couldn't really sell its oil overseas
But the real problem was the fact that
you had a monopoly of power this revolutionary
guard Corp controlling the entire economy
and this led to
Protests, okay. So
the first group protest was in 1999
you had 50,000 students
protesting the lack of democracy in
Iran what they were really
protesting of course
was the corruption of the Revolutionary
Guard Corp But you couldn't do that.
You can't say that so
they were protesting for
democracy They were crushed
then in 2009 to 2010 there's
something called a green movement
and the idea of the
green movement was that
people wanted a new government
that promised reform and
In election their candidate
the reform candidate lost
and people suspected that
the Revolutionary Guard Corp
Cheated and so there were
violent protests and again the
Revolutionary Guard Corp
suppressed the revolution
And at that
point basically people lost
faith in democracy and so
afterwards every other
President was basically a
puppet of the regime Okay,
and most the most recent protests that
in 2023 there was a young
woman named Massa a nanny
and She was arrested by the police
for failing to wear
head covering in public.
She died in custody.
People suspect that she
was beaten by the police.
This caused massive
protests across the country.
For the past 10 -20 years,
there have been continuous protests
in Iran about the government
and the economy, but
mainly about the fact that
the Revolutionary Guard
Corps has monopolized
the economy to its own benefit,
which has caused the economy to stagnate
and for people to become poorer over time.
But because the protests
are so widespread,
the Revolutionary Guard Corps
ironically has become more powerful
because they are more powerful. They are
seen as the most loyal to the current regime.
Their loyalty is not contested.
What this means is this.
What this means is that
if there is a change in leadership,
if the Ayatollah dies and a new
Ayatollah comes into power,
what the new Ayatollah will do
is reduce the power of the
Revolutionary Guard Corps.
Does that make sense to you guys? Because
he needs to establish his own power base.
And the Revolutionary Guard
Corps was loyal to the current...
The Revolutionary Guard Corps is
most loyal to the current leader,
the Ayatollah Khomeini.
But if there is a new
Ayatollah who comes into power,
he needs to establish his own power base.
So he will bring his
people into power. And that
means reducing the power of
the Revolutionary Guard Corps.
Does that make sense? And so there will be a
direct threat to the Revolutionary Guard Corps.
Now, if... But if the
current leader's son,
Mostaba Khomeini, were to
become the new Ayatollah,
then things would stay the same.
And the Revolutionary Guard Corps
would continue to control the economy.
Okay? Does that make sense to you guys?
Alright? So again,
I'm presenting a reason why the Islamic
Revolutionary Guard Corps would want to kill the current president
and ensure that
the Ayatollah's son
becomes the next leader.
Because they want to maintain the
monopoly of power over the country.
Does that make sense? Does
that make sense to you guys?
Alright? Now, I now want to discuss
who these people are and how
they think about the world.
Okay? Because they're corrupt,
but they're ultimately religious fanatics
that want to export the revolution
across the Middle East.
Okay? So,
let's talk about 1979.
In 1979, the Shah left Iran
because there were so
many protests against him.
The Shah realized that
it was very hard for him to stay in
power despite the brutality of the army
and the police. There were
just too many protests.
Too many people wanted to see him gone.
Okay? So he goes to America.
And there are many Iranians who are
outraged by this for two reasons.
The first reason is
that they want the Shah,
the king of Iran, to stand trial
for all his human rights crimes
while he was king of Iran.
Okay? That's the first reason. But
the second reason is they were afraid
that the Shah had gone to America
to win America's support
for an invasion of the country.
The Shah was trying to get
America to invade Iran and
put him back in power,
which happened in 1953.
Okay? And so,
to counter the threat of the Shah,
in November of 1979,
300 to 500 students,
college students, stormed the U.S.
Embassy and took it over and
held 53 Americans as hostages.
Okay? And they demanded the Shah
be returned to Iran to stand trial.
Now, this is obviously an
invasion of American territory.
This goes against international law.
But when the students did this,
there was so much public support
for the students that the authorities
didn't really do anything.
Also, the Ayatollah Khomeini
supported the students.
Okay? So there was widespread
public support for the students.
When the students invaded the embassy,
the first thing that
diplomats must do is basically
destroy all the files, right?
All the secrets. So,
all embassies come with
things called shredders.
Do you guys know what shredders are?
Okay? Shredders are
just basically machines,
and if you wanted to destroy paperwork,
very quickly, you put it in the machine.
And the machine will cut the paper into
about 100 different strips of paper.
Okay? And this is the fastest,
most effective way to
destroy your documents.
And there are about like
tens of thousands of pages.
Can you guess what the students did?
Over months, the students slowly
and methodically
pieced the documents
back together one by one.
And what these documents
revealed to the students
and to the public in Iran is that
the real center of power
in Iran was not the palace
where the Shah lived, but the U.S.
Embassy. It was the U.S.
Embassy that was directing policy in Iran.
It was the U.S. Embassy
that was responsible
for the brutality of the regime.
And it was the U.S.
Embassy that in 1953
staged a coup d 'etat against
the democratically
elected government of Iran
and installed the police
state of the Shah.
Okay? So these students,
when they read these
documents, were really angry.
Okay? And you can imagine that
these students, because they pieced
together these documents, right?
They're fanatics. And guess what, guys?
These students have gone on to
become the top military
leaders of the country.
Okay? And I'll just give you three names.
Hussein Dagan, who
was the Minister of
Defense from 2013 to 2017.
Okay? He was a student
protester in the U.S.
Embassy. That's one person.
Second person is Mohammad Ali Jafari, who
from 2007 to 2019
was head of the
Revolutionary Guard Corps. Okay?
And also, Mohammad Bagari,
who is still the Chief of
Staff of the Iranian Army.
So the Revolutionary Guard
Corps are staffed by individuals
who hate America and
see America as the great Satan.
And they basically want to go to war
with America to revenge the wrongs
and evils that America did to Iran.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Second thing I'll mention is that
when, when, sorry, when
Saddam Hussein invaded
Iran in 1980,
Iran didn't really have an army.
And the reason why is that
the Revolutionary Guard Corps
had arrested or exiled or executed
the officers of the military because they
were not seen as loyal to the Revolution.
They were seen as loyal to the Shah.
Okay? So, Iran didn't have an army.
And Saddam Hussein had airplanes.
He had tanks. He had lots of soldiers.
And everyone thought that the
war would end very quickly.
But then,
what the Revolutionary Guard Corps did
was they organized a new
army called the Basashi.
Okay? The Basashi.
And this was a very important
It was a volunteer army
of poor religious people
from the villages.
And what the Al -Atullah
Khomeini said to them is,
we don't have weapons, but
we have God on our side.
Okay? The Iraqis have armor,
but we have divine power.
And what they did was,
for, to these villagers, and these
guys are about your age, okay?
They're 16, 17, 18. And they
gave each of these guys
a rifle and
a key to put over their necks.
Okay? And the idea is that this
key is your entry into heaven.
Because when you die in war,
you are granted automatic entry
into heaven. And so, these guys,
and they were organized into
groups of like 22, okay?
They would run ahead
across Iraqi minefields.
Tanks would strike at them, okay?
Helicopters would come and strike at them.
And they would keep on
running. And of course,
they would die, okay?
Because they didn't have any armor.
But the Iraqis spent so
much ammunition and bombs,
on them, that
eventually, the Iraqi
army became exhausted.
Okay? Does that make sense?
And so, they withdrew.
But then, Iran took the fight to Iraq.
But this shows you that
the main power
in Iran, why Iran is such
a powerful military,
is that their Relative
Security Guard Corps
are run by fanatics with
a passion for revolution.
And they're supported
by the Bajajis, who are these poor,
illiterate religious volunteers.
And there's tens of millions
of them for Iran to draw on.
Okay? And,
what the Relative Security
Guard Corps has been doing,
after the Iraq war is,
they recognize that if an
enemy comes to attack Iran,
people are going to die. So they
want to take the fight to them.
Okay? And that's why, for
the past 20, 30 years,
the Relative Security Guard
Corps has been supporting
conflict in the Middle East.
They started something called
the Axis of Resistance.
So, the Axis of Resistance includes
Hamas in the Gaza Strip,
Hezbollah in Lebanon,
the Houthis in Yemen,
Syria, the Assad regime in Syria,
as well as Shia militia in Iraq.
Okay? And so, all the money that
the Relative Security Guard Corps makes
in Iran, is then
sent to this Axis of Resistance to
create conflict against Saudi Arabia,
United States, and Israel.
Okay? Does that make sense? But, so,
you can imagine that there's some people,
and actually a lot of people in Iran who
are like, why are we doing this? Again?
What if we withdrew from the Middle East
and just focused on our own economy?
Then, Israel,
Saudi Arabia, and
the United States won't
have a reason to attack us.
Okay? So, there are people who,
who are thinking like, maybe
the problem isn't Israel,
maybe the problem isn't the United States,
maybe the problem is these
guys because they're fanatics.
And they're creating all these
problems in the Middle East,
which is crippling our economy.
If we stop these conflicts and
just focus on our own
economic development, then
maybe our people will be better off.
And one reason to think
that there are people in Iran,
politicians in Iran, who
are extremely skeptical of Revenue Guard
policy in the Middle East
is that in January 2020,
remember that General Soleimani was
assassinated by the Americans, right?
The Iranian response
wasn't that big of a deal.
The Iranians basically didn't respond.
Whereas, the Revenue Guard Corps, because
their leader was killed, they demanded
vengeance, right?
They wanted to go to
war. But we can suspect
that it was the politicians like Raisi
who basically said, no guys,
let's be patient, okay?
Going to war against Israel and the
United States right now is suicidal.
So they were urging caution and restraint.
And the Revenue Guard
Corps didn't like that.
And then April 1st
of this year, the Israelis struck
down the Iranian embassy, right?
Which made matters worse.
And again, at that time,
I'm sure the Revenue Guard
Corps was let's just go to war.
And again, I'm sure Raisi and
his team said to them, guys,
we cannot beat the United
States and Israel in a war.
Let's be strategic about this.
Let's be patient. Our time will
come, but we need to be patient.
Okay? And
I'm sure that because of
fanatics, they were like,
they are in a way, these
politicians are cowards.
They're weak. They're soft.
They're not believers.
Let's get rid of them. Okay?
And then what happened on May 19th
was an opportunity arise
where there was fog and they were
like, well, here's our opportunity.
And so they caused an accident.
Okay? Does it make sense, guys?
Okay. So,
again, I don't know what happened, but
if we look at game theory and
we examine who would benefit
from the death of Raisi,
this group of people, the
Revolutionary Guard Corps,
would most benefit because
it is very likely that if Raisi
became the next Supreme Leader,
their authority and their
policies would be challenged.
Okay? And
so, by getting rid of Raisi,
it makes Mojaba Khomeini,
the son of the Ayatollah,
that much more probable
in ascending to the Supreme Authority.
And that allows them to maintain
their power, monopoly of power.
And even if this accession
causes a legitimacy crisis,
well, it's good for them because
then the regime is even
more dependent on them.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So, during these protests,
especially the Green Movement,
the Revolutionary Guard Corps was the
ones responsible for cracking down.
And they were violent and
brutal in cracking down.
Okay? So, okay.
Are you guys clear about the logic here?
Any questions?.
Okay. That's a great question.
So, Suning asked, does
the military still exist?
And the answer is yes, it still exists.
Okay? But again,
the Revolutionary Guard Corps
has certain responsibilities
that make it the most powerful group.
Okay? So, the first thing is that
it's responsible for the Navy.
Okay? Why is this important?
Because the Strait of Hormuz
is a very strategic shipping lane.
And so, they're responsible
to maintain that strait.
Okay? And the Navy allows
them also to smuggle,
which means that they can make
more money for themselves.
Okay? So, that's the first thing.
Second thing is that they're also
responsible for the missile program.
. Okay?
And this is where actually the military
spends most of its money, the missiles.
Okay? And the third thing is,
of course, foreign policy.
Meaning that the acts of resistance gets,
sorry, the acts of resistance only interacts
with the Revolutionary Guard Corps.
Okay? So, General Soleimani
and the two generals who died
in the iftar, the Israeli airstrike,
they all belong to the Islamic
Revolutionary Guard Corps.
Okay? So, these three things mean
that the Islamic
Revolutionary Guard Corps,
they control basically all the money
and all the power in the country.
Okay? But they're still military.
Does that make sense? All right.
Any more questions?.
...
..
Okay. So Jack asked a great question.
Why is the Revolutionary Guard Corps,
why do they believe that they
can control Moshtaba Khomeini?
Okay? Okay. So, in 1989,
the first Ayatollah Khomeini died.
And Ayatollah Khomeini succeeded him.
And the moment he became
the new Ayatollah,
he focused on the fact that
he focused on cultivating his personal
relationship with the Revolutionary Guard Corps.
Okay? So basically, he knows,
there's about 250,000 of them.
And he made a point of meeting
everyone and memorizing their names.
He even knows the names
of their children. So
the current Ayatollah Khomeini has a
great personal relationship with the
Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps.
Okay? They're basically his private army.
And the reason why
that the Revolutionary Guard Corps
would transfer loyalty to Moshtaba is
that Moshtaba himself is an
extremely unpopular figure.
If he were popular,
if he were like a clever politician,
then he would most likely
become the next Ayatollah.
But because he's very unpopular,
there's a lot of resistance to him.
So if he's unpopular, if he becomes the
next Ayatollah, it would be only because
the Revolutionary Guard Corps
put him there, which means that
he must be loyal and
obedient to their policies.
Does that make sense, Jack? Okay.
But that's a great question. Any
more questions before I move on?
Okay. So Celine asked a great question.
What changes now that Raisi is dead?
Okay. Now, all right.
So if it was an accident,
then in theory, nothing changes because
ultimately, it's the Ayatollah Khomeini
who is responsible for policy.
Okay? But
if I am correct and
it was a planned assassination
by the Revolutionary Guard Corps,
then everything changes.
Okay? What this means is that
the political class goes away
and the military class takes
over and they dictate policy.
Okay? So you will see,
first of all, there's
going to be an election.
Okay? So in late June,
there will be someone to
replace the president.
And it's most likely that
the current vice president
who is Mohammad Makbar,
the current vice president,
will become the new president.
And this is important
because Raisi does not come from
the Revolutionary Guard Corps.
He comes from the judiciary.
Okay? That's a different power base.
But Mohammad Makbar comes from
the Revolutionary Guard Corps.
So he would advance Revolutionary
Guard Corps interests.
Okay? And if that's the case, then
what we'll see is
the country, the leadership,
preparing its people for total war.
Okay? We will see that the
rhetoric becomes more extreme
and preparing its people for
an eventual American invasion.
There will be much more harsh
crackdown on political dissent.
Okay? So that's the first thing.
Second thing is that
the Revolutionary Guard Corps
cannot defeat America face to face.
Okay? The only thing that they
can do to defeat America and
Israel is to lure them into the country.
And they do that by provoking them.
Okay? So there are different things
that they can do to provoke America.
The first is to accelerate
the nuclear program. Okay?
And the second thing is to encourage
the proxies. What America and
Israel have said is they see
Iran possessing nuclear weapon
as an existential threat
to the safety of Israel.
So this is a no -no.
Okay? So if Iran accelerates the program,
this is a direct provocation.
Okay? That's the first
thing. Second thing is to
encourage the proxies.
Okay, so
right now Israel is very concerned
about Hezbollah in the north.
Hamas has already attacked them.
Hezbollah could also attack Israel.
If Hezbollah attacks Israel,
then Israel can only interpret this as
Iran encouraging Hezbollah to attack them.
But if Hezbollah attacks Israel,
then Israel and the United States
would see this as an escalation
and
they would be much more determined to
eventually attack Iran in some way.
You also have Shia
militias in Iraq
who could attack US military bases.
You also have the Houthis in
Yemen who can attack Syria.
You also have Saudi Arabia, oil fields.
So you're encouraging your proxies to
make things worse in the Middle East,
in which case the United
States can only conclude that
we need to destroy the head
of the snake, which is Iran.
The second thing that could happen.
The third thing that could happen is
basically Iran
starts to attack shipping lanes.
Okay? It makes shipping
much more difficult.
And the fourth thing is basically terror.
Basically Iran,
through its proxy,
launches terror attacks
against America and its allies.
So there are many things that
Iran can do to provoke a war.
And again, if I'm right.
And again, I don't know. I
don't know if I'm right or not.
Then we should expect that in late June,
Mohammed Markbar wins the
election and his rhetoric
becomes much more extremist.
We need to take a fight to America.
We need to avenge Soleimani.
We can also expect that
the fighting in the Middle
East becomes much more extreme.
Okay? So, I'm going to stop here.
I'm going to stop. I'm going to stop.
And we should see escalation.
The acceleration of the nuclear program,
proxies become much more violent.
Shipping is disturbed.
And you have a terror
campaign throughout the world.
Okay? Does that make sense?
All right. But again, I don't know.
And also, by the way, just because
these things might happen, does not mean
that we're going to see
a lot of people kill.
Okay? Do you understand?
But I'm saying that if,
in fact, the Revolutionary
Guard Corp did kill Raisi,
then we should see these things happening.
But just because these things
happen does not mean that
Raisi was killed.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
Any more questions? So, you're saying that
the war is going to be more international
or maybe it's going to be more global?
Okay. So, Celine's question is,
how will they fight the war?
And they can only fight
the war in one way, which
is to lure the Americans
into attacking Iran.
Okay? Does that make sense? It is
suicide to attack America in the open.
Remember that America has
shock and awe, which means that
they have air supremacy, which
means they have satellites
that can see everything that you do,
which means they have special forces.
Okay? It is suicide to
attack America in the open.
So what Iran needs to do is trick
America into invading Iran,
and then America would lose for sure.
Okay? And that's something
that we'll discuss next week.
But that's what they have to do.
And again, if they provoke America enough,
then America will eventually get angry enough
to send an invasion force against Iran.
Does that make sense? Okay.
Any more questions?
Is this clear to you guys, the logic here?
Okay? So again,
this is all speculation.
I have no actual information or evidence.
Okay? I'm just saying, okay, Raisi died,
and it was probably an accident.
But if it was not an accident,
then who would most benefit?
Who would benefit from
killing him or his death?
And the answer is the
Revolutionary Guard Corps,
because they see him as a direct
threat to their authority.
Okay? But at the same time,
what's important to remember is
that any new leader would
see these guys as a problem,
because they have too much power, and they
are creating too much tension overseas.
And they're too fanatical.
Okay? And so...
It's mostly... It's most likely that
they would want to
elevate Mostaba Khomeini,
because Mostaba Khomeini
is not popular, and
he would have to be loyal to
the Revolutionary Guard Corps,
or he would need their
help to maintain power.
Okay? But I...
Okay. Does that make sense, guys?
All right? So next class,
we'll discuss what an actual war between
the United States and Iran would look like.
And what's important
to remember is that...
I've been slacking off for a while.
I've been saying all semester that
the United States will lose the war, but
never have I said that Iran will win the war.
Okay? And the reason why is that
this war will be brutal for Iran.
Tens of millions of people
will die for no reason.
And that's why policies like Raisi and
others are like, let's not go to war.
Okay? All right.
So I'll see you guys next week.