Okay, so
today we will discuss Putin's plan
to destroy the American Empire.
So last class we discussed that
Putin loves his country, Russia,
and he believes that
Western consumerism has
corrupted his nation.
And he recognizes that
the source of Western consumerism
is the American Empire.
So in order to completely free its people,
he needs to destroy the empire.
And historically,
empires die when
three things happen
concurrently, together.
The first is overextension.
And this is the main
reason why empires die,
when they fight too many wars at once.
Okay. And the reason why
they're overextended is hubris.
And what hubris is in military
strategy is the idea of blindness.
So you are blind to the fact
of your own limitations.
You are blind to the
strategy of your opponents.
You are blind to the overall
geopolitical picture.
Okay. You're just blind.
And the example is American
strategy nowadays,
where America is fighting
Russia and Ukraine,
where it is fighting Hamas in Israel,
and there's a threat
of Iran on the horizon.
But for whatever reason,
most American policymakers believe
that the real threat is China.
We must prepare for China in Taiwan.
And if we don't, then
Taiwan is straight. Okay?
Eventually, China will invade
Taiwan, and we must be ready.
Right now, this week,
America also announced massive tariffs
on Chinese electrical vehicles.
And so America is engaged
in all these wars at once.
It's antagonizing Russia,
Iran, China at the same time.
And so that's just
overextension because of hubris.
Okay? Um, second,
second way to kill an empire is debt.
So the source of American
power is the US dollar.
Remember that in 1945, Bretton Woods,
there was an agreement that the US dollar would
become the reserve currency of the world, okay?
And the word, the phrase for
that is exorbitant privilege.
Exorbitant privilege just means that
America has the right
to manufacture gold from nothing.
And the world has to buy it because
that's what underpins global trade.
Okay? But when you can do that,
what happens eventually is that
your nation becomes fat,
rich, and lazy, and corrupt.
When money just falls off the sky,
you're just used to borrowing money, okay?
So all America does right now is
print money and not make money.
The problem with this is that
eventually the world is not going
to want the US dollars anymore
because each time you use it, you're
being taxed, right, by the Americans.
And that's what breaks the law.
So what's the BRICS Plus? You
may have heard of BRICS Plus.
It is an organization
established initially by Brazil,
Russia, India, China, and South
Africa in order to create its
own financial system to counter
the US financial system.
But now there are more countries
that have joined BRICS.
Most prominently are Saudi Arabia.
And UAE and Bahrain.
These countries, okay? They're important
because they are the basis for the petrodollar.
Remember that all US dollars
can be used to purchase oil,
and that's why US dollar is
worth a lot of money, okay?
So if these countries go to BRICS and
opt out of the US financial
system, then basically
this American mountain of debt,
okay, $3,500, $200 of
debt comes crashing down.
That's the second way
to kill an empire. And
the third way is
civil dissent or
eternal discord.
Civil war, basically. And so
what we're seeing in America right
now is growing political polarization,
okay, between the left and the right.
Why this happens is that
people no longer believe
the binding myths.
Okay? And stories that
build a nation, okay?
Nowadays young people
no longer believe that
America is the source
of good in this world.
An example why this is
happening is, of course,
because Israel right now
is committing genocide
in Gaza. Right now
Israel is attacking Rafa,
and they're killing a lot of children.
Most people who are dying
in this war are children.
And America is not doing
anything to stop this.
In fact, America is the one who is
providing the issue of all the weapons.
So young people are turning against
the idea of America as the good empire.
And there's this amazing statistic that
one quarter of young Americans now believe
that Osama bin Laden was a good guy.
Okay? Okay? And, you know, when I grew up,
Osama bin Laden was
considered Satan because
he was the one who was responsible for terrorism
around the world and for the 9 -11 attacks.
Okay? But this just shows you that
the ideas and the myths that bind the
country together are falling apart.
And that's what's causing
the nation to fall apart.
Okay? So the more
overcommitted America is,
the more debt it creates
and the more civil discord.
Okay? All right?
So this is how you kill an empire. When
all three things reach a tipping point,
when it becomes too much, the empire dies.
Okay? And the most likely outcome for
America is it goes into civil war.
Okay? It descends into civil war.
And that's something that
I will discuss next class.
All right? So
let's discuss how Putin is doing this.
Okay? So the first thing that
Putin did was the Ukraine war.
Right? So in February 2022,
Putin invaded Ukraine.
And at that time, America was confident
that three things would happen.
Okay? The first thing
that would happen is that
Ukraine would destroy the Russian army
and perhaps even march to
Moscow and overthrow Putin.
Okay? At that time, that's what
the news media was reporting.
The Ukraine media was so much
stronger and more confident.
And the Russian forces.
The second thing was that
the Russian economy would be destroyed.
Why? Because America was
imposing sanctions on Russia.
So America, because it controls
the global financial system,
the ability to trade,
America just basically
sanctioned Russia and said,
you are no longer allowed to sell your oil
on the black market.
There was so much loss
in the global market.
There was so
much loss in the global supply chain.
There was so much loss in
the global supply chain.
There was so much loss in the global
supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain.
supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain. There was so much loss in the global supply chain.
There was so much loss in
the global supply chain.
happened was that it would
make NATO much stronger
and more united and
it would make Russia into
a pariah state meaning
that no one would want to ever
associate with Russia again.
Okay so that was the argument back
then and today what we have seen is
that the complete opposite has happened.
Okay so
first of all Russia has
basically won the war
and it's won the war
because of attrition right?
Ukraine has lost maybe
500,000 men in this war
so they have no more manpower.
If you don't have manpower you're not
going to be able to fight this war.
So this war has basically been
lost and Russia is dominant.
Russia has basically achieved
its main strategic objectives
which are which is basically the
Donetsk region in eastern Ukraine.
Secondly, not only has the Russian
economy not been destroyed
but it's been doing extremely well okay
and the reason why is that
ultimately all economies, China, India,
Europe, Africa,
Middle East, they all need resources
in order for their economies to work.
You need oil, you need food.
And Russia has a lot of oil and food.
And that's why countries
have been going to Russia
and making side deals.
Also, Russia has been
transitioning to a war economy,
so its manufacturing
base has been increasing.
So overall, the economy has
been doing a lot better.
U.S. sanctions have not been working.
The third of all, NATO
has become more divided
and less united.
Why? Because Germany,
which is the most powerful
country in Europe right now,
is completely dependent on Russian
resources to fuel its economy.
That's how the German economy works.
It's a manufacturing economy.
It takes cheap Russian gas,
manufactures it into cars,
and sells it to China.
But the United States
blew up the North Sea.
That's why it's completely dependent on
Russian resources to fuel its economy. That's how the Germansaurium orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig been a tremendous success for Putin
and it's really shown that
America is a paper tiger
and it's also creating a lot
of civil dissent in America
because the majority of
Americans are asking the
question why are we giving
Ukraine hundreds of billions of dollars
when our people don't even have health
insurance our people are suffering
and we're giving Ukraine
hundreds of billions of dollars.
The other thing that
this Ukraine war has exposed is
that the American empire is
overextended and what I mean by that
is that
in order to give Ukraine
weapons what America
is doing is basically
taking weapon systems
from in Japan in South Korea
and other places and giving it to Ukraine.
So America is not manufacturing more
weapons it's just taking other weapon systems and giving it to Ukraine.
It has elsewhere and
moving it to Ukraine so
America is badly overextended okay
and of course by giving all this money to
Ukraine it's causing American debt to go up
and after Ukraine loses war
this debt will be gone okay because
Ukraine cannot pay it back okay. So
right after the Ukraine war what happened
next was on October 7th of last year remember
that Hamas launched an attack on Israel
that killed about about
a thousand people and
Israel responded by attacking Gaza
and by doing this this has helped Putin
and has hurt the United States okay.
Mainly by first of
all diminishing American prestige right
because America right now is
helping Israel commit genocide
so the entire world is basically
turning against America.
Even the young people
in America are turning
against America you know
these college protests
in America they will only
expand in the fall okay.
And the other problem is
that America has shown it cannot
control Israel in fact people say
that Israel now controls America and
the third thing is that this
war threatens to explode.
There's so much origination around the
Middle East so the origination around the Middle East so the origination around the Middle East so
the origination around the Middle East so
the origination around the Middle East
origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East
origination around the Middle East
origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East origination around the Middle East
origination around the Middle
East origination around the
Middle East origination around
the Middle East
knew about the Hamas attack
or even encouraged the attack, okay?
Because the main winner of the Hamas
attack is obviously Vladimir Putin,
and the loser is America, okay?
So does this make sense so far?
All right, so
let's talk about the future or what
are predictions moving forward.
So if it is true that
Putin's intention is to destroy the
American Empire by focusing on
these three fundamental
weaknesses in the Empire,
and if it is true that
he started the Ukraine war to further
the deterioration of
the Empire, if he is one
who is abetting Hamas, then
we can predict that Putin will continue
to destroy the American Empire.
So if it is true that Putin's intention is
to destroy the American Empire, then we can predict that Putin's intention is to destroy the American Empire. certain things, okay? The first thing that
he will do is he will
drag on the Ukraine war.
So he will not end it,
he will not seek peace,
he will not negotiate peace terms,
he will continue to drag it on,
okay? Why would he do that?
Why not just declare victory?
Or why not just negotiate peace?
Why would he do that? Why not just declare
victory? Or why not just negotiate peace? orig Why would he want to drag it on?
Okay, yeah, the Russian people
will constantly be at war, but
then the question then is, why would
he drag it on and not expand it, right?
He wants to drag it on, but
he doesn't want to expand it.
Expand it means he attacks Poland.
He doesn't want to do that,
he just wants to drag it on.
Why? Yeah,
okay, so the reason is that
Ukraine is turning out to
be a black hole for NATO.
NATO and the United States
is putting in all this money,
weapons, and manpower,
and it's just losing it all, okay?
So, in other words,
Ukraine is a battlefield
to increase American debt
and create civil discord
among NATO and America, okay?
Germany does not want to fight this war.
Germany wants out, you understand?
So as long as this war keeps on going,
it's gonna create more friction between NATO and
the United States, and that's what Putin wants.
But if Putin attacks Poland,
then all NATO is forced
to fight him, okay?
Does that make sense? So he
does not want to expand the war,
he just wants the war to
maintain a status quo and
for it to drag on, okay?
So that's the first prediction.
Second is that
to control the situation in Ukraine,
he needs America to
fight another war, okay?
He needs to distract America,
and the distraction will be Iran.
Remember how, for the past few classes,
we've been discussing how
America wants to attack Iran and
Iran wants revenge against America, okay?
But for this to happen, what
Putin needs to do is talk to Iran
and guarantee that
Iran will be protected by
the Russian nuclear umbrella.
Which means that
America will not be allowed
to use nuclear weapons
when it invades Iran, because
Putin will respond with nuclear weapons
of his own, okay, does that make sense?
So as long as Putin comes
to an agreement with Iran
and say that, I will use my nuclear weapons
to protect you from US nuclear weapons,
then Iran will take the initiative
and start to provoke
America into a wider war.
And again, there are many
ways Iran can do that, okay?
It can use Hezbollah to attack
Iran, to attack Israel,
it can expand its nuclear program,
it can disrupt Red Sea shipping, okay?
There are lots of ways that
Iran can use to provoke America
into a full -scale invasion,
which is what Putin wants, all right?
North Korea. So,
as the United States becomes
distracted in Ukraine
and Iran, North Korea can now
take the initiative, right?
Because what North Korea can do
is threaten to invade South Korea.
And there are about 30,000
US troops in South Korea.
So North Korea doesn't actually
have to do anything, but
the threat of North Korea will force
America to divert
resources to South Korea.
Does that make sense? Okay? And
this will probably even have to force South Korea
in the United States to start to bribe North Korea.
Okay? And we can expect that
North Korea does this because
Putin has given North Korea his assurance
that he will protect North
Korea in the event of a war.
Okay, does that make
sense? All right, BRICS.
We will see BRICS continue to expand,
okay? We will also see BRICS
maybe formally announce
a new currency or a new trading
system to counteract, okay?
Whether the US dollar или
US dollar или US dollar или
US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или
US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US
dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US
dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или
US dollar или US dollar или US dollar или
US dollar или US dollar или US dollar
или US dollar или US dollar или you
will no longer want to use it okay does
that make sense and
um the last thing is to maintain
close relationships to maintain maintain
a very close relationship with china
so putin will come to china more often
and he and xi jinping will hug each other
more okay they might even kiss one day
who knows okay but and
again listen the reality
is if you look at game
theory there are lots of geopolitical
differences between russia
and china much more so than
between china united states
but again putin that
doesn't actually need china
to do anything all putin
needs is for china not to
work united states okay
because in this situation one way
that the united states
can survive or protect its
empire is by working with china
right to triangulate against
russia does that make sense
so as long as china remains neutral then
russia and putin can continue to
exert pressure on the american empire
okay so
over the next three to four years we
should see all these things happen okay
so first thing is the ukraine war does not
end putin will find a way for it to drag on
but actually expanding
okay that's the first
thing second thing is iran um
takes the initiative against united states
third thing is that the united states is going to be a very important part of the united states and the united states is going to be a very important part of the united states and the third thing
is north korea starts being becoming
much more belligerent against south korea
and japan forcing america
to focus more attention
in east asia briggs will
continue continue to expand
uh and then the putting relationship with cdp
will continue to blossom okay does that make sense
all right any questions
so far before i continue
excuse me okay
that's a good question so
why would america want
china's help okay the
first thing is you have an
over extension problem okay
you don't want to be fighting
too many wars at once so
you come to a piece of china you don't
have to worry about east asia anymore
because the real threat from
america's perspective is
that china invades taiwan okay that's the
first thing okay second thing is that
china is a major buyer of u.s dollars
because because of its trade with america
and because china buys our oil right you
want china to keep on buying u.s dollars
so you can sustain the debt okay does
that make sense and
third of all there are a lot
geopolitical conflicts between russia
and china
if you think about it russia is more of
a threat to china than
united states is okay
Does that make sense? Historically,
Russia and China fought wars,
many wars, over the border.
So if you become friends with China,
then Putin needs to take the defensive and
focus more on protecting
the Russia -China border.
Does that make sense? Because right now,
Putin can just focus on the offensive,
but if China's on the side of the United
States, then Putin is forced on the defensive.
Does that make sense? Any
more questions, yeah, Peter?
China's done a lot of this US funds.
That's right. And they've made it.
That's right, that's right. So basically,
what's been happening is China is
now no longer buying US dollars.
And it's transferring its
US dollars into gold, okay?
So China's encouraging
everyone to buy gold.
Don't buy any more US
dollars, guys, buy gold.
And the reason why is
because America's debt
is a huge problem.
There's so much loss loss loss loss loss
loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss
loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss
loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss
loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss loss for China
and the United States
to be friends, right?
Because China exports a lot of
commodities to the United States.
The United States is a huge market.
The United States also provides China
with a lot of technology, right?
And Jack asked the question, why would
China want to be friends with Russia?
And the answer is because China right now
feels threatened by the
United States, okay?
The United States is launching
an economic war against China.
And if you look at a map,
okay, China is surrounded
by US military bases.
And the problem is that
China needs imports of oil
and food to sustain its economy.
Does that make sense? So
if America ever launches
a embargo against China,
China collapses, okay?
So in other words, China needs
to open up new trade routes.
And the best partner right
now is Russia because
it has a lot of access
to energy and oil, okay?
So right now, the situation in China is
that Chinese policymakers know that
the situation in China is terrible.
The economy has collapsed.
Demographics has collapsed.
China is completely dependent
on the world for oil.
China is extremely vulnerable right now.
If America says to the
world, China is our enemy,
then China has no choice
but to find a new friend.
And unfortunately, the only friend that
China has right now is Russia, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay.
So, but look,
I mean, the geopolitical situation for
China, it's really, really bad, okay?
Any more questions before I continue?
Okay. Okay,
so, Selena asked a great question.
Why does the United States think
that China will attack Taiwan?
And the answer is that
America is always looking
to start new wars, okay?
It has something called a
military -industrial complex.
And America is always fighting wars.
So to justify all this defense spending,
it needs to find new enemies.
And it believes that
the greatest threat to the American
empire right now is China,
even though, by the way, there's
no evidence this is the case, okay?
Right now, the relationship
between the United States and
China is China sends
America a lot of cheap goods
and the US gives China
a lot of US dollars,
okay? So basically what's happening is
that the Communist Party is storing
the wealth of the Chinese people
in American banks. This is a
great deal for both America,
Wall Street, and the Chinese
Communist Party, okay?
So there's no reason for these countries
to be in conflict with each other,
but unfortunately, the
American policymakers
always need an enemy to justify the
incredible amount of money
they spent on defense, okay?
Does that make sense? Okay, any
more questions before I continue?
Excuse me?
I didn't understand the question.
Can you repeat that?
The United States is not
trying to attack Taiwan
and the US is very interested in China.
Oh, that's a great question. So
what happens if China takes over Taiwan?
What does America lose? And the
answer is not that much, okay?
You can make the argument that China takes over
Taiwan that Taiwan has a semiconductor industry,
but guess what? You can move that
semiconductor industry elsewhere,
okay? For America, it's just
one of face, you understand?
America doesn't really lose
anything if China takes over Taiwan,
but for America, it's the empire.
It has hubris, and therefore,
it must save face,
right?
Does that make sense?
All right, all right.
So this is Putin's plan.
To destroy the American empire.
And so the question then is,
well, this makes Putin a genius.
So how is he able to do this?
And the argument I want
to make to you today is
that for many reasons,
Russian leaders have a
strategic imagination.
They just think differently.
And more strategically
than anyone else, okay?
And so the example I want
to use is Joseph Stalin.
Because we actually know
a lot about Joseph Stalin.
All right, so let's look
at the world in 1939.
And in 1939, there are about
six global powers, okay?
There's Soviet Union, okay?
There's Japan. There's United States.
There's Britain. There's UK,
Britain, the British empire,
Germany, and France, okay?
So this is the map of the world in 1939.
Now, let's talk about each country.
United States is far
away, and it's neutral.
It does not like to get
involved in affairs of Europe.
But it's suffering from
the Great Depression.
Its economy has collapsed, okay?
Japan, the Japanese
empire, is a war machine.
But the problem for Japan is that
it is completely reliant on imports,
okay? It needs oil for its
empire, its war machine.
And there are only two
sources of oil close by.
There's the Soviet Union far east,
and then there's Southeast Asia, okay?
Now, Japan is getting most of its oil
from the United States.
But the United States is angry at Japan.
Why is the United States angry at Japan?
Do you guys know? Exactly, okay,
because Japan invaded China.
And the United States
doesn't want that, okay?
So it's very likely that
the United States will eventually
cut off all exports to Japan.
And so Japan has a choice.
You can either invade here,
or you can invade here.
But those are your two choices, okay?
That's Japan. You can either invade
the Soviet Union or Southeast Asia.
Okay, the Soviet Union
is a communist country.
Okay? And for the past 20, 30 years,
it's been trying extremely
hard to industrialize.
But it's hard to industrialize because,
first of all, no one wants to
trade with the Soviet Union, okay?
So they can't get any resources.
The Soviet Union is still very
much an agricultural nation.
And the Soviet Union doesn't really
have that much technology and expertise,
okay? Doesn't really have
that much human capital.
So the Soviet Union, it's a huge country.
It's a huge country. It's an empire.
But in terms of manufacturing and
technology, it's behind the West, okay?
Now in Europe, there are three nations.
You have France, Germany, and the UK.
The UK is an empire, okay?
It has colonies all around the world.
Germany lost World War I,
and so it has to pay all
these reparations to UK
and France, okay?
And now Hitler is in power.
And Hitler is determined
to reunite Germany,
okay? Because Germany lost a lot of
land because of World War I, okay, so
he wants to reunite greater Germany, okay?
That's his ambition. It's not to conquer
the world, it's to reunite Germany.
All right? And then you have France,
which is the weakest of all these powers,
but it still has an empire, okay?
So looking at a map in 1939,
and we use game theory,
what should be happening, or what should
happen maybe five years from now, 1945,
okay? Let's use game theory to
map out what should be happening,
or what will happen, given this map,
and given the individual players, the
interests of these different nations.
What do you expect to happen?
What does everyone hate?
Who does everyone hate? Who
does everyone want to go invade?
Why? Why does everyone want
to invade the Soviet Union?
Okay, yes, first of all, it has a lot
of resources, and it's not that strong,
okay? That's the first reason, but there's
actually a better reason why, okay?
Everyone wants to attack the Soviet Union.
Why? What's happening internally
in the United States right now?
The Great Depression. What ideology is
a threat to the American government?
Communism, okay, do you understand? So
there's a global communist
movement in the 1930s that's very,
very powerful. In fact, in the 1930s, and
you guys don't know this, but America
was on the brink of revolution, okay?
The communists could have any time took
over America if America failed
to stop the economic bleeding
that was happening, all right?
So everyone was afraid of communism.
Japan would have loved to invade Soviet
Union because Japan hates communism,
and Soviet Union has a lot of oil, right?
So here comes Japan.
Germany would love to destroy
the Soviet Union because
Nazis hated who the most?
Who did Nazis hate who the most?
The Nazis. Why did they hate
Jews? Why did they hate Jews?
What did Hitler believe about Jews?
Okay, they controlled the world economy, but
there's actually a better reason why he hated Jews.
What was the problem with Jews? Okay,
you guys don't know this, but
they were all communists, okay?
Hitler thought that all
Jews were communists.
So Hitler hated, first and
foremost, communism, okay?
Not so much communism. Marxism
hated communism the most.
So Hitler wanted to
invade the Soviet Union.
How about France and the UK?
What did they want to
do? Who did they hate?
Russia, right, Soviet Union.
United States, sure, why not,
okay, do you understand?
So 1945, if we just game theory, okay,
we should have expected that
Soviet Union would have been
partitioned into different countries.
These powers would have
invaded the country together
and colonized the Soviet Union
and destroyed the threat of global
communism once and for all.
Does that make sense? But
that's not what happened.
What happened was
that in 1939,
Hitler invaded Poland.
The moment that Hitler invaded Poland,
France and Britain
declared war on Germany.
And then Germany defeated
France and Britain.
Britain was forced to return to Europe.
Britain was forced to
return to its island. But
Churchill refused to
seek peace with Hitler.
In fact, Hitler tried to seek
peace with Churchill seven times.
And each time Churchill
was like, go to hell.
We're going to fight this war to the end.
Why was Churchill so angry at Hitler?
What happened? I don't know.
I don't know. I don't know. I don't know.
Because Germany destroyed
the British army, right?
It's a complete loss of face
for the British empire.
So Churchill was very,
very angry at Hitler.
And Churchill refused to
ever negotiate with Hitler.
In fact, Hitler sent this emissary
called Rudolf Hess to Britain,
to Scotland, to negotiate a truce.
And Churchill just put him in prison.
Okay? But,
he didn't. So, what's
the irony of all this?
Germany invades Poland.
Why does Germany invade
Poland? Do you guys know?
Have you guys studied this history?
Okay. It's because
of something called the
Molotov -Rippentrop Pact.
So this was an agreement
between the Soviet Union
and Germany to partition Poland into two.
Do you understand? So, Germany
and the Soviet Union
invaded Poland together.
Soviet Union attacked from the east,
and the Germans attacked from the west.
But what happened was, Britain
and France declared war on
Germany, but not the Soviet Union.
Okay? That's pretty clever
of Stalin, don't you think?
In fact, you can make the argument that
if this thing was not signed,
then the Soviet Union would
not have attacked Poland.
And the reason why is, the other
thing about this pact is that
Soviet Union agreed to give Germany
resources for its war machine.
Oil and food and other inputs.
Okay? Does that make
sense? Because, remember,
the Soviet Union has the Ukraine,
which produces a lot of food and oil.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
Next thing that happened was that in June,
1936, the Soviet Union was in power.
In 1941, Operation Barbarossa.
So Hitler invades the Soviet Union.
Okay? And if you read history,
anyone will tell you that
this Operation Barbarossa was a
tremendous success for Germany
and a strategic failure
for the Soviet Union.
It was a great mistake,
strategic blunder for Stalin.
Okay? What did Stalin do
wrong? Well, first of all,
he refused to defend the border.
Okay?
There were 45 million Soviet troops at
the border defending the Soviet Union.
But they were given direct
orders to not, to not,
to not, sorry, given direct
orders not to provoke the Germans.
You understand? The Germans
fire at you, don't fire back.
And because of this order.
The German army, which was
about three to four million,
was able to overrun the border
and almost reach Moscow.
Okay? That was a great
mistake on the part of Stalin.
Second is that Stalin
ignored intelligence.
Okay? There was a lot of
intelligence that said that
Germany was going to
invade the Soviet Union.
How could you hide the fact that
you have four million troops
assembled to attack the Soviet Union?
Okay? So there's a lot of
intelligence going to Stalin and
telling Stalin, hey,
the Germans are coming.
And Stalin said, nope, I refuse
to believe this intelligence.
In fact, you had German
soldiers desert the German army,
swim across the river to the Soviet side
and tell the Soviets, hey, my comrades,
the entire army is about to attack you.
And the Soviets shot these German soldiers
because they thought these
German soldiers were spies.
Okay? So
Stalin ignored intelligence.
The third thing that Stalin did was,
before the outbreak of war,
he purged the Red Army,
the Soviet Army, of its leadership,
of general orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig
orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig orig prison
because Stalin got rid of them for
not being politically loyal enough.
But the fourth thing is
why did Stalin do this?
And the answer is, what
historians will tell you is that
Stalin trusted Hitler.
This was the ultimate
mistake that Stalin made.
Stalin believed Hitler was his friend.
He believed that Hitler
would never invade him.
So this is what you're
taught in history class.
When you go to the United
States, you'll be taught this.
When you go on the internet,
you'll be taught this.
This is completely wrong.
This analysis is completely wrong.
So we're going to use game theory
to understand why this is wrong.
So using game theory, let's
look at four possible scenarios.
Scenario A is Soviets attack first,
and they encircle Berlin.
Second scenario is Soviets attack,
and they're stopped at the border.
Scenario C is Germans attack,
and the Soviets stop them.
Scenario D is Germans attack,
and they reach Moscow, which
is actually what happened.
So these are four possible
different scenarios
that could have happened in June 1941.
Remember that
there were four to five million
Soviet troops at the border.
What were they doing there?
They were about to attack Germany.
The Soviets had a plan to attack Germany,
but the Germans struck first.
So let's look at these four possible
scenarios and see what happens.
First scenario is the Soviets attack
Germany first, and they reach Berlin.
What happens now? What happens now?
What do all the other countries do?
Yes, do you understand?
Stalin reaches Berlin, and
he's going to attack Moscow.
And then, boom, Japan comes from the east.
Britain comes to the aid of Germany.
The United States comes
to the aid of Britain.
All the world unites
against the Soviet Union.
Okay? So
what would happen in this war?
The Soviet Union loses this war.
Do you understand? Okay?
Now let's look at B.
The Soviets invade,
and they stop them at the border.
Okay? Now what happens?
Now what happens?
Yeah, so Japan still invades.
Okay? And Britain starts
to negotiate with Germany
and seek a peace. Because
Britain cannot afford for the
Soviet Union to overrun Germany,
because then communism takes over Europe.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So in B, we can't say that
the Soviet Union would lose,
but they would not win the war.
Okay? Do you understand? So
B is not that good either.
And let's look at C. The Germans attack,
and the Soviets hold them at
the border. Now what happens?
Now what happens? They
just destroy each other,
right? The United States, Britain,
Japan, they're all laughing.
They're like, oh, they're just
killing each other. Who cares?
Not a problem. Okay? But
now let's look at situation
D, where the Germans attack,
and they are about to
destroy the Soviet Union.
What happens now? The other
countries have to come
and help the Soviet Union.
Why? Why is it the United States and
Britain must come to help
the Soviet Union? Why?
What would happen if Germany
takes over the Soviet Union?
Why would they take over the
Soviet Union? That's right.
Okay? They take over the resources,
therefore they take over the world.
You understand? Because Germany has
technology, it has military power,
but it lacks resources. You combine
the resources with the German military,
they're invincible now. The United States
will be forever shut out of the world.
The United States will be forever shut out
of the world. Germany will not invade the United States, but the United States will never ever attack Germany again.
Does that make sense? So
what happens is after the Soviets invade,
sorry, after the Germans invade,
and the Soviet army is destroyed,
America immediately gives the
Soviet Union a lot of aid.
America immediately gives the Soviet Union
a lot of aid. America immediately gives the Soviet Union a lot of aid. It's what we call land lease.
1941 to 1945,
America gave 200 billion dollars
to the Soviet Union for free.
to the Soviet Union for
free. It gave weapons,
resources, technology, and
food to the Soviet Union.
Basically, what America did was
industrialize the Soviet Union.
Does that make sense?
That's what America did.
The Soviet Union could not
industrialize by itself, but
America helped the Soviet
Union to industrialize.
Let's look at land lease, okay?
Weapons. America gave the Soviet Union one
third of all ammunition used in the war.
One third of all explosives.
One half of all aircraft.
14,000 airplanes.
One half of all tanks.
13,000 tanks.
America gave oil and food.
80% of all copper.
55% of aluminum
and steel. Technology.
America gave the Soviet
Union radio technology,
radio communications,
railroad, transportation,
heavy industry, and lots and lots of food.
In other words,
America basically built the Soviet
Union in heavy industry for it,
okay? Does that make sense?
And also, at the end of the day,
what the Soviet Union can do is
reverse engineer all this technology
and build its own industry.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So, land lease really turned
the Soviet Union into a superpower.
And Stalin could get all
this for free because
America could not afford for the
Soviet Union to lose the war.
Okay? What's the other benefit of
having the Germans attack first
and almost destroy Moscow?
What's the other benefit? And
Stalin really needed this.
This is actually more important
than land lease. Which is what?
National unity. Right?
Now all the Soviets were
united in the fight against
Nazi Germany. Before communism
was tearing the country apart,
there was a civil war. The rich
people all fled the country, right?
But now because the Germans were invading,
the entire country was
united against Germany.
This is what they call
the Great Patriotic War.
They were fighting this war
for the love of their country.
The love of Mother Russia.
Okay? So, and
what turned the war was the way
the Germans had the will to fight.
The Russians lost 26
million people in the war.
That's a lot of people. But by losing this
many people, it made the entire nation
refuse to surrender. They
had the will to fight.
Okay? Much more so than the Germans.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So in history, you're taught
that Operation Barbarossa
proved that Stalin was
not a strategic genius.
That he was
played by
Hitler. But if you just
do game theory analysis,
this was the best possible
outcome for the Soviet Union.
Okay? In 1939,
the world should have united
against the Soviet Union.
But what happened was the world
united against Nazi Germany
and gave the Soviet Union
the technology, the money,
and the resources to become
a global superpower.
Right? Does that make sense?
And because the Soviet Union
became a global superpower,
it was able to turn China
into a communist country.
Does that make sense?
If the Soviet Union did not become a global
superpower with all this heavy industry,
then China would not
become a communist power.
Moscow would not have won the war.
Okay? So
in other words, all this
is telling us is that
Stalin is a genius.
He turned a losing war into a winning war.
Okay? So the last thing I
want to do is Okay, fine.
How was Stalin able to do this?
What makes the Russian imagination
different from the Western imagination?
Okay? So I would say three things.
The first thing is just intuition.
And intuition means that Putin and
Stalin they're able to
read the political winds.
They're able to sense
the mood of the world.
The German word for this is Zeitgeist.
Spirit of the times.
But they're able to sense
the mood of the world.
Putin knows that the American empire
is about to die. And so
he feels important to act.
Okay? So it's intuition.
Second is imagination.
So Putin and Stalin both
have a strategic imagination.
Which means like, okay, they sense
these winds, but they can also imagine,
hey, if I did this, how
would these winds change?
Okay? That's an imagination.
Or imagine the future. And
the last thing, which
is the strangest of all,
is multiple personalities.
Meaning that Putin and
Stalin are such brilliant men that
they embody multiple
personalities in them.
And that's why they're so unpredictable.
Alright? So the example is this.
Everyone says that
Stalin trusted Hitler.
So Hitler played Stalin.
But if you just look at,
if you just analyze the game, okay,
then the conclusion is Stalin played
Hitler. You understand?
Hitler did everything
that Stalin wanted him to do.
Hitler invaded Poland, which caused
France and Britain to declare war on him.
Okay? Then Hitler attacked Soviet Russia,
which brought America into the war
and helped the Soviet
Union become an empire.
You understand? So Hitler was
completely played by Stalin.
And the answer is, so the
question then is, how?
Because in 1941,
June 1941, Hitler did not have to invade
Soviet Union. Okay? He could have waited
for Stalin to invade him.
Then the opposite would have happened.
Then America would have joined
the war on Hitler's behalf.
And they would have
defeated the Soviet Union.
Okay? So
what convinced Hitler to
do the most insane thing
and invade Russia first?
And the answer is,
Hitler trusted Stalin.
Does that make sense? Alright?
So imagine this. Hitler and
Stalin, they're having drinks.
Okay? They're both drunk. And
they're on the porch and they're
staring at the mountains and the moon.
Okay? And Stalin and Hitler are talking.
And all Stalin has to
do is say three words.
And then Hitler is like, I'm gonna come
and invade you. What are these three words?
How can Stalin get
Hitler to invade Russia?
What are the three words that
Stalin can say to Hitler?
I trust you.
Okay? I, Joseph Stalin,
trust you out of Hitler.
I don't trust anyone. I
don't trust my own mother.
But I trust you, Hitler. Okay?
Then why would Hitler invade?
Exactly. Okay? Because Hitler
thinks now that Stalin is his target.
As Jacques says. Stalin is a sheep.
I, Hitler, am a lion.
I am a wolf. You are a sheep.
Therefore I eat you. You understand?
Okay? And, but
Stalin could only do this if
he had multiple personalities.
Okay? Stalin
had to be a sheep in front of Hitler.
He couldn't pretend. He had to be.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So this is, these three things
are the Russian strategic
imagination. The ability to feel
the political winds of the moment.
The ability to prophesize and predict.
The ability to be multiple
individuals at once.
And that's how Stalin was
able to win World War II.
And this is why Putin
will be able to destroy
the American Empire. Okay?
Any questions? Okay.
So Stalin asked the most
important question.
Why are the Russians different?
Okay. Alright. So
the problem isn't Russia.
The problem is us.
The West. Okay? So
when we talk about the
West, Western thinking,
it comes from British thinking.
And there are three distinct
characteristics of British thinking
that's different from Russian thinking.
Okay? Alright. Let's look at
British philosophy versus
Russian philosophy.
Alright? Okay.
The first major difference is that
British philosophy tends to be narrow.
Whereas Russia tends to be broad.
Okay? The reason why is
Britain is an island.
Therefore it thinks very
narrowly about the world.
Whereas Russia is a huge country.
It's the world's largest country. Therefore
it thinks very broadly about the world.
And to understand the difference, what
you do is you read British literature
and compare it with Russian literature.
Okay? Russian literature,
you have war and peace.
And these are very huge
epics. And then
British literature, you have
Jane Austen, Thomas Hardy.
They're great. Okay? But they're
very narrow in their focus.
So that's the first big difference.
Second big difference is
British philosophy believes in the idea of
skepticism. Okay? And
Parasome is a philosophy developed by
British philosopher like David Hume.
And the idea is we can only know
what we experience.
We can only know what we see.
Okay? So another word for Parasome
is the idea of skepticism.
Be skeptical of abstract philosophy.
Okay? Because we can never know it.
For example, you can never really
understand mathematics because
mathematics is beyond your experience.
Okay? You can only know
what you experience.
Okay? And it's true.
But it's very but it
limits your imagination.
Okay? The Russians believe in mysticism.
Okay? So they're very spiritual
religious people. So
there are forces we don't understand.
There are individuals who are prophets who
are sent to us by God.
We can never know who they are.
We can never know how they think. But
we just have to believe that's the case.
Okay? So the Russians are
going to be much more mystical
in their thinking than the British are.
Okay? And the last thing is
the British believe in logic.
Okay? It's like mathematics. You can go
from one to two to three to four to five.
Okay? Everything has to be logical.
Everything has to be connected together.
Whereas the Russians,
they believe in intuition.
Okay? You can jump.
You can imagine things.
You don't have to be logical. Whereas
the British say you have to be logical.
And these three ideas, neural, empiricism,
and logic, they created the western
mind of today.
Okay? So this is what
dominates in academia.
So when you go off to university,
they expect you to think in this way.
Neural, empirical, and logical.
Okay? And if you think about it, this is
perfect if you want to build a bureaucracy.
Right? This is bureaucratic thinking.
This is the bureaucratization
of the imagination.
Okay? You're not allowed to
say things without evidence
and logic and experience.
Okay? And the Russians
don't have this. So they can do this.
Alright? Now,
there's obviously more good things about
this system than about this system. But
the problem with the British system
is like no great man could ever arise
from western society.
Does that make sense?
Because all this creates a
process -orientated,
systemized, bureaucratic
thinking. Okay?
So, for example,
I give this talk, right?
I could never give this
talk in America or Britain
because they would all think I'm crazy.
Okay? Does that make sense? They're
like, what's your evidence for this?
Wait, are you refuting
decades of scholarship about World War II?
Are you telling me that Stalin
was a genius when no one
thought he was a genius?
How dare you
refute these thousands of scholars
who have put all this work
into World War II scholarship?
Okay, do you understand? Alright?
So, in the British system,
no one like Putin can arise.
But, in the Russian system, someone
like Stalin and Putin can arise.
The problem though is that
what happens if you don't have
Putin or Stalin? Well, then
you're, you're, you're, then
this system, this system
becomes very weak.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
So, the British system doesn't
really need great leaders.
The Russian system, you
do need great leaders.
And if you are a great leader,
then you are allowed to completely
follow your intuition and
imagination to do great things,
like Joseph Stalin in World War
II and what Putin is doing today.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay.
Any more questions? Oh,
that's a great question.
Okay? So, last semester
we said the Greeks.
And the Greeks
are more like the Russians
than they are like the British.
Okay? So,
the Russian system, the Greek system,
it's a much more natural human system.
Okay? And the British system
basically, it's trying to remove
intuition and imagination
from the decision making process,
from the intellectual process,
because intuition and imagination
are too mysterious.
Okay? So, in other words, okay, let's
just say that I'm Joseph Stalin in
World War II, okay, 1939.
For me to execute my plan,
I need to write a memo
detailing my thinking.
Okay? Now, obviously I can't
do that, because if I did that,
first of all, I couldn't
execute my plan, but second,
it would confuse everyone. Like,
what are you trying to do again?
Okay? Do you understand? Okay?
And so, the Greeks believed in
imagination and intuition as well.
Okay? But not the British. And
we live in a British system.
Okay? All right? Any more questions?
Okay, so, Jack asked
a good question, okay?
How, like, how much did the
Greeks influence the British?
And the answer is not that much, because remember,
like, after the Greeks came, the Romans.
The Romans were like this.
And it was the Romans who influenced the
British, who then influenced the Americans.
Okay? So we're living basically in a
Roman world as opposed to a Greek world.
Right? Does that make sense? Okay.
Any more? Okay. So, any more questions?.
..
So, um,
this is a really hard question, okay?
What influences Russia?
Well, I mean, what the Russians will
say is that they're a Christian nation.
That they come from a Christian
tradition. And the Christian tradition
comes from a Greek tradition, okay?
Okay? Does that make sense?
So, Christianity, um, Christianity,
they would say that Christianity
is the main influence, okay?
And there's some Greek
elements to Christianity.
What the Russians say is that
their Christianity is a more
pure, or more ancient form
of Christianity, okay?
Because remember, like,
when we study Christianity,
Christianity changed over
the centuries, right?
So, basically, this is a pre
-Augustine Christianity,
okay? Before Augustine..
Any more questions?.
Okay, great. So, um,
next class we do the
American Civil War, okay?
..