Okay, so we will do a quick theater today.
Now, as a society, every
society has a problem.
The problem is,
how do we organize the thinking
of the people within our society?
Okay, how do you create an identity?
And in modern society,
there are three institutions
that create a collective
identity for society.
Okay, so the first would be what?
Exactly, thank you, schools, right?
So public schools, you're here to
learn about the history of China.
You're here to learn about
the politics of China, right?
And the idea is to organize.
Make everyone think alike.
Or have the same basic
knowledge and worldview, okay?
What's another institution
that does this in society?
The media, right? Okay, so mass media.
So when you turn on the TV, when
you read a Chinese newspaper,
it's presenting a particular worldview.
And when you absorb this worldview,
you become more Chinese.
Right? And what's the last institution
that helped us form a
collective identity in China?
Entertainment, right? Mass culture.
This includes, you know, TV shows.
This includes movies, okay?
This includes books. Does that make sense?
So through these three institutions,
societies can create a national identity.
And that's what we're going to do today.
And depending on your society, you create a different worldview, right?
So in America,
Americans would want to create
an individualistic identity.
Whereas in China, we want to
create a collectivist identity,
okay? So
what I will show you
today is Greek society,
Athenian society was doing
the same thing, okay?
But it was doing it through theater.
And the main function of theater
is to create a collective identity.
And the main function of theater was to
create an identity as a democratic citizen,
okay? Democratic citizen.
Why do we have a democracy?
What does it mean to live in democracy?
What is your responsibility as
a citizen to be in a democracy?
Okay? So that's what
theater does in Athens.
So let me give you some
background about theater.
Okay? Theater was the form,
the basic structure of Athenian society.
So there are two months of the year when
everyone went to the theater, okay?
So once in winter and
once in the summertime.
And they were called the
festival of Dionysus,
okay? Dionysus was the god,
the Greek god of the
theater, of art, of culture.
Of music, of sex, of wine.
And so the festival of Dionysus,
there were religious elements to it.
But it was mainly about watching theater.
And through the process
of watching theater,
Athenians created a national identity
that they all believed in.
Okay? So this happened
twice a year for one month.
And it was free for everyone.
So it was the rich who...
Paid for all the plays to be performed.
And that's how the rich,
the aristocratic families,
won favor from the people. In fact,
Athenians considered going to theater the
greatest birthright of being an Athenian.
Okay? That was the privilege and
the right of being an Athenian.
It was the highest honor in
Athens to participate in the
festival as a playwright.
And every festival,
there would be two competitors.
Okay? And they were
called the protagonist.
Okay? And antagonist.
So today, we know that protagonist
means the hero of a novel.
Antagonist means the villain of a novel.
But back then, all this meant was
you were the first competitor.
And then the antagonist
was the second competitor.
Okay? And the entire process...
The entire point of theater was
to promote democracy in Athens.
And they did that through many mechanisms.
First of all,
whoever won the festival
was decided by popular vote.
Okay? The entire process
of theater was democratic.
So there were no professional
actors in Athens.
People were selected from the
community to act out the play.
And everyone participated
in watching the play.
In fact, the largest amphitheater...
These are all outdoor theaters in Athens.
Could hold 10,000 people.
Okay? 10 to 15,000 people.
The maximum population of
Athens was 50,000 people.
Okay? So this is a huge community
event that brought everyone together.
And they loved the theater. Um...
The three most famous
playwrights in Athens at that
time were Aeschylus,
Sophocles, and Euripides.
Okay? And these were
really playwrights, poets.
But they were first and
foremost prophets of democracy.
They were teachers of democracy who
told the Athenian people,
Why do we have democracy?
Why is democracy good?
And how should we protect
and promote our democracy?
Alright? So in their plays,
the very heart and
soul of their plays was about the
promotion of democracy in Athens.
And these three were the most
admired of all the playwrights.
Everyone at that time
wanted to be a playwright.
Because that was the
highest honor in Athens.
Okay? So to win first place
at the Festival of Dionysus,
is like winning the Nobel
Prize in Physics today.
Okay? So, um, what I will do now,
is go over the most famous plays,
so we can understand how
they promoted democracy
through their artwork.
But are there any questions
so far? Before I continue.
Yes, it's an amphitheater.
the theater is kind of like
a theme park in the theater.
Yes, it's an amphitheater.
So how did you all come together?
How can you all come together
and do a play as an ensemble?
Okay, so that's a great
question about acoustics.
We call this acoustics. So how the
theater was designed was like this, okay?
You have the stage, and then
the theater was designed like
this, like an oval, okay?
So in other words,
the sound was captured in
like a cavern in a cave.
So there was resonance. But
obviously you were required
to shout out the words slowly
so everyone can hear, okay?
That's the first thing. Second thing is,
these plays were so popular,
everyone memorized the lines.
Do you understand? So
they already knew the
content of the plays,
but they wanted to participate in
the community aspect of the play.
Does that make sense?
So the two things is,
the theater was designed in a way so that
sound traveled very freely in the theater
so everyone can hear, but also everyone
memorized the lines anyway, okay?
Does that make sense?
Okay, great question.
All right, any more
questions before I continue?
All right, so let's talk
about Ischeles, okay?
Because he was really the first
of the major playwrights.
And he wrote a play called Oresteia.
And I will explain to you the plot of
the play, the plot of the Oresteia,
before I explain to you the meaning and
the interpretation of the play, okay?
So all these plays come
from Greek mythology,
because everyone knows the mythology. And
so what the playwrights did was, they
took material from Greek mythology
and packaged it in a contemporary context
to explore modern themes, okay?
All right, so the Oresteia,
the play is set in a place called Argos.
And during the Mycenaean period, okay, so
this is before the Bronze Age
collapsed, Mycenaean Greece,
Argos was the most powerful
city in Mycenaean Greece.
And when the king died,
he left the throne to his
eldest son named Atreides, okay?
But often what happens in these cases is the
younger brother refuses to accept the authority
of the eldest, and he rebels, okay?
So war was fought over the
Argos throne, Atreides won,
and then his brother comes
and begs for forgiveness.
And Atreides, being the king, says,
you're my brother, I want to
show I'm a benevolent king,
so I will forgive you.
And to show that I forgive you,
I will host for you a
banquet and a feast, okay?
And so the younger brother is
like, he's very happy about this.
But during the feast, before the feast,
what Atreides does is
he kills all the sons,
all his younger brother,
and he cooks them.
And during the feast,
he feeds it to his younger brother.
And when his younger brother
finds out about this, okay,
he dies after this, but before he dies,
he curses Atreides and says,
curse upon you and your house, because
a feast is a contract between you
and the gods, okay?
When you hold a feast,
you promise the gods this
feast will be peaceful.
And so people trust you
and come and eat your food.
So when you poison your food like this,
you are in the hands of the gods,
so I curse you and your
entire house, okay?
And then he dies. But before he dies,
his son,
Agittas, okay, Agittas, escapes, okay?
So his only remaining son is Agittas.
And Agittas is responsible now
for avenging the death
of his family, okay?
All right, so Atreides becomes king.
He has two sons who
inherit his throne, okay?
The first is Agamemnon, who
becomes king of Argos, and
he is the king of kings.
He is the one who will start the Trojan
War and launch an invasion of Troy, okay?
And his brother is Menelaus,
who becomes the king of the Argos,
okay? And he becomes king of Sparta.
And they both marry sisters, okay?
They marry two sisters.
Agamemnon marries Platamestra,
and Menelaus marries Helen, okay?
This is important because,
remember, Helen runs away to Troy,
and Menelaus tells his brother,
Agamemnon, he gets upset, and
they agree to organize this
massive Greek army to invade,
destroy Troy, and get Helen back, okay?
But when they're about to set
sail for Troy, there's no win.
And Agamemnon knows the gods
are not happy with them, okay?
So Agamemnon consults a fortune teller
who tells him how to win
the favor of the gods.
He tells Agamemnon, you have
to sacrifice your daughter,
Iphigenia. And at this point,
Agamemnon should be like,
I'm not going to do that. I'm not
going to sacrifice my daughter,
Iphigenia, so that I could go to Troy.
And why do I want to go to Troy
in the first place, right?
Helen's not my wife. It's Menelaus' wife.
Not my problem, right?
I should just give this up because
obviously the gods don't want me to go.
That's what he should do.
But instead, he's like, fine,
I'll sacrifice my daughter, okay?
So he kills his daughter, Iphigenia.
The wind is released from the skies,
and he sets sail to Troy, okay?
And we know what happens. They're there for
ten years, and they end up destroying Troy.
Who's really pissed now?
Who's really angry now?
Who's really angry about all this?
Cladamestra, right? The wife of Agamemnon.
Because their daughter has been
killed for no reason, okay?
So Cladamestra, while
Agamemnon is away for ten years,
she plots her revenge.
What she does is she finds Agittes
and they become lovers, okay?
And they plot how to avenge
the death of Iphigenia.
So ten years later, when Agamemnon
comes back from Troy victorious,
Cladamestra kills him, okay?
And she makes Agittes now king of Troy.
Okay,
so now
if you
imagine if you imagine if
you imagine about what to do.
So he consults Apollo,
who is basically the god of justice.
And Apollo tells him, you are right
and just to want to avenge your father.
So Aristides goes back to Argos and
he kills his mother, Cladamestra, and
Aegisthus. And now he's king of Argos.
The problem now is, because
he's killed his mother,
there are these demons
called the Furies who
come up from the underworld
and they begin to haunt him.
They're torturing him.
And Aristides
becomes so tortured he
runs away from Argos.
And he's trying to run away from the Furies,
but the Furies refused to let him go.
And Aristides says to them,
I killed my mother in
order to avenge my father.
That was the runaway. So he goes back to Argos
and he says, you are right and just to do.
And the Furies say to him,
we are all gods.
We are responsible for maintaining
order and structure in the universe.
One thing that you cannot do is kill
your parents, especially your mother.
By doing so, you are breaking
the order of the universe.
Therefore, we will haunt you
for the rest of eternity.
We will not let you go.
Okay. Aristides goes talks to Apollo
and Apollo tries to intercede
on behalf of Aristides.
And the Furies say to
him, you are a young god.
You are a new god. We are the old gods.
We are much older than you are.
We are much wiser than you are.
You have no authority over us.
We don't care about justice. We
don't care about the laws of men.
We care about the laws of the universe.
And Aristides has broken
the laws of the universe.
Okay. So now Aristides
is in a lot of trouble.
And so, out of desperation,
the last thing he does is he
runs to Athens, where Athena is.
And Athena is the goddess of wisdom.
So Aristides tells Athena,
the goddess, his story.
And he begs for her help.
Okay. And Athena takes pity on Aristides.
And she says, basically,
I'm going to convene a jury.
Okay. Of 500 Athenian citizens.
And you will make your case before them.
The Furies will make
their case before them.
And they will decide whether
or not you are guilty.
Okay. So both Aristides and
the Furies make their case.
And morally speaking,
both cases are compelling.
Okay. Because even though
Clytemnestra killed Agamemnon,
the fact of the matter is
Agamemnon was an asshole.
Right? Agamemnon killed their
daughter for no particular reason.
And then he went off to Troy and killed a
lot of people for like no reason as well.
Okay. So both cases were very strong.
And so at the end of the day,
250 Athenians decided
Aristides was guilty.
250 decided he was innocent.
Okay. So it's what we call a hung jury.
Okay. It was divided evenly. So what then
happens now is Athena comes in and
says that because you are deadlocked,
I will be the deciding vote.
I vote in favor of Aristides.
Okay. So now Aristides is free to go home
and live his life in peace.
Now the Furies say to her,
no, no, no, no, no, no.
We don't accept your laws, Athena.
Okay. And then Athena says to them,
fine, you guys, I'll make you a judge.
Okay. So they accept the deal.
Okay. Right now you're a demon
and everyone fears and hates you.
But I will now make you stand for justice,
truth, and righteousness
so that we, the Athenian
people, will worship you
and admire you.
Okay. And the Furies say, okay,
that's a pretty good deal.
Okay. So the Furies accept this deal.
And Aristides is allowed to go home.
And the story ends.
Okay. Does that make
sense? So that's the story.
Why, so what's the
relevance of this story?
Well, for Athens, it tells them
where democracy comes from.
Okay. Right? Athena, the goddess herself,
gave democracy to Athens.
Right? But it also tells them how,
what a tremendous gift this is.
Because by giving the
Athenian people democracy,
it basically gave them the power of gods.
Right? Because when you
have these 500 jurors,
each of them has the same power and
authority of the god Athena herself.
Athena can only cast one vote.
Right? Okay.
And so what this is telling the Athenian
people is the gods gave you democracy.
Honor them. By taking it very seriously.
Okay. When you vote, do so very seriously.
Because when you vote in a good way,
meaning you've fought very
clearly over your decision,
then you bring justice,
truth, you bring justice
and truth and righteousness
into the world.
Okay? Does that make sense?
And that's why I say Isulis
is a prophet of democracy.
Because through this play,
he is telling the truth.
Okay. He's telling the Athenian
people where democracy comes from,
what's important, and
what they can do to ensure
democracy stays in Athens.
Okay? Any questions so far about this?
Alright? Okay.
Let's move on to Sophocles.
Okay? So, Sophocles wrote many plays.
His most famous is the Oedipus Trilogy.
Okay? Oedipus Trilogy. Now,
you may have heard of the Oedipus Trilogy,
but I will summarize the story for you.
Okay? So, what happened is,
in the city of Thebes,
a king and
his wife, they have a young son.
And as is the custom at that time,
they go see a fortune teller.
And the fortune teller tells them,
your son is going to kill you,
the father, and marry the mother.
And the king freaks out.
And he's like, I don't
want that. So, he tells,
he orders his soldier to
go out and kill the baby.
Okay? And the soldier takes the
baby, and again, it's just a baby.
Like, you know, maybe a
few days, a few weeks old.
He goes out in the woods. He goes out in the
woods, and he's supposed to kill the baby.
But he's a soldier. And
he feels it would be
dishonorable to kill a baby.
So, what he does is, he just leaves
the baby in the woods, and runs away.
Thinking, maybe the wolves
will come and eat the baby.
Okay? Instead,
a shepherd from another city
comes and finds the baby.
And he takes care of the baby.
Okay? He goes home. In the city, the king
and the queen have no child.
They have no son. They have no heir.
Okay? So, the shepherd
presents the baby to the king.
And the king names him Oedipus.
And Oedipus grows up to
be a very beautiful baby.
A very strong, very noble,
very handsome young man.
When he is of age, he goes
and talks to a fortune teller.
And the fortune teller tells him,
I am sorry, but you are cursed.
You are cursed to kill your
father and marry your mother.
So, Oedipus freaks out and
says, I don't want to do that.
I don't want to kill
my parents who love me.
So, he runs away from his city.
Okay? And he's going to Thebes.
And on the way to Thebes,
he gets into an argument with an old man
and his friends. And he kills all of them.
Okay? And this old man happens to be
his real father, the king of Thebes.
He goes into Thebes
and everyone is crying.
And Oedipus asks what the problem is.
And the citizens there tell
him, well, our king is dead.
And also, there's a Sphinx.
An evil demon who is haunting us.
Okay? So,
Oedipus volunteers to challenge
the Sphinx to a duel.
And the Sphinx asks Oedipus a riddle.
If Oedipus can get it right,
the Sphinx will go away.
But if Oedipus gets it wrong,
then the Sphinx will eat Oedipus.
Okay? And the riddle is,
what walks in the morning with four legs,
what walks in the
afternoon with three legs,
and then what walks in the
evening with three legs?
And the answer is? Yeah, man.
Okay? So it's a very famous
riddle. Oedipus gets it right, and
the Sphinx loses and he flies away.
Okay? The people of
Thebes are so thankful,
they make him king of Thebes.
If you're king of Thebes, you
marry the queen of Thebes.
Okay? So he's done this.
He's married his mother
and killed his father. Okay?
Twenty years later,
there's a plague in Thebes.
And Oedipus, now the king, knows
that somehow he's angered the gods.
So he talks to a fortune teller.
The fortune teller tells him,
well, the gods are angry at you
because you've killed your father and
you've married your mother, and
you've had children of your mother.
Okay? So all your children
are products of incest.
So the gods are angry at you.
So what Oedipus does,
is he blinds himself,
and he exiles himself, okay?
To die somewhere else.
Okay? Now the problem now
is, who inherits the throne?
So his eldest son is supposed
to inherit the throne,
but he has another son, named Polyneices.
Polyneices. Who rebels, and
he fights for the throne.
The two brothers kill
themselves in battle.
Okay? They kill themselves,
fight each other, and now Creon,
who is um,
the brother to the dead queen, the
queen has killed herself, okay?
He now inherits the throne.
Okay? And the first thing
he does, is announce
that the dead king will
be given a state funeral.
Okay? We will honor him.
But Polyneices, who
rebelled against the king,
and who caused all this suffering and
misery in the world, he
will not be given a funeral.
He will not be buried.
And the reason why is, Greeks believe that
only by burying the dead, can
they find peace in the afterworld.
Okay? So it's a very serious
thing not to bury the dead.
Antigone, who is the daughter of Oedipus,
and the sister of Polyneices,
she finds out about this, and
she thinks this is unjust.
Polyneices has done a lot of bad things,
but no one deserves this.
Okay? So she secretly buries Polyneices.
Creon finds out, and demands
Antigone to be arrested.
And Creon says to her,
how dare you defy my laws?
How dare you disrespect my orders?
And Antigone says to him,
your laws are unjust.
And Creon says,
the laws are the laws.
Without laws, there
would be complete chaos.
And Antigone responds by saying,
human laws must conform to justice.
There are these laws in the
universe that are divine,
unwritten, and immutable.
And we must respect these laws.
Human laws cannot override
these laws of justice.
And this makes Creon very angry.
And so he sentences her to
death for disobeying him.
The problem is,
Antigone is the fiance of Haman,
who is Creon's son.
So Haman, the prince, comes and
begs his father to relent.
And Haman says,
can you please forgive Antigone?
And Creon thinks his son has betrayed him.
Your love for Antigone has blinded you
from seeing the truth,
from doing what is right.
And Haman responds and says, father,
I'm not doing this for Antigone,
I'm doing this for you.
And the reason why is,
the people of Thebes
fully support Antigone.
They think she is a hero.
They think she is just and right
to want to bury her brother.
They think you are a tyrant, father.
And Creon says,
should I obey the mob?
Should I, the king,
listen to the mob?
And then Haman says, no, you should
listen to what is right and just.
Creon gets very angry and kicks Haman out.
But then Creon has a change of heart,
and he doesn't know if he
has done the right thing.
So he talks to a fortune teller.
And the fortune teller tells him,
Antigone is right in this situation.
You have to save her. If you don't save her, if
she dies, the gods will be very angry at you.
And that scares Creon.
So Creon and his guards,
they look for Antigone.
But when they find Antigone, she
is in a cave and she is dead.
She has killed herself. Because
she doesn't want to be executed.
And weeping over the bones,
the body of Antigone is Haman.
He is crying. He is so depressed and sad.
And Creon sees his son crying.
And he tries to put his hand on him
and console him. The moment
that Haman sees his father,
he becomes so angry, he
lunges at him with his sword.
But he misses.
And when he finds out he has
failed to kill his father,
in his anger and in his
grief, he kills himself.
So both Antigone and Haman are now dead.
And when Haman's mother
finds out about this,
she kills herself too.
And now Creon is alone in the world.
Does that make sense?
So does this story make sense to you?
Now what does this story mean?
Well, remember, Athens is a democracy.
And so this is a message that's
very much anti -king, right?
Like, let's not have a king,
because kings do stupid things.
And why do kings do stupid
things? Because of hubris.
The problem with kings,
with monarchy, with power
is people develop hubris,
arrogance, right? Violent,
excessive arrogance.
And that makes them do stupid things.
Like, listen, like, refuse to listen,
to what is right and good and just.
That's why kingship is a bad thing.
That's why we Athenians have
democracy and not a king.
So that's the first message.
The second message is basically,
the world works when
the old give way to the young.
The old must always listen to the young.
So remember that in the Oresteia,
the play ends with the
Furies, the old gods,
giving way to the new gods, who
bring justice into the world, okay?
The Oedipus trilogy ends in tragedy
because the old king refuses
to give way to young people.
So the other message is,
society works, there is truth and
justice in the world when the
old give way to the young.
Right? So those are the two
main messages of this play.
Any questions so far? Before I move on.
Oh, that's a great question.
Why do people trust the fortune tellers?
Because remember, everyone's religious.
So the fortune tellers
speak on behalf of the gods.
Okay? They're called seers or prophets.
Or, uh, divinity need whores, okay?
So their job, what makes them special is,
they're able to interpret
the will of the gods.
And that's why the kings listen to them.
Okay? And remember, this is,
for most of human history,
humans were extremely religious
people, including the Greeks.
The Greeks were especially,
incredibly religious.
Okay? Does that make sense?
All right. Okay.
Any more questions before I move on?
All right. Let's talk
about, um, Euboides, okay?
And Euboides, was,
he's the youngest of these three.
And he's the least, he
was the least prized,
or the least respected,
in Athens, when he was alive.
Okay? And the reason why is,
as you can see, there were
Scylla and Oedipus, Rex, um,
trilogy, they celebrate
Athenian democracy.
But Euboides, he criticized
All right? So the example is, in 415 BCE,
and this is the height of
the Peloponnesian War, okay?
He put on a play called, Children, Woman.
And, this play is about the
aftermath, of the Trojan War.
So at the end of the Trojan War,
all the Trojan men are killed.
And, the custom is to enslave,
the Trojan, uh, woman.
Okay? So, one character is Hecuba.
And Hecuba is the queen, of Troy.
And Priam, um, her
husband, he's been killed.
Okay? Hecuba, is a tragic figure, because,
um, she's seen all her sons die.
And then one of her daughters,
has been sacrificed,
killed, by the Trojan War.
Uh, for Achilles. Achilles
died in, in the war.
And, Achilles is dead.
So they sacrificed, a young
girl, who's a princess of Troy,
Hecuba's daughter, in order to
accompany him, in the afterworld.
So either, uh,
so all her daughters, have either been killed,
by the Greeks, or they've been enslaved.
Okay? And, been forced to be
the mistress, or the concubine,
of the Greek, uh, heroes, like Odysseus.
Okay? Then you have, Andromache.
Andromache, um,
is the wife of Hector, the
prince of Troy, who died,
at the hands of Achilles. Okay?
So, she saw the death, of her husband.
And she has a young baby.
Okay? And he, and this young
baby, is only, a few months old.
But, he's a boy. And the
law, at that time, is,
all boys, must be killed, because
the Greeks fear, if he goes up,
and he's a, and he's the
son of Hector, right?
He might want revenge. Okay?
So, Andromache, must witness,
the Greeks killing, um,
her son. Who's only, again,
only a few months old.
And then, and then, Hecuba is
dragged away, to be a slave.
To be basically, a mistress, a
lover, of a Greek general, Odysseus.
And so, Hecuba, must
portionally, bury, the dead,
child. Okay? And, and so, it is,
a play that made everyone, in Athens,
weep. What makes this play
powerful, is that, the year before,
416 BCE, and this is again, during
the height, of the Pelagian War,
Athens was attacking, everyone.
Okay? Including, Melos.
An island, called Melos.
And when they, attacked Melos, they killed
all the men, and enslaved all the women.
So, in many ways, children, the
children, women, is a direct response,
to, what happened in Melos.
Okay? Euripides is telling the Athenian
people, do you see how terrible we are?
We are a terrible people.
Do you see, all the hurt, and suffering,
we've brought onto the world,
because of our empire?
Okay? Now, obviously,
the Athenian people
didn't like this, play.
And so he lost,
in the competition, to this obscure,
nobody. Okay? And Euripides got
really angry, about all this.
He was very bitter, about all this.
So he exiled himself, to Macedonia.
Okay? Where he died.
Okay? He died, away from Athens.
And his last play, he wrote his
last play, called the Bacchae,
in Macedonia. And after he died,
his friends, brought this
play, back to Athens.
And this play, Bacchae, is
considered, his masterpiece.
His best play. Okay?
So again, what I will do now,
is, I will explain to you,
the Bacchae, the plot of the Bacchae, and then
I will explain, what the interpretation is.
Okay? All right.
So, there's a god, there's
a god, named Dionysus.
Another name for Dionysus, is Bacchus.
Okay? So the Bacchae, are
people who worship, Dionysus.
The god of, theater, of music,
of festivals, of wine, of sex.
Okay? Now,
Dionysus, the last, legend
is, he was born, in Thebes,
to a, Theban princess.
And, his father was, Zeus,
the king of the gods.
Okay? Zeus likes to go
around, and rape women.
Okay? And he has many, many
children, including Dionysus.
But when, the princess
of Thebes, announced,
that she's been, impregnated
by Zeus, no one believed her.
Everyone laughed at her. Okay? And,
the people of Thebes, refused
to believe, refused to worship,
Dionysus. Now, Dionysus, is worshipped,
all around the world, including
in India, as far away as India.
So, Dionysus, has always
been bitter, about all this.
Okay? He's bitter about the fact, that
his wife, his mother, was insulted,
by the Theban people. He's also
bitter about the fact, that
people, Theban people,
don't pay homage to him.
Okay? So, he plots his revenge.
What he does is, he disguises,
disguises himself, as a wanderer.
Okay? He makes the woman,
of Thebes, insane.
Okay? He makes, he makes them,
worship him. And, what they do is,
they run off, to the mountains,
where they have sex orgies.
Okay? They're having like, sex,
they're doing all these crazy things,
in the worship of Dionysus.
The king of Thebes, his name is Pentius,
Pentius, he hears about this.
He hears, he hears about all this chaos.
And, he decides, to go to the temple, and he decides, you know what?
I'm going to, get my army, go in
the mountains, and kill everyone.
Okay? Because, the Bacchae,
are too disruptive. They are,
amoral. Okay? And, he's about
to do this, but then, Dionysus,
the wanderer, tells him,
hey, I'll make you a deal.
Don't kill the Bacchae.
I want to take you,
into the mountains, and together, we
can watch them, have sex together.
Okay? We can, watch their sex, parties.
And, Pentius says, okay,
that's interesting. Okay?
So, together, the two,
go into the mountains, and
they hide behind, a rock,
as the Bacchae, are about,
to worship, Dionysus.
Pentius, is hiding behind the rock,
and he can't really see, that clearly.
Okay? But, he's really excited.
He really wants to see,
the Bacchae, in action.
So, Dionysus says,
why don't you climb, that tree,
and you'll have a better
view, of all the action.
Okay? So, Pentius climbs the
tree, and he hangs by the branch.
Okay? And he has a very clear view,
of the Bacchae, who are in a circle.
Then, what Dionysus does
is, he lowers the branch,
so, like, Pentius,
is now in a circle, of the woman.
And, Dionysus commands the woman,
to kill Pentius, to rip his body apart.
Okay? And, when the woman, in that circle,
is actually Pentius' mother, and she's
the mother, she's the head of Pentius.
Okay? So, Pentius dies in the,
mountains. The people of
Thebes, are now very anxious.
The king, has disappeared.
The woman of Thebes, are in the mountains.
Then, Pentius' mother, comes back,
and she's running, she's really excited.
Okay? And she's holding,
the head, of Pentius.
And she's shouting to the people of
Thebes, look how, wonderful I am.
Look how, brave, you are.
How brave, and courageous, and strong I
am, because I'm holding a lion's head.
By my bare hands, with
my bare hands, I killed,
a lion, and ripped the head off, his body.
Here it is. Okay? And it
takes a very long time,
for the people of Thebes, to convince her,
that's not a lion's head
man, that's your son's head.
Okay? So, this is an extremely,
weird, play. Okay?
It's really weird. And, there
are different, interpretations,
of what this means. And I'll
tell you, my interpretation.
Alright? So,
a, think about this image.
Okay? A mother, holds, the son's head,
in her hand, and she's
celebrating, how brave she is.
Right? Now,
I think this is a metaphor for,
war and empire.
The reason why is, war and empire,
happens, when,
old people, send their children,
to die, to fight and
die, for, their glory.
Does that make sense? Right?
So, this image, of a mother,
holding the son, holding her
son's head, and shouting,
to the whole world, look how brave I am.
Look how great I am. Okay? It's
really a metaphor, or an image, for,
war and empire. Okay?
Because remember, the Peloponnesian
War, is really about, building empire.
Right? Athens wants to build its empire,
and it's sacrificing its young
people, in order to accomplish this.
So the Bacchae, is a direct criticism,
of, the Athenian Empire,
and it's direct criticism,
of the Peloponnesian War.
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright.
So, the Peloponnesian War, some further
evidence, to support this interpretation,
is, in 431 BCE,
the Peloponnesian War, between
Sparta and Athens, started.
And about a year afterwards,
a lot of Athenian men, are dead.
And it is the custom,
at that time, to honor,
the war dead, by holding,
a huge, state funeral.
Okay? So the state, Athens,
will pay for the burial,
of all its war dead.
During this huge funeral,
all Athenians come out,
to watch an oration.
And so, Pericles,
who, again, remember, we'll talk
more about Pericles, later on.
But Pericles, he's the, basically,
the first citizen, of Athens.
Which basically means,
he's the king of Athens.
Okay? And he gives his funeral oration,
during this time. And the funeral oration,
is considered, by many, to be
the greatest speech, ever made.
Okay? It is beautiful, it is, um,
extremely eloquent, it's very powerful.
In the speech, he says this,
Athens, is the greatest place,
ever. And that's because,
we celebrate, excellence.
Athens is a place, where
anyone can come, and
through hard work, through
talent, can achieve greatness.
We are an open, tolerant,
cosmopolitan, people.
We have a democracy.
Where everyone can participate, in the
civic life, the political life, of Athens.
That's what makes Athens glorious.
Therefore, we must protect,
our democracy, through war.
It is good, that the young, go out and
fight, for our empire, our democracy.
Because that's what gives,
meaning, to their lives.
These men, who are dead, to the people,
who are dead before us, they died well.
Because they died, protecting Athens.
And defending, our democracy.
And we should, have all young
men, go and fight for us.
Okay? That's the speech.
That's literally, what he says.
So, Euripides, was probably,
in the audience, right?
Because everyone was, in the audience,
when, when the speech was given.
Okay? And he, reimagines, his funeral,
as, the, the mother,
holding, the son's head,
and saying to the world,
look how brave I am.
Okay? What Pericles is really saying is,
we're an empire, an empire is so good,
because it brings glory,
to the old people.
And so, the young, must protect the glory,
of the old people, by dying in a war.
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
So, but, if you think about it, okay?
Even though, Euripides, is,
criticizing Athenian democracy,
what he's really doing, is also,
trying to defend, Athenian democracy.
Because a democracy only happens,
when, citizens are
engaged in a process of,
argumentation, debate,
and self -reflection.
And so, what Euripides
is really trying to do,
is put a mirror,
before, the Athenian people, and
he's saying to the Athenian people,
look how awful we are, we can do better.
And that's what a democracy, really is.
It's an open, and honest discussion,
about, how we can be better.
Okay? And again,
these three, Isulis,
Sophocles, and Euripides, are considered,
the three greatest playwrights, in the world.
In, Athenian history.
And, these plays are actually
still performed today.
Okay? So, the Orestia,
Oedipus Rex, and the Bacchae,
are still performed,
in theaters, around the world, today.
That's how, amazing,
they were. So, any questions?
Oh, okay, great question.
Okay? So, the Bacchae,
how do other scholars
interpret the Bacchae?
Right? Okay. So, they're
given interpretations, but
the most common interpretation is, it is,
a play, that explores,
the idea of religious yield.
Religious devotion. Or,
religious fanaticism.
Okay? Okay?
Does that make sense? That's
the most common interpretation.
This play is really about,
the power, of religion, and faith.
And how it drives us, into madness.
Okay? That's the, most
common interpretation.
Another interpretation is,
well, Dionysus,
is the villain.
Okay? He's not really the villain,
but he's, the main focus, of,
this play. And Dionysus, the main
character, does a lot of bad things.
Well, guess what? For most of his life,
Euripides, was participating, in the
festival of Dionysus, hoping, to,
win first place. Right?
To, to be the protagonist.
Uh, to, win, first place.
But, most of the times, he lost.
Because, he, he kept on,
offending the Athenian people.
Right? So, another
interpretation is, this,
play, Bacchae, it's a
satire, on the power,
of Dionysus, and of theater in general.
Okay? It's a direct criticism,
of the festival of Dionysus.
And what he, and what, and what,
Euripides is really saying is, the
festival of Dionysus, it's not,
about, art,
and reflection, and democracy.
It's really just a, wild sex party.
That's trying to please everyone.
Okay? So, so you can also,
interpret this as, a,
direct criticism, of democracy itself.
Democracy is just a wild sex party.
Right? So these are the
two, major interpretations,
that it is, that Bacchae, it's about,
the power and dangers,
of religious devotion,
fanaticism. Okay? And
also, the, play Bacchae,
it's a direct attack,
on the idea of theater
itself, and democracy.
Okay? But I don't see it that way.
I think, the most likely
explanation for me, is,
that, it is a direct criticism, of empire.
Okay? And you can believe,
whatever you want.
And that's the power of,
Athenian theater. There are
different ways, to interpret it.
Okay? So even today,
modern audiences, are still amazed,
and, inspired,
by, these plays.
Any, any more questions? Yeah,
it seems to me, like, all these plays,
have a lot of, these things, that,
they all, come from, the same,
very very very very
very very very very very
very very very very very very very
very very very very very very very very
very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very
very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very
very very very very very very very very
very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very
very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very very
very very very very very very very very very
very very very very very very very very very very
So revenge is the main plot
device we use to drive action.
It's what motivates us
to do violent things.
And that's why throughout all these plays,
revenge is a common theme. But
another very common theme
is the idea of hubris.
Hubris, arrogance.
And this is what the Greek,
this is what the Greek
playwrights focus a lot on.
What they discovered is,
things go awry in society when
the leaders, when the elite, when
the kings, they develop hubris.
Because it leads to bad judgment.
But what they also discovered is,
hubris is just a part of human nature.
If you put someone in a position of power,
he or she will always feel like they're in a position of power.
And that's why they develop hubris. So
hubris is basically the most common
theme throughout all these plays.
And you're right, revenge is also
a very common theme as well.
So yeah, there are these common themes.
And the reason why is, these playwrights,
these poets, they're trying to
explore what it means to be human.
They're trying to decipher
the essence of being human.
They're trying to look into the human heart,
and trying to figure out what makes us,
human, basically.
And all humans are alike, okay?
Okay? Any more questions?
Yeah, the Athenians, okay,
so the thing about Eupredes, was
that we, today, scholars, will all agree,
Eupredes was the most talented.
Meaning, his use of poetry,
his use of metaphors,
imagery, it was the
most imaginative, okay?
We also agree that
he is the most shocking,
okay? His ideas,
the way he presents things, it is the
most visual and imaginative, okay?
So in terms of pure talent,
he's the most talented.
But when he was alive, okay?
He was an extremely arrogant person,
who believed theater should
be about awakening people,
should be challenging
people's sense of reality,
okay? It should be about
education and edification.
And these people tend to
be hated by contemporaries,
okay? But after they're dead,
later generations respect them more.
So even though, you know, the Athenians, you
know, the Athenians, the Chovs, the Chovs,
the Chovs, the Chovs, the
Chovs, the Chovs, the Chovs,
the Chovs, the Chovs,
the Chovs, the Chovs, the Chovs, the Chovs,
the Chovs,
was rejuvenated after his death, but
during his lifetime he was
despised by a lot of people.
People respected his genius, but
they didn't like the fact that
he was so arrogant and candid.
And that's true for most
of human history, where
if you are a controversial writer,
you are not respected by contemporaries,
but after you're dead, people
appreciate your genius.
And this is true for most
really famous writers.
Any more questions? These are
great questions, by the way.
Okay, great. So next class we
will do Socrates and Plato, okay?