Okay, so we are doing
Socrates and Plato today.
Last class we did Greek theater.
And remember I said that
Aeschylus, Sophocles,
and Eupodes, they're really
prophets of democracy.
They see themselves as
teachers who teach Athenians
how to practice democracy.
We also said that there
are three major benefits
to democracy. The first major
benefit is kings are bad.
Okay? Kings have hubris and hubris
creates all sorts of problems.
So remember in the play,
Antigone, by Sophocles,
the king Creon sentences
Antigone to death even
though he was unjust and
that was because of hubris.
Second major benefit of democracy
is it is a gift from the gods
that teaches citizens individual
responsibility and accountability.
Okay, so remember that in Eurostia,
Aeschylus told us that
democracy is a gift from Athena
in order to promote justice
and truth in the world. And
the third major benefit is democracy is
really the best way to promote justice
and truth in the world.
If citizens come together
and they deliberate and act
with in good faith, then the
world will be a better place.
Okay? So that is the argument
from the playwrights of Athens.
Now, obviously there are people
who disagree with this perspective.
And one of the most famous
opponents of democracy
is Socrates.
Socrates lived during the time of
the golden age of Pericles in Athens
and he was a very vocal opponent.
He was a very vocal opponent of
democracy for the following reason.
In order to practice democracy properly,
people need to access the truth.
But to access the truth,
you need to have reason.
And his argument was that
most people are not capable
of exercising reason in their thinking.
Okay? And to prove this,
every day he would be
sitting outside the Agora,
which is the marketplace of Athens.
And this is where the!
everyone came together.
And he would spend all day arguing with people
in something called a psychotic dialogue
and showing the flaws in your reasoning.
Okay? Showing you why you don't
really understand the world
when you think you do.
Okay? Trying to prove
that you are ignorant.
Okay? So let me give you a
demonstration of what Socrates did.
Okay? So give me a statement
that is fundamentally,
and inherently true. Give me a statement
that you think is fundamentally,
and inherently true.
The earth is a sphere, right?
The earth is a sphere.
And so, this is a statement
that we think is true, right?
And so what Socrates would
do is, he would slowly
and methodologically expose
the flaws in this statement.
Okay? So the first question for you is,
what is a sphere?
Explain what a sphere is.
Okay, so you have three -dimensional
round -shaped energy, okay?
And give me an example of a sphere.
A ball, right? So you're saying
the earth is like a ball.
Is that correct? It's all round.
Okay? And how do you know
the statement is true?
Who told you this? I mean,
you can know a ball is a sphere because
you hold it in your hand, right?
But you're not a god. You don't
hold the earth in your hand.
So how do you know it's true? Anyway,
I can go on like this,
obviously, for a very long time.
But I'm going to go on like this, obviously, for a
very long time. And so this is what Socrates did.
And this is what he called
a psychotic dialogue.
And actually, we still use this in many
different places, like, for example, law school.
So in American law schools, if you have,
if you ever make the stupid mistake
of ever applying to law school and
you get into law school, they will
teach you using the psychotic dialogue.
Okay? But the idea is to show
the flaws in your reasoning.
And obviously, if you get
an argument from Socrates,
you come out as a very mad person.
Okay? So the representation is this. The
representation of Socrates in Athens during this time was he was either a,
you could either see him as a bully, okay?
He was an intellectual bully.
Or he was a clown.
Or the most common understanding
of Socrates was he was a trickster.
Okay? He tricked you
into making statements
that were illogical because
fundamentally, language
does not capture the truth.
Okay? Language is just a convention we
have to make statements that are illogical.
Socrates was not meant to, in
order for us to communicate.
But it's not meant to
reflect reality. Okay?
And Socrates was exposing the fundamental
flaws in our language system.
So any questions about this so far?
All right. So to give you a sense of
how Athenians thought about Socrates at
that time, let me describe
to you a play by Erzophanes.
Okay? Erzophanes. Okay.
So, Erzophanes was a very
famous satirist in Athens.
And he made fun of all the very
famous individuals of Athens,
including Pericles, who as we said was
the de facto king of Athens at this time,
but also Cleon, who
replaced Pericles as the leader of Athens.
He also made fun of Socrates.
Okay? And the play is called, The Clouds.
So the play was produced in 423 BCE,
and the play was called The Clouds.
So let me first explain the plot of The Clouds,
and then we will interpret what it meant.
Okay? So in The Clouds,
there's this Athenian farmer,
a normal citizen, and
he's in a lot of trouble
because his wife spends a lot of money.
So he owes a lot of money to creditors.
And his creditors are banging at the
door and demanding their money back.
So he comes up with this plan.
He has a plan to get rid of his debts.
There's a school called a thinkery.
Okay? And it's run by
a man named Socrates.
The thinkery proposes to teach you reason,
logic, truth, so that you
can go and deceive jurors.
Okay? You can basically go
and manipulate people and
deceive them in a trial
to get out of your debts.
So he wants to send his son to...
to the thinkery to learn
how to lie to juries.
His son, who is a playboy, refuses
because he says that Socrates, he's
a cheat, he's a liar, he's a fraud.
I refuse to go. The man decides to
check out the thinkery by himself.
He goes in, and he sees Socrates,
okay, hanging from a
basket from the ceiling.
And the man's curious, like,
what are you doing up there?
And Socrates says, well, from up there.
Up here, I have a clearer and
higher vision of the world.
I can access truth better.
Also from here, I can draw inspiration
from the clouds, who are the true gods.
Okay? Not Zeus, not Heracles.
The clouds are the true gods.
And they're the ones who
give me inspiration to come up
with all these brilliant ideas.
Okay? So the man and Socrates has...
They have a very long conversation, and
he's completely convinced Socrates is a...
Sage, okay? He's a philosopher.
He runs back, and he tells his son,
you must go enroll in the
thinkery and learn from Socrates.
Okay? So the son decides this
is the path of least resistance.
He goes to the thinkery, and
he becomes Socrates' student.
Meanwhile, the man's creditors
are banging on the door and
saying to him, where is my money?
And the man says...
The man is now going to use all the
tricks that Socrates taught him.
Okay? So what he says is,
I don't owe you any money.
And then the creditor says,
you swore by Zeus that
you would pay me back.
The man says, oh, guess what?
Zeus doesn't exist.
Okay? He's not a god.
So I swore an oath to nothing.
Therefore, I owe you nothing.
The creditor obviously
gets angry, and he leaves.
Okay? Now, the son comes back.
And he... And the first thing he
does is start beating his father.
And the father is like, why
are you beating me, son?
And then the son says,
Socrates taught me to beat you.
And the father's like, what?
He didn't... Why is he teaching you that?
And the son says, he taught me justice.
Now, when I was young, did you beat me?
The father says, yes, of course I beat
you, because you were a naughty boy.
And then the son says, therefore, I can now
beat you, because you're a naughty father.
You're a naughty father.
You're a naughty father. You're a
naughty father. You're a naughty father.
You're a naughty father.
You're a
naughty father.
The pagans didn't think much of Socrates. He
worships the clouds, right, which is nothing.
So what they're saying is Socrates
makes things out of thin air.
He's just a fraud, he's a
manipulator, he's a liar.
But Socrates did have a lot of fans,
specifically people who
really hated democracy.
And so the people who really hated
democracy were the children of the rich.
These were aristocrats,
born into the wealthiest,
most noble aristocratic
families of Athens,
who hated the fact that the normal people
thought they were their equals, okay?
So what Socrates did was
he taught them basically
mental or linguistic kung fu, right,
to go beat up these commoners who
dared to think they're equals.
One of the most famous of
Socrates' students included Plato,
who we all know. But
also Alcabias, who
was one of the wealthiest
members of Athenian society.
He actually became leader
of Athens as well, okay?
So Socrates had his fans,
and because Athens was such a wealthy
and open and tolerant society,
they allowed Socrates to
basically do whatever he wanted.
Until 404 BCE.
This was the year
that Athens lost the Peloponnesian
War to Sparta, okay?
And when Athens lost the war,
Sparta did not burn Athens down.
Sparta had the right to burn
Athens down, but it did not, okay?
Instead, Athens imposed a dictatorship
called the Thirty Tyrants.
And the Thirty Tyrants came from
the wealthiest families of Athens,
who also happened to be
students of Socrates.
Socrates did not actually
participate in a tyranny.
Socrates refused to
participate in a tyranny, but
there were many of these tyrants
who were Socrates' students.
And they were terrible people.
They killed at least 5% of
the Athenian population.
They stole a lot of wealth.
And they were so terrible that ultimately,
the Athenian people revolted against them
and reinstalled their democracy, okay?
So, when the tyranny was overthrown,
the Thirty Tyrants were exiled,
but most people were given clemency, okay?
They were forgiven if they
participated in the regime.
Then what happens next is very strange.
In 399 BCE,
Socrates is put on trial.
Remember, this is after the
democracy is reinstated.
And this is when people who
participated in the tyranny
were forgiven, okay?
But in 399 BCE,
Socrates was put on trial.
And he was put on trial and
charged with two crimes.
The first is impiety, okay?
Which basically means he was
insulting the gods of Athens,
including Zeus, which is what he
did in the plague clouds, okay?
The second is corrupting
the youth of Athens.
Okay, basically, miseducating
the youth of Athens,
which is also what he did in the clouds,
okay? So, it almost seems
like this entire trial
was a cruel joke put on by the people
of Athens to teach Socrates a lesson,
okay? Does that make sense?
So, the people of Athens
expected Socrates to apologize,
make some jokes, be funny, and
then all is forgiven, right?
During the trial,
Socrates refused to defend himself.
What he said was this.
I am not a good speaker.
I am bad with words.
I'm just a poor person, okay,
who comes from a poor family,
who spends every day
seeking out the truth.
I spend all my time seeking out the truth,
thinking about the truth, that I
have no time to practice rhetoric.
I'm not good with words.
Also, I should not have to defend myself
because you're all capable of reason.
You're all capable of logic.
Therefore, if you just think for yourself,
you will realize I'm not guilty.
I have absolutely nothing
to do with the 30 tyrants.
I spent all my life trying to help Athens.
Therefore, if you're stupid,
you will vote me guilty.
If you're stupid, there's
nothing I can do about it, okay?
Obviously, the jury was
insulted by his speech,
and they voted out of 500 people,
280 to 220,
they voted that he is guilty, okay?
They declared he was guilty
of these two charges.
Now, as you can see, it's still
a pretty close vote, okay?
I mean, Socrates was basically
being a jerk during the trial,
and they still, they voted him guilty, but
it was a pretty close trial, 280 to 220.
Now, the second part of the trial
is, if you're found guilty,
they have to figure out what
your punishment is, okay?
So, the jury asked Socrates to
propose a punishment for his crimes.
And then, what Socrates said was,
you have found me guilty, and the
reason why you found me guilty is
because I speak the truth.
I am a gadfly, okay?
Gadfly. I go around and
I point out the nasty
truths of Athenian society.
I put a mirror to your face, and
I show you your warts, your
pimples, your ugliness.
Therefore, you hate me.
But, what I've been doing all
my life has been for the good
and betterment of Athens.
I'm a public servant. I am the
most selfless public servant,
okay? Because I speak the truth,
and by showing the truth,
I make you a better person.
Therefore, I think a just
punishment would be a penchant.
Okay? You guys should pay
me to retire in peace.
But, you know what?
I'm a generous and forgiving individual.
Therefore, if you don't want to give
me a pension, I will understand.
Therefore, I am willing
to pay a small fine, okay?
I'll pay a fine, okay?
And then, we're good.
How about that? And again,
the Athenian jurors
were pissed off, right?
So, they voted to
condemn him to death by
tricking him with a hemlock.
Okay? They basically gave
him the death penalty.
After they did so, they came to realize
that they were perhaps
tricked by Socrates.
Okay? Socrates was 70 years old.
That's very old for back then, okay?
70 years old was probably
the age limit back then.
He really didn't have much to live for.
And here was the opportunity for
Socrates to be a martyr for the truth,
right? All his life,
he's been trying to convince
people democracy does not work.
Because people are incapable
of reasoning out the truth.
And what this trial shows
us is he was correct.
Right? Does that make
sense? So, in many ways,
you can make the argument
that for Socrates,
this trial was a type of performance art.
Okay? He was a performance artist.
Okay? And so, the people
of Athens realized
that they were probably tricked.
And they were trying to get out
of condemning Socrates to death.
But Socrates insisted. And
it came to a point where
Socrates was just left alone.
And he had to demand
to be given a hemlock.
And he had to administer
the hemlock by himself.
And so, when he drank it, he died. Okay?
Now, I'm going to give you a little
bit of a story. After his death,
Socrates remained an extremely
controversial individual in Athens.
And he had a student, Plato, who
was maybe 28, 29 at the
time his mentor died.
Okay? And he loved Socrates.
And he committed the rest
of his life to restoring
and redeeming the reputation of Socrates.
So, when he was 40 years old,
he founded a school called
The Academy. Okay?
Which was inspired by the vision
of Socrates as a philosopher
who sought the truth. In 375 BCE,
he wrote a book called The Republic.
And The Republic is the most
famous of Plato's work.
It is arguably the greatest
work of Western philosophy.
And many today consider The Republic
the greatest book ever written.
Okay? There are people in this world
who have written a lot of great books.
But they've never read The Republic. And it
forever transforms the way they see the world.
Okay? It's a life transforming
event to read The Republic.
And next semester, we will actually
read The Republic together.
Okay? But let me give you a quick
introduction to The Republic.
So, in The Republic, there's
a very famous metaphor.
And it's called Allegory of the Cave.
And this is really the most famous
allegory or metaphor or analogy
in Western thought, okay?
By fall. Nothing comes second to this.
So before I start the
allegory of the cave,
are there any questions so far about
what I've discussed? Anything unclear?
Anything you would like to question or
doubt or argue with if I continue with the allegory of the cave?
Okay? Clear so far?
All right. So this is the allegory.
Imagine a cave deep under the earth, okay?
There's a cave. Now, in
this cave, at the back,
there's a large fire that
shines light into this cave, okay?
There are these prisoners who
are chained to the floor,
and they're chained so that
they cannot move their necks.
They can't move around, okay?
They can't move. The only thing they can do is
steer at a wall, and they can't move around.
That's the only thing they can do. Okay?
Now, there are these people behind
them who are like puppeteers.
They hold up cardboard
pictures of maybe rats
and birds, okay?
And the fire will project
these images onto the wall.
And so these people, who
again cannot move around,
and they can only see the wall in
front of them, they come to think that
this wall is the truth.
Okay? It's the only reality that exists.
And they start naming things that
they see, and that creates language.
And they like to play
games and try to figure out
who can create the best language, okay?
And then they give awards to the people
who create the best language
who are playwrights, right?
Okay? So what Plato is saying is
that we may honor art
and poetry and drama,
but they're all lies.
Okay? Now,
one day, for whatever reason,
we don't know why, but
one man finds his chains are loosened.
And he's able to get up.
Okay? And he swims around, and
he sees a light coming from the top.
So he's curious, and he
climbs all the way to the top,
and he's now outside in the free world.
Okay? And it's painful,
because his eyes are not
trained to see the sunlight.
Okay? So the sunlight,
it's like burning him.
Okay? It's like burning him alive.
And so at first, all he's
doing is staring at the ground.
And so he's seeing reflections
in the pond, in the pool.
But then he slowly acclimatizes himself.
Two. And he starts to see
the world around him.
And it's beautiful. Okay?
But it's so beautiful
that it's beyond language.
He doesn't have the language to
describe this world that he's in.
Okay? This is beyond
language. And finally,
he develops the courage to
stare up in the sky, and he sees the sun.
Okay? The sun.
And he is amazed.
He is amazed by how the sun
is a source of all life.
And now, for the first time,
he fully understands
the truth of the world.
Okay? And when he does,
he is seized by regret, because
he remembers he has all these friends
who are still trapped and
in prison in the cave.
And he pities them. So
he swears that he will.
Even though he. He loves where he is.
He will still venture back into the cave
in order to show people
the truth of the world.
And to tell them that you've
been living a lie all your life.
Okay? So he goes back into the cave.
Now remember, his eyes are
now accustomed to sunlight.
So in the cave, it's all dark.
So he stumbles around. He stumbles around.
He falls. And he hurts himself.
Okay? And then he goes
and talks to the prisoners
and tells them, hey.
I've been to the outside world.
I've been to the sunlight.
I know what truth is.
And then they're like, can you
describe to us what it's like then?
And he can't do it.
Okay? And then they're like,
tell us what you see on the wall.
And because he's been
so accustomed to truth,
he can no longer use human
language to describe anything.
Okay? Okay? And so the
people are convinced.
Utterly convinced. He's an idiot.
He's insane. He's a clown.
And so they refuse to follow him.
And at some point, because
he insists on revealing the truth to them,
they kill him. Okay?
That's the allegory of the cave.
Okay? And you'll remember this
allegory for the rest of your life.
Now this allegory is
powerful for three reasons.
Okay? Okay? And I want you to
remember these three reasons.
Because we will go into them
later on in the course.
The first reason is, who's the man
who goes out in the
sunlight and sees the truth?
It's obviously Socrates.
Right? So with this allegory,
Plato redeems the reputation of Socrates.
Right? Because remember,
before, Socrates was despised.
He was laughed at by the Athenians.
And what this allegory is saying is,
that's because Socrates is a man.
Socrates is a philosopher of the truth.
Okay? And people cannot
deal with the truth.
So that's why today we celebrate
Socrates as the greatest philosopher
who ever lived. Not only that, but we
consider him the first philosopher,
even though he was not
the first philosopher.
Okay? Right?
So that's the power of
the allegory of the cave.
This image forever transforms
the way humanity understands
and perceives Socrates.
That's the first thing. Second thing is,
this allegory becomes so powerful
that
in the imagination of Christians,
Socrates becomes Jesus.
Right? Does that make sense?
Socrates is Jesus for Christians.
Because Jesus was God, and
he came down to our world
in order to speak the truth.
And... Because we feared
the truth, we killed him.
Okay? So, for Christians,
allegory of the cave is really
the story of Jesus as well.
Another martyr for the truth.
But, and the last thing is,
this allegory of the cave becomes
the framework for Christianity.
Okay? Okay? It becomes the
intellectual framework for the...
Religion of Christianity.
So let me show you how.
Okay? So, this is an allegory.
And behind the allegory,
there is an understanding of
reality, a philosophy, a religion.
Okay? So here is the platonic
understanding of the world.
There's something called
the form of the good.
Okay? And the, obviously the
metaphor would be the sun.
Okay? And the form of the good is the sun.
It's a source of everything.
Okay? It's a source of all truth.
It is the truth. It's
called the form of the good.
And emanating from the form
of the good are concepts
and ideals that structure the universe.
And they are reason,
beauty, and
truth.
And justice. Okay?
And there are others. Okay?
But these are the main ones.
Reason, truth, beauty, and justice.
They emanate from the form of the good.
Okay? And then emanating from
these concepts are these forms
that are perfect.
Okay? So, for example, maybe the
perfect horse, which represents beauty.
Okay? Or the perfect woman, who
represents justice and beauty as well.
Okay? But this is all perfection.
And from this higher world comes...
The lesser world, the reality we live in.
So everything that we see here, everything
that we are here, is only an imitation.
A shadow of this world.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Imitation. So there are horses, but
these horses are just copies
of that perfect horse up there.
Okay? So the major difference is, in
this world, this world is eternal.
It has always existed,
and it will always exist.
It's eternal. Second is,
it is immutable.
Immutable just means it will never change.
Okay? And the reason why is, it's perfect.
Okay? So these are three distinct
qualities of this higher world.
Eternal, immaculate, and perfect.
And everything down here is
basically the complete opposite.
Okay? We will all die.
We will all feel pain. But up
there, no one feels any pain.
Okay? No one dies. It's all perfect.
Okay? Does that make
sense? Guess what, guys?
What is this? This is
the Christian universe.
Right? This is God.
This is heaven. This is earth.
Okay? Does that make sense?
This is the allegory of the cave.
And you can see how it
does these three things.
It redeems the reputation of Socrates.
It gives Christians an
understanding of Jesus.
And it becomes the framework from
which Christians will build
their understanding of the world.
It becomes the basis of
the Christian religion.
Okay? So Plato is the real founder
of the Christian religion, not Jesus.
Okay? And we will go more into this
when we discuss
Christianity in the future.
All right? Any questions?
Any questions? You look confused.
Just ask any question.
Let's start having a discussion.
Okay? Because I know this is a lot.
Let's try to unpack it. Okay? Yep.
Oh, great. Okay. Very public.
Okay. So
the Republic isn't really
about the allegory of the cave.
Okay? The allegory of the cave
actually appears in the Republic.
The Republic itself,
Plato is trying to answer the question,
what is a good society?
Okay? What is a good society?
That's the question he's trying to answer.
Because it's clearly not democracy.
Because democracy kills Socrates.
Okay? So it's clearly not democracy.
So what makes a good society?
And the answer is, a society
that is not a good society.
It's a society that's based on justice.
Okay? It's a society
that's based on justice.
But then what is justice? It's truth.
Okay? But then what's truth?
Well, truth is the form of the good.
Then what's the form of
the good? It is the thing
that philosophers can access
for their own reasoning.
Right? Right? Therefore,
a good society is one that is ruled.
By philosopher kings.
Because they're the only ones
who can access the truth.
Okay? And this society that's
perfect, he calls the Republic.
That's why it's called the
Republic. The Republic, and
we'll read this again next semester is,
it's really trying to figure
out what makes a good society.
Okay? And to further his argument,
Plato uses the allegory of the cave.
And like, listen.
Fifty years from now. You will still
remember the allegory of the cave.
Maybe you won't remember the Charles Socrates
or anything else you've learned in this class.
But you will definitely remember
the allegory of the cave.
Okay? Because it's embedded. First
of all, it's a beautiful metaphor.
But it's also embedded in our society.
Okay? So,
does that answer your question, Echo?
Yeah. Do you have more questions?
All right. Okay. So, something
else I want to explain is, okay.
Some might be interested as to why Plato is
considered the greatest philosopher of all time.
Okay? All right.
So, it's not because he's the best.
All right? It's not because he's the best.
I would say there are three good
reasons why he's so influential today.
The first is Plato,
the way he writes.
It's unique and original to him.
Plato originally trained as a playwright.
Okay? So, he wanted to be Ischilus.
He wanted to be Sophocles. Eupatius.
Because everyone wanted to
be a playwright in Athens.
It was the highest honor. So,
he learned the art of dialogue.
Okay? Because dialogue
is the basis for theater.
And so, what he did that was
innovative, and no one did this before,
was he basically took the
dialogue of the stage.
And he transferred onto the stage.
So, when you read Plato,
it's actually a lot of fun.
Okay? Because it's basically
Socrates, his main character,
having arguments and
conversations with other people.
So, in terms of readability,
Plato is definitely probably one
of the most readable philosophers.
Okay? He's definitely the most
readable famous philosopher.
Later on in the semester, we
will talk about Immanuel Kant
and Hegel.
And they are not readable. Okay?
But Plato, anyone can read
Plato and enjoy Plato.
Okay? So, his readability,
the originality of his writing is
one really good reason why he remains
so popular today.
Second is he
is extremely anti -democratic.
Okay? His thinking is...
Because, like, remember, the most traumatic
event in his life was the death of his mentor,
Socrates. And so, it's the Athenian
democracy who killed his mentor.
So, he passionately hates democracy.
Okay? Well, you know who
else hates democracy?
Kings hate democracy. And
throughout most of human history,
kings ruled the world. Right?
So, what's amazing about Plato is
he's the only writer in human history
who has ever been a writer. He's the only
writer in human history who has been a writer continuously for 2,000 years.
Does that make sense?
We lost Homer for a bit.
We lost the playwrights,
Aeschylus, Sophocles, and
Eupatius for a long time.
But Plato has always
been read continuously.
And he's been the most...
And as a result, because
it's easy to access Plato,
he's become the most influential
philosopher of all time.
Okay? Does that make sense? And
third of all was his academy.
Okay? And the academy in Athens at
that time, it's like Harvard, right?
Or Oxford today. It's a place where
all the elite children went.
Okay? So, his students were the most
powerful people in the world basically.
And his most famous student was Aristotle.
And as we'll discuss in future classes,
Aristotle is the one who basically...
packaged and promoted Greek culture. And
Plato became a very important
individual in the spreading
of Greek culture.
In fact, he was basically the
main hero in this process.
Okay? So, does that make sense?
All right? Feel free to
argue with me, by the way.
I mean, like, if you feel I've said anything
controversial or you sort of disagree with,
let me know. And I will rebut.
We can have a psychotic dialogue.
Okay? Any more questions?
Ask a question. Okay.
That's a good question. Okay?
What are the influences of Plato?
Okay? So, you can make the argument that
Socrates was not that
much of an intellectual
influence on Plato.
And the reason why is, remember,
Socrates questioned your wisdom.
But he himself did not propose
any of his own theories.
Okay? So... Right.
So, what we know is this.
First of all, during this time,
this was the golden age
of Greek philosophy.
Right? And at that time, you had lots
of philosophers in different policies,
different places, proposing
all these wonderful theories.
So Plato definitely had access to them.
Plus, they were all friends.
Okay? And
we also know this world of Greek
thought was heavily influenced by Egypt.
Right? Because Egypt was really
the epicenter of learning
and philosophy at this time.
And Egypt was actually
very close to Greece.
Also, Mesopotamia.
Right? The Persians.
Okay? So, 399 B.C.
Socrates dies. And then Plato spends the
next 12 years traveling around the world.
And while he's traveling, he's
absorbing lots of different philosophy.
Okay? So, look.
We don't have access to
Egyptian sources. Right? So
we don't know what sources
would influence Plato.
But we know the Egyptians
heavily influenced him.
And we know the Greeks. So we
can make the assumption that
the Egyptians were heavily
influenced on Plato.
As well as Mesopotamia.
As well as the other Greek
philosophers like Pythagoras
and Democritus.
And so
what's really important is Athens at
this time was not an isolated society.
It was part of a larger
intellectual landscape.
And a lot of these places had richer
intellectual histories than Athens.
Okay? Egypt definitely. Mesopotamia.
Okay? So does that answer your question?
The answer is we don't know. Okay? And the
reason, again, is most of this is lost to us.
Right? I'm sure there were
philosophers at this time
who were the equal of Plato
in terms of originality.
Okay? But we don't know
who these people were.
Because remember, citizenship, it's not
really just about changing the past.
It's also about improving the past.
Okay? Eliminating most of the past.
Right? Okay? .
..
...
.....
..
....
...
................ of Syracuse
invited Plato to come counsel
him on how to be a tyrant,
a good tyrant, right?
He wanted to be like a philosopher king.
And then Plato basically said to him,
well, you should let me be the king,
and then you will have a philosopher king.
And of course, the king of
Syracuse didn't like this idea, so
he almost killed Plato, okay?
But Plato had very, again,
Plato has very wealthy friends,
and he was very rich himself, so he
basically ransomed his way out of Syracuse.
So as a politician,
as a practitioner of philosophy,
he's terrible, okay?
Right? He tried his philosophy in Syracuse,
didn't work out, pissed off a lot of people,
okay? But
everyone wanted to be a philosopher king.
Any more questions?
Okay. So
next class we will do
The Rise of Macedonia, okay?
So remember, these are ideas that
are being incubated in Athens
and in Greece at this time.
But ultimately, these ideas
conquer the world, right?
Greek theater, Greek philosophy
spread all around the world.
And the main reason is Macedonia.
The main reason are two individuals,
Philip II of Macedonia and
Alexander the Great, okay?
Who together will create
the Hellenistic Empire.
And this is why Greek culture
will spread around the world
and become the basis of
Western civilization.