Okay, so today we will discuss
the Bronze Age collapse.
I want to paint you a picture
of the world in about 1200 BCE.
So, in this world,
the center of this world
is what we call Mycenaean Greece.
Okay, across from the Mycenaean Greece,
across the Aegean Sea,
okay, this is the Aegean,
is what we call Anatolia.
Today we refer to
Anatolia as Turkey, okay?
And in Anatolia,
the Hittite Empire
rules Anatolia.
Further south is a place called Cyprus.
Canine, okay? Canine is important
when we do the Bible
because that is the
birthplace of the Israelites.
Okay, so Canine today is
what we refer to as Lebanon,
Syria,
and Israel today.
Canine is a province of
the Egyptian Empire, okay?
So this is Egypt, okay?
Over here,
is a place called Mesopotamia.
And we today call Mesopotamia Iraq.
Okay? Over here is today
what we call Iran.
Back then it was basically Persia.
Over here is Afghanistan.
And then next to Afghanistan is India.
And of course, remember
these are the steps.
Okay? So for Mesopotamia and Greece,
you also had the Mediterranean.
And over here are the
islands of Cyprus and Crete.
And then over here is
a place called Iberia.
And over here is Britain.
Okay? So
this is a map
of the world in 1200 BC.
And what's really important for you to recognize
about this world is it's interconnected.
Meaning that they are trading and
communicating with each other.
Okay? This is what we call the Bronze Age.
The Bronze Age.
And why is it called the Bronze Age?
Because they're trading basically
bronze during this period.
Back then, bronze is like oil today.
Okay? It is the basis for the economy.
The very structure of their economy.
Bronze is an alloy made of copper
and tin.
Copper and tin you have to mine.
Okay? And only a few places
will have these resources.
So tin is found in Britain,
in Iberia, in Anatolia,
in Afghanistan. Okay?
Copper is mainly found in Cyprus
and Crete and
also in Anatolia.
Okay? Now, meaning
and what this means is
in order to make bronze,
you basically have to trade
with the entire world.
Okay? So India,
this world,
the trading would go as far as
from India to the Middle East.
From India to Britain.
Even China over here
was part of this world
but not to the degree
as these other places.
Okay? In this world,
there are different ways that
you can profit or make money.
Okay? The first way is mining.
So basically extracting resources, tin
and copper in order to make bronze.
Second way is industry manufacturing.
Right? So turning,
so making bronze from tin and copper
and then turning bronze into weapons,
into pottery to be sold elsewhere.
Okay? The third way you
can make money is by what?
Trading. Right? So
in this world, if you look at this map, who
is the most important person in the world?
Basically profit the most from trading.
If you look at this map, who would
make the most money from trading?
This area, right? Does that make sense?
Because it is the center of the world,
you have to pass through this world
in order to access everywhere else.
Okay? And this place over here,
you look at the map, it
becomes the center of the world
because this place.
This place becomes the
logistics hub of the world.
To get to anywhere, you have
to pass through this place.
And so this place can
basically collect tolls.
Right? This place is called what?
Do you guys know? Yeah,
it's the toll gate of the world.
Right? You have to pass through this
place in order to access other places.
Therefore, this place is very wealthy.
This place, can you guess
what this place is called?
You guys, can you guys guess?
Troy. Have you guys
heard of the Trojan War?
Okay, we will do the Iliad next semester.
We will discuss the
Iliad in the next class.
But I want you to understand
this place is called Troy.
And because this place is so
important, for centuries,
they've been fighting
wars over this place.
Because it's really the
center of the universe.
Right? If you can control this place, you
become very wealthy because everyone has passed through you.
You can collect tolls.
You can trade. Okay?
Does that make sense? And the last way
you can make money off this world is what?
What's the last way in which you can
make a lot of money in this world?
You can do it through
mining, industry, trading.
What else can you do to make money?
Piracy, right? Does that make sense?
Steal. Right?
Piracy. Right?
So, when we read the Iliad, what
you will discover is the Greeks
who attacked Troy, they
were basically pirates.
Troy made a lot of money off trading and
pirates went to steal a
lot of their resources
and, well, okay, does that make sense?
So, the main point is that
this world was interconnected.
It was a globalized world.
We call this globalization.
But at the same time,
it was very chaotic.
It was very dynamic.
Okay? They traded with each other, but
they also fought wars against each other.
Okay? Does that make sense?
And these places in the center of
the universe might seem inglorious.
So, the Greeks, okay,
became very wealthy because
they traded and they engaged in piracy.
The Hittites became very wealthy.
Egypt became very wealthy.
Okay? Because they were
the center of the universe.
But a couple of decades later,
this entire world collapsed.
This world disappeared, meaning that
Mycenaean Greece was destroyed.
It was completely burned down.
And they lost about a
quarter of their population.
Okay? The Hittite Empire?
Destroyed. And even
though Canaan disappeared,
and even though Egypt was not destroyed,
it ceased to be a hegemon.
It ceased to be a global power.
And a few decades later, they
were conquered by outside powers.
Okay? After 1200 BCE,
Egypt ceased to be a power.
So, this is what we call
the Bronze Age Collapse.
And for the decades,
scholars have been trying
to figure out what happened.
Why is it that in 1200 BCE,
this world was wealthy,
it was interconnected, and
then a few decades later,
it all disappeared.
It collapsed. And that's
a great mystery that
no one has been able to solve.
Okay? So, let me tell you what we know.
We know that
what caused this collapse are
what we call the Sea Peoples.
Sea Peoples. And we know because
Egypt has written
records of battling the Sea Peoples.
So, basically, over the
course of a few decades,
people were coming in from
the west and attacking Egypt.
Okay? This was not one people.
This was a series of different
people attacking Egypt from the sea.
And
Egypt had to spend decades in
order to repulse the Sea Peoples.
What we know is the Sea
Peoples, whoever they were,
they did destroy Egypt, but
they did destroy the Hittites, and
they did destroy the Mycenaean Greeks.
Okay? So, and
what we know is the Sea Peoples,
they were basically, they were basically,
they were basically a combination of pirates
and also refugees.
These people attacked Egypt because
Egypt was the breadbasket of the world.
That's where all the food was. So,
they were attacking Egypt for the food.
Okay? These are people who are hungry.
They joined with pirates at ships, and they
were trying to take over Egypt together.
They destroyed Mycenaean Greeks.
They destroyed the Hittites, but
they failed to destroy Greece.
They were stopped, they
were stopped in Egypt.
Okay? So, another question then is,
what's driving this population
movement from west to east?
Okay? That's a great mystery.
And over the past few decades,
different solutions, different
ideas have been proposed.
Okay? Before, we thought that
it must have been an invasion.
So, the idea is, that what's happening
is, you have to destroy Egypt.
Okay, and you have
to
destroy占卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬
natural disaster. So
the idea is maybe there was a
volcanic explosion somewhere, okay?
And this caused the weather to change.
And now farmers could no
longer feed themselves,
so they may start to move
westwards and attack Egypt, okay?
That's the second theory. And
there's more evidence for this,
but the theory
that we have today is
a perfect storm, okay?
Or a systems collapse.
And the idea here is that
it was not one thing in one year
that caused the system to collapse, it
was a series of events over decades,
okay? And these three major events are
natural disasters, or so
basically earthquakes.
So we have archaeological evidence that
there is a series of earthquakes
in this region at this time.
Which destabilized the region, okay?
So earthquakes happened. We also
have evidence of climate change,
okay? So the weather became cooler
over the course of this period,
which meant that it was
harder to grow crops, okay?
And we also have evidence
of eternal revolt,
okay? Meaning that people
rebelled against the elite,
overthrew kings,
and there was a lot of war and violence.
So the theory that
we have today is what caused the Bronze
Age collapse was a perfect storm,
basically a multiple factor
which led to systems collapse.
Okay, does that make sense guys?
Any questions so far?
Any questions so far? Are we clear?
All right, so one thing that
you have made notice
in this class is that,
I have a very different understanding
of history than other people,
okay? So I happen to disagree
with this theory of the first storm, even
though it is the scholarly consensus,
all right? So I want to explain to
you today my theory of what happened.
All right, so
the first thing you need to understand
is this system collapsed even
though it was traumatic for Europe.
It is not unique in human history.
So what happened? This sort of
stuff has happened before, okay?
So if we go over here to North America,
to the Mayas, okay?
So the Maya civilization existed
in Central America, okay?
Or Guatemala, basically.
And so we find a similar pattern
where in about 200 AD, okay?
In the year 200, their civilization
started to explode, okay?
It started to increase. It
reached its peak at about
900 AD, okay?
In the year 900, its civilization was
over the place in Central America.
But then after 900,
it went all the way down, okay?
So about 30 years' time, by 1200,
they're basically, their entire
civilization almost collapsed.
So it's a very similar pattern
to what's happening in the Bronze Age.
So the question then is,
why does this happen?
Why does this happen? All right?
And so to understand this,
I am going to present
you with a new theory
that we will use a lot in this class.
So I want you to understand
this theory, okay?
But it comes from a historian
by the name of Peter Turchin.
Peter Turchin, who's a historian.
He's American, but he
came over from Russia.
He's basically Russian -American. And
he has a theory called
elite overproduction.
And elite overproduction,
the theory is very interesting because
it's arguing against the way
we traditionally understand
why societies collapse, okay?
So the way we usually understand why
societies collapse is we get from Karl Marx.
And basically, what Karl Marx says
is eventually your society collapses
because the people revolt, okay?
So basically, people rebellion.
So in other words, Karl Marx believes that
society collapses because
it is a bottom -up process,
okay?
It's a bottom -up process.
If you treat workers badly,
they will stop working.
If you force them to work,
they will go on strike.
If you force them to work again,
they will fight against you.
They will rebel, okay?
A worker revolution.
Okay, that's what Karl Marx argues.
And Peter Turchin says, okay,
that's a really interesting theory,
but if you look at the historical
data, if you look at the evidence,
the problem is in the bottom, okay?
If you look at why societies collapse,
it's not because of the people rebelling.
it's because there's
infighting among the elite.
So there's civil war among the elite.
Does that make sense? That's his theory.
If the problem with society isn't that
there's too many poor people,
the problem is there are
too many rich people.
That's the real problem. And
that's why societies collapse.
Alright, so let me explain to
you this theory slowly, okay?
Elite overproduction.
Alright. Alright.
Okay, it's fine. Alright, so
in this world of 1200 BCE,
we have something called a permanent,
hereditary, elite, okay?
Permanent, hereditary, elite.
Permanent just means
they're always there, okay?
Hereditary means they pass on their status and
their privilege and their wealth to the children.
And this is new in human history
because before there was an elite,
but they were not permanent, meaning
they could be changed over time.
And they didn't pass their
privileges on to their children.
Everyone had to earn
their privilege and power.
Okay? So the elite was
constantly shifting in society.
But now in about the year 1200 BCE,
you had a permanent hereditary elite.
When you have that, you
have three advantages.
Okay? What the elite gives society
are three major advantages.
The first major advantage
is the idea of organization.
Okay? So the idea of organization
is that you have to be a leader.
Right? Basically think of the elite
as your brain, as society's brain.
They can help ornate resources, okay?
And that's good for war.
If you're fighting an enemy, you need
an elite to lead you into battle, okay?
It's also good for public works.
Okay? So think of the pyramids in Egypt
and the Great War of China, right?
You need an elite to, um,
organize your resources in order to create
public works that benefit all society.
So the main thing here
would be irrigation, right?
Yes? So you need an elite in
order to have irrigation. So
that's the first major benefit of
having a permanent hereditary elite.
Second major advantage is because you have
better organization, you have more wealth.
Okay? So
it becomes wealthier, if
you have a permanent elite.
People work harder.
Okay? And even though
there's more inequality,
inequality also forces
people to work harder.
Does that make sense? Okay?
And because you have these two
things, organization and wealth,
you also have scale.
And what scale basically means is
your population now can move up.
Before, in the egalitarian society,
when you didn't have a permanent elite, at
most society could reach about 10,000 people.
But now when you have a permanent elite,
you can reach about a million people.
Okay? So now you can scale up.
So these are three major advantages
to having an elite.
Okay? But there's a problem
with having an elite.
And the problem is they engage in
something called rent -seeking behavior.
All right? I want you guys to remember
this term, rent -seeking behavior,
which is very important for our class.
So what does this mean?
It means basically,
so think of a landlord, right?
A landlord doesn't really do
anything, but a landlord has land
that it can rent to you, the farmer,
in exchange,
you give me a share of your crops.
Right? So I don't do anything, but because
I have land, I can rent it out to you.
Right? It turns out the elite
mainly make their money
through rent -seeking behavior.
So let me give you another
example of rent -seeking behavior.
All of you want to go
to university, right?
Why do you want to go to university?
What's your purpose? Okay.
What's your purpose in
going to university?
Be honest. It's to get the degree,
right? Okay?
The degree. Okay?
And the degree is your ticket
to success in society, okay?
You believe that you go to university,
you are getting a ticket, the degree,
in order to access social mobility,
okay? To access wealth in society.
In other words, the universities
are charging you rent, okay?
So the degree is basically
rent. Does that make sense?
Okay? Now, some of you may say, wait,
that's wrong because I'm going
to university to learn, right?
It's about learning. Well,
guess what? When you actually go to
university, you're going to discover
they don't actually teach
you that much, okay?
They don't have to teach you that much and the
reason why is you're stuck paying the rent.
You need the degree, right?
So you don't have to
actually teach anything.
You have to come to class anyway.
Does that make sense? The
same thing for the school
where in order to get to university,
you have to go through this high school.
So you're here paying tuition
and you're paying rent.
Does that make sense? You're
not here in the school to learn,
you're here in school to get the degree
so you can access university
and get that degree,
okay? And all this process, all
you're doing is paying rent.
So if you are, if you have a school,
you can charge for rent.
Just as if you're a landlord,
you can charge for rent for renting
your room or real estate property, okay?
Does that make sense? This is what
we call rent -seeking behavior.
Okay? Now, you're like, okay, well,
this kind of sucks, okay?
And it does suck. But
what keeps the system together
is the idea of a social contract.
Okay? Basically, the idea of social
contract is, yes, we the elite,
we know we are charging you rent and
we know this sucks for you, the people,
but we have a contract.
So as the elite, I'm
obligated to help society.
Okay? So
the way they help society is by
giving back to society, okay? So
what the elite do throughout society in
the past is they organize public feasts.
Okay? And also public temples.
So in today's society,
you know, like the parks,
the schools, the temples, they're
built by the government, right?
But back then, they didn't have a government,
they had the elites who were responsible
for building temples,
for building, for holding public feasts.
Okay? So this is the idea
of a social contract.
Okay? And the reason why you
need a social contract is
because if you don't have a social
contract and you just charge rent,
people will leave.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So in this world, it's very chaotic,
but there are different places,
there are different social
organizations you can go to.
So if you are in Egypt and you
don't really like Egypt, guess what?
You can go to Mesopotamia.
Okay? So these cities were in
competition with each other for people
because people provided
labor and resources.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
So this is how it usually works.
But over time, this
system will break down.
Okay? This system will break down.
And it's because of
rent -seeking behavior.
Okay? So the first issue is this.
With rent -seeking behavior,
you create something called debt.
Okay? So I'm a landlord
and you are paying me rent
in order to use my land,
right? And that land,
and that rent is usually
a portion of your crops.
Okay? So you, does that make sense?
Maybe 10% of your crops.
But let's just say, for
example, it's a bad year.
It doesn't rain. Okay? And you
don't have any crops to pay me rent.
So what do you do? You're
supposed to pay me a rent,
but you don't have the
money, so what do you do?
No, that comes later.
What do you do first?
Exactly. Thank you. Yes.
Okay. So the first thing
that happens is boring.
Okay? You're basically going to debt.
Okay? So
you promise to pay me
double in the next year.
And I'm like, okay, fine. Right?
But you get unlucky and the next year,
it's also a bad year. And
so for five years in a row,
you, you are in debt.
The problem with debt is this.
It's something called compound interest.
Okay? Meaning like over time,
the debt becomes so large,
there's no way you can pay it off.
If you can't pay it off, what happens now?
..
...... Okay,
good, yeah, so the idea
is debt slavery, okay?
So you can't pay me back,
you become, you become my slave,
okay, you promise me that
your children work for,
work for me for free,
okay? And so,
debt slavery, becomes the natural
product of rent -seeking behavior,
does that make sense? Over time, you're always
going to have a percentage of your population
who go into debt slavery,
okay, And this creates a lot
of instability in society
because obviously they either want
to run away or they want to rebel.
Okay? Does it make sense?
The other problem is
Elite overproduction And
the idea here is
Everyone wants to be the renter, right?
Everyone wants to be the landlord, right?
But there's only so much land
So now people are competing for
The power to charge rent.
Does it make sense? Okay,
so over time in any society
As a population increases
No people who go into
that slavery increase
and therefore people at
the bottom are very angry
and At the same time
the elite, the number goes up, but
there's only A set amount of land
and therefore they have
to fight over the land
Okay Does it make sense and
So eventually what happens is
The society goes into War okay
I see elite fight each over,
as elite fight each other For
the占 the right to charge rent.
Doesn't make sense. And so
the main message of
elite overproduction is
unless you can control the amount,
the number of the elite in your
society, your society must collapse.
Doesn't make sense. It must collapse
because you have too many people
fighting for too little power.
It must collapse. So
historically, what are things
you can do to control the elite?
What are things you can do to
control the number of the elite?
Jimmy? Kill the elite?
Okay. So,
but then where does the property go?
Okay, so
one possible thing you can do is
the idea of land redistribution.
Okay? So historically,
this is one mechanism you can use
to control the growth of the elite.
And this is how kings can do it.
So the king came into power. Okay?
So most societies have an elite.
And then one person from the elite said,
listen, this society's not working.
Let me redistribute the land and
cancel debt in order for our
society to keep on going.
Okay? And this person became the king.
So that's one possible solution.
Okay? What's another possible solution?
The question of the mandatory.
Jimmy?.
...
....
Okay. So you can also have a civil war.
Okay?. Civil war.
. Okay.
The elite can fight amongst themselves.
And whoever wins, gets everything.
Okay? So it's a second possible solution.
What's another possible solution?.
...
What's another possible solution?
Empire building, right?
Does that make sense? Empire building.
In other words, let's not
fight amongst ourselves,
let's go and conquer new territory.
It doesn't make sense. So because
you have a permanent territory elite,
over time they're going to
reach a mass, too many people.
We have too many elite, you have to
resolve this issue through three ways.
The first thing you can do is kill
the elite and redistribute the land.
That's what a king does. The second
thing you can do is have a civil war.
The third thing you can
do is create an empire.
But these three solutions by
themselves are also unfair.
And stable, okay? Because land
redistribution is basically a revolution.
So war is war.
Empire building is also war.
Does that make sense? So
no matter how you do these things, you're
always going to create instability.
And eventually your empire,
your society will collapse.
Does that make sense? So.
Let me give you another
example of how this works.
To clarify for you, okay? So
there's a book called Capital in
the 21st Century by Thomas Piketty.
Thomas Piketty is a French economist.
And this is a very famous book
that's been recently published.
And in the book,
he looked at the past 100
years of economic growth.
And what he discovered over
time is the
financial economy grows
faster than the real economy.
Capital grows faster than manufacturing.
Okay? So if you look at capital,
it grows at 5%.
Real economy grows at 2%.
Alright? Right? So if things
stay stable over time,
this will happen to all societies.
Capital will grow faster
than the real economy.
What this means is, let's just say
you have a million dollars, okay?
I have a million dollars. I have
different options to invest my money.
I can start a factory or I
can put all my money into real
estate or the stock market.
Where should I put my money?
I can open a factory, right?
Or I can put it in the stock market.
Where should I put my money?
Yes and why?
Exactly. You understand?
If you have money today,
you do not put your
money into the factories.
You do not open a new business.
You put it in the stock market
because you make more money that way.
What's the problem with that? Okay? I have
more resources,
more resources, more resources, more
resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
more resources, more resources, more
resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
more resources, more resources, more
resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
more resources, more resources,
more resources,
more the rent seeking behavior
we have too many people doing
that you have a society where nobody works
doesn't make sense nobody
does any work because
all the well is being
put into rent sinking
behavior it's being put into speculation
so no one's doing any more work
no one's creating more wealth
and this eventually leads
to social collapse at some
point okay does it make sense all right
so Peter torchins theory
of elite overproduction is
because
the number of rich people can only go up
over time your society must
clap at some point unless you
choose to have a revolution
or you have a civil war or you go invade other
countries okay those are your three options
but you need but if you did that that
creates more instability so
over time no matter how how you
structure your society
it will collapse does
that make sense okay so
that's what happened during
the branch it's collapsed
where these societies must
have in Greece high tides
each of canane they were
fundamentally unstable
because of red seeking behavior
okay saving with the Mayans
where okay they were going very fast but
eventually they clapped
all studies will do this
at some point no society is stable
okay the reason why is you
have an elite in charge
who
helped society grow over time they will
just engage in red seeking behavior
which will eventually lead
to collapse of society okay
so that's why I'm saying that the only way
to get rid of the red seeking behavior is to have a civil war right and
this is a pattern that we'll see over and
over again in human history and
we'll discuss this idea throughout this
semester all right doesn't
make sense any
questions all right
so let's look at a very
specific example of
red seeking behavior my city in Greece I'm
going to talk about the red seeking behavior in Greece all right my city in Greece
so my city in Greece and
you may remember this from last
class it was a long time ago
but last class we talked about the
Yemnaya right the Yemnaya
right they conquered Europe
so the my city in Greece and
the high tides are direct
descendants of the Yemnaya
and as you remember this is
a warrior culture okay so
these societies are
warrior societies meaning
like the warriors are in charge and
they have a system called
a palace
economy a
palace economy a palace economy is basically
the palace is at the center of society
and
everyone brings their wealth to
the palace to be redistributed
to everyone else okay
so the idea here is we're
all farmers right and
maybe you could say that
the you have 100 100
bushels of wheat maybe 20
bushels of corn okay everyone
brings everything to the palace
and then
the king redistributes
the everything to you okay
but obviously he takes a cut understand
so this is called red
seeking behavior where
I'm where you're basically paying
taxes okay does it make sense
okay now this is fine
when things are good okay
but
if there be the weather becomes
bad this system starts
to collapse why the
weather is bad things
start to become chaotic why
okay the reason why is the lead
still okay the reason why is the
lead still okay the reason why is the lead
still what their cut you understand it's not what their cut you understand it's not what their cut you understand it's not like oh this year the weather is bad
so like oh this year the weather is bad so
like oh this year the weather is bad so let's just suffer together okay let's let's just suffer together okay let's make sacrifices together no it's like no make sacrifices
together no it's like no make sacrifices
together no it's like no we don't care the weather is bad you we don't care the weather is bad you we don't care the weather is bad you start to pay our pay our cut okay you start to pay our pay our cut okay you start to pay your taxes
start to pay
your taxes
that during the Bronze Age,
there was an internal revolt
in Mycenaean Greece.
And the reason why is we
can dig up Mycenaean Greece,
the palace, and what we see
is the palace is burned down,
but the surrounding houses are fine.
Okay, does that make sense? We also have
written records from Mycenaean Greece
that show how the palace
economy worked, okay?
We can also dig up the
graves of the kings and show
that over time, they became
wealthier and wealthier
because when they were buried,
the things they were buried
with were very expensive.
Does that make sense?
Okay, so that's Mycenaean Greece.
Any questions so far? Okay,
it's clear about this idea.
Okay? So,
what a lot of scholars believe is
that this is,
the Bronze Age Collapse was a
unique event in European history.
And what I'm trying to show you is,
it was not a unique event,
it was not a revolution,
it's just part of the
natural cycle of history.
Because when you have the elite,
who engage in rhetoric and behavior,
eventually this society will collapse.
Because you have too many
elite who want their cut.
And when we look at other societies,
you will discover this
pattern repeats itself.
Right? So, this is Peter Turchin,
his theory of elite over production.
Are we clear? Yes?
Okay, alright,
so, okay, let me clarify,
about Mycenaean Greece, okay?
All right, the problem is, that
you have too many rich people, who
wanna charge rent, right, and
that creates pressure on society,
and this instability, Stability means
that your society is no longer resilient.
Okay, resilient And
the idea of resilience is
that it survives disasters
Right. So think of a tower
That's about to collapse. Okay,
it will not clap on its own Something
must hit it for it to collapse.
But this one thing could be anything
Okay, it could be the people get angry
and they riot it could be the weather turns
bad Okay, it could be a there's an earthquake.
It could be there's an invasion.
Does it does that make sense?
So these different societies,
okay, my city agrees high tides
The Canaanites they class
for different reasons
But the fundamental reason is because
of societies were unstable The reason why they
were unstable is you had too many elite people
Trying to charge rent on everyone else.
Does that make sense? Okay,
anyway any more questions,
but that's a good question.
Thank you To me
Oh Can you avoid the
cycle in today's society?
Okay, that's a good question
and the answer is no
Okay, it is impossible to build a society
That that
is stable over a long period of time
in fact You can make the argument
that it is good for societies
to rise and fall Okay,
it's the same thing as it's really some question
as is it possible for us to live forever
Is it possible for us to live
forever then the question then
is why would we want to live forever?
You understand innovation
happens when we die
Okay, so So what's amazing
about the Bronze Age collapse is
because of Bronze Age collapsed?
Mycenaean Greece changed
into a new society that
gave us Greek civilization
Which then gave us Western civilization?
Okay So in other words if my city agrees
that collapse we will not have today
Also because kind of collapse a
new society came into being called
the Israelites, okay, Israel and
Israel gave us what you guys know
the Bible right
and guess what guys the Greeks and
the Bible are the two foundations
of Western civilization
so we would not have
Western civilization if this
Society that collapse and new
studies could come into being
All right, so you can
make the argument that
innovation progress is driven by death
and collapse All right
You understand And
if we if we got die if we
not if we do not die besides
that I collapse there'd be no progress
Okay Does it make sense?
But that's a good
question. Okay, but but and
people will happen debating this
question for a long time But
I think the answer is it is impossible
to build a society that lives forever even
though people have tried and also
we should even try okay, because
Collapse is good. Also
think of a forest fire.
Have you guys studied forest
fires in school in science class?
forest fires forest fires guys
Each time there's a forest fire
Okay, the force burns out.
That's good Because
it allows the force to
regenerate and become stronger
Right. What happens if you
don't have a forest fire?
Did you guys know? Okay,
the resilience goes down
Okay, and also
the ecosystem is less
Vibrant, they're less
They're less animals. The
trees are less strong.
Okay, do you understand? So that's why
it's important to burn down the force now
and then you don't burn
on the forest and there's
then it's less resilient
So there's a big forest fire
It was just bread and
destroyed entire force.
Okay, does it make sense?
So it's good for societies
to constantly change
over time Okay
Any more questions?
Okay, that's a great question, okay
All right So
before we talk about egalitarian societies
right how they were at most 10,000 people
and they did have an elite, okay?
They had an elite They
had people in charge,
but this elite didn't own the property.
There's no private property.
Okay, so it's egalitarian and
so These societies were pretty stable.
Okay, and the reason why is
Usually it was the woman in charge and
the woman could were good at
controlling population Okay,
because as a woman you have
control over your body.
So you could choose not to have
children or have less children
And it was very peaceful right people didn't
really fight which there's nothing to fight over.
Everything was owned by everyone else
Okay, the problem with egalitarian
societies are these three things Okay,
they're less organized
meaning like they are less
willing or less able to
create public projects
Okay, they have less wealth and
therefore they have less scale.
Okay, you can have at most 10,000 people
Which means what which means like
eventually Eventually,
they will be conquered
Okay, does that make sense? Because
if you are one of these societies, okay,
you're an empire you must
constantly expand in order to
Please delete basically, okay,
either you expand or you
fight a civil war and
So that you take over egalitarian societies
and you make them into your society.
Okay, do you understand? so
For most of the human
history were egalitarian,
but that's because we
didn't have that many people
Right But over time as
population increases
Then you are less egalitarian
you become more unequal
you stay egalitarian you will
eventually be conquered by a
Not not an egalitarian
society, does that make sense?
All right All right,
but that's a great question
You're exactly right.
Okay for most of human
history were egalitarian, but
once we start develop
elite societies, okay
Kingdoms then it could easily
conquer egalitarian societies
All right any more questions,
but but that's a fantastic question.
Okay any more questions
And when we do so we are skipping
ahead but when we do Samaria
Samaria Which is basically
Many different city -states in Iraq
Mesopotamia what we will discover is
that there are different
social structures, okay
There are different social structures
including societies that were egalitarian
But when you're in competition
with each other societies that
are more organized more wealthy now bigger
populations will always win out over
other societies Okay,
you have these three
things you need a permanent
territory elite because then
they are more incentivized in order to
Work harder, okay, does
it make sense and then
the question then is okay?
Why is that true? And it's true because
For societies become wealthier.
You don't need everyone to work
hard You just need a certain
number of people to work hard for You just
need a small group of people to work hard.
It doesn't make sense. So
think all like China, right?
How China became wealthier?
These past 30 40 years and
the reason why is you had a small
number of entrepreneurs who
worked really really hard
Okay, not everyone worked hard
Okay, but because you have these people who
did work really hard trying to become wealthier
Does that make sense?
Okay any more questions?
Okay, so great.
Okay. So Again,
what makes this class different from other
classes is we are looking at the entire scope of human history
All right, and it's what's very important for
you to not understand not remember the facts.
Okay, I don't need you
remember the facts Okay,
I don't need you remember my
son he agrees or the sea people,
but I do need you to remember
the concepts and the ideas
Okay, how the world history is constantly
in competition with each other
and Why is it that some ideas
win out over other ideas?
Okay, so that's saying
this is the best idea.
Okay. I'm not saying a permanent
Territory elite is a really good idea.
I don't think it's a good idea Okay, but
I'm showing you what wins out
and how it impacts human history
and the development of civilization
Does that make sense? Okay
Okay, any more questions?
Okay Okay, well that's it