Okay, so
last class we talked about Maria Kumbotas,
who is an anthropologist.
And she makes the argument that
for the longest time,
for most of its history,
Europe was egalitarian,
peaceful,
and artistic. But
today, we are a patriarchy.
There's a lot of inequality,
and we're always at war with each other.
So what changed? And
last time we discussed
that
old Europe was conquered
by a warlike people,
who we call today the Yemeniah.
So three questions I want to
answer in today's class is,
first of all,
who are the Yemeniah?
Second question is,
where did they come from?
And the third question is,
how did they conquer Europe?
Alright, so
let's go back in time
and look at the world
about 10,000 years ago.
So we believe that about 11,000
years ago, in the Near East,
we developed agriculture.
We developed the technology of farming.
And as we discussed in
our very first class,
it was because humans
are a religious people.
And farming allows us to
celebrate our religion.
And the reason why farming was
founded in the Near East is,
for the longest time, there's an ice age.
So you couldn't farm.
You had to move around
from place to place to hunt
and find food.
So after the ice age, which
ended about 12,000 years ago,
the climate became warmer, and
the Near East became the area where
you could grow crops, the easiest.
So Near East is what we
call the Middle East today,
which includes Turkey, Jordan,
Syria, and Israel.
That's where farming was invented.
About 7,000, 8,000 years ago,
the weather became a lot cooler.
There was another ice age for a
very short amount of time. And
this forced people to start to immigrate
or migrate to look for new land.
So people in the Near East,
they went off to Europe,
and these people were very lucky,
because the geography of Europe was not
that different from the
geography of the Near East.
So they could take their religion,
they could take their technology,
move over to Europe, and
still be about the same.
There were some minor changes,
but they were more or less the same.
So these people were very lucky.
And these people, as Maria Kambuta said,
these people have the same religion
as the people of the Near East.
They worship the Mother Goddess,
who gives life to everything.
They believe in the ideas of unity.
Unity just means that we are the same.
Every one of us are the same.
We have a responsibility to love each
other, and to love each other's children.
We're the same as animals.
We're the same as plants. So we
must do our best to protect nature.
The farms allow us to eat food, but
we should not destroy nature.
We should protect nature, because
it's all the Mother Goddess.
We're all the children
of the Mother Goddess.
So we also believe in balance and harmony.
And this is the religion,
as we discussed before,
of many indigenous
peoples around the world.
If you go to Africa, Australia,
the Amazon, and you meet
these indigenous peoples,
they have the same religion,
which is, we come from a Mother Goddess,
and we have a responsibility
to protect the nature,
the earth, because that's the
gift from the Mother Goddess.
And everyone has a soul.
So after we die, our soul still lives on.
Does that make sense, guys? So
this is the religion of old Europe.
And because of this religion,
they were egalitarian,
meaning there was no real
difference between men and women.
In fact, because women had
the power to give birth,
to give life, they were considered
in many ways superior to men.
And the political class was
mainly governed by women.
Okay? They were peaceful.
They really didn't have to
fight each other, because
they felt their resources
was enough for them.
Okay? And they were artistic. So
they focused their
intellectual energies on
creating art to celebrate the
Mother Goddess and their religion.
Okay? So the people of the Near East
and the people of Europe
were very similar.
Okay? The problem starts
when these people went off to
what we call the steppes.
The steppes is a huge ocean of grassland
that basically extends
from Europe into Mongolia.
Okay? And you know, the Chinese
word for this is taoyuan.
Now the problem with the
grassland is people can't eat grass.
And you cannot grow crops on grassland
that easily. Okay?
So the people on the steppes,
they struggle to survive.
And the people on the steppes
engage in a process we
call social evolution.
Okay? So you may have
heard the term evolution.
I want to explain what the term
evolution means for our class,
because we will refer to it a lot as
we progress through human history.
Okay? So for us, evolution means open
cooperative competition.
Okay? So this is what evolution means.
And
evolution has historically been the
greatest source of human
innovation and creativity.
Okay? So let me explain why.
Open means there's no central authority.
There's no great power.
Okay? There's no hegemon. Everyone's
competing against each other.
Competition just means these people,
these many different people, they're
trying to compete to survive.
Okay? There are very scarce
resources in the steppes.
It's not as wealthy as the
Near East and as Europe.
And they're all trying to survive.
They all adopt different
strategies in order to survive.
Okay? At the same time,
cooperative means they're still
communicating with each other.
They're still trading.
They're still friends.
Maybe they'll exchange wives,
exchange presents. So
this is a process of social evolution
that has created the most
innovation in human history.
So in Chinese history,
this most resembles what
period in Chinese history?
In Chinese history. Which
part of Chinese history
does this process where
you have many different people
in open competition with each other
but still learning from each other?
This period in Chinese history is called?
Exactly, right? And that's where
most of Chinese innovation and
creativity came from, from that period.
Confucius came from that
period. Laozi, okay?
A lot of major intellectual
breakthroughs came from that period.
Okay? But
not only the Chunchiu of China.
As we move on,
we will also look at two
other major periods where
there was a major outburst of innovation
and then very similar social
structure as like this, okay?
So we will also be studying
the Greek city -states.
In fact, we will spend a lot of time
on the Greek city -states like Athens
and Sparta and Thebes because
before,
we actually thought the origin
of Western civilization
were the Greek city -states, okay?
We no longer believe that,
but for the longest time,
we believe Western civilization
came from the Greek city -states.
And when we look at
the Greek city -states,
you will discover the system they had back
then is very similar to this system, okay?
We will also look at the
Sumerian city -states,
okay? Which is very similar
to the Greek city -states.
Yes, okay? So
we will be studying
these different periods,
okay? But I want you to remember,
the first important principle is whenever
there is an open cooperative competition,
tremendous innovation happens, okay?
That's the first principle
I want you to remember.
The second principle I
want you to remember is
eventually, someone triumphs
in this competition,
okay?
And the group, the people
that
triumphs are the people who
are most,
most open to adopting innovation
in order to destroy others, okay?
Does that make sense? They are the most
ruthless in adopting all innovations
for the sole purpose of destroying others
and becoming the sole hegemon, okay?
So we saw this with the
Greek city -states where
for hundreds of years, they were
in competition with each other.
And then there was a,
a group of people called the Macedonians
who weren't actually Greek, okay?
They were marginal to
the Greek city -states.
And the Greeks didn't really consider the
Macedonians part of their civilization.
But they were on the outskirts and
they observed all the innovations
that the Greek city -states were creating,
especially in terms of military innovation,
adopted all innovations
for their purposes, and
then conquered the city
-states before they moved on
and conquered Persia and Egypt, okay?
And the leader of the Macedonians
was called, do you guys know?
Who was the leader of the Macedonians
who conquered the Greek city -states?
I'm sure you know who he is, but you
may not know he was a Macedonian.
Who's the most famous
Greek you've heard of?
Yeah, he was actually Macedonian, okay?
Alexander the Great. Okay? And
what's amazing is we see the same
pattern play out with the
Sumerian city -states,
where for a hundred years,
the city -states were in
competition with each other.
They were all trying to conquer
each other without success.
And then an outside people, a
neighbor called the Akkadians,
the Akkadians,
they adopted all the innovation and
technology of the Sumerian
city -states, and
then they conquered the
Sumerian city -states and
established the first great world
empire called the Akkadian Empire.
And the founder of that empire, we
will learn, is called Sargon the Great.
Okay? Sargon the Great.
And Sargon the Great is considered
the world's very first empire builder.
So even though
we know almost nothing about
what was happening here,
from our knowledge of
the Greek city -states
and the Sumerian city -states
and what happened to them, we can guess or
hypothesize the same process played out here
where these different tribes,
these different groups were creating
all sorts of different innovations.
Then one outside group came in, adopted all
the innovations, and then conquered everyone.
Okay? And these people are
what we call the Anaya,
who originated, we believe, in Ukraine.
Okay? So let's now discuss the innovations
that these people created.
Okay? And the innovations
were pretty incredible because
they forever transformed human history.
Okay, so the first innovation they adopted
was a pastoral economy.
Okay? So basically, the pastoral economy,
basically raising cattle,
raising or herding cattle,
or cows.
All right. So
we cannot eat grass, okay?
But cows and sheep and
goats can eat grass, and
then we can eat the cows,
the goats, and the sheep.
Okay? Does that make
sense? So what we realize,
what these people realize
is they can take the cows,
the goats and the sheep,
from the farmers, okay?
Because there was a lot of
trading back then, and then
raise them in the steppes, and
because there's so much grass,
they'll grow very fast.
And then you can use that
as the source of your food.
Okay? So they created a new economy.
Well, then they, what
the second innovation is,
well, then they realize is, you know what?
We can also drink their milk.
Okay? Dairy.
And this is important because
for most of human history,
we cannot drink milk because
we're lactose intolerant.
Okay? In fact, most people in the world
today are still lactose intolerant.
But they developed the enzymes,
the peptides, in order to drink milk.
Okay? They became lactose tolerant.
So that's their second big innovation.
The ability to drink milk.
Okay? And now, if you're
able to eat protein,
and you drink milk a lot,
what happens to your body?
What happens to your body? Exactly.
Okay? You become very tall, very strong.
Okay? So, because of
these two innovations,
the people in the steppes
were on average, okay?
Just average, 20 centimeters taller
than the farmers in the Near East
and the people in the Middle East.
And in Europe. 20
centimeters is a lot, guys.
Okay? The reason why is the
farmers did not eat meat mostly,
and they could not drink milk.
They ate vegetables.
Okay? So,
the third big innovation
is the domestication of the horse.
The reason why is
the grassland is huge.
And they needed to travel huge
distances to trade, to communicate.
Okay? So, they started
to domesticate the horse.
And it's very hard to domesticate
the horse because horses are trained,
or horses are programmed,
hardwired, to run away from humans.
Right? If they see a
threat, they run away.
So, this process, we believe,
took at least 3,000 years.
Okay? But they kept on trying because
the ability to ride horses was very big.
And this is important for their
society and their economy.
And so, now they have the
ability to ride horses.
That's the third big innovation.
Then, they invent the wheel.
Okay? And what is important
is if you have the horse
and the wheel, you can create the wagon.
Okay? If you have the wagon,
it means you are no
longer stuck in one place.
You can move from place to place.
And so, this is what we call the nomadic
pastoral economy. Okay?
Does that make sense? They're able to move
from place to place because basically,
what happens is you have a lot of cows,
they're going to eat all the grass.
Okay? Now, you have to move somewhere
else for them to eat the grass.
Okay? Does that make sense? Now,
the problem with this is what?
If you move from place to place and the cows
are eating all the grass, what happens?
They're going to eat the grass.
Conflict, right? Because
you are now in competition for
what we call grazing rights.
Grazing rights.
If your cows go into a grassland and
they eat all that grass, well,
that's preventing other
people from going in
and having their cows eat that grass.
Okay? So, now they're
fighting over the grass.
They're fighting over and grazing rights.
Okay? What else are they
now going to fight over?
How about cows?
Right? Because
in this economy, one way to
survive is to feed your cows.
What's another way to survive? What
else can you do in this economy,
in this world? Steal other people's cows.
Right? Does that make sense? So, okay.
So, the protection of the cows
meant there was a greater emphasis on men.
Okay? So, remember, in this
society, in the Near East,
in Europe, these are
agricultural societies.
And for them, what mattered
was life giving, giving birth.
And maintaining a harmonious society.
So, women were more important than men.
in this society, where
there's a lot of violence,
there's a lot of conflict,
men became more important.
Okay? So, with these innovations,
they start to change their economy,
their society, and their religion.
Okay? Economy, society,
and religion. Okay.
So, in terms of the economy,
the first major
change from this society is
the idea of private property.
Private property. Okay? Because
cows are private wealth.
And you have to protect that wealth.
Okay? So, that's the
first major innovation.
The idea of private property
where this belongs to you,
and only you, and not to society
or to the mother goddess.
Okay? And that's very different
from the farmers in Europe
who had no concept of private property.
Okay? So,
the idea of private property, the society
changes and becomes a patriarchy.
Okay? Where men are in control.
Okay? And in a patriarchy
of private property,
the problem now is one of
inheritance. Right? So, let's just say
I have 10 sons and I have 100 cattle.
And I die. Who gets my cattle?
I have Who gets my wealth?
It has to be the older son.
Why? The oldest son. Why?
Exactly. Okay? So,
we need 100 cattle to survive as a family.
If I start splitting the
wealth up between the 10 sons,
we become a lot poor.
Right? The 10 sons have 10 sons,
then by the third generation
everyone has one cattle.
So, everyone's now poor.
Okay? So, the only way to
solve this problem is if I,
the patriarch, the father, give
everything to the eldest son.
Okay? And this is what
we call primogeniture.
So, this is a new
innovation. Primogeniture.
Where the eldest inherits everything.
Okay? Now, the problem is
what happens to the other nine sons?
So, you have to take
Exactly. Okay?
So, the eldest son gets everything and
the nine other sons, too bad.
You have to go build your own wealth.
And that means basically
stealing cows from other people.
Okay? So, this creates a war culture.
A war culture.
Right? So, does that make sense?
That's your society. This
is a society which is
which honors men above women.
Which has private property and
celebrates private property.
Which encourages young men to go out and
expand their civilization and fight wars.
Okay? So,
if you're making these changes, you
now have to change the religion.
Okay? The religion. So,
their religion makes major changes
to the mother goddess religion.
Okay? So, the first major change is
who's now God? Who
do they now worship?
A man. Right? Because men fight wars.
So, they worship someone
called the Sky Father.
And he's the source of who
the Greeks called Zeus,
the Thunder God. Okay? And who the Romans
called Jupiter, also the Thunder God.
So, the first god is
called the Sky Father.
Okay? That's the first change.
The second change is
whereas the mother goddess
gave us everything, right?
Nature. The Sky Father gave us
cows, cattle,
money, and wealth.
Okay? So,
the third change is whereas the mother
goddess asked us to love everything
and protect everything, the Sky
Father asked us to fight each
other for the right to have wealth.
Does it make sense? That's
now their new religion.
Okay? And so,
they adopt this new religion.
Okay. So, these are all major innovations.
Okay? And again, the
one group who comes in
and adopts all these innovations
are called the Yamnaya.
And so, if you're a group and
you adopt most of these innovations
but not all these innovations,
then you're going to lose to the group called
the Yamnaya who adopt all these innovations.
Okay? Does that make sense to you guys?
This is what we call social evolution.
Okay? And when they adopt
all these innovations,
then what happens is their religion
becomes aligned with their society
which becomes aligned with their economy.
Okay? And so, this is a
people who are obsessed with
collecting wealth and fighting wars and
expanding into new territories. And so,
what happens is over a process of a few
thousand years they conquer the steppes.
Okay? Their culture spreads
throughout the steppes.
It doesn't mean they're one people.
It means they're one culture.
Practice the same beliefs. Okay?
Does that make sense?
Any questions so far?
So, these are the Yamnaya people.
This is what they believe.
This is where they came from.
This is how they behave. Next
thing I'm going to look at is
fine, how do these people
conquer Europe?
Okay? Now, I already said
the Yamnaya are stronger and bigger and
more militaristic than
the farmers of old Europe.
Right? But what advantage
do the people of Europe have
over the Yamnaya?
What's the major
advantage that Europe has?
If you have farming, what
happens to your population?
It grows very fast, right?
So, in other words,
Europe has more population
than the steppes.
Does that make sense? Okay?
So, in theory, okay, well, yeah,
the Yamnaya, they have
this warlike religion.
They're extremely militaristic.
They're very strong. But in theory,
Europe could have understood
the Yamnaya because
Europe has more people.
Okay? So, the question now is,
how did the Yamnaya conquer Europe?
So, what's a problem with people
who live on farms? What's their ultimate
problem? Well, the problem that the people
have is they're living next to pigs
and rats
and there's a lot of garbage around.
Okay? So, it's very easy
for diseases to spread.
Okay? So,
we believe two things happen to reduce
the population of Europe significantly.
The first thing that
happened was the plague.
Okay? And this is what
communities. Now, the thing is, though,
the plague spread around the world.
Okay? Because, remember, what's important
to remember is these people in the steppes,
in the Near East, in Europe were
all in contact with each other
because they were trading with each other.
Okay? So, the plague we
know from DNA research
was in Europe,
in France.
So, the only thing
on the people in the
steppes was on the ovaries.
So, the ovaries believe that
most of the people were wiped
out by the plague in Europe.
So that reduced the
population significantly.
So that's the first thing
that happened in Europe.
Second thing that happened in Europe
is what we call climate change.
So about four,
sorry, yeah about,
let me do the math, about five thousand,
six thousand years ago, there
was a mini ice age in Europe.
And if you're a farmer, that's
really bad for you, okay?
Because you can't grow crops.
And it's bad for you if you live in the
steppes, because you can't grow crops.
steppes, because a lot of your crops will die, but not as bad, okay?
And the other thing is that now, the
ice age, because of climate change,
people in the steppes are now forced
to expand further into Europe,
okay? So this is what we think happened.
Three things, okay, that destroyed Europe.
The first thing is the plague.
That's actually the most important thing,
because it wiped out most of the people, okay?
So think of when
Europe conquered North and South America.
What killed most people in North
and South America was
actually the plague, right?
Europeans had these
diseases they brought over,
and that killed most of
the local population, okay?
So the plague was the main
culprit that destroyed all Europe.
Then climate change,
and then finally the Yemnaya
people, who came into Europe
and started to colonize Europe
and destroy the local population, okay? So
let me now explain why the
Yemnaya decided to kill the people,
the farmers of Europe, okay?
So let's just say that in Europe you
have a village, maybe a hundred men,
a hundred women. You have a hundred men,
young men, who have no wealth
and no wives, okay?
So what do they want to
do? If you're a young man,
you have no wife, and you have no
wealth, what do you want to do?
Yeah, you want to steal other
people's wife and property, right?
So they came in, okay?
So and what do they do?
You have a hundred men and a hundred
women in this village, so what do you do?
No, yeah, but yeah, they
killed a man, okay guys?
Okay? And then they married all the women.
And that's what happened, okay?
Now there are some circumstances when
the Yemnaya came in, because
again, this is a culture.
This is not one people. It's a culture of
people, and they adopted different strategies.
Some of them decided to come in and said, listen,
we'll take all the women and we'll let the men go.
And what did these men do
in return, in response?
What would you do?
Yeah.. So they went to
get their neighbors,
got a thousand of them, came
back and killed everyone,
okay? So
this was actually a violent,
violent process with
violence on both sides,
okay? But
eventually what happened was the
Yemnaya conquered all of Europe,
okay? And they even got to England.
They conquered England, okay?
. And then not only did
they conquer England,
but not only did they conquer Europe, then
they went to conquer India and Iran.
So this spread everywhere.
And even Mongolia, okay?
But not to China. Why
didn't it impact China?
What are the reasons why the
Yemnaya could not conquer China?
..
. What's between India and China?
They conquered India, right?
Why could they conquer China?
..
.....
........
...
.....
.....................................
..............
...........................
.................................................
.
.....................................................................................
Make sense? So, but
this conquest meant now there's a
common language among all
these people in India,
in Iran, in the steppes, basically
Russia, in the Near East,
and in Europe, okay?
This language is what we
call Proto -Indo -European.
That's a language they spoke, okay?
Now they have a common religion.
So, from this point on,
this world, okay,
stretching from Europe
all the way to India,
was in constant communication
with each other,
trading ideas, people, and gods, okay?
And this is what we call today the West.
Okay? And it's distinct from China,
which was isolated from this world.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay,
any questions? Yeah?
The Mongolian people are
descended from the Yamaya, yes.
And if you think about it, the Mongolian
people are very similar to the Yamaya, right?
The Mongolians are also
nomadic pastoral people
who are also very much warlike, okay?
And in fact, what we'll
learn later on is that,
Genghis Khan adopted very
similar policies as the Yamaya.
Okay? So
we'll see a lot of similarities
between Genghis Khan and
his conquest and the Yamaya
conquest of the world
at this time, about four
or five thousand years ago.
Yes?.
The plague, yes..
. It killed most Europeans, yes.
Because Europeans were
living on farms, right?
So they were living together.
. Yeah,
because it reduced the population of Europe,
so they were less able to resist the invasion.
..
Okay. Alright, so the plague
was all around the world, okay?
This is actually the bubonic plague, okay?
The bubonic plague. It's spread by rats.
And we have DNA of this plague, okay?
So we know the bubonic plague has been
with us for the longest time, okay?
So, the plague kills people
who live closely together.
You understand? Because
then it's easier to transmit the disease.
So if you live closely together,
you're much more likely to
catch the disease and die.
Does it make sense? But
if you live far apart,
then you're less likely
to catch the disease.
So in Europe, people were living on farms.
And there's like 10,000 people
who might live on a farm.
That's a lot of people who
live very closely together.
They're also living with animals.
So it's very unclean.
But if you're living on the steppes, okay?
First of all, you're living far apart.
That's the first thing. Second thing is,
your life is much more hygienic, okay?
Because you're not living
with pigs and rats.
And the third thing is,
your body is a lot stronger.
You're drinking milk, okay? You're
getting a lot of physical exercise.
Does that make sense? So these people
are less likely to die from the plague.
All right. Any more questions?
So are the Jews the
descendants of the Amnaya?
Exactly, yes. Okay.
So basically,
everyone in Europe, except for a few,
few people, are the descendants
of the Amnaya, okay?
The Indian people, the Iranian people,
also consider descendants of the Amnaya.
Now, when the Amnaya came,
the Indian people were considered descendants
of the Amnaya. These farmers in Europe, okay,
there were maybe three
major responses, okay?
The first response is, let's fight them.
And then they got killed. The second response
is, let's try to cooperate with them, okay?
The third major response is,
let's move somewhere else.
So the people who moved to islands, okay?
So for example, there's
an island called Sardinia,
okay? In Italy, okay? It's an island.
They survived against, they
survived against the Amnaya.
And they have less Amnaya
DNA than other people,
okay? But if you can't run off to an
island, you're gonna get wiped out, okay?
But basically, all of Europe
was conquered by the Amnaya.
And when you look at the, later on
I will show you the DNA evidence.
When you look at that evidence,
it's pretty stark, okay?
All right? How did they
conquer the Amnaya?
That's a great question,
okay? Thank you. All right.
So this process took a long time,
100 years, okay?
And during this time, this
is a spread of a culture.
So it's not one people.
It's not one nation.
So what's happening was, as they
conquered different territories,
they had to adapt themselves
to that territory.
Because the geography is different, okay?
So in the steppes, you're leading
a nomadic pastoral lifestyle.
And at first, they take a step.
They try that. So for example, we have evidence
that in Norway, which is in North Europe,
they burned down all the forests because
they were trying to replicate
their homeland, okay?
But then eventually they discovered
this is not gonna work, okay?
It's too hard. So then
they start to mix their lifestyle
with the local lifestyle,
and they became more
focused on agriculture,
okay? Does that make sense? All right.
And as they kept on spreading,
they also spread, stole the
technology of the local people.
So even though
the Yamnaya people
had no shipbuilding technology,
they couldn't sail the seas, they were
able to conquer people here off the coast
who did have access to the sea
and who did have boats, okay?
And then they stole the technology.
They killed the people, and they
learned the technology, okay?
Once they had the technology, then
they sailed off to England and
killed everyone in England.
Does that make sense? Okay.
So it's a very slow process.
And these are different
groups of Yamnaya, okay?
Okay. But that's a very good
question. Any more questions?
Are you guys clear about this?
Okay. All right.
All right. Absolutely clear?
Okay, good. So when
we come back from the break,
okay, we will discuss the new world
that this creates, okay?
Because when you think
of Western civilization,
the Greeks, the Romans,
well, they all come from this world, okay?
So basically what the Yamnaya do is
they create a new history for humanity.
Before the Yamnaya,
humans were egalitarian,
peaceful, and articulate.
They were artistic, okay? And now
with the Yamnaya, you have patriarchy.
You have war. You have money.
But before, we didn't have these concepts.
So this marks a new history for humanity.
When we come back from the break, we'll
start exploring this history. Okay?